<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101701807</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">46280</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clim Risk Manag</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clim Risk Manag</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Climate risk management</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2212-0963</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40008304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11848723</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2024.100631</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EPAPA2022566</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial for <italic toggle="yes">climate risk management</italic>, special issue: Building resilience in communities confronted with contaminated land, disasters, and changing environmental conditions<sup><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="fn">&#x02606;</xref></sup></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>Meridith M.</given-names></name><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>Susan H.</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="A1">US Environmental Protection Agency Office of Research and Development, 1200 Pennsylvania Ave, NW, Washington, DC 20460, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author at: US Environmental Protection Agency Office of Research and Development, 1200 Pennsylvania Ave, NW, Washington, DC 20460, USA, <email>fry.meridith@epa.gov</email> (M.M. Fry)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>45</volume><fpage>100631</fpage><lpage>100631</lpage><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><label>1.</label><title>Overview</title><p id="P1">Certain communities, populations, and localities face disproportionate risk of exposure to multiple stressors due to neighboring contaminated land, as well as changing environmental conditions and disasters (e.g., extreme heat, drought, flood, wildfire). Understanding the extent and severity of potential community impacts is important for responding to events and for improving local planning and decisions to protect human health and the environment. Case studies demonstrate how fine-scale data are needed to design more effective strategies. At the same time, planning and recovery efforts need to equitably and inclusively consider communities that face extreme climate and potential pollutant exposures. This Special Issue presents research that addresses these interwoven issues, with the overarching goal of building resilience in communities vulnerable to the direct and indirect effects of extreme climate events and disasters. Papers in this issue offer insights into equitable resilience planning for under-resourced communities, as well as methods for adapting and preparing for future contaminant releases and subsequent exposures. This editorial describes key findings from the papers included in this Special Issue.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><label>2.</label><title>Investigating the extent and severity of potential impacts at a fine scale</title><p id="P2"><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Samson et al. (2023)</xref> investigate the health impacts of populations vulnerable to flooding and in immediate proximity to industrial facilities. This research reveals that physical health scores are significantly lower in medium and higher risk locations, and that chronic conditions and cancer diagnoses were heightened in the highest risk areas. Even in a geographically compact community, researchers show that health outcomes can vary significantly at a finer scale. Not only does general proximity to contaminated land matter, but within potentially exposed communities, there are significant differences in health outcomes, which warrants finer grain analyses to respond to community needs and improve design plans and interventions.</p><p id="P3">Working at a fine scale is also important in terms of understanding both the direct and indirect effects of extreme climate and disasters on communities due to potential contaminant exposures. <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Atoba et al. (2023)</xref> assert that residential communities in proximity to petrochemical facilities are likely to experience multiple and sometimes cascading impacts from a single flood event. This can include flood inundation as well as the transport of contaminants into homes. Currently, property buyout selections only account for flood exposure and no other hazards, like potential contaminant exposure. The authors conclude that there is a potential economic benefit from recognizing multiple hazards for flood and contaminant-prone properties and applying a multi-hazard selection criterion, especially in socially vulnerable communities with greater potential for flooding and contaminant transfer.</p><p id="P4"><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. (2023)</xref> further build on the importance of studying underlying risks at industrial facilities (that emit chemical pollution) at a finer resolution when evaluating multiple hazards (health, physical, environmental hazards) that a community could face from a single extreme climate event. The authors demonstrate how to map these risks spatially along with sources of contamination and flood exposure, so unseen risks can be visualized and communicated for appropriate preparedness and response, especially for underserved and socially vulnerable communities.</p><p id="P5"><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Sinha et al. (2024)</xref> present an indicator screening approach, given that resources are often scarce for communities to conduct detailed modeling. The geospatial indicators developed represent four key sources of vulnerability in a common framework, which is used to screen for areas that may be impacted the most, isolate the reasons for these impacts, and assist with prioritizing resources and actions. The researchers demonstrate how fine-scale information, presented through indicators, offers transparent, actionable information that can be used directly for preparedness, response, and recovery.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><label>3.</label><title>Representing communities equitably in planning and recovery</title><p id="P6">Not only are certain communities more vulnerable to extreme climate events and disasters, but many of these communities are often inadequately represented in planning and recovery efforts (e.g., targeted monitoring for higher risk sub-populations to improve responses). <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Hochard et al. (2023)</xref> find that more work is needed to understand post-disaster water sampling approaches and how these methods might underrepresent vulnerable populations. The study suggests that sophisticated and holistic water quality prediction models might be needed to support post-disaster sampling, by targeting more vulnerable, individual households that are at higher risk for groundwater contamination.</p><p id="P7">Robinson et al. (2024) discuss hurricane-related population displacement in The Bahamas and the differential community- and island-level vulnerabilities based on various demographic and development factors. Issues of race and nationality, poverty and social class, economic structures, and power differences are shown to be central to these vulnerability differences among communities. More broadly, this study offers insights into equitable resilience planning for islands in The Bahamas and key considerations for mitigating future exposures.</p><p id="P8"><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Fry et al. (2023)</xref> demonstrate that in resilience planning, unless equity is at the center of the process, some vulnerable communities will continue to experience undue exposures and harms because they are not given a voice in the resilience planning process. The study examines the importance of centering equity in the development of content and process of using tools and resources for strengthening community resilience. The authors share how human-centered design principles provide a way to address both resilience and equity in managing the risks of extreme climate events and potential community exposures to contaminants.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><label>4.</label><title>Closing</title><p id="P9">The papers in this Special Issue demonstrate the importance of using fine-scale information and defining the extent and severity of impacts, which can be useful in community planning, response, and mitigation. By implementing a more equitable approach to post-disaster sampling and community resilience planning, responses and actions can be better tailored to those populations facing the greatest undue exposures and harms.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><label>&#x02606;</label><p id="P10">
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/special-issue/10TXGF85VQB" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.sciencedirect.com/special-issue/10TXGF85VQB</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p id="P11">Disclaimer</p><p id="P12">The views expressed in this article are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily represent the views or the policies of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Atoba</surname><given-names>Kayode</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>Galen</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sansom</surname><given-names>Garrett</given-names></name>, <year>2023</year>. <article-title>Multi-Hazard property buyouts: Making a case for the acquisition of flood and contaminant-prone residential properties in Galena Park, TX</article-title>. <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>100529</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2023.100529</pub-id>. <comment>ISSN 2212&#x02013;0963</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38312112</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>Meridith</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>Keely</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiessling</surname><given-names>Brittany</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsler</surname><given-names>Marissa</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ollove</surname><given-names>Margaret</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romanoski</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name>, <year>2023</year>. <article-title>Centering equity in the development of a community resilience planning resource</article-title>. <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>100520</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2023.100520</pub-id>. <comment>ISSN 2212&#x02013;0963.</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hochard</surname><given-names>Jacob</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abashidze</surname><given-names>Nino</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bawa</surname><given-names>Ranjit</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>Grace</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirkland</surname><given-names>Bailey</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yuanhao</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matlock</surname><given-names>Kayla</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>Wai Yan</given-names></name>, <year>2023</year>. <article-title>Predicting groundwater contamination to protect the storm-exposed vulnerable</article-title>. <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>100499</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2023.100499</pub-id>. <comment>ISSN 2212&#x02013;0963.</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Ryun Jung</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Zhihan</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prybutok</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>Suji</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dalaijamts</surname><given-names>Chimeddulam</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>Weihsueh A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>Galen</given-names></name>, <year>2023</year>. <article-title>Unseen risk: Mapping contamination hazards to enhance risk perception in Galena Park, Texas</article-title>. <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>100532</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2023.100532</pub-id>. <comment>ISSN 2212&#x02013;0963.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38298905</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>Garett T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>Ruby</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Jacquita N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>Galen</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atoba</surname><given-names>Kayode</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masterson</surname><given-names>Jaimie Hicks</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Deidra</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fawkes</surname><given-names>Leanne S.</given-names></name>, <year>2023</year>. <article-title>Evaluating the impact of proximity to reported toxic release facilities and flood events on chronic health outcomes in the city of Galena Park, Texas</article-title>. <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>100507</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2023.100507</pub-id>. <comment>ISSN 2212&#x02013;0963.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37975020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>Paramita</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>Meridith</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Truesdale</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cajka</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>Michele</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doraiswamy</surname><given-names>Prakash</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>Rosanne</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riemenschneider</surname><given-names>Julie</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potzler</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richkus</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O&#x02019;Neal</surname><given-names>Maggie</given-names></name>, <year>2024</year>. <article-title>Building resilience to extreme weather events in Phoenix: Considering contaminated sites and disadvantaged communities</article-title>. <source>Climate Risk Management</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>100586</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crm.2024.100586</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>