<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neuroimage: Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-9560</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40160454</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11951442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-9560(25)00010-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynirp.2025.100242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100242</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Utilization of resting-state electroencephalography spectral power in convolutional neural networks for classification of primary progressive aphasia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Craik</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Tessmer</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>Maya L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Dial</surname><given-names>Heather</given-names></name><email>hrdial@central.uh.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Communication Sciences and Disorders, University of Houston, 3871 Holman St, Houston, TX, 77204, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Houston, 4226 Martin Luther King Boulevard, Houston, TX, 77204, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Geriatric Research, Education, and Clinical Center, VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System, University Drive C, Pittsburgh, PA, 15240, USA</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Speech, Language, and Hearing Sciences, The University of Texas at Austin, 2504a Whitis Ave a1100, Austin, TX, 78712, USA</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Neurology, The University of Texas at Austin Dell Medical School, 1501 Red River St, Austin, TX, 78712, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Communication Sciences and Disorders, University of Houston, 3871 Holman St, Houston, TX, 77204, USA. <email>hrdial@central.uh.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>100242</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We investigated relative power spectral density (PSD) in primary progressive aphasia (PPA) in delta, theta, alpha, and beta frequency bands in eyes open and closed resting-state electroencephalography (EEG). Our aims were to assess whether discernible differences could be observed between each PPA variant and to determine the utility of PSD for PPA classification when used as input to a convolutional neural network (CNN). Findings in the current study were similar to previous studies in logopenic PPA, with a significant increase in relative PSD in delta and theta bands and a significant reduction in the beta band (consistent with oscillatory slowing). We did not observe a significant increase in power for lower frequency bands or a reduction of power in higher frequency bands for semantic or nonfluent PPA, in contrast to what has been previously reported. In semantic PPA, evidence pointed to oscillatory speeding, not the slowing that was previously reported in a single-case study. In nonfluent PPA, spectral power fell between logopenic and semantic PPA, suggesting there is oscillatory slowing but to a lesser extent than logopenic PPA. The CNN was relatively successful in distinguishing PPA from healthy controls (F1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.851). The CNN did not perform as well on four-way classification (lvPPA, svPPA, nfvPPA, controls; F1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.586) but was significantly above chance. These results are promising and suggest that resting-state EEG may prove useful as a biomarker for PPA diagnosis. Potential factors underlying the differences between the findings of the current study and previous work are discussed.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Resting-state electroencephalography</kwd><kwd>Primary progressive aphasia</kwd><kwd>Deep learning</kwd><kwd>Classification</kwd><kwd>Power spectral density</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0015">In 2011, consensus was reached on the diagnostic criteria for a relatively new neurodegenerative syndrome, primary progressive aphasia (PPA). With the advent of the criteria for PPA diagnosis comes the opportunity to explore potential diagnostic tools for more accurate and earlier detection of PPA and its three variants. Earlier and more accurate detection leads to faster implementation of a treatment plan, which can then be better tailored to suit the needs of the patient and lead to better outcomes. The current study aimed to investigate the potential use of resting-state electroencephalography (EEG) and convolutional neural networks (CNN) as a tool for accurate diagnosis of PPA.</p><p id="p0020">PPA is a relatively rare form of dementia that is primarily characterized by impairments in speech and language that gradually worsen over time. Unlike other types of dementia, in PPA, speech and language deficits are the predominant clinical features at onset and continue to be primary domains of impairment with disease progression. Standard exclusionary criteria for PPA diagnosis include symptoms caused by another neurological or psychiatric condition, prominent memory impairment, prominent visuospatial deficits, global motor impairment, or prominent behavioral disturbances (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gorno-Tempini et al., 2011</xref>). Early and accurate diagnosis of PPA can be difficult due to the relative rarity of the condition and subtle symptoms that characterize the earliest stages of disease progression. The insidious nature of symptoms and the early age of onset, generally in the patient's mid-40's to early 60's (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gorno-Tempini et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Mesulam et al., 2014</xref>), are also important clinical considerations in PPA, necessitating effective tools for detection and diagnosis.</p><p id="p0025">Once a PPA diagnosis is established, the disorder can be further delineated into three variants by the presence or absence of specific speech and language characteristics and further supported by distinct underlying patterns of brain atrophy. The core features of the nonfluent/agrammatic variant (nfvPPA) are apraxia of speech and/or agrammatism due to fronto-insular atrophy that is greater in the language dominant hemisphere. Individuals with nfvPPA must also have at least two of the following: impaired syntax comprehension, spared single word comprehension, and spared object knowledge. Individuals with semantic variant (svPPA) have a loss of core semantic knowledge due to anterior temporal lobe atrophy (greater in the language dominant hemisphere) leading to the presence of both anomia and single-word comprehension deficits. Individuals with svPPA must also have at least three of the following: loss of object knowledge, surface dyslexia/dysgraphia, spared repetition, and spared grammar and motor speech. The logopenic variant (lvPPA) is characterized by both impaired word retrieval and impaired phrase and sentence repetition due to temporo-parietal atrophy that is greater in the language dominant hemisphere. Individuals with lvPPA must also have at least three of the following: phonemic paraphasias, spared single word comprehension and object knowledge, spared motor speech, and lack of frank agrammatism (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gorno-Tempini et al., 2011</xref>). Each of these three canonical PPA variants has been linked to distinct neuropathology. Frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) is the underlying cause of most nfvPPA and svPPA cases whereas Alzheimer's disease has been linked to lvPPA (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Spinelli et al., 2017</xref>). For nfvPPA and svPPA, the specific proteinopathy of FTLD varies, with FTLD-tau being the primary cause in nfvPPA and FTLD-TDP43 being the primary cause in svPPA. Diagnosis typically requires extensive, time-consuming assessment batteries inclusive of neurological, neuropsychological, and speech and language tests. Further, although there are characteristics that are unique to each clinical variant, there is some overlap across variants, which can introduce complication into differential diagnosis (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">In recent years, researchers have sought to identify biomarkers to aid in PPA diagnosis using non-invasive functional neuroimaging. Non-invasive neuroimaging methods like EEG, magnetoencephalography (MEG), and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) are typically well tolerated and can be applied in a clinical setting. However, MRI and MEG are costly, and the use of a high-powered magnet makes them unsafe for people with certain contraindications, including medical devices such as pacemakers or cochlear implants, or implanted metal following surgery. Utilizing EEG has certain advantages in that the cost of EEG recording is negligible, and it is safe for use in all individuals.</p><p id="p0035">EEG is a type of non-invasive neuroimaging technique that records the brain's electrical activity via electrodes that are placed on the scalp (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Luck, 2014</xref>). Data collected via EEG can be either resting-state (i.e., task-free), whereby the participant's behavior is passive and not directed by any external stimulus, or can be task-based, in which the participant is asked to engage in some activity. In EEG (and MEG), researchers can use spectral analysis to examine the frequency content of the neural signal in different frequency bands, including delta (1&#x02013;4&#x000a0;Hz), theta (4&#x02013;7&#x000a0;Hz), alpha (8&#x02013;12&#x000a0;Hz), and beta (12&#x02013;30&#x000a0;Hz) bands. In individuals with a suspected neurodegenerative disease, resting-state data are easier to obtain and interpret than task-based data, as patients may be unable to complete tasks due to cognitive or other impairments (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Dalton et al., 2021</xref>). Examination of power spectral density (PSD) in resting-state EEG has potential for use in early detection of neurodegenerative disease due to its high accessibility, relatively low cost, good test-retest reliability, and lack of contraindications (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Dalton et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Moral-Rubio et al., 2021</xref>). Spectral analysis of resting-state EEG may offer benefit as a tool for detection of PPA, allowing for efficient diagnosis and effective management.</p><p id="p0040">Distinct spectral changes have been observed in individuals with PPA (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Shah-Basak et al., 2019</xref>). <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Shah-Basak et al. (2019)</xref> identified oscillatory slowing in PPA using resting-state MEG, noted by increased power in the delta band and decreased power in the alpha band. <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al. (2019)</xref> extended these findings by examining both resting-state and task-based MEG. Findings revealed that individuals with nfvPPA and lvPPA showed slower processing in language-elicited responses using task-based MEG, as evidenced by a significant delay in their peak latencies (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>). Additionally, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Shah-Basak et al. (2019)</xref> observed spectral slowing, evidenced by an increase of resting-state delta and theta power in association with decreases in alpha and beta power (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>). These results are notable, as they are distinct from neural oscillations seen in typically aging adults: oscillatory speeding characterized by decreased power in lower frequency bands and increased power in higher frequency bands (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>). However, distinguishable differences in PSD between nfvPPA and lvPPA were not observed (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>). In svPPA, a single case study utilizing task-based and resting-state MEG revealed slower processing speeds in the language-elicited task-based MEG and decreased power in the higher frequency alpha and beta bands in the resting-state MEG (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2022</xref>). There was no evidence of increased spectral power in the lower-frequency delta and theta bands. While this may seem to contradict previous studies examining PSD in PPA, these results are not entirely incongruous with PSD changes observed in people with FTLD, the underlying pathology for svPPA (and, often, nfvPPA; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Spinelli et al., 2017</xref>). Previous studies have observed a decrease in spectral power in the alpha and beta frequency bands and no increase in the delta or theta frequency bands in FTLD (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Lindau et al., 2003</xref>). Overall, these findings indicate that examination of PSD could contribute to PPA diagnosis.</p><p id="p0045">Only a few studies have attempted PPA classification using resting-state EEG or MEG. <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe and colleagues (2017)</xref> used resting-state MEG connectivity in delta, theta, alpha, and beta frequency bands to perform PPA subtype classification via logistic regression. The resting-state MEG findings mirrored the findings of <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al. (2019)</xref> and <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Shah-Basak et al. (2019)</xref>, revealing a slowing of neural activity, indicated by reduced spectral power in the alpha and beta frequency bands in all three PPA variants (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2017</xref>). Increased spectral power in the delta-theta range was also observed in all three variants of PPA, but was most notable in lvPPA (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2017</xref>). Logistic regression with PPA variant as the outcome measure and MEG connectivity as the predictor was moderately successful in discriminating the three PPA variants, with the best outcomes observed for lvPPA relative to nfvPPA and svPPA.</p><p id="p0050">Of greatest relevance to the current study, two recent studies examined resting-state EEG in relation to PPA diagnosis (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Moral-Rubio et al., 2021</xref>). <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al. (2024)</xref> observed an overall slowing in lvPPA and increased power in the theta band in nfvPPA, consistent with other studies. The most significant finding of the study was the identification of distinct patterns of activity associated with lvPPA. The results aligned with previous studies that demonstrated an overall slowing, as evidenced by increases in the delta and theta bands, and decreases in the alpha band compared to healthy controls, nfvPPA, and svPPA (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al., 2024</xref>). <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Moral-Rubio et al. (2021)</xref> utilized graph-theory derived metrics from resting-state EEG combined with machine learning to distinguish PPA from healthy controls and for four-way classification of healthy controls, svPPA, lvPPA, and nfvPPA. Classification of PPA vs. healthy controls was reasonably good (F1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.83), but four-way classification was less successful (F1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.60).</p><p id="p0055">With advances in computational modeling, more sophisticated classification approaches could be useful, such as CNNs, networks that are highly effective at automatically and adaptively learning spatial hierarchies of features from data. Much of past research into EEG analysis with deep learning has been focused on CNNs (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Lawhern et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Craik et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Roy et al., 2019</xref>) for the benefits of spatial pattern detection, reduction in trainable parameters as compared to other deep learning models, and modifications that help to prevent overfitting. Outside of the direct classification of the EEG voltage values, CNNs have also been employed to classify spectral features of the EEG signal (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hasan et al., 2020</xref>). Classifying spectral features directly has been considered a valid input modification that can help to avoid overfitting to participant-specific EEG amplitude differences or the presence of artifacts. Employing spectral features of EEG signals derived during resting state with the computational power and generalization abilities of CNNs may allow for fast and accurate detection of PPA and potentially the classification of PPA subtype.</p><p id="p0060">The current study sought to contribute to the evidence base evaluating the use of resting-state EEG to distinguish PSD differences in each variant of PPA. This study builds on previous research by using relative PSD in the delta, theta, alpha, and beta frequency bands as input to a CNN for classification of PPA vs. healthy controls and four-way classification of healthy controls, svPPA, lvPPA, and nfvPPA. In addition, in previous research it was not always clear whether resting state data were collected in eyes open or eyes closed conditions. Some research suggests that differences exist in resting state eyes open versus closed conditions, even in the absence of visual input (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Boytsova and Danko, 2010</xref>). Thus, in the current study, both eyes open and eyes closed resting stage data were collected and reported. Based on the findings in previous research using resting-state EEG, we expected to see a difference in PSD between individuals with PPA and healthy controls within the delta, theta, alpha, and beta frequency bands. We further hypothesized that there would be discernible oscillatory changes in each variant of PPA, facilitating CNN classification. We did not have specific predictions regrading differences between eyes open and eyes closed conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Material and methods</title><p id="p0065"><bold><italic>2.1. Participants</italic></bold><italic>.</italic> Data were collected at the Aphasia Research and Treatment Lab at the University of Texas at Austin. Participants with PPA were recruited through a larger clinical trial of speech-language interventions in PPA (NCT04881617). The control participants were either care partners of the PPA participants or were recruited from the Austin, TX community or by word-of-mouth. Thirty-seven participants with PPA (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14 lvPPA, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11 nfvPPA, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12 svPPA) and nine age- and education-matched controls participated in this study. Participants with PPA met diagnostic criteria for PPA and for PPA subtype (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gorno-Tempini et al., 2011</xref>) as determined by a comprehensive neurological, neuropsychological, and cognitive-linguistic assessment (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Gorno-Tempini et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kramer et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Knopman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Staffaroni et al., 2019</xref>). This assessment was designed to probe general cognitive-linguistic function (e.g., Mini Mental State Exam) and each of the domains needed for differential diagnosis of the three PPA variants (e.g., single word retrieval [Boston Naming Test], single word comprehension [Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test], syntactic processing [Northwestern Anagram Test, Syntax Comprehension], phonological short-term memory [Western Aphasia Battery-Repetition], apraxia of speech [AOS rating]). Participants with PPA were in the mild to moderate stages of PPA progression. Demographic information and results of neuropsychological testing are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. This study was approved by the University of Texas at Austin Institutional Review Board and written informed consent was obtained for all participants. Control participants were compensated $15/hour for their time in the study.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic information for each participant group.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>HC (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9)</th><th>svPPA (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12)</th><th>lvPPA (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14)</th><th>nfvPPA (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Hearing Thresholds (Pure Tone Average)</td><td align="left">22.2 (12.2)</td><td align="left">30.1 (19.4)</td><td align="left">19.1 (7.2)</td><td align="left">29.3 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex</td><td align="left">8F/1M</td><td align="left">6F/6M</td><td align="left">9F/5M</td><td align="left">3F/8M</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">67.4 (6.3)</td><td align="left">65.6 (8.0)</td><td align="left">67.9 (8.2)</td><td align="left">68.6 (8.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education (years)</td><td align="left">15.6 (2.2)</td><td align="left">16.4 (3.0)</td><td align="left">16.2 (2.2)</td><td align="left">16.1 (2.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Notes: Pure Tone Average (air conduction) across both ears at 500, 1000, 2000, and 4000&#x000a0;Hz, M&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Male, F = Female. The mean (standard deviation) for each group is reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Results from cognitive-neuropsychological assessment for each PPA variant. Brackets indicate the total possible score on a test.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>svPPA</th><th>lvPPA</th><th>nfvPPA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">MMSE [30]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">24.67 (3.03)</td><td align="char">23.71 (3.2)</td><td align="char">27.91 (1.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">California Verbal Learning Test Total [36]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">14.17 (8.67)<xref rid="tbl2fng" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="char">9.92 (8.53)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">24.82 (4.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">California Verbal Learning Test Recall [9]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">1.91 (1.87)<xref rid="tbl2fng" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="char">3.15 (2.79)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">6.82 (1.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Complex Figure Copy [17]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">16.45 (0.69)<xref rid="tbl2fng" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="char">15.07 (2.34)</td><td align="char">14 (3.52)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Complex Figure Recall [17]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">11.27 (3.20)&#x02217;</td><td align="char">8.85 (3.46)</td><td align="char">11.18 (3.79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Forward Digit Span<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">6.50 (1.24)</td><td align="char">4.29 (0.91)</td><td align="char">5.36 (0.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Backward Digit Span<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">5.08 (1.38)</td><td align="char">3.21 (0.80)</td><td align="char">3.36 (0.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test [16]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">9.64 (2.62)<xref rid="tbl2fng" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="char">14.69 (1.80)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">14.91 (1.22)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal Fluency (Letter-D)<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">6.58 (3.34)</td><td align="char">6.83 (3.30)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">5.27 (2.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal Fluency (Category-Animals)<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">6.50 (2.94)</td><td align="char">9.42 (3.92)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">11.27 (3.88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Western Aphasia Battery-Revised Aphasia Quotient [100]<xref rid="tbl2fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char">84.94 (7.02)</td><td align="char">82.77 (5.01)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">86.99 (5.71)<xref rid="tbl2fni" ref-type="table-fn">i</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Western Aphasia Battery-Revised Repetition [100]<xref rid="tbl2fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="char">92.00 (5.03)</td><td align="char">72.50 (10.53)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">89.60 (5.46)<xref rid="tbl2fni" ref-type="table-fn">i</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pyramid &#x00026; Palm Trees: Pictures [svPPA/lvPPA: 52; nfvPPA: 14 or 25]<xref rid="tbl2fnc" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td align="char">41.83 (6.58)</td><td align="char">47.67 (2.64)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">14.00 (0.00)/24.00 (1.00)<xref rid="tbl2fni" ref-type="table-fn">i</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Boston Naming Test [svPPA/lvPPA: 60; nfvPPA: 30]<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">13.08 (9.02)</td><td align="char">33.17 (14.94)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">19.00 (5.74)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Syntax Comprehension [100]<xref rid="tbl2fnd" ref-type="table-fn">d</xref></td><td align="char">98.16 (2.53)<xref rid="tbl2fng" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="char">88.52 (8.30)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">26.18 (3.84)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NAT [100]<xref rid="tbl2fne" ref-type="table-fn">e</xref></td><td align="char">79.70 (26.27)<xref rid="tbl2fng" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="char">68.75 (23.06)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">90.44 (8.39)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AOS Rating<xref rid="tbl2fnf" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td><td align="char">0.00 (0.00)</td><td align="char">0.08 (0.28)<xref rid="tbl2fnh" ref-type="table-fn">h</xref></td><td align="char">62.12 (18.52)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Notes: MMSE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Mini-Mental State Exam, AOS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Apraxia of Speech (0&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;no AOS, 3&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;moderate AOS, 7&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;severe AOS), NAT = Northwestern Anagram Test. The mean (standard deviation) for each group is reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">Assessments from neuropsychological battery described in <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Knopman et al. (2008)</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kramer et al. (2003)</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Staffaroni et al. (2019)</xref>. For the Boston Naming Test, the full 60-item version was only administered to individuals with svPPA and lvPPA. Individuals with nfvPPA received a shortened 30-item version.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnb"><label>b</label><p id="ntpara0020">From <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kertesz and Raven, 2007</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnc"><label>c</label><p id="ntpara0025">The full 52-item Pyramids and Palm Trees test (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Howard and Patterson, 1992</xref>) was only given to individuals with svPPA or lvPPA. Individuals with nfvPPA received a shorter version, developed by <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Breining et al. (2015)</xref> from the standard 52-items version.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnd"><label>d</label><p id="ntpara0030">From <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al., 2010</xref>). A subset of participants completed an auditory sentence-picture matching task developed by <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Lukic (2024)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fne"><label>e</label><p id="ntpara0035">From <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Weintraub et al., 2009</xref>). The full 30-item version was only administered to individuals with nfvPPA. Individuals with lvPPA and svPPA received a shortened 12-item version. Percent correct is reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnf"><label>f</label><p id="ntpara0040">Subjective clinician ratings from the Motor Speech Examination (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Wertz et al., 1984</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fng"><label>g</label><p id="ntpara0045">Of the 12 individuals with svPPA, one did not complete the California Verbal Learning Test, Complex Figure Copy and Recall, or Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test, and one did not complete the syntax comprehension or the NAT.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnh"><label>h</label><p id="ntpara0050">Of the 14 individuals with lvPPA, three individuals completed different testing batteries due to changes in the testing protocol over time. One participant did not complete the syntax comprehension or NAT. One participant did not complete the California Verbal Learning Test, Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test, verbal fluency, Western Aphasia Battery, syntax comprehension, or NAT, and did not receive an AOS rating. One participant did not complete the Western Aphasia Battery, verbal fluency, or syntax comprehension. The latter two participants also completed the 30-item version of the Boston Naming Test (correct responses&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;22 and 20) and a 25-item version of the Pyramids and Palm Trees Test (correct responses&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24 and 25). The Boston Naming Test and Pyramids and Palm Trees data are not included in the mean (standard deviation) presented in the table above.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fni"><label>i</label><p id="ntpara0055">Of the 11 participants with nfvPPA, one participant did not complete the Western Aphasia Battery. Six of the 11 participants completed the 14-item version of the Pyramids and Palm Trees and five completed the 25-item version. Separate means (standard deviations) are presented.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>EEG acquisition and procedure</title><p id="p0070">EEG data were sampled at 25,000&#x000a0;Hz using a 32-channel active electrode system (BrainVision actiCHamp, Brain Products, Gilching, Germany) with 10&#x02013;20 placement, the ground electrode at Fpz, and an average mastoid reference (TP9 and TP10). Pre-recorded instructions were presented binaurally using insert earphones (ER- 3A; Etymotic Research, Elk Grove Village, IL) via E-Prime 2.0 software (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>). Participants were instructed to sit with their feet flat on the floor and to either keep their eyes open or closed. Eyes open and eyes closed conditions alternated in pseudo-randomized one-minute intervals (closed, open, open, closed, open, closed, closed, open). We recorded eight minutes total of resting-state EEG: four minutes with eyes open and four minutes with eyes closed (note that this is twice as much resting-state EEG data as <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Dalton et al., 2021</xref>). The specific instructions that participants heard were.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>1.</label><p id="p0075">Intro prompt: &#x0201c;We will now be making some baseline recordings with your eyes open and closed. This will take us about ten&#x000a0;minutes&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>2.</label><p id="p0080">Eyes closed prompt: &#x0201c;Now let's record with your eyes closed. Sitting as you are now, simply close your eyes and relax. I'll record for one minute and then let you know when I'm done. While I'm recording, please sit with your feet flat on the floor and keep your head and body still. Ready?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>3.</label><p id="p0085">Eyes open prompt: &#x0201c;Now let's record with your eyes open. Sitting as you are now, I would like you to focus your gaze on a spot of the wall in front of you that you can see comfortably. I'd like you to keep looking at that spot while I record your brainwaves for about one minute. It's okay if you need to blink, however I need you to hold your head and body still while I record. So look at that spot and I'll let you know when I'm done recording. Ready?&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><label>4.</label><p id="p0090">Subsequent prompts for eyes open/closed are simplified versions of the above (e.g., &#x0201c;Now let's record again with your eyes closed. Sitting as you are now, simply close your eyes and relax. I'll record for one minute and let you know when I'm done. Ready?&#x0201d;)."</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>EEG preprocessing</title><p id="p0095">EEG data were preprocessed using EEGLAB 2019.1 (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Delorme and Makeig, 2004</xref>) in MATLAB 2021b (MathWorks Inc., Natick, Massachusetts, USA). Preprocessing was blinded by participant. Raw EEG data were resampled to 128&#x000a0;Hz, then filtered from one to 60&#x000a0;Hz using a non-causal, Hamming windowed-sinc FIR filter (high pass filter cut-off&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;Hz, filter order&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;212; low pass filter cut-off&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60&#x000a0;Hz, filter order&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44). Channels with activity greater than three standard deviations from surrounding channels were rejected and replaced via spherical spline interpolation; the mean number of interpolated channels for control participants was 1.4 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0&#x02013;3), for participants with svPPA was 1.3 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0&#x02013;3), for participants with nfvPPA was 1.8 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0&#x02013;3), and for participants with lvPPA was 2.0 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0&#x02013;3). Artifact subspace reconstruction (ASR) was subsequently used to suppress large artifacts (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Mullen et al., 2015</xref>). Approximately 60&#x000a0;seconds of clean data were manually identified and input as the calibration data for ASR. Lastly, independent component analysis (ICA) was performed to correct eye-movement, muscle, and electrocardiographic artifacts. ICA was performed using the infomax algorithm runica, adjusted to extract 25 components in order to meet full rank order assumptions of ICA (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>). Components were removed based on manual inspection of the time-course, topography, and power spectra of the component. The mean number of components removed for control participants was 5.2 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3&#x02013;8), for participants with svPPA was 6.7 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0&#x02013;13), for participants with nfvPPA was 5.2 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2&#x02013;10), and for participants with lvPPA was 5.4 (range&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3&#x02013;8).</p><p id="p0100">From the preprocessed data, PSD was computed using the pmtm function in MATLAB 2021b with a time-half bandwidth product of 4. Relative power was then extracted for the delta (1&#x02013;4&#x000a0;Hz), theta (4&#x02013;8&#x000a0;Hz), alpha (8&#x02013;12&#x000a0;Hz), and beta (12&#x02013;30&#x000a0;Hz) bands for further analysis. Of note, several previous studies examined combined delta and theta bands rather than evaluating delta and theta separately. Thus, as a complement to our separate delta and theta analyses, we also ran analyses with a combined delta-theta band. The results for the combined delta-theta band are presented in Supplementary Materials.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Data analysis</title><p id="p0105">PSD data were analyzed using linear mixed effects modeling (LMEM) in R (version 4.1.2) using the lme4 package (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bates et al., 2015</xref>). We included relative PSD as the outcome measure and group (controls, svPPA, lvPPA, nfvPPA) as the fixed effect. We included participant as a random intercept. Separate models were run for each electrode channel for each frequency band of interest and for eyes open and eyes closed conditions (e.g., Channel 1 delta band eyes open, Channel 1 delta band eyes closed, Channel 2 delta band eyes open, etc.). Data met assumptions for the use of LMEM. Electrode clusters were subsequently identified based on the magnitude of the F-statistic and spatial proximity using the spatial_neighbors and find_clusters functions (retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kutaslab.ucsd.edu/matlabmk_fn_docs/index.html" id="intref0010">http://kutaslab.ucsd.edu/matlabmk_fn_docs/index.html</ext-link>). Only electrodes where <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 were considered for inclusion in a cluster and only clusters containing more than one electrode are reported. LMEMs were then run for each cluster and pairwise post hoc analyses were conducted to identify differences across groups. The emmeans package (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Lenth et al., 2019</xref>) was used to conduct these pairwise comparisons with Tukey's family-wise correction for multiple comparisons.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>CNN architectures and leave-one-out training</title><p id="p0110">To assess the capability of a deep learning network to distinguish between classifications in both four-class (control, nfvPPA, svPPA, lvPPA) and two-class (control, PPA) problems, a leave-one-out (LOO) training approach was designed. Within this framework, data from a single participant were excluded from the training process, enabling the training of the model with the data from the remaining participants. Subsequently, the trained model predicted the classification of the left-out participant. This procedure was iterated for each participant, and the performance metrics for both the two-class and four-class categorizations were then reported. LOO training was selected rather than a standard train/validate/test split, as the latter may lead to higher or lower performances depending on the random selection of participants for each set.</p><p id="p0115">A custom CNN was developed to differentiate among participant PSD curves derived from EEG data recorded during resting state.<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref> In computing PSDs, we assessed the impact of varying EEG sample lengths (one, two, and 4&#x000a0;seconds) on the consistency of PSD estimates, observing that longer samples led to reduced within-participant variability. PSDs were calculated using the Welch method at a resolution of 1&#x000a0;Hz, producing data of size (32, 64) for each PSD sample. The gamma band was then removed by keeping only the first 30 frequency bins. Given the considerable variability in channel-wise PSDs and the limitations imposed by our dataset size, we opted for channel-averaged PSDs, thereby condensing the data to a size of (1, 30).</p><p id="p0120">Our exploration into CNN architecture was aimed towards minimizing the number of trainable parameters and implementing design choices to curtail overfitting. Each assessed CNN was constructed with a varied number of convolutional blocks. Specifically, each convolutional block consisted of a 1D convolution layer, average pooling, batch normalization, ReLU (rectified linear unit) activation, and dropout. Both dropout and batch normalization have been used successfully to prevent overfitting. Through employing 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;2 average pooling post-convolution and dense concatenation connections between each block, the receptive field of the network across PSD frequency bins was progressively broadened. Following the feature extraction architecture section facilitated by the convolutional blocks, each evaluated architecture incorporated two dense layers before the classification layer, further reducing the number of trainable parameters. The final architecture is presented in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>CNN architecture employed for classification. The only modification when comparing the two- and four-class formulations was in the final dense classification layer. CNN&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;convolutional neural network, ReLU&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;rectified linear unit activation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0125">The limited optimization of the aforementioned CNN architecture was accomplished by comparing performance outcomes across the LOO training. For each participant, all available resting-state EEG data were segmented into samples corresponding to the selected duration for each PSD calculation. The LOO CNN model was trained using the data from all other participants and then evaluated on the data from the left-out participant. The allocation of participant data into training and validation sets (60% for training and 40% for validation) was chosen to improve model generalization to novel participant data. Meticulous measures were undertaken to avert potential data leakage during the formation of LOO datasets. The determination of each participant's decoded class was based on the majority class among all decoded PSD samples. Training was executed utilizing the ADAM optimizer with a learning rate of 0.005, categorical cross-entropy loss, and a batch size of 32.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Power spectral density (PSD) analyses</title><p id="p0130">Spectral power plots for each participant group for a subset of electrodes are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figs. 8&#x02013;16</xref>. Each plot presents the mean for each group along with the individual participant data, providing information about individual participant variability. Note that these plots do not distinguish eyes open and eyes closed conditions but are intended to provide a representative view of the spectral power for each group.</p><sec id="sec3.1.1"><label>3.1.1</label><title>Cluster identification</title><p id="p0135">The results of the LMEM for each frequency band and condition (eyes open, eyes closed) are presented in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> (delta-theta is presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). Clusters were identified based on these data (i.e., the <italic>F</italic>-statistic and spatial proximity). Separate clusters were identified for eyes open and eyes closed conditions, although substantial overlap was observed across conditions. The clusters are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figs. 2&#x02013;4</xref>. Data from these clusters were used for subsequent analyses.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Topoplots of the <italic>F</italic>-statistics derived from the linear mixed effects models with power spectral density as the outcome measure and group as the predictor. Panel A is delta band, panel B is theta band, panel C is alpha band, and panel D is beta band. Results presented separately for the eyes open and eyes closed conditions.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2"><label>3.1.2</label><title>Eyes open</title><sec id="sec3.1.2.1"><label>3.1.2.1</label><title>Delta</title><p id="p0140">Clusters 1&#x02013;3 are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>. Significant differences were observed between controls and lvPPA in cluster 2 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.090, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.032, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.844, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.033), between lvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1 and 2 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.144, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0328, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.378, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.096, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.297, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.010), and between lvPPA and nfvPPA in cluster 3 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.078, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.290, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.708, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.046). In all instances, this reflected a greater relative PSD in the delta band for lvPPA (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). No other significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the delta band, eyes open condition.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the delta band eyes open condition for clusters 1&#x02013;3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the delta band eyes open condition for clusters 1&#x02013;3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Mean</th><th>Standard Error</th><th>95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.231</td><td align="char">0.028</td><td align="left">0.174&#x02013;0.287</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.321</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.276&#x02013;0.366</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.237</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.187&#x02013;0.288</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.178</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.129&#x02013;0.226</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.163</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.113&#x02013;0.213</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.253</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.213&#x02013;0.293</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.179</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.134&#x02013;0.225</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.157</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.114&#x02013;0.200</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.146</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.097&#x02013;0.194</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.227</td><td align="char">0.019</td><td align="left">0.188&#x02013;0.266</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.149</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.105&#x02013;0.192</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.160</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.118&#x02013;0.201</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2.2"><label>3.1.2.2</label><title>Theta</title><p id="p0145">Clusters 1&#x02013;4 are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>. Significant differences were observed between lvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1, 2, 3, and 4 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.108, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.769, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0027; Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.112, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.888, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.116, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.052, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001; Cluster 4: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.090, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.070, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.019), and between HC and lvPPA in cluster 3 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.100, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.031, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.206, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.013). This reflects increased relative PSD in the theta band for lvPPA compared to HC and svPPA (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). No other significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the theta band, eyes open condition.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the theta band eyes open condition for clusters 1&#x02013;4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the theta band eyes open condition for clusters 1&#x02013;4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Mean</th><th>Standard Error</th><th>95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.217</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.168&#x02013;0.266</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.268</td><td align="char">0.019</td><td align="left">0.229&#x02013;0.307</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.200</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.156&#x02013;0.245</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.161</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.118&#x02013;0.203</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.185</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.136&#x02013;0.234</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.255</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.215&#x02013;0.294</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.184</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.139&#x02013;0.228</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.143</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.100&#x02013;0.186</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.164</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.115&#x02013;0.213</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.264</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.225&#x02013;0.304</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.195</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.151&#x02013;0.240</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.148</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.105&#x02013;0.190</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 4</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.208</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.158&#x02013;0.258</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.260</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.220&#x02013;0.300</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.207</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.161&#x02013;0.252</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.171</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.128&#x02013;0.214</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2.3"><label>3.1.2.3</label><title>Alpha</title><p id="p0150">No significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the alpha band, eyes open condition.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2.4"><label>3.1.2.4</label><title>Beta</title><p id="p0155">Clusters 1&#x02013;4 are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>. Significant differences were observed between HC and lvPPA in cluster 2 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.126, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.035, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.639, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004), between lvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1, 2, 3, and 4 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.168, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.042, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;4.036, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001; Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.115, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0318, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.618, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.112, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.034, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.305, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.010; Cluster 4: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0,111 SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.030, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.720, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.003), and between nfvPPA and svPPA in cluster 4 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.093 SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.032, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.951, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.026). In cluster 1, there was a trend toward increased beta power in svPPA relative to HC and nfvPPA, though this did not survive correction for multiple comparisons (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.080 and 0.081, respectively). Overall, the findings reflected a greater relative PSD in the beta band for HC and svPPA relative to lvPPA and nfvPPA (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). No other significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the beta band, eyes open condition.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the beta band eyes open condition for clusters 1&#x02013;4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the beta band eyes open condition for clusters 1&#x02013;4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0080">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Mean</th><th>Standard Error</th><th>95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.333</td><td align="char">0.035</td><td align="left">0.262&#x02013;0.405</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.280</td><td align="char">0.028</td><td align="left">0.223&#x02013;0.338</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.340</td><td align="char">0.032</td><td align="left">0.275&#x02013;0.404</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.449</td><td align="char">0.031</td><td align="left">0.387&#x02013;0.511</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.405</td><td align="char">0.027</td><td align="left">0.350&#x02013;0.459</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.279</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.235&#x02013;0.323</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.324</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.275&#x02013;0.373</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.394</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.347&#x02013;0.441</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.408</td><td align="char">0.029</td><td align="left">0.350&#x02013;0.466</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.313</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.266&#x02013;0.359</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.345</td><td align="char">0.026</td><td align="left">0.292&#x02013;0.397</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.425</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.374&#x02013;0.475</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 4</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.366</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.316&#x02013;0.417</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.304</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.264&#x02013;0.345</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.322</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.276&#x02013;0.368</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.415</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.371&#x02013;0.459</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.1.3"><label>3.1.3</label><title>Eyes closed</title><sec id="sec3.1.3.1"><label>3.1.3.1</label><title>Delta</title><p id="p0160">Clusters 1&#x02013;4 are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>. Significant differences were observed between HC and lvPPA in clusters 2, 3, and 4 (Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.096, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.032, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.030, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.021; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.102, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.030, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.384, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.008; Cluster 4: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.088, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.028, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.172 <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.015), between lvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1, 2, 3, and 4 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.131, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.034, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.884, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002; Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.105, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.594, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.005; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.088, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.028, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.165, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.015; Cluster 4: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.083, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.025, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.279, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.011), and between lvPPA and nfvPPA in clusters 1 and 3 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.095, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.035, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.761, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.041; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.087, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.057, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.020). In all instances, this reflected a greater relative PSD in the delta band for lvPPA (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). No other significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the delta band, eyes closed condition.<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the delta band eyes closed condition for clusters 1&#x02013;4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the delta band eyes closed condition for clusters 1&#x02013;4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0085">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Mean</th><th>Standard Error</th><th>95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.211</td><td align="char">0.029</td><td align="left">0.153&#x02013;0.268</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.303</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.257&#x02013;0.349</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.208</td><td align="char">0.026</td><td align="left">0.156&#x02013;0.260</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.172</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.122&#x02013;0.222</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.145</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.0948&#x02013;0.195</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.241</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.201&#x02013;0.282</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.163</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.117&#x02013;0.208</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.136</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.093&#x02013;0.180</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.114</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.067&#x02013;0.162</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.216</td><td align="char">0.019</td><td align="left">0.178&#x02013;0.254</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.129</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.086&#x02013;0.172</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.128</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.087&#x02013;0.169</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 4</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.121</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.078&#x02013;0.165</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.209</td><td align="char">0.017</td><td align="left">0.174&#x02013;0.244</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.150</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.111&#x02013;0.189</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.126</td><td align="char">0.019</td><td align="left">0.088&#x02013;0.163</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.3.2"><label>3.1.3.2</label><title>Theta</title><p id="p0165">Clusters 1&#x02013;3 are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>. Significant differences were observed between HC and lvPPA in cluster 2 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.116, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.034, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.432, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.007) and between lvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1, 2, and 3 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.110, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.032, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.510 <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.006; Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.131, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.031, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.217, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.097, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.033, <italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.978, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.024). This reflects increased relative PSD in the theta band for lvPPA compared to HC and svPPA (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, <xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). No other significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the theta band, eyes closed condition.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the theta band eyes closed condition for clusters 1&#x02013;3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the theta band eyes closed condition for clusters 1&#x02013;3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0090">Table 7</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Mean</th><th>Standard Error</th><th>95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.202</td><td align="char">0.027</td><td align="left">0.148&#x02013;0.256</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.268</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.225&#x02013;0.311</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.195</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.146&#x02013;0.244</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.158</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.111&#x02013;0.204</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.161</td><td align="char">0.026</td><td align="left">0.108&#x02013;0.214</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.277</td><td align="char">0.021</td><td align="left">0.234&#x02013;0.319</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.192</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.144&#x02013;0.240</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.146</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.100&#x02013;0.192</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.202</td><td align="char">0.028</td><td align="left">0.147&#x02013;0.258</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.268</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.224&#x02013;0.313</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.201</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.150&#x02013;0.251</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.171</td><td align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">0.123&#x02013;0.220</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.3.3"><label>3.1.3.3</label><title>Alpha</title><p id="p0170">No significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the alpha band, eyes closed condition.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.3.4"><label>3.1.3.4</label><title>Beta</title><p id="p0175">Clusters 1&#x02013;3 are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>. Significant differences were observed between nfvPPA in cluster 2 (beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.096, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.034&#x000a0;<italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.866, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.032), between lvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1 and 3 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.103, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.034&#x000a0;<italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;3.076, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.019; Cluster 3: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.103, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.037&#x000a0;<italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.764, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.041), and between nfvPPA and svPPA in clusters 1 and 2 (Cluster 1: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.097, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.036&#x000a0;<italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.728, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.044; Cluster 2: beta&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.090, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.031&#x000a0;<italic>t</italic> (42)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.903, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.029), This reflects reduced relative PSD in the beta band for nfvPPA compared to HC and svPPA, and between lvPPA and svPPA (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, <xref rid="tbl8" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>). No other significant differences were observed for relative PSD in the beta band, eyes closed condition.<fig id="fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the beta band eyes closed condition for clusters 1&#x02013;3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl8"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Relative power spectral density in the beta band eyes closed condition for clusters 1&#x02013;3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0095">Table 8</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Mean</th><th>Standard Error</th><th>95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.326</td><td align="char">0.028</td><td align="left">0.269&#x02013;0.383</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.236</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.190&#x02013;0.282</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.242</td><td align="char">0.026</td><td align="left">0.191&#x02013;0.294</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.340</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.290&#x02013;0.389</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.357</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.307&#x02013;0.407</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.273</td><td align="char">0.020</td><td align="left">0.233&#x02013;0.314</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.261</td><td align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.216&#x02013;0.306</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.351</td><td align="char">0.022</td><td align="left">0.308&#x02013;0.395</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left"><bold>Cluster 3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>Control</bold></td><td align="char">0.279</td><td align="char">0.032</td><td align="left">0.216&#x02013;0.343</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>lvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.249</td><td align="char">0.025</td><td align="left">0.198&#x02013;0.300</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>nfvPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.248</td><td align="char">0.029</td><td align="left">0.191&#x02013;0.306</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<bold>svPPA</bold></td><td align="char">0.352</td><td align="char">0.027</td><td align="left">0.297&#x02013;0.407</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.1.4"><label>3.1.4</label><title>Summary</title><p id="p0180">The results were largely consistent across the eyes open and eyes closed conditions. Within each frequency band, similar, though not identical, clusters were identified between eyes open and eyes closed conditions (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Figs. 2&#x02013;5</xref>), and all findings were in the same direction. Consistent significant findings were observed across conditions in the: delta band, where individuals with lvPPA had greater PSD than controls and individuals with svPPA and nfvPPA; theta band, where individuals with lvPPA had greater PSD than controls and individuals with svPPA; alpha band, where no significant differences were observed in either condition; and beta band, where individuals with lvPPA had reduced PSD relative to individuals with svPPA and individuals with svPPA had increased PSD relative to individuals with nfvPPA. In the eyes open condition only, individuals with lvPPA had significantly decreased beta relative to the control group. In the eyes closed condition only, significantly decreased beta power was observed for individuals with nfvPPA relative to healthy controls. Taken together, unique patterns of PSD emerged across frequency bands in each PPA variant. Most importantly, this motivated the second part of the study, where relative PSD was used as input to a CNN developed to classify participants by PPA variant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>CNN classification of PPA</title><p id="p0185">The general CNN architecture and input formulation derived from the limited LOO optimization resulted in a 4-s derived PSD input, and an architecture with three convolutional blocks, each linked with the previous block's feature vector through dense concatenation connections, followed by two dense layers comprising 32 and 8 hidden units, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The classification of each participant was found based on a majority of classified PSD samples. The resulting recall, precision, weighted F1, and overall accuracy are reported in <xref rid="tbl9" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref> and confusion matrices are presented in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl9"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Summary of the performances obtained through the LOO training for both the four- and two-class problem formulations.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0100">Table 9</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="8">Subtype Classification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Class</td><td align="left">Recall</td><td align="left">Precision</td><td align="left">F1</td><td align="left">Weighted F1</td><td align="left">Accuracy</td><td align="left">Weighted Accuracy</td><td align="left">Chance Accuracy</td><td align="left">Weighted Chance Accuracy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td align="left">0.667</td><td align="left">0.600</td><td align="left">0.632</td><td rowspan="4" align="left">0.586</td><td align="left">66.7%</td><td rowspan="4" align="left">58.7%</td><td align="left">19.6%</td><td rowspan="4" align="left">25.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lvPPA</td><td align="left">0.714</td><td align="left">0.714</td><td align="left">0.714</td><td align="left">71.4%</td><td align="left">30.4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">nfvPPA</td><td align="left">0.455</td><td align="left">0.556</td><td align="left">0.500</td><td align="left">45.5%</td><td align="left">23.9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">svPPA</td><td align="left">0.500</td><td align="left">0.462</td><td align="left">0.480</td><td align="left">50.0%</td><td align="left">26.1%</td></tr><tr><td/><td colspan="8" align="left">Presence of Aphasia</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Class</td><td align="left">Recall</td><td align="left">Precision</td><td align="left">F1</td><td align="left">Weighted F1</td><td align="left">Accuracy</td><td align="left">Weighted Accuracy</td><td align="left">Chance Accuracy</td><td align="left">Weighted Chance Accuracy</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td align="left">0.667</td><td align="left">0.600</td><td align="left">0.632</td><td rowspan="2" align="left">0.851</td><td align="left">66.7%</td><td rowspan="2" align="left">84.8%</td><td align="left">19.6%</td><td rowspan="2" align="left">68.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PPA</td><td align="left">0.892</td><td align="left">0.917</td><td align="left">0.917</td><td align="left">89.2%</td><td align="left">80.4%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Resulting confusion matrices for the four- and two-class PPA classification. Each value in the confusion matrix represents the number of participants classified with that True and Predicted class label, with the diagonal blue squares representing correctly classified participants. The confusion matrices in the bottom panel also present model performances in a per-class perspective. The blue percentages on the bottom of each confusion matrix represent the portion of <italic>predictions</italic> of each class that were correct, whereas the blue percentages to the right of each confusion matrix represent the portion of <italic>participants</italic> that the model correctly predicted.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig></p><p id="p0190">The four-class results in <xref rid="tbl9" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref> and <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> show that, whereas classification of the control and lvPPA classes was moderately effective, the CNN model had trouble differentiating nfvPPA and svPPA. Whereas the model classified more participants with these variants as the correct variant than any other individual variant, further optimization of the model and/or feature inclusion methods may improve upon these results. The promising lvPPA classification and the two-class presence of progressive aphasia results provide support that deep learning and PSDs can be used for PPA detection as well as classification, particularly for individuals with lvPPA.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0195">Diagnosis of primary progressive aphasia (PPA) presents challenges due to the insidious nature of disease progression and subtle and overlapping clinical features in PPA variants. Extensive neurological, neuropsychological, and speech-language assessments are typically used to arrive at an accurate diagnosis, often leading to fatigue and frustration for the individuals undergoing testing (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Gall&#x000e9;e et al., 2023</xref>). Previous studies indicate that shifts in EEG power spectral density (PSD) could serve as a preclinical assessment to identify neurodegenerative syndromes before clinical criteria are met (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Rossini et al., 2007</xref>). In PPA, changes in PSD have been observed, primarily reflecting an overall slowing of neural oscillations, characterized by reduced relative PSD in the higher frequency bands, alpha and beta, and increased relative PSD in the lower frequency bands, delta and theta (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Shah-Basak et al., 2019</xref>). In the current study, we built on previous research by investigating PSD as a potential PPA biomarker across all three PPA variants. Specifically, we analyzed relative PSD in the delta, theta, delta-theta (supplementary materials), alpha, and beta frequency bands in eyes open and eyes closed resting-state conditions. Additionally, we explored the utility of these data for automated classification of PPA using a convolutional neural network (CNN).</p><p id="p0200">We observed distinct patterns of relative PSD across the three PPA variants. In lvPPA, our findings were in line with previous research: we observed a significant increase in relative PSD in the delta and theta bands and a significant reduction in the beta band, consistent with the hypothesis of oscillatory slowing (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>). This pattern was observed across the brain, in left frontal, left temporo-parietal, left posterior, posterior central, right posterior, and right frontal electrode clusters. The finding of oscillatory slowing is also in line with findings in Alzheimer's dementia (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Lindau et al., 2003</xref>), which, like lvPPA, is typically caused by underlying Alzheimer's disease pathology (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Spinelli et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al., 2019</xref>). In contrast to previous findings, we did not observe the same decrease in power for lvPPA in the alpha band. This may reflect differences in disease severity across the two samples, as the current sample tended to be relatively mild. Notably, three out of six participants with lvPPA in <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al. (2019)</xref> had Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nasreddine et al., 2005</xref>) scores of 18 or lower, indicating moderate cognitive impairment. Of relevance, previous work in Alzheimer's dementia suggests that oscillatory slowing worsens with disease progression (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cassani et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0205">For svPPA, our findings partially converged with previous research. We observed increased power in the beta band relative to participants with lvPPA and nfvPPA in the eyes open and eyes closed conditions. This was observed across the brain, in left frontal, left temporo-parietal, left posterior parietal, central, right temporo-parietal, and right frontal electrode clusters. PSD for individuals with svPPA was similar to the control participants, with the only difference being a trend toward increased PSD in the beta band in a left frontal cluster in the eyes open condition. As in the current study, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cecchetti et al. (2024)</xref> found that participants with svPPA did not differ significantly in PSD from a control group. However, they did not differ from individuals with lvPPA or nfvPPA either, unlike in the current study. In contrast to the single case study by <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kielar et al. (2022)</xref>, we did not observe the same reduction of PSD in the higher frequency bands, although we note that the participant in Kielar et al. was significantly more advanced than participants in the current study (e.g., the participant had a score of 6 on the MoCA). The finding in the current study is also partially consistent with some previous findings in frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD), which is likely to be the underlying pathology in svPPA (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Spinelli et al., 2017</xref>). <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Lindau et al. (2003)</xref> observed a decrease in PSD in the alpha and beta frequency bands (inconsistent with current findings) with no increase in the delta or theta frequency bands (consistent with current findings). In contrast, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Pijnenburg et al. (2008)</xref> found that PSD was normal in FTLD. It may be worth noting that <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Lindau et al. (2003)</xref> reported greater slowing in Alzheimer's versus FTLD relative to healthy controls, which is consistent with the findings in the current study. The slight trend toward speeding in svPPA may signify a unique feature of svPPA and should be considered in future research. We also note, however, that the findings are more consistent with what is seen in typical aging (oscillatory speeding) and FTLD than previous work in svPPA.</p><p id="p0210">For nfvPPA, the results indicate an intermediate pattern between lvPPA and svPPA. In the delta and theta bands, the degree of difference between lvPPA and nfvPPA was smaller than that between lvPPA and svPPA in both eyes open and eyes closed conditions. Differences between lvPPA and nfvPPA were observed primarily in left frontal and central electrode clusters. In the beta band, individuals with nfvPPA also displayed a pattern that was more similar to lvPPA, with a smaller difference observed between nfvPPA and lvPPA than between nfvPPA and svPPA. Differences between nfvPPA and svPPA were primarily observed in left posterior parietal, central, and right frontal electrode clusters.</p><p id="p0215">In sum, the primary findings for the PSD analyses were the replication of oscillatory slowing in lvPPA and the novel finding of oscillatory speeding in svPPA (similar to controls in the current sample). In nfvPPA, which is primarily associated with FTLD but may also be caused by other conditions (e.g., Parkinson's disease), the findings fell somewhere between lvPPA and svPPA. Taken together, this lends some support to the hypothesis that changes in oscillatory dynamics may be best explained in relation to the underlying neurodegenerative disease rather than to specific PPA variants (e.g., <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cassani et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Goossens et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Nishida et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2017</xref>). Considering that, for the most part, the three canonical PPA variants are caused by different underlying pathologies (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Spinelli et al., 2017</xref>), the findings in the current study still suggest that there is potential value in using resting-state EEG PSD for PPA diagnosis.</p><p id="p0220">The findings from the CNN provide preliminary evidence that deep learning classification using PSD as input can help to inform diagnosis of PPA. The CNN performed best on the two-class classification of PPA vs. control (F1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.851) but was still above chance for four-way classification (F1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.586). Four-way classification revealed better classification for controls and individuals with lvPPA, with relatively less effective classification for svPPA and nfvPPA. Compared to <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Moral-Rubio et al. (2021)</xref>, which is similar in scope to the current study, the confusion matrices presented in the current study are substantially better, without requiring the extraction of graph-theoretical measures or data reduction techniques that were employed by Moral-Rubio et al. We note, however, that in Moral-Rubio et al., the authors chose a train/test split, rather than a leave-one-out training approach, so the results are not directly comparable. Overall, this study provides preliminary evidence regarding the utility of resting-state EEG PSD as a PPA biomarker.</p><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Differences across eyes open and eyes closed conditions</title><p id="p0225">In previous research using resting-state EEG in PPA, it has rarely been specified whether the resting-state EEG was collected with eyes open or eyes closed. It has been suggested that differences exist between eyes open and eyes closed resting-state and that these differences are not simply due to the lack of visual input in the eyes closed condition, as differences have been observed even when comparing eyes closed to eyes open in a dark room (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Boytsova and Danko, 2010</xref>). In the current study, subtle differences were observed across the eyes open and eyes closed conditions, with differences primarily reflecting minor variations in the electrode clusters or in magnitude. The direction of the effects did not change across the two conditions. The differences in localization and magnitude may explain some of the discrepancies observed in the current study relative to previous resting-state research in PPA, although no obvious pattern emerged regarding the clustering of specific electrodes across conditions. Due to the absence of prior information about the nature of the resting-state condition, further examination of this hypothesis is not possible at this time. Given that greater test-retest reliability has been observed in the eyes closed condition (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Dalton et al., 2021</xref>), it may be the case that the findings from the eyes closed condition in the current study are the most reliable. Future work should investigate the reliability of resting-state EEG in PPA specifically, particularly for eyes-open and eyes-closed conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><label>4.2</label><title>Limitations and future directions</title><p id="p0230">As with much research in aphasia and particularly in PPA, the main limitation of the current study is the relatively small sample size (with an unequal number of participants per group). Future studies can be improved by including a greater number of PPA participants and a more equally distributed PPA sample across variants. Furthermore, investigating PPA classification relative to related disorders, such as Alzheimer's dementia, would strengthen the evaluation of the CNN's discriminative abilities. Relatedly, a comparison of each PPA variant to other forms of dementia that share pathology (e.g., Alzheimer's dementia and lvPPA) would help to discern whether the findings in the current study relate primarily to specific syndromes/patterns of brain atrophy vs. underlying disease. If the patterns are indeed better explained by underlying disease, it will also be critical to determine whether there are differences in PSD between FTLD-tau and FTLD-TDP43 proteinopathies, especially considering that both svPPA and nfvPPA have been linked to FTLD. Additionally, exploring the relationship between resting-state EEG and behavioral language measures could deepen our understanding of the deficits observed in PPA and their neural underpinnings. Finally, in the current study, the cognitive-neuropsychological evaluation indicated that all PPA participants were in mild-moderate stages of severity and clearly classifiable as one of the three canonical PPA variants. The longer-term goal of this line of research is <italic>early</italic> detection and classification of PPA and thus, an important future direction is to examine PSD in a longitudinal design from preclinical to more advanced stages. Of particular relevance, extending investigations to include prodromal PPA cases will bolster the evidence supporting resting-state EEG PSD as a potential PPA biomarker in early disease stages. It is also worth noting that the approach used in the current study may only be useful for canonical PPA variants, whereas up to 40% of PPA cases may be unclassifiable (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Sajjadi et al., 2012</xref>; although estimates typically are closer to 20%, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Utianski et al., 2019</xref>). That said, if the findings of the current study indeed extend to prodromal PPA, it would be worth considering whether resting-state EEG could be incorporated into standard clinical assessment and screening for neurodegenerative conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><label>4.3</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0235">Previous studies suggest that shifts in PSD could be an indicator of neurodegeneration and may be useful as a preclinical assessment before a disorder becomes severe enough to meet clinical criteria (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Rossini et al., 2007</xref>). Resting-state EEG is a particularly promising technique for examining PSD, as it makes neuroimaging available to patients that are precluded from other widely used forms of imaging and could be better tolerated by some patients. In the current study, unique PSD patterns were observed across three PPA variants and CNN findings suggest that PSD holds promise for PPA classification. Future work should focus on extending these findings to prodromal PPA to determine whether the patterns observed in this study will extend to the preclinical stage. Overall, this study represents a positive step toward utilizing resting-state EEG as a potential PPA biomarker.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0245"><bold>Christina Quinn:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Methodology, Conceptualization. <bold>Alex Craik:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Software, Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Rachel Tessmer:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Methodology, Investigation. <bold>Maya L. Henry:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Supervision, Resources, Funding acquisition. <bold>Heather Dial:</bold> Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Supervision, Resources, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>TOP guidelines statement</title><p id="p0250">The conditions of our ethics approval do not permit public archiving or sharing of the EEG data supporting this study with any individual outside the author team without an institutionally approved data use agreement. Please contact the corresponding author if you are interested.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0255">This was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1">National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (NIDCD F32DC016812, awarded to Heather Dial; NIDCD R03DC013403 and R01DC016291, awarded to Maya L. Henry).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0260">There are no competing interests to disclose.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maechler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>R.H.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Package &#x02018;lme4&#x02019;</article-title><source>Convergence</source><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>2</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boytsova</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danko</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EEG differences between resting states with eyes open and closed in darkness</article-title><source>Hum. Physiol.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>369</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breining</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lala</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez Cuiti&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manes</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peristeri</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsapkini</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A brief assessment of object semantics in primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Aphasiology</source><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>488</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02687038.2014.973360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estarellas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>San-Martin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraga</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review on resting&#x02010;state EEG for Alzheimer's disease diagnosis and progression assessment</article-title><source>Dis. Markers</source><volume>2018</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5174815</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cecchetti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basaia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cividini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cursi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caso</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EEG correlates in the 3 variants of primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>102</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e207993</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras-Vidal</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep learning for electroencephalogram (EEG) classification tasks: a review</article-title><source>J. Neural. Eng.</source><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">031001</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>S.G.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectral resting-state EEG (rsEEG) in chronic aphasia is reliable, sensitive, and correlates with functional behavior</article-title><source>Front. Hum. Neurosci.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>624660</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2021.624660</pub-id><comment>624660</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33815079</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makeig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EEGLAB: an open source toolbox for analysis of single-trial eeg dynamics including independent component analysis</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Methods</source><volume>134</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15102499</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gall&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitworth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Please don't assess him to destruction&#x0201d;: the RAISE Assessment framework for primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Am. J. Speech Lang. Pathol.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36763839</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep convolutional neural network-based epileptic electroencephalogram (EEG) signal classification</article-title><source>Front. Neurol.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>375</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32528398</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Schependom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gielen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyfs</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Mossevelde</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EEG dominant frequency peak differentiates between Alzheimer's disease and frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title><source>J. Alzheim. Dis.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorno&#x02010;Tempini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dronkers</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogar</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phengrasamy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cognition and anatomy in three variants of primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Ann. Neurol.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14991811</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertesz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendea</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogar</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roher</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeve</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manes</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dronkers</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenberghe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rascovsky</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopman</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesulam</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of primary progressive aphasia and its variants</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>76</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1006</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e31821103e6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21325651</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep state classification using power spectral density and residual neural network with multichannel EEG signals</article-title><source>Appl. Sci.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>7639</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Pyramids and Palm Tress: A Test of Semantic Access from Pictures and Words</part-title><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Thames Valley Test Company</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kertesz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>WAB-R: Western Aphasia Battery-Revised</part-title><year>2007</year><publisher-name>PsychCorp</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kielar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah-Basak</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Slowing is slowing: delayed neural responses to words are linked to abnormally slow resting state activity in primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>129</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2019.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31029594</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kielar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah-Basak</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrophysiological abnormalities as indicators of early-stage pathology in primary progressive aphasia (PPA): a case study in semantic variant ppa</article-title><source>Neurocase</source><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13554794.2022.2039207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35230912</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knopman</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeve</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caselli</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graff-Radford</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercaldo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of methodology for conducting clinical trials in frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title><source>Brain</source><volume>131</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>2957</fpage><lpage>2968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awn234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829698</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>J.H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>S.J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinctive neuropsychological patterns in frontotemporal dementia, semantic dementia, and alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Cognit. Behav. Neurol.</source><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14665820</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawhern</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solon</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waytowich</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lance</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EEGNet: a compact convolutional neural network for EEG-based brain&#x02013;computer interfaces</article-title><source>J. Neural. Eng.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">056013</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jelic</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S.-E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahlund</surname><given-names>L.-O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almkvist</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative EEG abnormalities and cognitive dysfunctions in frontotemporal dementia and alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Dement. Geriatr. Cognit. Disord.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566600</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenth</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerkner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herve</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Package &#x02018;emmeans&#x02019;</part-title><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demystifying signal processing techniques to extract task-related EEG responses for psychologists</article-title><source>Brain Science Advances</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26599/BSA.2020.9050018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sentence-picture matching test: ordering vs storage effects</article-title><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17605/OSF.IO/QAZ34</pub-id><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>An Introduction to the Event-Related Potential Technique</part-title><edition>second ed.</edition><year>2014</year><publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mesulam</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogalski</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieneke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geula</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigio</surname><given-names>E.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary progressive aphasia and the evolving neurology of the language network</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurol.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2014.159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25179257</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kothe</surname><given-names>C.A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojeda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makeig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>T.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cauwenberghs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time neuroimaging and cognitive monitoring using wearable dry EEG</article-title><source>IEEE (Inst. Electr. Electron. Eng.) Trans. Biomed. Eng.</source><volume>62</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>2553</fpage><lpage>2567</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moral-Rubio</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balugo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraile-Pereda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pytel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Romero</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado-Alonso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado-&#x000c1;lvares</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matias-Guiu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matias-Guiu</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of machine learning to electroencephalography for the diagnosis of primary progressive aphasia: a pilot study</article-title><source>Brain Sci.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1262</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci11101262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34679327</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasreddine</surname><given-names>Z.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;dirian</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charbonneau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.</source><volume>53</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isotani</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitaura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differences in quantitative EEG between frontotemporal dementia and Alzheimer's disease as revealed by LORETA</article-title><source>Clin. Neurophysiol.</source><volume>122</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1718</fpage><lpage>1725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21396882</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pijnenburg</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strijers</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>vd Made</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Flier</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheltens</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stam</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of resting-state EEG functional connectivity in frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title><source>Clin. Neurophysiol.</source><volume>119</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1732</fpage><lpage>1738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18490193</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranasinghe</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinkley</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beagle</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuiri</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Honma</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandelli</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>La</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boxer</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houde</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vossel</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct spatiotemporal patterns of neuronal functional connectivity in primary progressive aphasia variants</article-title><source>Brain</source><volume>140</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>2737</fpage><lpage>2751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awx217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28969381</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babiloni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical neurophysiology of aging brain: from normal aging to neurodegeneration</article-title><source>Prog. Neurobiol.</source><volume>83</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2007.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17870229</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banville</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faubert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep learning-based electroencephalography analysis: a systematic review</article-title><source>J. Neural. Eng.</source><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">051001</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sajjadi</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nestor</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary progressive aphasia: a tale of two syndromes and the rest</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>78</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1670</fpage><lpage>1677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22573633</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eschman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuccolotto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>E-prime User's Guide</part-title><year>2012</year><publisher-name>Psychology Software Tools, Inc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Pittsburgh</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah&#x02010;Basak</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kielar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoeff</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous oscillatory markers of cognitive status in two forms of dementia</article-title><source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source><volume>40</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1594</fpage><lpage>1607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30421472</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandelli</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos&#x02010;Santos</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosta</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinberg</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Comi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinovici</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorno&#x02010;Tempini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Typical and atypical pathology in primary progressive aphasia variants</article-title><source>Ann. Neurol.</source><volume>81</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28133816</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staffaroni</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljubenkov</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobigo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olney</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elahi</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopman</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickerson</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeve</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinberg</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal multimodal imaging and clinical endpoints for frontotemporal dementia clinical trials</article-title><source>Brain</source><volume>142</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awy319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30698757</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Utianski</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botha</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and neuroimaging characteristics of clinically unclassifiable primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Brain Lang.</source><volume>197</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104676</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesulam</surname><given-names>M.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieneke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rademaker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogalski</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The northwestern Anagram test: measuring sentence production in primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Am. J. Alzheimer's Dis. Other Dementias</source><volume>24</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1533317509343104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertz</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>LaPointe</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenbek</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title><italic>Apraxia Of Speech in Adults: the Disorder and i</italic>ts M<italic>anagement</italic></part-title><year>1984</year><publisher-name>Grune and Stratton</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Besbris</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogar</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dronkers</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarrold</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Connected speech production in three variants of primary progressive aphasia</article-title><source>Brain</source><volume>133</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>2069</fpage><lpage>2088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awq129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20542982</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0270">The following is the Supplementary data to this article.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0010"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0010">Data sharing requires a Data Use Agreement.</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0265">This material is based upon work done as part of the Advanced Fellowship in Geriatrics supported by the US Department of Veterans Affairs Office of Academic Affiliations, the VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System, and the Department of Veterans Affairs Pittsburgh Geriatric Research, Education, and Clinical Center. The contents do not represent the views of the Department of Veterans Affairs or the United States Government. We want to thank the members of the Aphasia Research and Treatment Lab who contributed to participant assessment and care. We also wish to thank G. Nike Gnanateja for sharing his expertise and providing training on EEG data analysis methods. Most importantly, we sincerely thank our participants and their loved ones for their hard work and dedication.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0275">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ynirp.2025.100242" id="intref0015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ynirp.2025.100242</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Attempts to decode PPA variants directly from raw EEG voltage data and through conversion to covariance matrices were explored but yielded inferior performance when compared to PSD-based input formulations.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>