<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-06-17T16:33:21.984Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Promot Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Promot Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">heapro</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health Promotion International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0957-4824</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2245</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40498771</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12154209</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/heapro/daaf053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">daaf053</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Health Literacy</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Little Aussie Bugs: piloting health literacy educational resources at Early Childhood Education and Care</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5392-5195</contrib-id><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>Ruth</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Nutrition and Health Innovation Research Institute (NHIRI), School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--ruth.wallace@ecu.edu.au--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8315-5803</contrib-id><name><surname>Ruscoe</surname><given-names>Amelia</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Education, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1139-3228</contrib-id><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>Leesa</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6386-9016</contrib-id><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>Gillian</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Education, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8799-3441</contrib-id><name><surname>Sambell</surname><given-names>Ros</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Nutrition and Health Innovation Research Institute (NHIRI), School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff>
<institution>National Nutrition Network &#x02013; Early Childhood Education and Care, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>471K, 270 Joondalup Drive, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6978-6249</contrib-id><name><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Nutrition and Health Innovation Research Institute (NHIRI), School of Medical and Health Science, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff>
<institution>National Nutrition Network &#x02013; Early Childhood Education and Care, Edith Cowan University</institution>, <addr-line>471K, 270 Joondalup Drive, WA 6027</addr-line>, <country country="AU">Australia</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author. Ruth Wallace, 31.464, 270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027, Australia. E-mail: <email>ruth.wallace@ecu.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-06-11"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>daaf053</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact reprints@oup.com for reprints and translation rights for reprints. All other permissions can be obtained through our RightsLink service via the Permissions link on the article page on our site&#x02014;for further information please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="daaf053.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Building health literacy in early childhood is essential for lifelong health and underpins children&#x02019;s learning and developmental trajectories. This study assessed the efficacy of the Little Aussie Bugs books, designed to enhance health literacy in Australian Early Childhood Education and Care (ECEC) centres. The books, featuring inclusive characters and key health literacy catchphrases, were distributed to &#x0003e;1200 early learning settings Australia-wide. Exploratory research design used online surveys (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;110) and in-depth interviews with ECEC teacher participants (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;8) to determine the compatibility of the books with ECEC contexts and practices to facilitate the delivery of health literacy education. The findings were conceptualized through a socioecological lens, using the process, person, and context over time model. Participants reported high overall satisfaction with the books, alongside increased confidence to deliver health literacy messages. Key advantages included the dialogic nature of the books, children&#x02019;s familiarity with catchphrases and characters, and children&#x02019;s understanding of otherwise abstract concepts, such as &#x02018;invisible germs&#x02019;. However, these benefits were limited for less experienced educators who may not have understood the dialogic nature of the books, subsequently not utilizing them to their full capacity. These limitations indicate the need for further support to accompany the resources and maximize their impact. Further research is planned to inform the design of effective and appropriate professional learning to complement the resources, supporting educators to optimize their use of the books and promoting sustained delivery of health literacy messaging in ECEC settings.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>health literacy</kwd><kwd>Early Childhood Education and Care</kwd><kwd>dialogic reading</kwd><kwd>socioecological lens</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Nutrition and Health Innovation Research Institute</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>School of Medical &#x00026; Health Science</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Edith Cowan University</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001798</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Channel 7 Telethon Trust 2021 Approved Grant Recipient</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text position="float"><label>Contribution to Health Promotion</label><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>This article highlights the impact of the Little Aussie Bugs resources on educator confidence to deliver health literacy education.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The value of dialogic reading is promoted as an interactive tool for health education in early learning settings.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The focus is on early childhood as an important life stage to promote lifelong healthy behaviours and reduce health disparities.</p></list-item><list-item><p>We provide recommendations for optimizing the use of the resources through the development of online professional learning to build educators&#x02019; capacity.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Health literacy is a well-known yet complex concept with many interrelated determinants across multiple contexts, such as health promotion or health care, and in different settings, e.g. education or medical (<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">Van Boxtel et al. 2024</xref>). The importance of health literacy in preventing communicable and non-communicable diseases is highlighted internationally by the <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO 2022</xref>) and similarly appears in agendas for national and state level health promotion and preventative health measures (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Western Australian Department of Health 2019</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Department of Health 2021</xref>). Defined as the ability to access health services and to understand, interpret, and act upon health information (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Australian Institute of Health &#x00026; Welfare [AIHW] 2022</xref>), health literacy has been widely promoted and measured among adults (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Osborne et al. 2022</xref>). There is a limited amount of literature focussing on health literacy in young children (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000e1;nfai-Csonka et al. 2022</xref>), and as such, the WHO has, in recent years, called for renewed focus on child health literacy, particularly in early childhood (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">WHO and Okan 2019</xref>). Government data indicate approximately 17% of Australian adults feel unable to appraise health information (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">AIHW 2022</xref>), similar to &#x02018;low&#x02019; health literacy skills reported in up to 48% of a European sample (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Baccolini et al. 2021</xref>) and 36% of a US sample (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Coughlin et al. 2020</xref>). Poor adult health literacy is linked to less healthful behaviours such as lower engagement with preventative screening services and less capacity to self-manage healthcare (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Coughlin et al. 2020</xref>), leading to delayed diagnosis, treatment, and poorer health outcomes (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Aljassim and Ostini 2020</xref>). Furthermore, primary adult caregivers (e.g. parents, early childhood educators) have been shown to play an important role in developing young children&#x02019;s health literacy (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000e1;nfai-Csonka et al. 2022</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Csima et al. 2024</xref>). Health literacy developed in early childhood supports physical, emotional, and cognitive development, and behaviours learned in childhood can track into adulthood (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Csima et al. 2024</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Nash et al. 2024</xref>); hence the argument for health literacy strategies focussing on young children is clear.</p><p>Health literacy is considered an intrinsic right of the child (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Otten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>) as the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>) stipulates their right to health, health care, and education. The period from birth to age 5 years is crucial for a child&#x02019;s growth, development, and learning. During this time, children begin to grasp concepts of health, establishing a robust basis for their future educational achievements, employment, and lifelong wellbeing (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Center on the Developing Child 2023</xref>). Health literacy for children (aged 3&#x02013;18 years) has been specifically defined as &#x02018;a set of skills that involve recognizing, processing, integrating, and acting on information from a variety of platforms&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Borzekowski 2009</xref>, p. 284). For young children, this implies access to health literacy resources that provide meaningful information, alongside appropriate support to comprehend, evaluate, and apply health literacy concepts that promote lifelong healthy trajectories. Nutbeam describes health literacy as a midstream determinant of health but states that it cannot address health inequities caused by inadequate opportunity and resourcing (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Nutbeam and Lloyd 2021</xref>). That noted, providing health literacy resources in early childhood that are culturally relevant and socially supported (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Borzekowski 2009</xref>) presents an opportunity to reduce the disadvantage and inequities that emerge from social determinants (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Nutbeam and Lloyd 2021</xref>), e.g. living in poverty, which inevitably lead to poorer developmental outcomes (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">AIHW 2022</xref>).</p><p>The settings where people live, work, and play influence health literacy and how people engage with health services and systems (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">AIHW 2022</xref>). Early Childhood Education and Care (ECEC) services present an ideal setting where children can begin to learn health literacy skills and embed healthy habits (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">WHO and Okan 2019</xref>). In 2023, over 1.4 million children attended one of 14&#x000a0;528 approved early learning services in Australia (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Australian Government 2023</xref>), and globally, children can spend between 50% and 90% of the working week in such settings (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">OECD Social Policy Division 2019</xref>). Pertinent to the ECEC setting, Outcome 4 of the Australian Early Years Learning Framework [EYLF 2.0] prioritizes that children should have a strong sense of their own wellbeing (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Australian Government Department of Education 2022</xref>). Moreover, young children hold the potential to be significant &#x02018;agents of change&#x02019; by taking part in health literacy programs, where learning can extend beyond the service through partnerships with families and communities (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">WHO and Okan 2019</xref>). Therefore, teaching health literacy concepts at ECEC, where children develop their understanding of health and wellbeing through education and the social practices embedded in such settings (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Nash et al. 2024</xref>), can promote good health across communities and across the lifespan by encouraging health behaviours from a young age and combating health inequities in the longer term.</p><sec id="s2"><title>Strategic methods for building health literacy in early childhood</title><p>Exposure to health practices through familiar routines and rituals in ECEC settings presents a meaningful platform to build shared understandings of health literacy with lasting effects for children (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Degotardi et al. 2022</xref>). The National Quality Standard (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Australian Children's Education and Care Quality Authority [ACECQA] 2011</xref>) Quality Area 2: Children&#x02019;s health and safety provides regulations that aim to promote child wellbeing, including learning about healthy lifestyles, e.g. good nutrition, personal hygiene (handwashing, tooth brushing, etc.), physical activity and social and emotional wellbeing. Guidance for ECEC staff to communicate health messages with children and their families is advocated, but in practice is inconsistent as they are subject to ECEC staff interpretation of the NQS quality areas and their pedagogical expertise (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Phillips and Fenech 2023</xref>). However, building health literacy among very young children presents a unique opportunity as it occurs alongside children&#x02019;s language and literacy development and social learning. Bandura&#x02019;s social learning theory posits young children learn by observing, imitating, and modelling others&#x02019; behaviours (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">1977</xref>). Alongside this, children&#x02019;s lexical mapping of new words and phrases is rapid and complemented by shared experiences to assist approximations of meaning (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly and Kidd 2021</xref>). Importantly, <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Distefano et al. (2020)</xref> assert children require regular &#x02018;serve and return&#x02019; with an adult or a &#x02018;more capable other&#x02019; (Vygotsky cited in <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Smolucha and Smolucha 2022</xref>) to refine communication and comprehension of ideas. Utilizing pedagogical knowledge that aligns with a child&#x02019;s development is a necessary consideration in health literacy strategy design in the early years. Dialogic reading offers a suitable platform for delivering health messages with young children as they acquire and develop language in early learning settings. Furthermore, the pedagogical practice exposes children to meaningful experiences with books that support the development of pre-literacy concepts and skills needed for later literacy success (<xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Zevenbergen and Whitehurst 2003</xref>). Dialogic reading is unlike conventional text reading as it provides a democratic approach to early book &#x02018;reading&#x02019;, sharing power with the child to navigate each page at their own pace, &#x02018;read&#x02019; the visual images and build associated vocabulary in context (<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Whitehurst et al. 1990</xref>). This method is used widely to support children&#x02019;s reading development in the early years. Educators use the method reflexively to sensitively facilitate authentic, child-responsive dialogue, restating and recasting the child&#x02019;s language and approximations to clarify meaning and expand ideas (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Pillinger and Vardy 2022</xref>). Consequently, dialogic reading provides opportunities to expand young children&#x02019;s repertoire of vocabulary and phrases through repeated &#x02018;readings&#x02019; of books, effecting rapid adoption and translation of new language and concepts into familiar routines and rituals (<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Wall et al. 2022</xref>). Moreover, picture-based or story-based messages enhanced with illustrations can help support the development of health literacy in early childhood (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000e1;nfai-Csonka et al. 2022</xref>). Hence, a series of books and associated resources were developed, designed specifically for educators and the children they teach in ECEC.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>METHODOLOGY</title><sec id="s4"><title>Development of the Little Aussie Bugs books</title><p>A cross-disciplinary team of nutritionists, early years educators, health promotion and literacy experts, clinicians, and illustrators developed new educational materials to promote literacy and health literacy for children attending ECEC. In 2021, ECEC educators were consulted about preliminary character and storyline development, facilitated through discussions at professional development workshops conducted by the researchers, and their feedback informed this developmental process. Quality children&#x02019;s literature designed to support dialogic book talk with young children was a central component of the program. Notes for educators were also developed to complement the books and were situated in the inside back cover of the books, with the purpose of identifying further learning activities for educators to engage children in health literacy activities.</p><p>The characters developed were based on well-known Australian animals to appeal to young children, alongside supporting characters, namely the <bold>&#x02018;</bold><italic toggle="yes">ugly bugs&#x02019;</italic><bold><italic toggle="yes">&#x02014;</italic></bold>detrimental to health, and &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">power bugs&#x02019;</italic> promoting, e.g. good eating habits. Each book included catchphrases (some repeated across several books) to reinforce key health literacy messages (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Little Aussie Bugs catchphrases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Book title</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Storyline</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catchphrases</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When we are hungry</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mealtime at ECEC.Messages about:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>hand hygiene;</p></list-item><list-item><p>sharing healthy food;</p></list-item><list-item><p>recognizing hunger/satiety signals.</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Try it, I like it!</italic> (encouraging children to try new foods)<italic toggle="yes">1 2 3 healthy me, 4 5 6 veggie sticks</italic> (encouraging vegetable consumption)<italic toggle="yes">Bubble, bubble, bubble, rinse</italic> (encouraging handwashing before/after meals)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When we are sick</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A character is unwell and cannot attend ECEC.Messaging supports a speedy recovery:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Seeking medical assistance;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Resting;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Drinking water;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Eating healthy food.</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Try it, I like it!</italic> (to encourage children to take medicine prescribed by a doctor)<italic toggle="yes">Ugly bugs need snuggle rugs</italic> (encouraging children to rest/sleep)<italic toggle="yes">Swing your trunk, cover the gunk!</italic> (encouraging children to cover coughs/sneezes)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">My healthy tummy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focus on the digestive system. Messaging reiterates recognizing hunger/satiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Talking tummy, are you full</italic>?<italic toggle="yes">Full? Stop!</italic> (encouraging children to recognize hunger signals)<italic toggle="yes">Stinky poo, we don&#x02019;t need you&#x02019;</italic>(encouraging good toileting habits)<italic toggle="yes">Bubble, bubble, bubble, rinse</italic> (encouraging handwashing after toileting)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">My healthy teeth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral health.Messaging includes:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Tooth friendly foods;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dental hygiene:</p></list-item><list-item><p>Normalizing dental visits for preventative care</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Chew, chew, crunch, crunch, teeth love a healthy lunch</italic> (encouraging tooth friendly foods)<italic toggle="yes">Brush, brush, brush, there&#x02019;s no rush</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ready, steady, spit</italic> (encouraging dental hygiene)<italic toggle="yes">Show me your shiny smile</italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A series of four books (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) were produced to pilot the concept, characters, and storylines with educators, and their compatibility with ECEC contexts and practices to deliver health literacy education was tested&#x02014;the focus of this article.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The Little Aussie Bugs books</italic> (TM &#x00026; &#x000a9; Edith Cowan University 2025. All rights reserved) (<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Wallace and Ruscoe 2021</xref>). This figure showcases the cover design of &#x02018;The Little Aussie Bugs&#x02019; books, featuring vibrant illustrations of various Australian animals. The covers highlight the main characters, a kangaroo, koala, echidna and turtle, accompanied by the &#x02018;bugs&#x02019;. The titles are prominently displayed at the top, with the author&#x02019;s name below. The design aims to capture the attention of young readers and introduce them to the fascinating world of the Little Aussie Bugs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf053_fig1" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Introducing the Little Aussie Bugs through a PPCT theoretical framework</title><p>Given calls for a renewed focus on health literacy for young children and the well-documented value of dialogic reading (e.g. <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Murray et al. 2023</xref>), the Little Aussie Bugs book series was developed primarily for the Australian ECEC sector. Health promotion strategies that integrate socioecological principles can support capacity building, and the empowerment of individuals and communities (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Dawkins-Moulton et al. 2016</xref>). This premised the approach adopted to promoting health literacy using the books, underpinned by <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris&#x02019;s (2006)</xref> theoretical model of the mutual interrelationships amongst processes, people, and contexts, over time (PPCT). This approach considers the educator and children (person) <italic toggle="yes">before</italic> they engage in dialogic reading with the Little Aussie Bugs books (process), as well as the educator and children (person) <italic toggle="yes">after</italic> they have engaged with each other and the books (proximal processes, context) across time (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Navarro et al. 2022</xref>). This ecological model, revised from Bronfenbrenner&#x02019;s Ecological Systems Theory (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>), helps conceptualize the complexity of the process undertaken by the participants when engaging with the Little Aussie Bugs books, and the children across time.</p><p>In the PPCT model (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), Bronfenbrenner&#x02019;s ecological systems have been integrated as one quadrant within a larger framework.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Applying <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris&#x02019;s (2006)</xref> PPCT (people-place-context-time) model to health literacy practices (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Navarro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2022</xref>, p. 236; <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Tong and An 2024</xref>). This figure illustrates the interaction between various personal characteristics and proximal processes in the context of early childhood education using &#x02018;The Little Aussie Bugs&#x02019; books. The diagram is divided into four main components, including process, person, context, and time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf053_fig2" position="float"/></fig><p>The microsystem considers reciprocal interactions between people in the immediate environment, such as educators and children. The mesosystem connects processes across multiple settings involving the children, like home and early education settings. The exosystem includes processes that affect children indirectly, such as adult decision-making. The macrosystem covers broader cultural contexts, including the culture of the centre or the broader ECEC sector (<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Tong and An 2024</xref>). External factors are specifically recognized as the Australian ECEC sector is heavily legislated and mandated to support child health and wellbeing (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">ACECQA 2011</xref>), but interpretation of this legislation varies, relying on educators own pedagogical and health knowledge. Additionally, the model introduces three other important quadrants: process, people, and time. These quadrants emphasize the types of interactions, resources, and demands. Micro-time refers to continuity in interactions (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris 2006</xref>), meso-time to the frequency of interactions, and macro-time to historical events and social norms (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Navarro et al. 2022</xref>). The chronosystem represents changes over time affecting both people and their environments, highlighting the need for adaptable approaches to building health literacy in varying contexts. The aim was to build a positive shared culture of health literacy knowledge and skills, and a strong foundation for adulthood. Moreover, opportunities to extend this learning beyond ECEC to families and communities in the mesosystem exist, recognizing children also hold autonomy to impact change.</p><p>This project aimed to establish the compatibility of the Little Aussie Bugs children&#x02019;s books with ECEC contexts and practices to enable early years educators to deliver health literacy education to young children aged 2&#x02013;4 years attending Australian ECEC centre-based services.</p><p>Specifically, we sought to understand:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To what extent did educators consider the book content relevant to ECEC settings?</p></list-item><list-item><p>To what extent educators deem the books and associated resources useful for delivering health literacy messages to young children?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What reflections did early years educators have about how children interacted with the books?</p></list-item></list><p>An exploratory research approach was adopted to gather data to address the research questions. Typically, this approach examines cases where there is little to no previous data, and the phenomenon studied is a novel project where the problem has not clearly been defined (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Rendle et al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mbaka and Monday Isiramen 2021</xref>). In this instance, while the method of dialogic reading is well-established (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Murray et al. 2023</xref>), using the Little Aussie Bugs books in ECEC settings was new and unique to this study. The compatibility of the Little Aussie Bugs children&#x02019;s books with ECEC contexts and practices to promote health literacy through dialogic reading was the undefined problem (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mbaka and Monday Isiramen 2021</xref>).</p><p>Exploratory research is well placed in social sciences, and when conducted in a transparent and self-reflexive way, it is both a reliable and valid method (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Swedberg, 2020</xref>). Moreover, this approach can &#x02018;provide new and innovative ways to analyse reality&#x02019; (p. 1) and, through a PPCT lens, allowed the researcher to focus on the participants&#x02019; realities, not just their words (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Swedberg, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Navarro et al. 2022</xref>). Furthermore, exploratory research helps show how children and educators, and the Little Aussie Bugs books (through dialogic reading) interact to build a shared understanding of health literacy messages.</p><p>Ethics approval was granted by ECU&#x02019;s Human Research Ethics Committee: Approval # 2021-02462-WALLACE.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials" id="s6"><title>METHODS</title><p>Exploratory design is embedded within the qualitative paradigm; however, there are instances where quantitative methods are also introduced (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Benbrahim et al. 2024</xref>). In this study both qualitative and quantitative methods were employed, including an online survey (comprising closed and open-ended questions), followed by an optional interview. Before completing the survey, participants either attended a face-to-face instructional workshop to coach them on the use of the books, receiving a set of books as part of their attendance OR participants received a set of books without attending a workshop. Both sets of participants were asked to use the books in their early learning settings and were then invited to complete the same online survey and follow-up interview.</p><p>Purposive sampling guided the recruitment of participants (early years educators) for the face-to-face workshops based on their presence in the population of interest (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Stratton 2024</xref>), which in this case was the ECEC sector. This recruitment was conducted through the research team&#x02019;s existing networks. This subjective, purposeful sampling provided the opportunity to explore the rich and insightful examples of how educators engaged with the books and engaged children with the books (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Stratton 2024</xref>), contributing toward a knowledge base that may be useful in informing future research.</p><sec id="s7"><title>Data Collection tools&#x02014;online survey</title><p>All book recipients were invited to participate in an online Qualtrics survey, which included a participant information letter and consent statement. The online survey included closed-ended questions to gather demographic data and eight statements to ascertain the compatibility of the books with ECEC context and practices to facilitate the delivery of health literacy education and about participant perceptions of how children engaged with the books, using the scale (1) strongly agree to (7) strongly disagree. The survey also included open-ended questions about how participants used the books and how they perceived children engaged with the characters and the health messaging. In addition to being cost-effective and expedient (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Morgan and Ahmad 2021</xref>), online surveys have the additional benefit of capturing a greater number of participants. It is also acknowledged that many educators are time poor, and hence surveys were more convenient.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Data Collection tools&#x02014;interviews</title><p>Interviews are fundamental to qualitative research and consistent with the exploratory research design (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Jain 2021</xref>). They have the added advantage of providing depth of feedback and responses, which are further enriched through additional explanatory comments and opportunities for clarification. Educators who agreed to be interviewed (following their attendance at a workshop and/or interaction with the books) provided informed consent prior to the interviews, which were audio-recorded via MS TEAMS for ease of transcription. Not all educators interviewed had attended the workshops.</p><p>The semi-structured interviews were guided by an interview protocol, which allowed interaction between the researcher and participant and allowed unexpected topics to emerge and be explored (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Busetto et al. 2020</xref>). Questions explored how educators used the books at their centre, what interested them in using the books, how the children they taught with the books interacted with the characters and storylines, and the opportunity for educators to note any features they liked or disliked, including suggestions for new storylines or features.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Participant engagement with the books</title><p>In 2022, three face-to-face workshops were conducted with educators (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;28) from three Western Australia (WA) ECEC companies, purposively recruited from the researcher&#x02019;s existing networks. The purpose of these workshops was to train the educator participants on the intended use of the books prior to their use at the ECEC service. An ECE literacy expert (Ruscoe) coached the educators on dialogic reading techniques and health literacy concepts specific to ECEC and young children and their connection to early literacy was discussed. Post-workshop and once the educators had used the books at their service, they completed an online survey to determine their usability and likeability, whilst also providing the opportunity to provide examples of how the books were used and how the children engaged with the books.</p><p>Across the course of 2022/23 and simultaneous to the delivery of the face-to-face workshops, approximately 1200 book sets were distributed to all WA centre-based services, state and local libraries, and child/parent centres in the Perth metropolitan area. Convenience sampling was used as these organizations were easy to reach through publicly available information and they would have an interest in early literacy (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Greenhalgh et al. 2023</xref>). The books were also advertised to ECEC Australia-wide through our existing networks on social media. All recipients were provided with access to the same online survey as workshop attendees and invited to provide feedback once they had used the books with the children at their service.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Quantitative survey data were aggregated and descriptively analysed using Qualtrics functionality. Open-ended survey data were combined with interview data, uploaded to NVivo, and explored using codebook thematic analysis, which provided a structured coding framework building predetermined themes from the open-ended survey questions and interview guide questions (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Braun and Clark 2021</xref>). This type of analysis does not usually rely on coder consensus and inter-rater reliability as measures of quality (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Braun and Clark 2021</xref>), so during the analysis process, authors Wallace and Ruscoe included regular checks to refine codes and resolve discrepancies, resulting in the final themes: Popular catchphrases; Children&#x02019;s interactions with the &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">bugs&#x02019;</italic>; Using the books beyond &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">story time&#x02019;</italic>; and There&#x02019;s no words! Participant quotes are presented throughout the findings section of this manuscript to illustrate these themes and enhance transparency by linking the findings to the original data collected in this study. Finally, pseudonyms were used to ensure the confidentiality of interviewees.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s11"><title>FINDINGS</title><sec id="s12"><title>Survey data</title><p>Participant (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 110) demographic details are presented in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The majority were educators or educational leaders (53.5%), aged between 18 and 35 years (47.25%), female (95.5%), located in WA (59%) with more than 10 years&#x02019; experience in the sector (57.5%) and holding either a Diploma of Childcare Services or Bachelor of Education (71%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Survey participant demographic data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Age (in years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#x02013;55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56&#x02013;65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prefer not to say</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Location</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSW</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VIC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QLD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experience in the ECEC sector</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;2 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;10 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Qualifications</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working towards Certificate III Childcare Services</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Certificate III Childcare Services</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diploma Childcare Services</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor Early Childhood Education</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Role</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trainee</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">educational leader</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food coordinator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manager/Director</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Participants responded to eight statements about the compatibility of the books to ECEC context and practices (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, 1&#x02005;=&#x02005;strongly agree to 7&#x02005;=&#x02005;strongly disagree), with over 80% of participants agreeing with all statements, apart from &#x02018;increased knowledge of personal hygiene requirements&#x02019;, where only 60% of participants agreed. Of note, 76% of participants reported increased confidence to deliver health promotion messages.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Compatibility of the Little Aussie Bugs books (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;110). This figure illustrates the data collected in response to a series of questions about the compatibility of the books within ECEC context and practices.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf053_fig3" position="float"/></fig><p>Similarly, participants reported their perceptions of how children engaged with the books (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, 1&#x02005;=&#x02005;strongly agree to 7&#x02005;=&#x02005;strongly disagree). Participant responses were largely positive, as &#x0003e;80% agreed with all statements.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Participants perceptions of child engagement with books/characters (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;106). This figure illustrates the data collected in response to a series of questions about participants perceptions of child engagement with books/characters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf053_fig4" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Open-ended survey data and interview data</title><p>Eight participants agreed to provide a follow-up interview. Of the eight interview participants, five had attended a workshop. Their demographic profile mirrored that of the survey respondents. Open-ended survey data were combined with interview data for analysis. The symbol <inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig1.jpg"/> is used to indicate survey data and <inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig22.jpg"/> to indicate interview data.</p><p>Four key themes emerged from the data analysis: (1) Popular catchphrases; (2) Children&#x02019;s interactions with the &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">bugs&#x02019;</italic>; (3) Using the books beyond &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">story time&#x02019;</italic>; and (4) There&#x02019;s no words!</p><sec id="s14"><title>Popular catchphrases</title><p>The first theme examined how educators used the catchphrases, a key feature of the books intended to reinforce key health literacy messages, and how they were received and interpreted by the children they taught.</p><p>Many participants reported using the &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">bubble, bubble, bubble, rinse&#x02019;</italic> phrase, where the ugly bugs are washed away down the drainpipe to encourage handwashing. A survey participant noted: &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">The catch phrases were simple and catchy. After the first session the children initiated the repetition of them as they washed their hands! Bubble, bubble, bubble rinse!&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig2.jpg"/>).</p><p>Another commonly used phrase was &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">try it, I like it</italic>&#x02019;, with educators and children working together to adapt the phrases, combining them with others to reinforce healthy eating messages and trying new foods:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;Try it, I like it&#x0201d; we modified to &#x0201c;try it, you might like it&#x0201d; but most of</italic> [all] <italic toggle="yes">they love &#x0201c;FOOD POWER&#x0201d; and these phrases we use in our daily routine at meal times now to promote eating as we have fussy eaters. The children also use the phrase &#x0201c;full stop, if you&#x02019;re full, stop eating</italic>&#x0201d; (Tracey <inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig3.jpg"/> educator &#x02013; no workshop).</p></disp-quote><p>&#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">Swing your trunk, cover the gunk&#x02019;</italic> was the most recalled message, encouraging children to &#x02018;cover&#x02019; their sneezes and coughs. Thea (educator &#x02013; workshop attendee) recalled: &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">They enjoyed saying &#x0201c;Swing your trunk!&#x0201d; and all laughed as they pretended to be elephants as they &#x0201c;swing their trunks&#x0201d; and they all pretended to cough</italic>&#x02019; (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig4.jpg"/>).</p><p>A survey respondent noted, &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">the covering of mouth and nose has improved so that was great&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig5.jpg"/>).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Children&#x02019;s interactions with the &#x02018;bugs&#x02019;</title><p>The overwhelming response from interview and survey participants was children liked or loved the bugs, actively looked for them in the books and were interested in learning about them: <italic toggle="yes">&#x02018;The children loved the &#x0201c;power bugs&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;ugly bugs&#x0201d;. They pointed them out on each page and cheered for the power bugs&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig6.jpg"/>).</p><p>They described how children mimicked the power bugs: &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">The children really engaged with the &#x0201c;power bugs&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;ugly bugs&#x0201d;. They pretended to be the power bugs making super-hero gestures&#x02019;,</italic> understanding their different roles: &#x02018;[the children] <italic toggle="yes">understood the difference between &#x0201c;ugly bugs&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;power bugs&#x0201d; and the different roles they play&#x02019;.</italic></p><p>Survey participants described children&#x02019;s understanding of the bugs&#x02019; connection to wellness or illness:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Seeing the ugly bugs on the hands they recognised them as bad and needing to wash [</italic>their<italic toggle="yes">] hands</italic></p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">They love it and talk about it in different situations: when someone puts their hand in their mouth or when someone doesn&#x02019;t want to wash their hands or when someone didn&#x02019;t show up due to illness</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig7.jpg"/>).</p></disp-quote><p>Survey participants also talked about associating the bugs with germs, language commonly used at ECEC: &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">They understood that ugly bugs could represent germs</italic>&#x02019; and &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">drew connections to their previous germ experiences&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig8.jpg"/>).</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Using the books beyond &#x02018;story time&#x02019;</title><p>Participants described numerous ways they used the books at their service, including implementing routines at a newly opened centre, transitioning between activities, helping children understand COVID-19, and reinforcing existing practices. Some educators described activities they implemented using additional props to create learning opportunities for children.</p><p>Liam (educational leader &#x02013; no workshop) explained how &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">When we are sick</italic>&#x02019; was used at their service to help children transition from play time to mealtime:</p><disp-quote><p>&#x02026; <italic toggle="yes">they can visualise the germs and washing down the sink and they say, &#x0201c;bye germs&#x0201d;. So now we use this [book] &#x02026; moving from say, the mat session into a meal time &#x02026; So, it helps the children I think with understanding some of those abstract concepts</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig21.jpg"/>).</p></disp-quote><p>Several participants noted the books were useful to explain managing COVID-19 with children, as the books were trialled in 2022 when WA&#x02019;s borders had reopened. Molly, an experienced educator who attended a workshop explained:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Especially this time of the year, there&#x02019;s COVID going on. We&#x02019;re trying to teach the kids about &#x02026; how to keep our bodies healthy &#x02026; to keep our bodies away from germs and washing hands &#x02026; it&#x02019;s [</italic>When we are sick<italic toggle="yes">] easy to use and it&#x02019;s really hard to find good books about &#x02026; germs and how to keep our &#x02026; bodies healthy and stuff</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig10.jpg"/>).</p></disp-quote><p>Reinforcing existing practices, especially around mealtimes, was noted. For example, Tracey (educator &#x02013; no workshop) explained how she used the &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">When we are hungry&#x02019;</italic> book to promote positive mealtime environments:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">&#x02026; I try to make mealtimes as positive as possible &#x02013; like if there&#x02019;s something on their plate that they really don&#x02019;t like, I&#x02019;ll encourage them to just take a &#x02026; tiny little bit, or maybe we&#x02019;ll just put one thing on the plate at a time and we&#x02019;ll see what happens but the kids got really good conversations from this book &#x02026;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig11.jpg"/>).</p></disp-quote><p>Workshop attendees reported creating specific activities to reinforce the health messages. For example, Thea created an activity where children painted their hands with purple paint, then touched toys&#x02014;the paint representing the &#x02018;ugly bugs&#x02019;, then demonstrating how handwashing got rid of them. Others reported using props to create puppet shows or a &#x02018;Doctor&#x02019;s corner&#x02019; where children could care for sick toys, whilst educators reinforced key messages from the book, &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">When we are sick&#x02019;</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>There&#x02019;s no words!</title><p>Most participants felt the dialogic characteristics of the books (i.e. few words) were an important feature, contributing to children&#x02019;s autonomy. Two survey participants noted:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The children were very engaged with the books from the first time. I believe that the fact there isn&#x02019;t much text and simple images helped keep them more engaged</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig12.jpg"/>).</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">At times, children want to take the story telling over to point to the pictures and tell it as they want. Probably because they see there aren&#x02019;t many words on the page, so they feel more free to interpret it their way and to express it</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig13.jpg"/>).</p></disp-quote><p>Other survey participants used the books to promote discussions with children, describing them as &#x02018;tools&#x02019; to facilitate conversations and co-create stories, reporting this as more engaging because they prompted children for ideas rather than &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">just me talking</italic>&#x02019;. One interviewee described how the image-based nature of the books facilitated &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">lots of conversations&#x02019;</italic>, further elaborating:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">I showed the children</italic> [the book] &#x02026; <italic toggle="yes">and ask them what they think is going on and then we&#x02019;d have a chat about it and then we go to the next page &#x02026;</italic> [children] <italic toggle="yes">create a story themselves through the pages they could imagine what was going on &#x02026;</italic> [an] <italic toggle="yes">awesome aspect</italic> (Barbara, educator &#x02013; no workshop).</p></disp-quote><p>Tracey related to how the books: &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">gives the children opportunity for input &#x02026; lots of different ways to go with the stories &#x02026; get something different from the children every time</italic>&#x02019; (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig14.jpg"/>).</p><p>Liam alluded to how less experienced educators at his service might struggle to engage with the dialogic nature of the books, especially those with English as a second language who did not fully understand dialogic reading techniques, and subsequently: <italic toggle="yes">&#x02018;I had to sit with a few of the educators and just explain to them about how we use the resource &#x02026; some have picked it up really quickly. Others are less comfortable&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig15.jpg"/>).</p><p>Some participants referred to the absence of a written story lines in the books. For example, Lorna (educational leader &#x02013; workshop attendee) recalled their less experienced colleagues who had not attended a workshop: <italic toggle="yes">&#x02018;[the] educator mentioned that children didn&#x02019;t engage properly. She had to explain the story to children as there were limited words. She had to prompt a lot to get ideas from children&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig16.jpg"/>).</p><p>A survey participant concurred: <italic toggle="yes">&#x02018;I think the children would&#x02019;ve preferred more text. My children are strong talkers, and we used the picture prompts, covered the text, etc. But the children were done with it</italic> [the books] <italic toggle="yes">very quickly&#x02019;</italic> (<inline-graphic xlink:href="daaf053_iffig17.jpg"/>).</p><p>These findings are now conceptualized using a PPCT lens (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris 2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s18"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The Little Aussie Bugs educational resources were developed specifically for the Australian ECEC sector to support the development of young children&#x02019;s health literacy. Given effective health literacy promotion should consider bidirectional and reciprocal interactions between the educators, children, and their environment, the findings from this study are discussed using the PPCT model, considering these interactions at the micro-, meso-, and macro-levels.</p><sec id="s19"><title>Internal (micro-level) influences</title><p>In this study, micro-time examines the interactions and exchanges between educators and children (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris 2006</xref>) while reading the &#x02018;Little Aussie Bugs&#x02019; books. Specifically, the emphasis is on the strategy of dialogic reading, which in itself is reputed to support children&#x02019;s ability to retell stories (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Medeiros and Flores 2016</xref>). This is coupled with the developmentally appropriate catchphrases that through their simplicity, motivate children to engage in the &#x02018;proximal processes&#x02019; that occur between &#x02018;person&#x02019; in time and across time (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris 2006</xref>).</p><p>At the micro-level, the catchphrases proved successful in influencing children&#x02019;s knowledge, skills, and attitudes to health. The books were designed to support educators to introduce simple, memorable phrases into daily conversations with children. This repetition of phrases in continuous, but impromptu and authentic ways is consistent with young children&#x02019;s developmental level, which is considered in the &#x02018;person&#x02019; quadrant of the PPCT model (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris 2006</xref>). A typical characteristic of children&#x02019;s language development at age 2&#x02013;3 years is their use of telegraphic speech, where they move from single word &#x02018;naming&#x02019; to using simple three/four-word phrases (Australian Government, <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Department of Social Services n.d</xref>.). As these findings demonstrate, using catchphrases throughout the books made health literacy concepts accessible to young children, reinforcing ideas contextualized through images and dialogic reading. As these playful catchphrases were carefully written to align with the developmental scope of what young children could repeat during dialogic reading, they effectively invited repetition and reinforced new health literacy learning.</p><p>The use of catchphrases learned from the books enabled children and educators to then apply health literacy concepts in the &#x02018;real life&#x02019; experiences of their early learning setting. The educators&#x02019; remarked the children themselves made these connections and used the phrases spontaneously, providing evidence of their propensity to be the &#x02018;agents of change&#x02019; anticipated by <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">WHO and Okan (2019)</xref>. Reinventing prior conceptions of &#x02018;pester power&#x02019;, where children implore adults to make unhealthy choices on their behalf (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Marshall et al. 2007</xref>), in this study, the children&#x02019;s ready adoption and familiarity with healthful ideas and practices from the books &#x02018;pestered&#x02019; educators to incorporate Little Aussie Bugs concepts into daily routines and rituals. For example, catchphrases related to personal hygiene (e.g. <italic toggle="yes">bubble, bubble, bubble, rinse</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">swing your trunk, cover the gunk</italic>) were spontaneously initiated by children, the educators following their lead. Personal hygiene is particularly important at ECEC given the increased risk for children younger than 5 years of contracting acute respiratory infections (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2014</xref>) and gastroenteritis (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2016</xref>) and contributing to the spread of these infectious diseases outside the ECEC setting (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2014</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al. (2022</xref>, p. 48) found there is &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">scope for improvement in [young] Australian children&#x02019;s hygiene behaviour&#x02019;</italic>. Key infection control measures to prevent the spread of infectious diseases include frequent hand hygiene and covering coughs and sneezes (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 2020</xref>), positioning the Little Aussie Bugs books and catchphrases as an important tool for mobilizing healthy hygiene practices.</p><p>The &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">power bugs</italic>&#x02019; and <italic toggle="yes">&#x02018;ugly bugs&#x02019;</italic> were key characters in the book series and well-received by participants, who reported children were very interested in them and wanted to learn more, further demonstrating knowledge and skill construction in health literacy. Participants reported children were able to make the connection between the term &#x02018;bugs&#x02019; (from the books) and &#x02018;germs&#x02019;, a term commonly used in ECEC (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Hernandez 2020</xref>). Participants reported the &#x02018;bugs&#x02019; characters and storylines helped children to &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">visualize germs&#x02019;</italic>, and &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">understand some of those abstract concepts</italic>&#x02019;, building their understanding that, even though not visible, germs are still present and potentially harmful to health.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Interpersonal (meso-level) influences</title><p>The books were designed to support educator knowledge of health literacy relevant to the ECEC context, as they play a significant role in supporting young children to develop health literacy skills. The survey data revealed educators found the books contextual to the ECEC setting and the practices within, increasing their confidence to deliver health promotion messages. Interview responses indicated the manner in which children engaged with the books was instrumental in the formation of their views, e.g. &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">They love it and talk about it [health concepts] in different situations&#x02019;.</italic> This was indicative of <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris&#x02019; (2006)</xref> meso-time, which is the time and frequency that educators engage in proximal processes (dialogic reading) with the object (Little Aussie Book) with persons (children). In turn, the time and frequency increased educators&#x02019; confidence to deliver health promotion messages.</p><p>The catchphrases relating to healthy eating and/or mealtimes were considered relevant and appropriate by participants. In particular, &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">try it, I like it&#x02019;,</italic> was used by participants to encourage children described as &#x0201c;fussy eaters&#x0201d; to try foods new to them or those they had previously refused. The books supported educators&#x02019; endeavours to promote positive mealtimes, important as research estimates approximately 50% of young children aged 2&#x02013;5 years were perceived by their parents as &#x02018;fussy eaters&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Boswell et al. 2019</xref>) and carers (including educators) often seek support on appropriate feeding practices to alleviate this issue (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Fraser et al. 2021</xref>). The importance of a balanced, nutritious diet to support young children&#x02019;s optimal growth is well-documented (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">National Health &#x00026; Medical Research Council 2013</xref>); hence ECEC-specific resources to support healthy eating are important tools to mitigate long-term chronic disease later in life.</p><p>Educators recounted many examples of using the books beyond traditional mat-time or story time, such as transitioning between activities (e.g. playtime to mealtime) and reinforcing existing practices, such as handwashing before mealtimes. These findings highlight the ability of educators to adapt the resources to support children to build skills that &#x02018;involve recognising, processing, integrating, and acting on information &#x02026;&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Borzekowski 2009</xref>, p. 289), defining health literacy specific to young children. Moreover, these familiar routines and rituals, experienced by children in ECEC settings, provide important ways to build shared knowledge, skills, and understandings that have lasting effects for children (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Degotardi et al. 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>External (macro-level) influences</title><p>The Australian ECEC sector is legislated to support child health and wellbeing (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">ACECQA 2011</xref>), but individual and service approaches to supporting health literacy and interpretation of the resources, may be influenced by educator pedagogical and health knowledge. The findings around the dialogic nature of the books (i.e. &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">there&#x02019;s no words</italic>!&#x02019;) highlighted differing interpretations of book use dependent on educators&#x02019; attendance (or not) at the workshops where dialogic reading skills were purposefully taught. Participants who understood dialogic reading acknowledged the books allowed children to &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">create a story themselves through the pages &#x02026; they could imagine what was going on &#x02026;</italic>&#x02019;, reinforcing opportunities to expand young children&#x02019;s repertoire of vocabulary and phrases through repeated readings of books, effecting rapid adoption and translation of new language and concepts into familiar routines and rituals (<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Wall et al. 2022</xref>).</p><p>Some participants appeared not to understand the intended nature of the books, reporting &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">children didn&#x02019;t engage properly. She</italic> [an educator who had not attended a workshop] <italic toggle="yes">had to explain the story to children as there were limited words&#x02019;.</italic> Using the PPCT model to conceptualize this finding, we can see a disconnect within proximal processes where the interactions (via dialogic reading) between the educators, children, and objects (Little Aussie Bugs books) become discontinuous, inauthentic, and ultimately less effective in supporting health literacy (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Bronfenbrenner and Morris 2006</xref>). This finding indicates ongoing professional learning to accompany these new resources is essential for empowering early years educators to &#x02018;<italic toggle="yes">contribute to developing practices</italic> [i.e. building children&#x02019;s health literacy] <italic toggle="yes">that are guided by current theory and research</italic>&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Russell n.d</xref>.).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s22"><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS</title><p>Children are aware of their own health and have their own unique health experiences; hence evidence-based, age-appropriate health literacy resources are important (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Broder et al. 2017</xref>). The resources (i.e. the books) were developed specifically to build health literacy among young children by a cross-disciplinary team that consulted with child-informed end-users (i.e. the ECEC community) during this process, ensuring the product was robust, relevant, and fit-for-purpose. The PPCT model enhances theoretical merit by effectively capturing the dynamic relationships between people and their environment (<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Tong and An 2024</xref>).</p><p>The qualitative interviews and open-ended survey questions allowed rich data to be collected, enabling participants to describe their thoughts and experiences, and those of the children they teach (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Tuckerman et al. 2020</xref>), whilst engaging with the books. This study was conducted with a strong focus on trustworthiness and dependability, offering detailed, contextualized descriptions and clear explanations of the methods used. However, it is important to note the subjective nature of the qualitative methods used, as the findings are grounded in the researchers&#x02019; interpretation of the data. Moreover, the purposeful and convenience sampling techniques used, also mean the findings cannot be generalized to the wider ECEC population.</p><p>Given the many ways educators described using the books at their service, it was likely there were more examples to be harvested, so we cannot conclude saturation was reached. It is typically hard to recruit busy educators and the ECEC sector has high staff turnover (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Australian Childcare Alliance 2022</xref>), meaning some workshop participants were no longer available for interview. However, this diversity of use within the sample was indicative of the contextual transferability of the books and expertise of educators to use them responsively to the unique backgrounds and knowledge of the children in their settings.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The positive responses to the Little Aussie Bugs book design provide evidence that educators will be likely to adopt the resource in early years settings. Interview data qualified that the books do support educators to enhance health literacy skills and knowledge in early learning settings. Key advantages linked to the adoption of key health messages that were designed to align with the development of young children. This, coupled with dialogic reading processes, picture-based messages, and illustrations facilitated robust understandings of health concepts over time. At an interpersonal level, educators&#x02019; confidence to promote health literacy messages improved and they embraced the resources. They reported creative and innovative ways of using the resources to support child health and wellbeing within the program. Health-based enhancements, e.g. discussions about nutrition at mealtimes and teaching effective handwashing techniques, added value to existing routines and rituals in these settings, therefore reinforcing health literacy in everyday concepts. At a macro-level, educators understanding of pedagogical issues around dialogic reading varied, emphasizing the need for ongoing professional learning to further support their ability to help children learn about health literacy. Further research is required to explore effective and appealing methods for providing such professional learning, thus optimizing the use of the Little Aussie Bugs resources and ensuring future generations of Australian children build their health literacy for a fruitful and productive future.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="a1"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Honorary Associate Professor Marianne Knaus; the early years educators who took part in the workshops and pilot study.</p></ack><sec id="s24"><title>FUNDING</title><p>This work was supported by (a) Nutrition and Health Innovation Research Institute (NHIRI), School of Medical &#x00026; Health Science, Edith Cowan University; (b) Channel 7 Telethon Trust 2021 Approved Grant Recipient.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s251"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>No authors declare any conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s25"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available on request from the corresponding author. The data are not publicly available due to privacy or ethical restrictions.</p></sec><sec id="s26"><title>ETHICAL STANDARDS DISCLOSURE</title><p>This study was conducted according to the guidelines laid down in the Declaration of Helsinki and all procedures involving research study participants were approved by the Edith Cowan University Human Research Ethics sub-committee, School of Medical &#x00026; Health Science. Written informed consent was obtained from all subjects.</p></sec><ref-list id="r1"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Aljassim</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Health literacy in rural and urban populations: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ Couns</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>2142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pec.2020.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32601042</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Australian Childcare Alliance</collab>. <italic toggle="yes">Solving the ECEC Workforce Crisis for Cost Effective, Long-Term Benefits</italic>. <year>2022</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://childcarealliance.org.au/documents/publications/205-aca-white-paper-submission-december-2022/file" ext-link-type="uri">https://childcarealliance.org.au/documents/publications/205-aca-white-paper-submission-december-2022/file</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Australian Children&#x02019;s Education and Care Quality Authority</collab>. <source>National Quality Framework</source>. <year>2011</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.acecqa.gov.au/nqf/national-quality-standard" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.acecqa.gov.au/nqf/national-quality-standard</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Australian Government</collab>. Child care subsidy data report &#x02013; September quarter 2023. <publisher-name>Department of Education</publisher-name>, <year>2023</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.education.gov.au/early-childhood/early-childhood-data-and-reports/quarterly-reports-usage-services-fees-and-subsidies/child-care-subsidy-data-report-september-quarter-2023" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.education.gov.au/early-childhood/early-childhood-data-and-reports/quarterly-reports-usage-services-fees-and-subsidies/child-care-subsidy-data-report-september-quarter-2023</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Australian Government Department of Education</collab>. Belonging, being and becoming: the early years learning framework for Australia (V2.0). <publisher-name>Australian Government Department of Education for the Ministerial Council</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.acecqa.gov.au/sites/default/files/2023-01/EYLF-2022-V2.0.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.acecqa.gov.au/sites/default/files/2023-01/EYLF-2022-V2.0.pdf</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Australian Government, Department of Social Services</collab>. Language development in children: 0-8 years. <publisher-name>The Australian Parenting Website</publisher-name>, <year>n.d</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://raisingchildren.net.au/babies/development/language-development/language-development-0-8" ext-link-type="uri">https://raisingchildren.net.au/babies/development/language-development/language-development-0-8</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Australian Institute of Health &#x00026; Welfare</collab>. <article-title>Health literacy</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/australias-health/health-literacy" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/australias-health/health-literacy</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Baccolini</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosso</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Paolo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>What is the prevalence of low health literacy in European Union member states? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-020-06407-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33403622</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bandura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<source>Social Learning Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Redwood City</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>General University Press, Standford University</publisher-name>, <year>1977</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="http://tecfaetu.unige.ch/etu-maltt/wall-e/gosetto0/bases/mooc_motivation/ressources_motivations/bandura_sociallearningtheory.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://tecfaetu.unige.ch/etu-maltt/wall-e/gosetto0/bases/mooc_motivation/ressources_motivations/bandura_sociallearningtheory.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>B&#x000e1;nfai-Csonka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Betlehem</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deutsch</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Health literacy in early childhood: a systematic review of empirical studies</article-title>. <source>Children</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>, p.<fpage>1131</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children9081131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36010022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Benbrahim</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frichi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benabdelhadi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>The qualitative exploratory study: a necessary prerequisite to the quantitative study</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Bentalha</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alla</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds.), <source>Data Collection and Analysis in Scientific Qualitative Research</source>. <year>2024</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/979-8-3693-8689-7.ch003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Borzekowski</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Considering children and health literacy: a theoretical approach</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> &#x000a0;<year>2009</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>S282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S288</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19861482" ext-link-type="uri">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19861482</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19861482</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Boswell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davies</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Byrne</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Prospects for early childhood feeding interventions: an exploration of parent&#x02019;s concerns and acceptability towards social media intervention opportunities</article-title>. <source>Nutr Diet</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1747-0080.12502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30548377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Braun</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clarke</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>One size fits all? What counts as quality practice in (reflexive) thematic analysis</article-title>? <source>Qual Res Psychol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>328</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14780887.2020.1769238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Broder</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bauer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>U</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Health literacy in childhood and youth: a systematic review of definitions and models</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-017-4267-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28441934</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bronfenbrenner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>U.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Ecological models of human development</article-title>. In: <source>International Encyclopedia of Education</source>. Vol. <volume>3</volume>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bronfenbrenner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname>, <given-names>PA.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The biological model of human development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Lerner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name></person-group> (ed.), <source>Handbook of child psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>, <fpage>793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>828</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Busetto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wick</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gumbinger</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>How to use and assess qualitative research methods</article-title>. <source>Neurol Res Pract</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42466-020-00059-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324907</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Center on the Developing Child</collab>. What is early childhood development? A guide to the science. <publisher-name>Center on the Developing Child, Harvard University</publisher-name>, <year>2023</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://developingchild.harvard.edu/guide/what-is-early-childhood-development-a-guide-to-the-science/" ext-link-type="uri">https://developingchild.harvard.edu/guide/what-is-early-childhood-development-a-guide-to-the-science/</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <source>Water, Sanitation and Environmentally-Related Hygiene</source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/hygiene/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/hygiene/</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ford</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Healthcare utilization and lost productivity due to infectious gastroenteritis, results from a national cross-sectional survey Australia 2008-2009</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>144</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26095130</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Risk factors for acute respiratory infection in the Australian community</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e101440</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0101440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25032810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Coughlin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vernon</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hatzigeorgiou</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Health literacy, social determinants of health, and disease prevention and control</article-title>. <source>J Environ Health Sci</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>3061</fpage>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7889072/#R1" ext-link-type="uri">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7889072/#R1</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33604453</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Csima</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Podr&#x000e1;czky</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keresztes</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>The role of parental health literacy in establishing health-promoting habits in early childhood</article-title>. <source>Children</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>576</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children11050576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38790571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dawkins-Moultin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McDonald</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKyer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Integrating the principles of socioecology and critical pedagogy for health promotion health literacy interventions</article-title>. <source>J Health Commun</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10810730.2016.1196273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27668970</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Degotardi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waniganayake</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bull</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Using a multidisciplinary, multi-method and collaborative research design to investigate the health communication power of the early childhood sector</article-title>. <source>Australas J Early Child</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/18369391221120958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>National Preventative Health Strategy 2021-2030</source>. <year>2021</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/2021/12/national-preventive-health-strategy-2021-2030_1.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.health.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/2021/12/national-preventive-health-strategy-2021-2030_1.pdf</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Department of Health, Western Australia</collab>. <source>Sustainable Health Review: Final Report to the Western Australian Government. Department of Health, Western Australia</source>. <year>2019</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.health.wa.gov.au/~/media/Files/Corporate/general-documents/Sustainable-Health-Review/Final-report/sustainable-health-review-final-report.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.health.wa.gov.au/~/media/Files/Corporate/general-documents/Sustainable-Health-Review/Final-report/sustainable-health-review-final-report.pdf</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Distefano</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galinsky</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zelazo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PD.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The influence of neuroscience on early childhood education</article-title>. In: <source>Scientific Influences on Early Childhood Education</source>, pp. <fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Donnelly</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kidd</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The longitudinal relationship between conversational turn&#x02010;taking and vocabulary growth in early language development</article-title>. <source>Child Dev</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cdev.13511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33547640</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fraser</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markides</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Fussy eating in toddlers: a content analysis of parents&#x02019; online support seeking</article-title>. <source>Matern Child Nutr</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e13171</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mcn.13171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33739624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Greenhalgh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bidewell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crisp</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<source>Understanding Research Methods for Evidence-based Practice in Health</source>. <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hernandez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<source>Preventing germs spreading in preschool children</source>. Capstone Projects and Master&#x02019;s Theses, <year>2020</year>;<volume>795</volume>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://digitalcommons.csumb.edu/caps_thes_all/795" ext-link-type="uri">https://digitalcommons.csumb.edu/caps_thes_all/795</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jain</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Survey versus interviews: comparing data collection tools for exploratory research</article-title>. <source>The Qualitative Report</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46743/2160-3715/2021.4492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Marshall</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Donohoe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kline</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Families, food, and pester power: beyond the blame game</article-title>? <source>Journal of Consumer Behaviour: An International Research Review</source> &#x000a0;<year>2007</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cb.217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mbaka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isiramen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>OM.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The changing role of an exploratory research in modern organisation</article-title>. <source>IJBM</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Medeiros</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flores</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EP.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Comprehension of stories after dialogic reading with questions based on narrative thematic dimensions</article-title>. <source>Teoria e Pesquisa</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0102-3772e32ne26</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kulasinghe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morawska</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Establishing healthy personal hygiene habits with young children in Australia: a cross-sectional mixed methods study</article-title>. <source>Behaviour Change</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/bec.2021.15</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Morgan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmad</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Using online surveys to capture health and social care data</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Tilly</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group> (ed.), <source><italic toggle="yes">Health and Social Care Research Methods in Context: Applying research to Practice</italic> (Chapter 4)</source>. <publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Murray</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennings</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perry</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Effects of training parents in dialogic book-sharing: the early-years provision in</article-title> &#x000a0;<article-title>children&#x02019;s centers (EPICC) study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ECRQ</italic></source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecresq.2022.07.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nash</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cruickshank</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elmer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Global perspectives of children&#x02019;s health literacy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Nash</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cruickshank</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S</given-names> &#x000a0;<surname>Elmer</surname></string-name></person-group> (eds). <source>Global</source> &#x000a0;<source>Perspectives on Children&#x02019;s Health Literacy: Intersections Between Health, Education and Community</source>. <publisher-loc>Gewerbestrasse</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>, <year>2024</year>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>National Health &#x00026; Medical Research Council</collab>. <italic toggle="yes">The Australian Dietary Guidelines</italic>. <year>2013</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eatforhealth.gov.au/guidelines/guidelines" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eatforhealth.gov.au/guidelines/guidelines</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Navarro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stephens</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodrigues</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Bored of the rings: methodological and analytic approaches to operationalizing Bronfenbrenner&#x02019;s PPCT model in research practice</article-title>. <source>J Fam Theory Rev</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jftr.12459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nutbeam</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lloyd</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Understanding and responding to health literacy as a social determinant of health</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Public Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-090419-102529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33035427</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>OECD social policy division &#x02013; Directorate of Employment Labour and Social Affairs</collab>. Enrolment in childcare and pre-school (public policies for families and children). <publisher-loc>Paris, France</publisher-loc>, <year>2019</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.oecd.org/els/soc/PF3_2_Enrolment_childcare_preschool.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">www.oecd.org/els/soc/PF3_2_Enrolment_childcare_preschool.pdf</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Osborne</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elmer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hawkins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Health literacy development is central to the prevention and control of non-communicable diseases</article-title>. <source>BMJ Global Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2022-010362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Otten</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moltow</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kemp</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>The imperative to develop health literacy: an ethical evaluation of HealthLit4Kids</article-title>. <source>J Child Health Care</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/13674935221143883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36461891</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Phillips</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fenech</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Educators&#x02019; perceptions of Australia&#x02019;s Early Childhood Education and Care quality assurance rating system</article-title>. <source>Eur Early Child Educ Res J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>988</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1000</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1350293X.2023.2211758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pillinger</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vardy</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The story so far: a systematic review of the dialogic reading literature</article-title>. <source>J Res Read</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-9817.12407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rendle</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abramson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garrett</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Beyond exploratory: a tailored framework for designing and assessing qualitative health research</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-030123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Russell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<source>Child Care Staff: Learning and Growing through Professional Development</source>. n.d.:Layout 1. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.earlychildhoodworkforce.org/sites/default/files/2022-05/child-care-staff-learning-and-growing-through-professional-development.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.earlychildhoodworkforce.org/sites/default/files/2022-05/child-care-staff-learning-and-growing-through-professional-development.pdf</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Smolucha</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smolucha</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Vygotsky&#x02019;s theory in-play: early childhood education</article-title>. In: <source>The Influence of Theorists and Pioneers on Early Childhood Education</source>. <publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>, <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Stratton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Purposeful sampling: advantages and pitfalls</article-title>. <source>Prehosp Disaster Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1049023X24000281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38647214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Swedberg</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Exploratory research</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Elman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerring</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahoney</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds), <source>The Production of Knowledge: Enhancing Progress in Social Science</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University</publisher-name> &#x000a0;<publisher-name>Press</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>, <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>An</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Review of studies applying Bronfenbrenner&#x02019;s bioecological theory in international and intercultural education research</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1233925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tuckerman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaufman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danchin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>How to use qualitative methods for health and health services research</article-title>. <source>J Paediatr Child Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpc.14849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32281207</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>United Nations General Assembly</collab>. <source>Convention on the Rights of the Child</source>, <year>1989</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://digitalcommons.ilr.cornell.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&#x00026;context=child" ext-link-type="uri">https://digitalcommons.ilr.cornell.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&#x00026;context=child</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Van Boxtel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jerkovi&#x00107;-&#x00106;osi&#x00107;</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoonmade</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Health literacy in the context of child health promotion: a scoping review of conceptualizations and descriptions</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>808</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-17955-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38486202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wall</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foltz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Embodied action scaffolds dialogic reading</article-title>. <source>Educ Psychol Rev</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1326164" ext-link-type="uri">https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1326164</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wallace</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruscoe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<source><italic toggle="yes">The Little Aussie Bugs</italic> (A. Zappia, Illus.)</source>. <publisher-loc>Perth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edith</publisher-name> &#x000a0;<publisher-name>Cowan University</publisher-name>, <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Whitehurst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnold</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lonigan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<source><italic toggle="yes">Dialogic reading: The hear-say method&#x02014;A video workshop</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Stony Brook, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Acron Films</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source>Health Literacy Development for the Prevention and Control of Noncommunicable Diseases: Volume 4. Case Studies From WHO National Health Literacy Demonstration Projects</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>, <year>2022</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/364206/9789240055391-eng.pdf?sequence=1" ext-link-type="uri">https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/364206/9789240055391-eng.pdf?sequence=1</ext-link> (28 April 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>; <person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Okan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>&#x02026; <article-title>The importance of early childhood in addressing equity and health literacy development in the life-course</article-title>. <source>Public Health Panor</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>, <ext-link xlink:href="https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/327054" ext-link-type="uri">https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/327054</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zevenbergen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitehurst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Dialogic reading: a shared picture book reading intervention for preschoolers</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>van Kleeck</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stahl</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bauer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds), <source>On Reading Books to Children: Parents and Teachers</source>. <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>