<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40502059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12154738</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.27.656342</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The impact of background selection in mutation-selection-drift balance models of complex trait evolution</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xinyi</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>Jeremy J</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Committee on Genetics, Genomics, &#x00026; Systems Biology, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Human Genetics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2025.05.27.656342</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and build upon the material in any medium or format for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2025.05.27.656342.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P1">Over the past three decades, theoretical population genetic models and empirical analyses have elaborated on how the elimination of deleterious variants reduces variation at linked neutral sites. This process is known as background selection. However, the impact of background selection has been studied almost exclusively without reference to its effect on phenotypic variation. Here, we use population genetic theory and simulation to investigate the consequences of background selection for linked variation impacting complex traits. We find the impact of background selection on a complex trait depends on the type of selection acting on the trait, the effect size distribution, and the background selection intensity. For instance, background selection impacts a much broader range of effect sizes for traits under directional selection via a liability threshold mechanism (i.e. when selection acts on individuals with phenotypes exceeding a threshold) than when fitness decays exponentially with trait value. We also find that background selection can increase the population prevalence of a liability threshold trait (e.g. a complex binary disease trait). Furthermore, while background selection can only reduce the genetic variance of a trait under directional selection (as might be expected from the classical population genetic theory for linked neutral variants) we find that background selection can increase the genetic variance of a trait under stabilizing selection. The results presented here use a synthesis of population genetic and quantitative genetic modeling, and overall, have relevance for understand the genetic architecture and evolution of complex traits, including complex diseases.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Any mutation that impacts fitness alters the fates of other mutations to which it is linked. If the mutation is sufficiently deleterious, it will quickly be purged from the population, carrying with it linked mutations on the same haplotype. To a first approximation, this &#x0201c;background selection&#x0201d; (BGS) acts like a local reduction in the effective population size, reducing the number of mutations that enter the population every generation, and increasing their rate of drift. This, in turn, leads to a local reduction in the level of neutral genetic variation (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Hudson &#x00026; Kaplan, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">Nordborg et al., 1996</xref>).</p><p id="P3">The strength of the reduction in neutral diversity depends largely on the density of deleterious mutations relative to the local recombination rate, and is often measured via a &#x0201c;B value&#x0201d;, which estimates the size of the reduction in neutral genetic diversity in a given genomic region, relative to what would be expected in the absence of BGS (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">McVicker et al., 2009</xref>). A recent study of population genetic variation in humans estimated that BGS has reduced neutral diversity by about 17% on average across the genome (i.e. mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.83</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Murphy et al. (2022)</xref>). In Drosophila, this reduction is plausibly as high as 80% when the effects of recurrent selective sweeps are also included (i.e. mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Elyashiv et al. (2016)</xref>). The existence of broad-scale correlations between recombination rate and levels of diversity across a wide range of taxa suggests that such linked selection effects are important broadly across the tree of life (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Buffalo, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Coop, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Corbett-Detig et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="P4">It is less clear how BGS shapes variation for complex traits. At least two empirical studies have invoked BGS to explain observed patterns of genetic variation for complex traits. In <italic toggle="yes">C.elegans</italic>, <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Rockman et al. (2010)</xref> observed that loci associated with gene expression in gene-poor, high recombination chromosome arms explain significantly more variance in transcript abundance than loci in the gene-rich chromosomal centers. They interpreted this pattern as evidence that BGS has played a significant role in shaping levels of genetic variance for gene expression, and has acted similarly to how it acts on neutral variation. In humans, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Pardi&#x000f1;as et al. (2018)</xref> found that the per-SNP contribution to heritability due to common variants associated with schizophrenia is greater in regions with lower B values (i.e. stronger background selection). They argue that this is consistent with the effect of BGS, as causal variants under negative selection would be expected to segregate at slightly higher frequencies when the local effect of genetic drift is greater.</p><p id="P5">The intuition behind these explanations may be correct, but we do not currently have mathematical modeling results that address the impact of BGS on genetic variation underlying complex traits, or its impact on the distribution of complex phenotypes in the population. Previous work has studied the impact of BGS on individual variants with fixed directional selection coefficients (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Barton, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Stephan et al., 1999</xref>). We refer to models of this type &#x0201c;single-site models&#x0201d;. These results can be applied to complex traits only if we assume the sites that contribute to variation in the trait evolve independently of one another (see, e.g. <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">McVEAN and Charlesworth (1999)</xref>). However, under the most plausible models for complex traits at mutation-selection-drift balance, the strength or even the direction of selection acting on an individual allele depends on the state of all the other loci that contribute to variation in the trait. As we will show, these dependencies in turn modify the impact of BGS on complex trait loci.</p><p id="P6">Here, we consider three models of selection acting on complex phenotypes, and study how background selection alters their evolution at mutation-selection-drift balance (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). We first consider two models of directional selection which lie at opposite extremes along a continuum of possible models for directional selection on a complex phenotype. On one end of the continuum is an exponential fitness function, which causes individual variants to evolve as if under independent additive directional selection (this model therefore maps to existing results from <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">McVEAN and Charlesworth (1999)</xref> which assume that individual variants are independently selected). At the other end of this continuum is a model in which selection acts against individuals whose phenotype exceeds a physiological threshold (<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">King, 1966</xref>), with this selection pressure balanced by a mutational pressure toward the threshold. Threshold selection represents the most extreme form of synergistic epistasis (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Crow &#x00026; Kimura, 1979</xref>). Models with other forms of synergistic epistasis (e.g. <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth (1990)</xref> and <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Kimura and Maruyama (1966)</xref>), would be expected to have an intermediate behavior between these two extremes. We return to this point in Discussion.</p><p id="P7">In contrast to directional selection, it is likely that many complex traits evolve under stabilizing selection around an optimum phenotype (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, 1930</xref>; <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">Robertson, 1956</xref>; <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">Simons et al., 2018</xref>). This is supported by evidence for stasis in the fossil record over long evolutionary timescales (<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 1983</xref>), by direct measurements in both wild (<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">Weber, 1990</xref>) and human populations (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Karn &#x00026; Penrose, 1951</xref>; <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">Sanjak et al., 2018</xref>), and by an emerging argument in human genetics that the genetic architectures of the most complex human phenotypes are best fitted by a model of stabilizing selection (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Connor et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Simons et al., 2022</xref>). Stabilizing selection results in qualitatively different evolutionary dynamics than directional selection, and to our knowledge, no prior work has considered the impact of background selection in the context of stabilizing selection.</p><p id="P8">Our paper is organized as follows. We first describe the assumptions of our genotype-to-phenotype model, and our model of BGS. These assumptions are common to all three models of phenotypic selection that we consider. We then reconsider the impact of background selection on individual sites experiencing directional selection, and show how the effect of BGS on heterozygosity at these sites can be understood simply in terms of the relationship between the expected contribution to heterozygosity and the fixation rate. These results, in turn, enable our analysis of both the exponential model and the threshold model for complex traits. We conclude with the model of stabilizing selection (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Model and Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Phenotype and mutation model</title><p id="P9">We assume that an individual&#x02019;s trait (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) arises from the standard additive model of quantitative genetics (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Falconer, 1996</xref>), with both genetic and environmental components: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. We assume that the total number of sites that affect the trait is large (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), and that at each site there is a trait-increasing and a trait-decreasing allele, each of which mutates into the other type with probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> per generation. The genetic component of individual <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>&#x02019;s trait value is thus a weighted sum of contributions from the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> loci: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the effect on the trait of substituting one additional trait increasing allele at locus <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" display="inline"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of trait-increasing alleles carried by individual <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> at locus <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" display="inline"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The minimum theoretically possible genetic value is therefore zero, while the maximum is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the mean effect size. In the absence of selection, the mean genetic value at mutation-drift equilibrium would be expected to vary around a long-term average of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, reflecting the symmetry of both mutation and drift. We assume that the environmental contribution, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, is normally distributed with mean zero and variance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Background selection model</title><p id="P10">We assume the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> focal sites contributing to the trait are embedded in a recombining chromosome of length <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> base pairs (with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), with recombination rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" display="inline"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> per base pair, in which background negatively selected mutations with selection coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> arise at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> per base pair among the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> sites that do not contribute to the trait. We assume that selection against these mutations is strong (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), so that they are all quickly purged, with no chance of fixing. The impact of this background selection can be approximated as a reduction in the effective population size. Here, we present the most relevant of these results for our work in intuitive and heuristic form.</p><p id="P11">The expected frequency of the deleterious allele at each background site is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>. It follows that we expect there to be a total of approximately <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> deleterious alleles in the population at any given time. When a new mutation arises on a background carrying one of these deleterious alleles, the probability that it will be purged by linked selection before recombining onto a different haplotype depends on the distance between the deleterious allele and the new mutation. To a first approximation, mutations that arise within <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> base pairs of a deleterious allele will be purged too quickly to recombine, while those at greater distances will recombine before being purged. As a result, only a fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> deleterious alleles segregating in the population will be located close enough to the new mutation to impact it before it can recombine. As a result, the probability that a new mutation escapes immediate loss either by arising on a background free of deleterious mutations or by quickly recombining onto one, is therefore approximately
<disp-formula id="FD1">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math id="M56" display="block"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Hudson &#x00026; Kaplan, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">Nordborg et al., 1996</xref>).</p><p id="P12">Then, to a first approximation, the effect of background selection is to remove a fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of newly arising mutations. Thus, because a fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of lineages in the population are always destined for immediate loss, mutations that survive the initial cull evolve as if the population size is reduced by a factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. For simplicity, going forward we represent the effect of background selection in terms of the reduction in effective size, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>The effect of background selection on phenotypes under directional selection</title><p id="P13">As we outlined in the Introduction, we will consider two different models which result in directional selection at the phenotype level. In both cases, we find the expected change for an individual allele currently found at frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" display="inline"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is
<disp-formula id="FD2">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math id="M62" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where the selection coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> does not change with frequency (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>; <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">Milkman, 1978</xref>). In other words, each individual allele&#x02019;s expected evolution is well described by a model of additive directional selection at a single site. We can therefore rely on standard diffusion results (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Kimura, 1964</xref>), in which the strength of selection relative to genetic drift is parameterized by the population scaled selection coefficient, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. We largely assume that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" display="inline"><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="|" close="|" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula>, though we comment briefly on violations of this assumption. Finally, we also assume that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that all segregating variants have a single mutational origin (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Kimura, 1969</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Single-site additive directional selection model</title><p id="P14">As background, we begin by considering the impact of background selection on contributions to heterozygosity at a single site without an explicit complex trait model. The results we discuss here are partly our own framing of existing results due to <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth (1994)</xref> and <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Stephan et al. (1999)</xref> and partly an extension of existing results by <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Cvijovi&#x00107; et al. (2018)</xref>. These results form a helpful preface for the complex trait models we study.</p><sec id="S7"><title>Impact of BGS the on heterozygosity at sites under directional selection</title><p id="P15">We imagine tracking a single allele under directional selection with selection coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, starting with its introduction at frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" display="inline"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, and recording its total contribution to heterozygosity during its transit through the population. Under our assumption that the population scaled mutation rate is low (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), so that most sites are fixed at any one time, this quantity is proportional to the expected per site heterozygosity. Summing the per generation change in allele frequency (i.e. <xref rid="FD2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (2)</xref>) over an allele&#x02019;s transit through the population and taking the expectation, the expected total change in frequency is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" display="inline"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> is the standard &#x0201c;small s&#x0201d; diffusion approximation for the fixation probability (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Kimura, 1962</xref>), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> is the fixation probability of a neutral allele. The expected total contribution to heterozygosity for an allele with scaled coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula>, is therefore closely linked to the fixation processes, as
<disp-formula id="FD3">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math id="M74" display="block"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Kimura, 1969</xref>) where
<disp-formula id="FD4">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math id="M75" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
is the total rate of fixation per <inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> new mutations. We refer to the quantity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> as the &#x0201c;selective fixation rate&#x0201d;: it gives the rate at which derived alleles are driven to (or prevented from) fixation by selection (recall that we expect one fixation per <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> mutations due to genetic drift; i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lim</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p><p id="P16">When selection is negative, this rate is negative, reflecting the fact that negative selection prevents some or all of these neutral fixations from occurring, thereby balancing the mutational input and ensuring that the net rate of change is zero. <xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (3)</xref> conveys the fundamental link between the long-term pace of evolutionary change due to selection (the selective fixation rate in the numerator), the variance created within a population by the sites responsible for that change (the heterozygosity on the left hand of the equation), and the strength of selection (the scaled selection coefficient, the denominator). This relationship will play an important role in our understanding of the phenotypic models below.</p><p id="P17">To understand the effect of background selection in the single-site model, we apply the reduced effective size approximation to <xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (3)</xref>. We assume that only a fraction B of new mutations survive long enough to contribute anything to heterozygosity, while those that do evolve with an &#x0201c;effective&#x0201d; scaled coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that selection is less effective due to the increased rate of drift. The reduction in heterozygosity at a linked selected site <inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" display="inline"><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula> due to BGS is therefore
<disp-formula id="FD5">
<label>(5a)</label>
<mml:math id="M82" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD33">
<label>(5b)</label>
<mml:math id="M482" display="block"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref> provides two different perspectives on how background selection impacts heterozygosity at directly selected sites. <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5a)</xref> captures the effects of the two channels through which the population size impacts the heterozygosity (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). For sites under weak negative selection (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5a)</xref> says that the heterozygosity reduction due to purging of new mutations on deleterious backgrounds (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) is partially countered by the fact that each surviving mutation contributes a bit more on average (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), so that the net effect is not as large as in the neutral case. When selection is strong and negative (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), the two effects cancel (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), so there is no net effect on heterozygosity. For sites under weak positive selection (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), each mutation surviving the initial purge contributes slightly less on average (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M89" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), so the net effect of background selection is to reduce heterozygosity by even more than in the neutral case. When selection is strong and positive (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), the contribution to heterozygosity conditional on surviving the purge becomes independent of population size effects (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), so the heterozygosity is affected only by the purging of new mutations.</p><p id="P18">In contrast, <xref rid="FD33" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5b)</xref> captures the effect of background selection in terms of its ultimate impact on the long-term rate of evolutionary change via the selective fixation rates (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). The effect on heterozygosity then simply follows from the relationship between the two quantities. From this perspective, the background selection effect on heterozygosity, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M92" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, weakens as direct selection becomes more strongly negative because the selective fixation rate becomes less and less sensitive to differences in (effective) population size as selection gets stronger, plateauing to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> in the limit as all fixations are prevented and the BGS effect on heterozygosity vanishes. In contrast, as selection becomes more positive, the effect initially strengthens, as the selective fixation rate initially becomes more sensitive to differences in (effective) population size as selection becomes more positive, before ultimately plateauing again as population size effects become unimportant to the fixation probability (among a reduced number of new mutations) in the strong selection limit. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref> illustrates the diversity reduction predicted by <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref> across a range of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, in comparison to simulations.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>The impact of BGS on the frequency spectrum</title><p id="P19">We can gain some further insight by considering the effect on the frequency spectrum of segregating alleles. In the low mutation rate limit that we employ, the frequency spectrum in the absence of background selection is proportional to the expected sojourn time of an allele at a given frequency, i.e. the number of generations it is expected to spend in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" display="inline"><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> frequency interval. In the absence of background selection, this is given by
<disp-formula id="FD6">
<label>(6)</label>
<mml:math id="M96" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Bustamante et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">Wright, 1938</xref>). In the insets of <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>, we illustrate how background selection impacts the frequency spectrum using the reduced effective size approximation (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>) by plotting the expectation for the frequency spectrum under direct selection (with and without background selection) relative to the neutral expectation (that is, we plot <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> is the neutral expectation), and by plotting the expectation for the frequency spectrum with background selection relative to that without (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003be;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>). We compare these predictions to the averages obtained from our Wright-Fisher simulations of recombining chromosomes.</p><p id="P20">These comparisons help to further illustrate the fundamental results expressed by <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref>, showing how, for example, alleles under weak negative selection spend slightly more time on average at higher frequencies (and fix at a correspondingly higher rate) when background selection is acting than when it is not (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C(ii)</xref>). The other relationships expressed by <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref> across other selection regimes, which we elaborated in the preceding paragraphs, can similarly be visualized in the corresponding <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref> insets.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>The impact of BGS on low frequency variants</title><p id="P21">While the reduced effective size approximation performs well at higher frequencies, it is inaccurate at low frequencies. This is because the impact of background selection is not in fact instantaneous but takes several generations to accrue. In a model where the focal sites are neutral and there is no recombination, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Cvijovi&#x00107; et al. (2018)</xref> showed that the effect of this process on the frequency spectrum of neutral alleles can be modeled in terms of two important thresholds. In their model, the frequency spectrum resembles that in the absence of background selection at frequencies less than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> (where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the standard deviation of fitness across backgrounds), because alleles found at these frequencies are too young to have experienced much background selection. In contrast, at frequencies greater than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> the reduced effective size approximation applies, because only alleles on backgrounds free of deleterious mutations can segregate above this threshold. Between these thresholds, there is a transition between the two regimes.</p><p id="P22">In our simulations, we find that these thresholds accurately describe the transitions in the shape of the site frequency spectrum for directly selected alleles experiencing background selection in the presence of recombination, provided that we use the standard deviation in fitness across the entire recombining chromosome (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula>) to determine the lower threshold, and the local reduction in effective size (i.e. <xref rid="FD1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (1)</xref>) to determine the upper threshold. The logic behind these choices is that alleles at very low frequencies are very young, and so have not yet had an opportunity to recombine very much. As a result, they are still associated with the original haplotype they arose on over a very long chromosomal scale. The initial onset of background selection effects in the frequency spectrum therefore depends on the effects of deleterious mutations arising over this very long chromosomal scale. In contrast, alleles that manage to reach the upper threshold <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, have had more time to recombine, and are thus associated with their initial haplotype over a shorter length scale of approximately <inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> bases. The alleles whose frequencies exceed this second threshold are those that arose on haplotypes carrying no deleterious mutations within a distance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> of the focal site, and which happened to recombine away from deleterious mutations at greater distances fast enough to avoid being purged.</p><p id="P23">These thresholds also help us to understand how and when the reduced effective size approximation begins to fully break down for directly selected loci. Specifically, alleles under very strong negative selection are removed from the population without ever reaching frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>. For these alleles BGS not only has no impact on the heterozygosity and fixation rate, but also does not impact the SFS (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1A</xref>). For very strong positive selection (i.e. stronger than the effect of BGS), positive selection can drive an allele to high frequency even if it is linked to one or more deleterious alleles, so long as the net effect on fitness of the haplotype is still strongly positive. BGS effects become unimportant in this limit, so there is no effect on fixation rates, heterozygosity, or the frequency spectrum (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1B</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Phenotypic models with directional mutation-selection-drift balance</title><p id="P24">With the insights from the single-site model in mind, we now turn to models of complex trait evolution. We consider two different trait-level fitness functions that result in directional selection on individual loci, and ask how background selection impacts the equilibrium state of the population under each fitness function.</p><sec id="S11"><title>Exponential fitness function</title><p id="P25">With exponential selection, fitness declines exponentially with increasing phenotype, i.e. individual <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>&#x02019;s fitness is proportional to:
<disp-formula id="FD7">
<label>(7)</label>
<mml:math id="M111" display="block"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x0221d;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> gives the rate at which fitness declines with increasing phenotype. Assuming the scale of the phenotypic variance is small relative to the rate of fitness decay, alleles contributing to the trait evolve independently under additive selection. Alleles with phenotypic effect <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> experience a directional selection coefficient of approximately <inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that the scaled selection coefficient is
<disp-formula id="FD8">
<label>(8)</label>
<mml:math id="M115" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
For simplicity, we initially assume that all sites have the same effect size. If the population size, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the rate of fitness-decay as a function of the phenotype, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, remain fixed over long timescales, then fixations of trait-increasing and trait-decreasing mutations eventually reach a detailed balance. Because we assume the population scaled mutation rate is low (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), most sites are fixed at any one time, and the mean phenotype of the population is well approximated by
<disp-formula id="FD9">
<label>(9)</label>
<mml:math id="M119" display="block"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where
<disp-formula id="FD10">
<label>(10)</label>
<mml:math id="M120" display="block"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
is the fraction of sites fixed for the trait-increasing allele at equilibrium. If selection is absent, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, as sites fix with equal probability at equilibrium. If selection is weak (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), some sites are expected to be fixed in both states but with a bias against deleterious alleles fixing (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" display="inline"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>). If selection is strong, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M124" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, because deleterious alleles cannot fix.</p><p id="P26">The total genetic variance is then due to a mixture of contributions from sites where the derived allele increases the trait (these mutations originated from sites previously fixed for the trait-decreasing allele, are deleterious, and contribute <inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" display="inline"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> to heterozygosity), and those where the derived allele decreases the trait (which originated from sites previously fixed for the trait-increasing allele, are beneficial, and contribute <inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" display="inline"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>), i.e.
<disp-formula id="FD11">
<label>(11)</label>
<mml:math id="M127" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
After applying <xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">equation (3)</xref> and simplifying, we find that
<disp-formula id="FD12">
<label>(12)</label>
<mml:math id="M128" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" display="inline"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tanh</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> measures the strength of the fixation asymmetry toward trait decreasing alleles, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total population scaled mutation rate across all sites contributing to the trait.</p><p id="P27">If we add BGS to the model, this leads to an increase in the fixation rate for deleterious alleles, and a decrease for beneficial alleles (see <xref rid="FD4" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (4)</xref> above). The mean with BGS is therefore
<disp-formula id="FD13">
<label>(13)</label>
<mml:math id="M131" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula></p><p id="P28">The variance, in turn, is given by
<disp-formula id="FD14">
<label>(14)</label>
<mml:math id="M132" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
so that the variance is reduced by a factor
<disp-formula id="FD15">
<label>(15)</label>
<mml:math id="M133" display="block"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tanh</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tanh</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). <xref rid="FD15" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (15)</xref> predicts essentially the same reduction in variance as <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref> does for the case when all alleles are deleterious, reflecting the fact that even weak selection creates significant fixation asymmetries, so that most new mutations are deleterious. Thus, for effectively neutral alleles in this model (i.e. those with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), the variance is rescaled by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, whereas for strongly selected sites (i.e. those with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) there is no effect. For weakly selected sites, the reduction is intermediate and changes monotonically with the scaled selection coefficient. If there is a distribution of effect sizes across sites, the magnitude of the reduction in variance for sites of each effect size follows from <xref rid="FD14" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (14)</xref> independently, given the scaled selection coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for sites of that effect size.</p><p id="P29">Due to the contrast with the threshold model that follows below, it is important to note that for weakly selected sites in the exponential model, the difference between the fraction of sites fixed for the trait-increasing allele with background selection, and that without, will be large, so long as there is a non-trivial reduction in effective size. Returning to the single-effect case for simplicity, the mean shift due to BGS, standardized by the scale of the genetic variance, is
<disp-formula id="FD16">
<label>(16)</label>
<mml:math id="M138" display="block"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
Thus, the mean phenotype at equilibrium in the presence of background selection may be well outside the range of phenotypes that are seen when it is absent.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Threshold model</title><p id="P30">In this model, an individual&#x02019;s fitness depends on whether their phenotype exceeds some threshold value, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" display="inline"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, or not. Individual <inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>&#x02019;s fitness is proportional to
<disp-formula id="FD17">
<label>(17)</label>
<mml:math id="M141" display="block"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x0221d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="double-struck">1</mml:mn><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" display="inline"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the cost of exceeding the threshold, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" display="inline"><mml:mn mathvariant="double-struck">1</mml:mn><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula> is an indicator that is equal to one if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M144" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and zero otherwise. One way to think of this model is as a model of complex disease, in which case we refer to the phenotype, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, as an individual&#x02019;s liability. Alternatively, threshold models of this form have also been used to study genetic load, in which case the underlying phenotype is sometimes called &#x0201c;fitness potential&#x0201d; (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">Kondrashov, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">Milkman, 1978</xref>). A complete analysis of this model at equilibrium is given by <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al. (2025)</xref> in the complex disease context, and we largely adopt this framing here. As with the exponential model above, it is easiest to begin by considering the case where all sites have the same effect size, which we term the &#x0201c;single-effect-size threshold model&#x0201d;. Before considering the effects of BGS in this model, it is helpful to first consider two features of the equilibrium in the absence of BGS, which were derived by <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al. (2025)</xref>.</p><p id="P31">First, the emergent selection coefficient acting on each site is approximately <inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the fraction of the population who would be pushed across the threshold by substituting one additional liability-increasing allele for a liability-decreasing one. The value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is given approximately by
<disp-formula id="FD18">
<label>(18)</label>
<mml:math id="M149" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M150" display="inline"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is the proportion of the population whose liability exceeds the threshold, or equivalently, the probability that a random individual will develop the disease, while <inline-formula><mml:math id="M151" display="inline"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> gives the same for a random individual that has had a single liability-decreasing allele substituted for a liability-increasing one. It follows that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M152" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the average effect of a liability-increasing allele on an individual&#x02019;s risk of developing the disease, i.e. its &#x0201c;risk effect&#x0201d; (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>).</p><p id="P32">If we assume that the liability effect, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, of an individual variant is small relative to the scale of the total variance in liability (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M154" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula>), then we can further approximate the risk effect as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M155" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is the density of liability at the threshold. The scaled selection coefficient is then <inline-formula><mml:math id="M157" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, in contrast to the exponential model, the selection coefficient of any given variant in the threshold model is highly sensitive to the state of the other variants contributing to liability, via the threshold density <inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Relatively small changes in the mean liability can therefore result in relatively large changes in the selection coefficient acting on each site, because they lead to changes in the threshold density <inline-formula><mml:math id="M159" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. The same is true for changes to the variance. <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al. (2025)</xref> also showed that for reasonable parameter values, the small effect approximation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, is always valid for sites under weak selection (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), and is also expected to hold for sites that belong to the &#x0201c;weak end&#x0201d; of the strongly selected regime (e.g. those with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p><p id="P33">Second, in the threshold model, the fraction of sites fixed for the liability-increasing allele is determined by the position of the threshold relative to the range of possible genetic liability values, not by the evolutionary dynamics. To see this, consider first that the fraction of sites fixed for the liability-increasing allele is approximately equal to the ratio of the mean liability to the theoretical maximum genetic liability, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref rid="FD9" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (9)</xref>). Second, when the population is at equilibrium, the mean must necessarily be within a few genetic standard deviations of the threshold (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M164" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula>). Because the per-site scaled mutation rate is low (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M165" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), the genetic standard deviation is small relative to the range of possible genetic liabilities (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M166" display="inline"><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>). This implies that the fraction of sites fixed for the liability-increasing allele is approximately
<disp-formula id="FD19">
<label>(19)</label>
<mml:math id="M167" display="block"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M168" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> measures of the relative position of the threshold along the liability continuum. It then follows from inverting the relationship between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M169" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="FD10" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (10)</xref>) that the value of the scaled selection coefficient at equilibrium is determined entirely by the relative position of the threshold, i.e.
<disp-formula id="FD20">
<label>(20)</label>
<mml:math id="M171" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
As we note in the previous paragraph, the scaled selection coefficient of small effect sites can also be expressed in terms of the threshold density, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M172" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. It follows that the equilibrium is established by evolving the correct threshold density necessary to ensure that <xref rid="FD20" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (20)</xref> holds, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M173" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>. As a result, at equilibrium in the threshold model, the genetic variance is the same as it is in the exponential model (i.e. <xref rid="FD12" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (12)</xref>), except that the scaled selection coefficient is determined by the position of the threshold (i.e. <xref rid="FD20" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (20)</xref>), rather than by the rate of fitness decline, as it is in the exponential model (i.e. <xref rid="FD8" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (8)</xref>).</p><p id="P34">Notably, because these results follow from the fixation dynamics, they apply when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that at least some sites are fixed for the deleterious allele at equilibrium, and fixations occur in both directions. This corresponds to the scaled selection coefficients of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M175" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and we can think of a single-effect-size model meeting this condition as belonging to a &#x0201c;weak selection&#x0201d; regime. In contrast, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M176" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02273;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> implies that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M177" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that there are no sites fixed for the deleterious allele. This corresponds to a strong selection regime, in which the selection coefficients are determined differently from those suggested by <xref rid="FD20" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (20)</xref>. Below, we first describe the impact of background selection in the weak selection regime, before considering the strong selection regime, and ultimately extending our analysis to include models with a distribution of effects.</p><p id="P35">To understand the impact of BGS, it is helpful to start with the effect on the mean liability, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M178" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>. In contrast to the exponential model, where the decreased effective population size due to BGS leads to a change in the selective fixation rates and thus a large change in the mean liability (<xref rid="FD16" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (16)</xref>), in the threshold model, selection against individuals exceeding the threshold prevents such a large shift. Rather, the mean must remain close to the threshold, and it follows that the selective fixation rates must remain approximately the same as they are in the absence of BGS. The increase in the rate of drift by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M179" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> must therefore be compensated by an increase in the (unscaled) selection coefficient by the same factor, i.e.
<disp-formula id="FD21">
<label>(21)</label>
<mml:math id="M180" display="block"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
The resulting scaled selection coefficient in the presence of BGS is
<disp-formula id="FD22">
<label>(22)</label>
<mml:math id="M181" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
i.e. unchanged from what it is when background selection is not acting. While the substantial shift in mean observed in the exponential model does not occur, there is still a small change in the mean liability. More precisely, to achieve the increase in the selection coefficient captured by <xref rid="FD21" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (21)</xref>, the risk effect must increase by the same factor. This is accomplished by a small shift in the mean liability toward the threshold, so that
<disp-formula id="FD23">
<label>(23)</label>
<mml:math id="M182" display="block"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
validated by our simulation results (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref>). The compensatory evolution of the mean liability also impacts the variance. It is still the case that a fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M183" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of all new mutations are removed by BGS without exceeding frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M184" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, along with their contributions to the fixation rate and the variance. However, because the scaled selection coefficient is unchanged, the changes to the rate of decay in the frequency spectrum at frequencies greater than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M185" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> do not occur. The selective fixation rates in both directions, and therefore the total heterozygosity, are just rescaled by a factor B, so the variance reduction is simply
<disp-formula id="FD24">
<label>(24)</label>
<mml:math id="M186" display="block"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
independent of the exact value of the selection coefficient. Notably, because this result follows largely from <xref rid="FD20" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (20)</xref>, we expect it to hold for the range of scaled selection coefficients for which <xref rid="FD20" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (20)</xref> holds, that is for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M187" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. This prediction is supported by our simulation results (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Impact on disease prevalence</title><p id="P36">The changes to the threshold density and variance also translate into an increase in disease prevalence. We can approximate the prevalence by assuming that the distribution of liability is Normal. With this assumption, the equilibrium prevalence can be found by standardizing the threshold density, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M188" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M189" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is a standard Normal PDF, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M190" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total variance and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M191" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> is the distance between the mean and the threshold in standardized units. The prevalence is then given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M192" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M193" display="inline"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> is the positively defined inverse of the Normal PDF, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M194" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the normal cumulative distribution function (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>). The prevalence scales close to linearly with the standardized threshold density as long as it is close to zero (which is a reasonable assumption for realistic parameter values). Thus, accounting for both the increase in the threshold density and the reduction in genetic variance due to background selection, the disease prevalence is increased in the presence of background selection approximately by a factor
<disp-formula id="FD25">
<label>(25)</label>
<mml:math id="M195" display="block"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>) where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M196" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> is the heritability in the absence of BGS (see <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary section A</xref> for a derivation of <xref rid="FD25" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (25)</xref>, and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3</xref> for an illustration). Thus, for a disease with a heritability close to zero, background selection would be expected to increase the prevalence by approximately a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M197" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, but this factor is closer to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M198" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> when the heritability is close to one. These calculations (and all others in this paper), assume a constant population size. In <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S8</xref>, we conduct a limited simulation of the single-effect-size model using a demographic history inferred by <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Gravel et al. (2011)</xref> for the 1000 Genomes sample of Northern Europeans from Utah, and find that background selection has a similar effect on the prevalence in this case as well.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Large effect sites are unaffected by background selection in the single-effect-size model</title><p id="P37">The above results depend on the assumption that the threshold is far from zero (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M199" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), so that sites are under relatively weak selection (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M200" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>). If instead we assume that the threshold is very close to zero (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M201" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), then there must be no sites fixed for the deleterious allele, and all sites will belong to the strongly selected regime (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M202" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>). In this case, BGS will have no effect on the genetic variance for liability (and consequently no effect on the disease prevalence), because BGS generally has no effect on the expected heterozygosity at sites under strong negative selection. These predictions are also supported by our simulation results (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>,<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Variation in effect sizes</title><p id="P38">So far, we have assumed that all sites have the same effect size. We now consider the extension to the case with a distribution of effects, which we denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M203" display="inline"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> (though we still assume all sites have the same B). With a distribution of effect sizes, sites with different effects will have different scaled selection coefficients, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M204" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, and therefore different fixation asymmetries, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M205" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, the fixation asymmetry for sites of a given scaled selection coefficient must still obey <xref rid="FD10" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (10)</xref>, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M206" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, while the mean phenotype is still determined by the relative position of the threshold, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M207" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Long term equilibrium is therefore achieved when the distribution of scaled selection coefficients across sites satisfies
<disp-formula id="FD26">
<label>(26)</label>
<mml:math id="M208" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>). In words, the average liability-weighted fixation asymmetry given the scaled selection coefficients must be equal to the relative position of the threshold.</p><p id="P39">If we first continue to assume that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M209" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> and we also assume that the distribution of effects is relatively narrow, then all the effect sizes will be small relative to the scale of variation in liability. This allows us to make the small effect size approximation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M210" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, across the full range of effect sizes, and we can rewrite <xref rid="FD26" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (26)</xref> as
<disp-formula id="FD27">
<label>(27)</label>
<mml:math id="M211" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>). <xref rid="FD27" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (27)</xref> shows that with a distribution of effects, the long-term equilibrium is achieved in the same way as in the single-effect-size model: by evolving the appropriate threshold density, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M212" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, given the relative position of the threshold, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M213" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. It follows that our results from the single-effect-size case also apply when there is a distribution of effect sizes. That is, the reduction in the effective population size by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M214" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is countered by an increase in the threshold density by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M215" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that the scaled selection coefficients remain unchanged across the range of effect sizes. As a result, the contribution to genetic variance is reduced by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M216" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, as in the single-effect-size case.</p><p id="P40">Interestingly, although <xref rid="FD27" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (27)</xref> employs the small effect approximation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M217" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, the solution for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M218" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> that it implies is in fact valid even if there are large effect sites, as long as a non-trivial fraction of the variance in liability is due to small effect sites for which the approximation holds. This is because the large effect sites will all be under strong selection (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M219" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), so that they are all fixed for the protective allele (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M220" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) regardless of the exact value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M221" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P41">Notably, this implies that when both small and large effect sites are present, background selection will also reduce the variance of large effect sites. This is because the selection coefficients of large effect sites are coupled to those of small effect sites via the negative synergistic epistasis created by the interaction between the liability distribution and the threshold. The size of the reduction in variance at large effect sites depends on the size of the variance reduction at small effect sites, as well as the magnitude of the large effect site&#x02019;s effect relative to the background variance in liability.</p><p id="P42">For example, first consider sites with scaled selection coefficients at the &#x0201c;weak end&#x0201d; of the strongly selected regime (e.g. sites with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M222" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>). Their effects are still small enough (in the sense that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M223" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>) that the small effect approximation, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M224" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, applies (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>). As a result, the increase of the threshold density by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M225" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> due to the impact of background selection on weakly selected sites also leads to an increase in the selection coefficients of these sites. Consequently, their contributions to variance are reduced by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M226" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, just like for weakly selected sites themselves (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D(i)</xref>). This occurs despite the fact that background selection has no effect on such sites in either the single-site model, or the single-effect-size model.</p><p id="P43">For sites with larger effect sizes, the small effect approximation does not apply at all, and the impact of BGS depends on exactly how large the liability effect is relative to the scale of the total variance in liability. If the liability effect is similar in size to the standard deviation of liability (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M227" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), then the non-linear relationship between the liability effect, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M228" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the risk effect, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M229" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, results in an increase in the risk effect, and therefore the selection coefficient, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M230" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, by a factor that is greater than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M231" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, driving an even larger reduction in variance than that experienced by sites belonging to the small effect regime (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D(ii)</xref>). In contrast, if the liability effect is so large that any individual who carries it is pushed across the threshold (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M232" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), then <inline-formula><mml:math id="M233" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M234" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Changes to the mean or variance of the liability distribution therefore have no impact on the risk effect, which implies that there is no impact on the selection coefficient, and consequently no effect on the contribution to genetic variance (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D(iii)</xref>). Thus, in the threshold model, only loci with the very largest effect sizes are free from the impact of background selection.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Stabilizing selection</title><p id="P44">As we have shown, fitness epistasis in the form of threshold selection results in substantial changes in the way that BGS impacts sites contributing to traits under directional selection. We now consider a different form of fitness epistasis, i.e. stabilizing selection toward an optimum value. As we will show below, this form of epistasis results in BGS effects differ from those described in the two directional selection models we consider above, although in this case, the effects can be understood purely in terms of a corresponding single-site model.</p><p id="P45">We model stabilizing selection in the standard way by assuming that fitness declines as a Gaussian function of an individual&#x02019;s deviation from an optimum phenotype. We assume this optimum is equal to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M235" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, and that the population mean is at the optimum, so that an individual&#x02019;s fitness is given by
<disp-formula id="FD28">
<label>(28)</label>
<mml:math id="M236" display="block"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M237" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> parameterizes the width of the fitness surface), and the mutational input is symmetric at equilibrium.</p><p id="P46">As is well-known, fitness epistasis due to stabilizing selection induces counterintuitive dynamics for individual alleles contributing to the trait. New mutations are always disfavored, regardless of the direction of their effect, because they push their carriers away from the fitness optimum. If an allele increases in frequency despite this selection against it, fitness epistasis between the focal site and the background results in small, compensatory shifts in frequency at all other sites that contribute to the phenotype, keeping the mean at the optimum. These dynamics lead to changes in the relative fitnesses of the three genotypes at the focal allele, the net result of which is that individual alleles evolve as if experiencing underdominant selection with a selection coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M238" display="inline"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> against heterozygotes (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, 1930</xref>; <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Hayward &#x00026; Sella, 2022</xref>; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Negm &#x00026; Veller, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">Robertson, 1956</xref>). We denote the corresponding scaled coefficient by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M239" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><sec id="S17"><title>Single-site underdominant selection model</title><p id="P47">Like the directional selection case, we can begin to understand the impact of BGS on traits under stabilizing selection by understanding the effect on individual variant in the corresponding single-site underdominant model. In the underdominant model, the expected change for an allele at frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M240" display="inline"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M241" display="inline"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>: selection acts symmetrically against the minor allele, but weakens as it climbs in frequency. Because the relationship between fitness and genotype is a function of the allele frequency in this model, there is no simple analog of <xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (3)</xref> relating contributions to heterozygosity to the strength of selection and/or fixation rate. However, we can largely understand the behavior of the single-site underdominant model in terms of its similarities and differences to the single-site directional model.</p><p id="P48">If selection is either very weak (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M242" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) or very strong (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M243" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), then the changes in the strength and direction of selection during an underdominant allele&#x02019;s transit are unimportant&#x02014;in the first case because selection is unimportant in general, and in the second case because selection is so strong that the frequency never rises far above zero. In these two cases, the evolution of an underdominant allele is identical to that of a negatively selected allele in the directional model (and we would naturally expect the impact of background selection to be the same as well). However, for alleles that arise under weak selection (roughly, those satisfying <inline-formula><mml:math id="M244" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), it is useful to think of them as having a frequency-dependent scaled selection coefficient, which is equal to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M245" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. For these alleles, the initial selection they experience is weak enough that they have an appreciable chance of drifting up to intermediate frequency (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary section C</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4</xref>). Once at intermediate frequency, they evolve as if neutral until the minor allele frequency drops back below a threshold of approximately <inline-formula><mml:math id="M246" display="inline"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula>, at which point selection again becomes effective and begins to push the allele either to fixation or loss. Such alleles therefore spend more time at the intermediate frequencies that contribute most to heterozygosity than a negatively selected allele with the same scaled selection coefficient in the directional model.</p><p id="P49">These dynamics can be summarized (for any value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M247" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) by the sojourn time of the minor allele at frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M248" display="inline"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is given approximately by
<disp-formula id="FD29">
<label>(29)</label>
<mml:math id="M249" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003a8;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="&#x02223;"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
(<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Hayward &#x00026; Sella, 2022</xref>). The expected lifetime contribution to heterozygosity is therefore
<disp-formula id="FD30">
<label>(30)</label>
<mml:math id="M250" display="block"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>&#x003a8;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="&#x02223;"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M251" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the Dawson function. <xref rid="FD30" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (30)</xref> coincides with the predictions of the negative directional selection model when selection is either very weak (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M252" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) or very strong (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M253" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), but predicts a greater heterozygosity than the directional model under weak selection (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M254" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>), consistent with the dynamics described above (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S6</xref>).</p><p id="P50">Applying the reduced effective size approximation, we find that background selection is expected to modify the contribution to heterozygosity of an underdominant site by a factor of
<disp-formula id="FD31">
<label>(31)</label>
<mml:math id="M255" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
Like the heterozygosity in general, <xref rid="FD31" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (31)</xref> simplifies in the same way as for the directional case when selection is either very weak (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M256" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M257" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) or very strong (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M258" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M259" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>; see <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref> inset). However, for some intermediate values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M260" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, implying that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M261" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, surprisingly, we find that background selection can increase heterozygosity for some combinations of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M262" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M263" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>).</p><p id="P51">This result is closely related to the observation that alleles under strong negative selection in the single-site additive selection model experience no reduction in heterozygosity due to BGS (see above). In that case, each allele that would have exceeded frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M264" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> in the absence of background selection does so only if it also initially arises on or quickly recombines onto a background free of deleterious alleles. This happens with probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="M265" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, the increased rate of drift that these alleles experience means that they attain a higher frequency on average, each contributing more to heterozygosity on average. In the directional selection case with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M266" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0226a;</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, we found that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M267" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, so these two effects cancelled out, and there was no net effect on heterozygosity (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C(i)</xref>). However, in the underdominant case, reaching higher frequency is accompanied by even weaker selection. This makes them even more likely to continue drifting to higher frequencies, so that the net result is an increase in heterozygosity.</p><p id="P52">The scaled selection coefficients that are most strongly impacted by this dynamic, and the size of their increase in heterozygosity, depend on the magnitude of the reduction in effective population size, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M268" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. For example, if the background selection effect is modest, as is the case for the mean effect in humans (where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M269" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0203e;</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.83</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Buffalo &#x00026; Kern, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Murphy et al., 2022</xref>), then alleles with scaled selection coefficients satisfying roughly <inline-formula><mml:math id="M270" display="inline"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> will see an increase in their probability of reaching intermediate frequency, with the biggest increase coming around <inline-formula><mml:math id="M271" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5</xref>). The biggest increase in heterozygosity occurs around <inline-formula><mml:math id="M272" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and is very modest, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M273" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.03</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>).</p><p id="P53">In contrast, if we consider a stronger background selection effect of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M274" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (consistent with the genome-wide average for <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic>; <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Elyashiv et al. (2016)</xref>), then for sites with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M275" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> the increase in the rate of drift is not enough to overcome the sharp reduction in the number of alleles exceeding frequency <inline-formula><mml:math id="M276" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, and there are roughly the same number of alleles reaching intermediate frequency as in the absence of BGS (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5</xref>). The biggest increase in the number of alleles reaching intermediate frequency instead occurs around <inline-formula><mml:math id="M277" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, but the range over which the heterozygosity is increased extends up to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M278" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. The biggest increase in heterozygosity occurs at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M279" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, and is more significant than the previous case with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M280" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.22</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5</xref>). Notably, the distortions to the frequency spectrum in this regime can be rather extreme, with significant decreases in the number of low-frequency minor alleles paired with large increases in the number of alleles near <inline-formula><mml:math id="M281" display="inline"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Stabilizing selection trait model</title><p id="P54">When we turn to considering the effect of background selection in a multi-locus model of a complex trait under stabilizing selection, we find the results for the single-site underdominant model are faithfully replicated at sites contributing to a trait under stabilizing selection. We verified this by simulating a polygenic trait under stabilizing selection in the presence of background selection, using the chromosome configuration described previously to ensure that QTLs experience background selection with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M282" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.83</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, consistent with the human average. We find good agreement between the single-site predictions of <xref rid="FD31" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (31)</xref> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M283" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and our simulation results (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>), validating our theoretical predictions. The applicability of the single-site results to the full multi-locus mode stands in contrast to the threshold model we considered above, and arises because selection does not have to maintain a fixation asymmetry in the stabilizing selection model.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P55">In this paper, we have used a combination of analytical theory and simulations to study the impact of background selection on individual variants, and on phenotypes, in three long-studied models of phenotypic mutation-selection-drift balance. Here, we consider 1) what we have learned in general about the impact of background selection in models of phenotype mutation-selection-drift balance, and 2) what our results imply about the likely impact of background selection on phenotypes in natural populations.</p><sec id="S20"><title>Directional selection models</title><p id="P56">The directional selection models we consider represent opposite ends of a continuum with respect to the role of synergistic epistasis. In the exponential selection model (i.e. without epistasis), sites with scaled selection coefficients in the effectively neutral regime experience diversity reductions in the presence of background selection that are similar to those of loci that are truly neutral, but this effect weakens as the strength of direct selection increases, so that background selection has a negligible effect on contributions to variance from loci with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M284" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02273;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. For loci with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M285" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02272;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, background selection has opposing impacts on the fixation rates of alleles under positive and negative selection, and therefore drives an increase in their contribution to the mean phenotype that is large relative to the scale of the standing genetic variation. However, because the rate of fitness decline is independent of the phenotypic value, this change in the position of the mean does not impact the underlying selection coefficients. These effects all follow directly from the local impact of selection against linked backgrounds carrying deleterious alleles, and can therefore be predicted straightforwardly from the classic &#x0201c;reduced effective population size&#x0201d; approximation for a single site.</p><p id="P57">In contrast, when selection acts through a threshold, there is strong synergistic epistasis among sites. The increase in the mean driven by the impact of background selection on fixation rates quickly causes an increase in the raw selection coefficients (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">unscaled</italic> by population size). This increase in the unscaled selection coefficients offsets the &#x0201c;reduced effective population size&#x0201d; effect on the fixation rates, so that the fixation rates ultimately remain unchanged. Because the selection coefficients of all sites are coupled to one another via the density of the liability distribution at the threshold (and, for loci with large effects, through higher moments of the liability distribution), the increase in unscaled selection coefficients, and therefore the reduction in genetic variance, extends even to strongly selected loci that would otherwise not normally be affected by background selection.</p><p id="P58">Notably, this is a global effect, which does not arise directly from the effects of linked selection on allelic dynamics, but from the downstream consequences of this change in the dynamics. In our analyses, we assume that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M286" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the same for all loci. The result is that the <italic toggle="yes">unscaled</italic> selection coefficients of weakly selected sites increase by a factor of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M287" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, exactly canceling the impact of the reduced effective population size on the scaled selection coefficients. If the value of B varies across the genome, then sites in different regions of the genome will experience different reductions in the effective population size, but because the increase in <italic toggle="yes">unscaled</italic> selection coefficients is mediated by the threshold density, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M288" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, they will all experience an increase in their selection coefficients by a multiplicative factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="M289" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M290" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is a weighted average of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M291" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> values at sites that contribute to the trait. A complete exploration of this case is beyond our scope, but in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Section F</xref> we consider the case of a single-effect-size threshold model in the weak selection regime, in which there are two different genomic regions with different <inline-formula><mml:math id="M292" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> values. There, we show how to solve this model numerically, and derive analytical solutions for two limiting cases. Briefly, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M293" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, so that there is little mutational pressure and selection is very weak, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M294" display="inline"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is approximately equal to a simple average of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M295" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> across the two regions, and the variance is ultimately reduced in each region in proportion to the local <inline-formula><mml:math id="M296" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> value. In contrast, in the limit as the fraction of fixed sites for the liability increasing allele goes to zero (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M297" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> comes to equal the minimum of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M298" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> values across regions, and the two regions experience variance reductions of the same size.</p><p id="P59">Because the two directional models we consider represent the ends of a continuum with respect to the effects of epistasis, our results also provide some insight into the behavior of models that are intermediate (e.g. <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth (1990)</xref> and <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Kimura and Maruyama (1966)</xref>), which would be expected to have intermediate behavior. Models with strong synergistic epistasis, in which fitness transitions from high to low over a narrow range of genotypes, would be expected to exhibit relatively small changes in the mean phenotype, and would be expected to exhibit reductions in the contribution to genetic variance across a broad range of selection coefficients. In contrast, models with weaker epistasis, in which fitness declines at a more steady rate with an increasing number of deleterious alleles, would be expected to exhibit relatively large changes in the mean, with reductions in variance mostly confined to weakly selected loci.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Stabilizing selection model</title><p id="P60">Our results regarding the stabilizing selection model are in some ways simpler, as the effects can be explained entirely in terms of the corresponding underdominant single-site model. Whether background selection increases or decreases a sites&#x02019;s expected contribution to heterozygosity and trait variance (or has no effect) depends on the strength of direct selection acting on the site. This simplicity results largely from the fact that we assume symmetric mutation in our analysis of stabilizing selection. As a result, selection does not need to maintain a directional fixation asymmetry, so the global dynamics that emerge in our analysis of the threshold model do not factor into the stabilizing selection model. However, this would be expected to change in a model with both stabilizing selection and a directional mutational pressure. The impacts of BGS in such a model would be expected to blend features of the threshold model and the symmetric stabilizing selection model that we consider here.</p><p id="P61">The linked selection effects we study in this paper are not the only channel through which linkage can impact the evolution of traits under stabilizing selection. This is because by selecting against individuals with extreme phenotypes, stabilizing selection generates negative LD between alleles of similar signs, resulting in a short-term decrease in the genetic variance, a phenomenon known as the Bulmer effect (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Bulmer, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Bulmer, 1971</xref>). The magnitude of this effect depends on the harmonic mean recombination rate across sites contributing to the trait, so it is stronger if sites are tightly linked. Viewed from the perspective of a single focal site, the Bulmer effect amounts to a negative covariance between the trait increasing allele at that site and the genetic background contribution from all other sites. This results in an attenuation of the marginal phenotypic association, and thus the marginal effect on fitness, of the allele at the focal site (i.e. a decrease in the site&#x02019;s &#x0201c;effective&#x0201d; selection coefficient; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Negm &#x00026; Veller, 2024</xref>). Although we did not set out to study this effect, in the process of calibrating our simulations we discovered that this decrease in the strength of selection experienced by individual sites leads to a long-term increase in the <italic toggle="yes">genic</italic> variance that is greater than the short-term reduction due to the negative LD. As a result, the total, long-term impact of the Bulmer effect is actually to increase the genetic variance, rather than to decrease it. We detail this incidental finding briefly in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary section D</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Implications for natural populations</title><p id="P62">Our study raises the important question of what effect we expect BGS to have on the evolution of complex traits in natural populations. It is useful first to revisit the existing empirical analyses that have invoked BGS effects to explain patterns in the genetic architecture of complex traits.</p><p id="P63">Specifically, working in <italic toggle="yes">C. elegans</italic>, <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Rockman et al. (2010)</xref> invoked BGS to explain the observation that loci associated with gene expression in gene-poor, high-recombination chromosome arms explain significantly more variance in transcript abundance than loci in the gene-rich chromosomal centers. This is a plausible explanation in light of our results, so long as most of the sites that <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Rockman et al. (2010)</xref> identified as affecting transcript abundance are effectively neutral or very weakly selected (if this is not the case, then BGS does not result in a local decrease in variance).</p><p id="P64">Alternatively, stratified LD score regression (S-LDSC) analyses of human complex traits and diseases have suggested that contributions to heritability are enriched in regions experiencing stronger background selection (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Gazal et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Pardi&#x000f1;as et al., 2018</xref>). These results are potentially consistent with any of the models that we consider, even though only stabilizing selection can drive an absolute increase in the heritability. This is because S-LDSC measures heritability enrichments on a per-SNP basis. While BGS reduces heritability in models of directional/negative selection by quickly removing a fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M299" display="inline"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of newly arising mutations, the contribution per segregating site is increased slightly due to the reduced efficacy of selection (see <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary section E</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S10</xref>). Second, because both the contributions to heritability (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Finucane et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Maurano et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">Pickrell, 2014</xref>) and the signals of BGS are enriched for signals of biological function in general (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Murphy et al., 2022</xref>), it is likely that causal alleles simply arise at higher rates in regions of stronger BGS. Thus, such enrichments may simply reflect the heterogeneous distribution of functional sites across the genome, rather than any specific effect of background selection.</p><p id="P65">More generally, as our results show, the exact impact of BGS on complex traits depends on the model of selection that acts on the phenotype. Much of the literature on complex trait evolution assumes that stabilizing selection is the norm (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Kingsolver et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Sella &#x00026; Barton, 2019</xref>). This assumption has been hard to assess, but GWAS data on human quantitative traits and diseases has recently begun to shed some new light, as analyses of the joint distribution of effect sizes and allele frequencies among genome-wide significant GWAS loci support a model of ubiquitous stabilizing selection across phenotypes (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Simons et al., 2022</xref>). Notably, this appears to be the case even for GWAS variants associated with disease traits (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2025</xref>; <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2024</xref>), which we might otherwise have expected to fit a model of directional selection. Assuming these results hold, the impact of background selection on human phenotypic variation may be modest, if somewhat complicated. For example, <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Simons et al. (2022)</xref> inferred a distribution of selection coefficients under a model of stabilizing selection for 95 quantitative traits from the UK Biobank, finding that this distribution spans several orders of magnitude. However, most of the mass falls into the weak selection regime. Thus, for the bulk of GWAS loci, the primary effect of background selection may be to marginally increase the number of generations that a typical variant spends drifting at intermediate frequencies before selection is able to push it back out of the population. The net effect on levels of genetic variance might in principle be positive, though the effect would be quite small, given the modest strength of background selection in humans.</p><p id="P66">It remains unclear to what extent the results of human GWAS should guide expectations about quantitative genetic variation in other species. Assuming stabilizing selection is the norm, then the impact of background selection in other species depends on how the strength of selection at a typical trait associated variant, the effective population size (before factoring in background selection effects), and the strength of background selection, all vary across taxa. For example, <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> is estimated to be impacted by much stronger linked selection than humans (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Elyashiv et al., 2016</xref>). Thus, if quantitative genetic variation in Drosophila is similarly dominated by weakly selected contributions to phenotypes under stabilizing selection, then the increase in genetic variance might plausibly be non-trivial. However, Drosophila are also estimated to have an effective population size two orders of magnitude larger than humans (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Buffalo, 2021</xref>). Thus, if the variants responsible for the bulk of quantitative genetic variation in <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> have similar (unscaled) selection coefficients as in humans, then we would expect them to be strongly selected, and we would conclude that background selection would have no impact on their contributions to genetic variance.</p><p id="P67">Of course, it is plausible that even if stabilizing selection is a sufficient model for GWAS traits in humans, it may not be a sufficient explanation for all quantitative genetic variation, either because the kinds of phenotypes that human geneticists are interested in and able to measure represent a biased subset of all axes of phenotypic variation, or because humans may not be an ideal model for other species. It would be particularly interesting, vis-&#x000e0;-vis our results, to know whether there exist axes of phenotype variation that clearly correspond to our threshold model, particularly if the threshold is positioned such that only a small number of deleterious fixations are tolerated. To the extent that axes of phenotypic variation fitting this description exist in natural populations, then background selection might ultimately be responsible for a rather large reduction in levels of quantitative genetic variance, in contrast to what we would expect in the case of stabilizing selection.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S24"><title>Simulation of single-site selection models</title><p id="P68">To validate the predictions of our single-site models, we performed SLiM simulations (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Haller &#x00026; Messer, 2019</xref>) on a single site under directional or underdominant selection, across a range of selection coefficients. In each case, we simulated 5, 000 recombining diploid genomes, with each genome having <inline-formula><mml:math id="M300" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> background sites, and a single focal site in the middle of the chromosome. The per-site recombination rate is set to 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, such that the map length is equal to 1 Morgan. The mutation rate at each of the M background sites is 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>. When we simulate without background selection, all mutations at the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M301" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> background sites other than the focal one are neutral. When we simulate with background selection, all mutations at these M background sites have a selection coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M302" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. With <inline-formula><mml:math id="M303" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M304" display="inline"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, this produces a <inline-formula><mml:math id="M305" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of 0.82. To vary the background selection strength, we tune the mutation rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M306" display="inline"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> with a fixed recombination rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M307" display="inline"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> to produce a specified <inline-formula><mml:math id="M308" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="FD1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (1)</xref>).</p><p id="P69">The mutation rate at the focal site is set to zero, and we introduce mutations at this site &#x0201c;manually&#x0201d;. We first let the simulation of the background sites run for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M309" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> generations so that the population reaches mutation-selection balance. After this burn-in period, we introduced a single selected allele at the focal site in the center of the genome.</p><p id="P70">To measure the reduction of heterozygosity by BGS, we adopt the method used by <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. (1993)</xref> to measure the expected total contribution to heterozygosity of a new mutation during its transit through the population (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M310" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tot</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>). This is given by the sum of heterozygosity at the focal site during the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M311" display="inline"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> generations that the mutation segregated in the population,
<disp-formula id="FD32">
<label>(32)</label>
<mml:math id="M312" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
which has a theoretical expectation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M313" display="inline"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tot</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, or <inline-formula><mml:math id="M314" display="inline"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tot</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, depending on the model, and is thus proportional to the expected heterozygosity for a single site at a random sampling time in the low mutation limit. For each selection coefficient, we average the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M315" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tot</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> across 10<sup>7</sup> separate focal sites. These mutations were simulated across 10<sup>4</sup> replicate burn-ins, with 10<sup>3</sup> mutations considered per burn-in. We then take the ratio of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M316" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tot</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> under BGS relative to no BGS as our estimator of the impact of background selection on the expected heterozygosity. To obtain a standard error, we treat the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M317" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">tot</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> for a single mutation&#x02019;s transit through the population as a single data point, and bootstrap across these values.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Simulation of complex Traits</title><sec id="S26"><title>Exponential selection model</title><p id="P71">To plot the reduction in variance due to background selection under the exponential model, we take advantage of the theoretical equivalence between the exponential model and the single-site additive model. To this end, we simulate a single site under directional selection with a fixed selection coefficient, as described above, except that each time a mutation ends its transit through the population and we revert the simulation back to the end of the burn-in, we choose the sign of the effect of the next mutation to be opposite to that of the allele that fixed at the end of the previous mutation&#x02019;s transit; i.e. if it was the deleterious allele that fixed, then the next mutation would be beneficial, and vice versa. This scheme simulates the long-term fixation dynamics under the exponential model. Calculations regarding the reduction in heterozygosity due to BGS are then otherwise performed as described above in the single-site case.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Threshold selection model</title><p id="P72">In this case, we simulate under the full threshold model, again with 5, 000 diploid individuals. For each choice of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M318" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> in the single-effect-size model, we simulated <inline-formula><mml:math id="M319" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> causal sites which contribute to phenotypic variation, set <inline-formula><mml:math id="M320" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, and choose <inline-formula><mml:math id="M321" display="inline"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> so as to attain the correct value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M322" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. We set the mutation rate for causal sites to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M323" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>. All causal sites are equally spaced along the chromosome. Between each pair of causal sites, there are 25 BGS sites, as well as a single neutral site (these neutral sites are used to empirically check the strength of the BGS effect, i.e. the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M324" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> value, against the expectation from <xref rid="FD1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (1)</xref>). For most of our simulations, the recombination rate among adjacent sites is set to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M325" display="inline"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the mutation rate at BGS sites is set to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M326" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, to yield an expected <inline-formula><mml:math id="M327" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M328" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.82</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, approximately equal to the estimated human average. To ensure that all causal sites experience a similar background selection effect, we added 6.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> negatively selected sites on each end of the chromosomes, such that the chromosome has a total map length of 0.8 Morgan. In the simulations where we vary the strength of the BGS effect, we do so by varying the mutation rate for BGS sites, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M329" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, with the recombination rate held constant.</p><p id="P73">To compare traits with and without background selection, we first simulate a trait with the environmental variance tuned so that the heritability is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M330" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> in the absence of background selection (i.e. setting <inline-formula><mml:math id="M331" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> for all BGS sites). We then rerun the same simulation with background selection turned on (i.e. with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M332" display="inline"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> for all BGS sites), holding the environmental variance constant at the same value used in the no background selection case. In all cases, we set the fitness cost of being across the threshold at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M333" display="inline"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. An individual&#x02019;s fitness is then computed as a product of their fitness effect due to the trait (<xref rid="FD17" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (17)</xref>) together with independent multiplicative contributions from the BGS sites.</p><p id="P74">To compare the single-effect-size trait model to the single-site results, we assign a scaled selection coefficient to each set of trait simulations. This quantity measures the average selection coefficient that causal variants experience in the trait model. For each choice of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M334" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> in the simulations, we estimated the unscaled selection coefficient by regressing individual fitness against genotypes in the absence of background selection. This regression was performed for each causal site segregating in a given generation and repeated across multiple generations, with the average slope serving as our estimate. We then obtained the scaled selection coefficient by multiplying this estimate by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M335" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The corresponding simulation run, conducted with the same <inline-formula><mml:math id="M336" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> but with background selection included, was assigned the same scaled selection coefficient. In principle, in the small effect regime we could obtain the scaled selection coefficient analytically using <xref rid="FD20" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (20)</xref>, but this method breaks down for large effects, so we use the empirical regression-based estimate across the full range.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Stabilizing Selection</title><p id="P75">Our simulations under stabilizing selection are similar to those under the threshold model, with a few key differences. Notably, to avoid the Bulmer effect in our simulations of stabilizing selection (see <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary section D</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S9</xref>), we had to increase the harmonic mean recombination rate between pairs of causal sites (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Bulmer, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Bulmer, 1971</xref>; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Negm &#x00026; Veller, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Veller &#x00026; Coop, 2024</xref>). In these simulations, we set <inline-formula><mml:math id="M337" display="inline"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, and split the causal sites across 6 independent chromosomes, so that each chromosome has 9000 causal sites. Between each pair of adjacent causal sites on a given chromosome, there are 98 BGS sites and 1 neutral site. The recombination rate is set to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M338" display="inline"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> per base pair, while the mutation rate is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M339" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> for both causal and BGS sites. We set the width of the stabilizing selection surface <inline-formula><mml:math id="M340" display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and vary the effect size for each site <inline-formula><mml:math id="M341" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P76">To compare the single-effect-size trait model to the single-site results, for each choice of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M342" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, we measure the average heterozygosity of all the causal sites in the simulations without background selection over multiple generations and solved for the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M343" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> with <xref rid="FD30" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (30)</xref>. We then multiply this estimate by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M344" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and assign it to the simulations with the same <inline-formula><mml:math id="M345" display="inline"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> with and without background selection.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHPP2025.05.27.656342V3-supplement-1.pdf" id="d67e7170" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S30"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P78">We would like to thank John Novembre for many helpful conversations, and for reading and commenting extensively on several drafts of the manuscript. We would also like to thank members of the Berg, Novembre and Steinr&#x000fc;cken labs for feedback on the work at various stages. XL was supported by NIH grant R35 GM151257 to John Novembre and R01 HG010773 to John Novembre and Xin He. JJB was supported by R35 GM149521.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P77">Resource</p><p id="P177">The documented code, including simulations, numerical solutions of the model, and figure-geneartion scripts, is publicly available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/xinyli/BGS_msdb.git" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/xinyli/BGS_msdb.git</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Linkage and the limits to natural selection</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>140</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>841</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7498757</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riall</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2025</year>). <source>Mutation-selection-drift balance models of complex diseases</source> [Preprint at bioRxiv <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.05.18.654722v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.05.18.654722v1</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Buffalo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Quantifying the relationship between genetic diversity and population size suggests natural selection cannot explain lewontin&#x02019;s paradox</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e67509</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34409937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Buffalo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>A quantitative genetic model of background selection in humans</article-title>. <source>Plos Genetics</source>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>e1011144</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38507461</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bulmer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>Linkage disequilibrium and genetic variability</article-title>. <source>Genetics Research</source>, <volume>23</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bulmer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>The effect of selection on genetic variability</article-title>. <source>The American Naturalist</source>, <volume>105</volume> (<issue>943</issue>), <fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wakeley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Directional selection and the site-frequency spectrum</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>159</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779814</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Mutation-selection balance and the evolutionary advantage of sex and recombination</article-title>. <source>Genetics Research</source>, <volume>55</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The effect of background selection against deleterious mutations on weakly selected, linked variants</article-title>. <source>Genetics Research</source>, <volume>63</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The effect of deleterious mutations on neutral molecular variation</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>134</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8375663</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <source>Does linked selection explain the narrow range of genetic diversity across species?</source> [Preprint at bioRxiv <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/042598v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/042598v1</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Corbett-Detig</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sackton</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Natural selection constrains neutral diversity across a wide range of species</article-title>. <source>PLoS biology</source>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>e1002112</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25859758</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Efficiency of truncation selection</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>76</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>399</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cvijovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The effect of strong purifying selection on genetic diversity</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>209</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1278</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844134</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Elyashiv</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sattath</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strutsovsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McVicker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A genomic map of the effects of linked selection in drosophila</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source>, <volume>12</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>e1006130</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27536991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Falconer</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Introduction to quantitative genetics</article-title>. <source>Pearson Education India</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bulik-Sullivan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trynka</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reshef</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>P.-R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anttila</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Partitioning heritability by functional annotation using genome-wide association summary statistics</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1235</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414678</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name> (<year>1930</year>). <source>The genetical theory of natural selection</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gazal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furlotte</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>P.-R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palamara</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schoech</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bulik-Sullivan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gusev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Linkage disequilibrium&#x02013;dependent architecture of human complex traits shows action of negative selection</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>, <volume>49</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1427</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28892061</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gravel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henn</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gutenkunst</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Indap</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>, <collab>Project, 1. G.</collab>, <name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Demographic history and rare allele sharing among human populations</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>108</volume> (<issue>29</issue>), <fpage>11983</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11988</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Slim 3: Forward genetic simulations beyond the wright&#x02013;fisher model</article-title>. <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source>, <volume>36</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>632</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>637</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30517680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Polygenic adaptation after a sudden change in environment</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e66697</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36155653</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Deleterious background selection with recombination</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>141</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1617</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8601498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karn</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Penrose</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> (<year>1951</year>). <article-title>Birth weight and gestation time in relation to maternal age, parity and infant survival</article-title>. <source>Annals of eugenics</source>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14885877</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>). <article-title>On the probability of fixation of mutant genes in a population</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>713</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14456043</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>). <article-title>Diffusion models in population genetics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Probability</source>, <volume>1</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>). <article-title>The number of heterozygous nucleotide sites maintained in a finite population due to steady flux of mutations</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>61</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>893</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5364968</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>1966</year>). <article-title>The mutational load with epistatic gene interactions in fitness</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>54</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1337</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248359</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name> (<year>1966</year>). <article-title>The gene interaction component of the genetic load</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>53</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>403</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5919323</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kingsolver</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berrigan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vignieri</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Beerli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The strength of phenotypic selection in natural populations</article-title>. <source>The American Naturalist</source>, <volume>157</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Connally</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reeve</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloemendal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sunyaev</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <source>Genetic association data are broadly consistent with stabilizing selection shaping human common diseases and traits</source> [Preprint at bioRxiv <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.06.19.599789v2" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.06.19.599789v2</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kondrashov</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Through sex, nature is telling us something important</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics</source>, <volume>34</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29409661</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maurano</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Humbert</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rynes</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Systematic localization of common disease-associated variation in regulatory dna</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>337</volume> (<issue>6099</issue>), <fpage>1190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McVEAN</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A population genetic model for the evolution of synonymous codon usage: Patterns and predictions</article-title>. <source>Genetics Research</source>, <volume>74</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McVicker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Widespread genomic signatures of natural selection in hominid evolution</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>e1000471</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19424416</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Milkman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Selection differentials and selection coefficients</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>88</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elyashiv</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amster</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Broad-scale variation in human genetic diversity levels is predicted by purifying selection on coding and non-coding elements</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e76065</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name><surname>Negm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Veller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <source>The effect of long-range linkage disequilibrium on allele-frequency dynamics under stabilizing selection</source> [Preprint at bioRxiv <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.06.27.601075v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.06.27.601075v1</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The effect of recombination on background selection</article-title>. <source>Genetics Research</source>, <volume>67</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schoech</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hormozdiari</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gazal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Extreme polygenicity of complex traits is explained by negative selection</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Human Genetics</source>, <volume>105</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31402091</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pardi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmans</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pocklington</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Escott-Price</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ripke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legge</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamshere</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Common schizophrenia alleles are enriched in mutation-intolerant genes and in regions under strong background selection</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>, <volume>50</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29483656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pickrell</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Joint analysis of functional genomic data and genome-wide association studies of 18 human traits</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Human Genetics</source>, <volume>94</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24702953</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> (<year>1956</year>). <article-title>The effect of selection against extreme deviants based on deviation or on homozygosis: With two text-figures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Genetics</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rockman</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skrovanek</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Kruglyak</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Selection at linked sites shapes heritable phenotypic variation in c. elegans</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>330</volume> (<issue>6002</issue>), <fpage>372</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>376</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20947766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sanjak</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sidorenko</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Evidence of directional and stabilizing selection in contemporary humans</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>115</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Thinking about the evolution of complex traits in the era of genome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Annual review of genomics and human genetics</source>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bullaughey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A population genetic interpretation of gwas findings for human quantitative traits</article-title>. <source>PLoS biology</source>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>e2002985</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29547617</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mostafavi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2022</year>). <source>Simple scaling laws control the genetic architectures of human complex traits</source> [Preprint at bioRxiv <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.10.04.509926v1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.10.04.509926v1</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>The genetics of stasis and punctuation</article-title>. <source>Annual review of genetics</source>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stephan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>McVEAN</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The effect of background selection at a single locus on weakly selected, partially linked variants</article-title>. <source>Genetics Research</source>, <volume>73</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Veller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Interpreting population-and family-based genome-wide association studies in the presence of confounding</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biology</source>, <volume>22</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>e3002511</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38603516</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Selection on wing allometry in drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>126</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>975</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>989</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2127580</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>1938</year>). <article-title>The distribution of gene frequencies under irreversible mutation</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p id="P79">Illustration of focal traits and linked deleterious selection. (A) We study models in which phenotypic variation for a focal trait is caused by a large number of loci that are linked to loci which have deleterious effects via other fitness components. We are primarily interested in models where the focal trait is a disease evolving under the liability threshold model (B) or a quantitative trait under stabilizing selection (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.27.656342v3-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p id="P80">Genetic diversity reduction for single-site additive directional selection model under background selection. (A) The predicted change in the contribution to heterozygosity conditional on not being removed via linkage to a BGS site (i.e. the ratio <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> from <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">equation (5a)</xref>). (B) The selective fixation rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, with and without BGS, over the range [&#x02212;50,50] in the main plot and [&#x02212;3,3] in the inset. (C) The solid black line shows the diversity reduction, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, predicted by <xref rid="FD5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref>, while the horizontal red dashed line shows the diversity reduction expected under neutrality, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. In simulations we used the chromosome structure shown on the top left (gray bars represent regions with BGS sites), varied the scaled selection coefficients of the focal sites and measured the average genetic diversity reduction over many replicates. In the insets (i)- (iv), the upper panels show the site frequency spectrum, scaled relative to its neutral expectation, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, &#x02212;1.5, 1.5, 25. The color indicates whether background selection is (blue) or is not (orange) operating. The solid line represents the predicted deleterious SFS with effective population size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>; while the dashed line represents the predicted deleterious SFS with effective population size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The left violet dashed vertical line plots <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the average genome-wide standard deviation of the background fitness from simulations. The right purple dashed vertical line plots <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" display="inline"><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>. Lower panels plot the density of alleles at each frequency under background selection compared to no background selection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.27.656342v3-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p id="P81">The impact of background selection in the liability threshold model. (A) The genetic variance reduction due to background selection for the exponential fitness function (black) and the threshold model (purple) in simulations. The schematic at top right illustrates the chromosome structure of these simulations, with trait loci (red bars) interspersed among BGS sites (grey regions) (B) The impact of background selection on disease prevalence in the single-effect liability threshold model, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0226b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>. (B; top inset box) Increasing the strength of BGS shifts the mean toward the threshold and decreases the variance (B; main figure) The disease prevalence increases with stronger background selection. The theoretical prediction of <xref rid="FD25" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (25)</xref> is plotted in a black dashed line. Red dots correspond to averages over individual simulation runs, while the solid line connect means for each value of B. (C) In contrast, when the threshold is close to zero in the single-effect-size model (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>), the liability distribution is not affected by background selection, as shown in the box. Consequently, the disease prevalence is not affected by increasing the background selection intensity. In (D), we simulated two-effect traits under the liability threshold model, with one of the effect sizes in the small-effect regime (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the other effect size in the large-effect regime. We varied the effect sizes of the large-effect alleles. (i) &#x02013; (iii) illustrates how the risk effect size for the large-effect-size allele changes with background selection depending on its effect size. The region in red represents the proportion of diseased individuals no matter whether the individuals carry the large effect allele; orange represents the proportion of individuals that will develop the disease if they carry the large effect allele but will be healthy otherwise (risk effect size); and blue represents the proportion of healthy individuals no matter whether they carry the large effect allele. (i) The effect size is relatively small and the risk effect size can be linearly approximated with the darker orange region. (ii) The linearity does not hold and the risk effect size increase is larger than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" display="inline"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>. (iii) When the effect size has a similar scale as the phenotypic variation, the change in liability distribution has a negligible impact on risk effect size. (D) While the small-effect-size alleles (green) have a constant reduction in variance (approximately at a ratio of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), the reduction of variance varies for the large-effect-size allele (brown). With an increased effect size, the ratio drops below B-value and then increases to one. The theoretical predictions (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary section B</xref>) of variance reduction for the small-effect and large-effect alleles are plotted in green and red dashed lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.27.656342v3-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4:</label><caption><p id="P82">Stabilizing Selection. In (A), we simulated traits with a single constant effect size under stabilizing selection with chromosome structure shown on the top right. Across different settings, we varied effect sizes and measured the reduction in genetic variance due to background selection (y-axis). The x-axis represents the measured average selection coefficient at each causal locus. The method used for these estimations is detailed in Methods. The red dashed line is the expected genetic diversity reduction of a neutral allele at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.83</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. The blue solid line is the theoretical prediction of the genetic reduction of a single selected focal allele with a BGS intensity at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" display="inline"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.83</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. The prediction aligns well with the single-locus simulation results, shown in the insect. To demonstrate that the size of increase in heterozygosity due to BGS depends on the magnitude of the BGS effect, we also plot the predicted reduction of genetic diversity with different BGS intensities in grey lines.</p><p id="P83">In (B) we plot the &#x0201c;relative&#x0201d; site frequency spectrum of the focal selected site with different selection coefficients (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.5</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> on the left panel and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" display="inline"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> on the right panel) observed in single-locus simulations. The <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" display="inline"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-axis is the number of sites at each frequency relative to the neutral expectation with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The color represents the scenario whether there is background selection or not. The solid line represents the predicted deleterious SFS with effective population size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>; while the dashed line represents the predicted deleterious SFS with effective population size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The insets show the relative density of alleles at each frequency bin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.27.656342v3-f0004" position="float"/></fig><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float"><caption><title>Significance</title></caption><p id="P84">Physical linkage of genetic variants to nearby deleterious mutations shapes their evolution. The effect of this linkage is similar to a reduction in population size, because chromosomes carrying deleterious alleles are quickly removed. This leads to reduced genetic variation for neutral variants, and for variants under weak directional selection. Here, we analyze the impact of linkage in models of selection on complex, polygenic traits. We find that when selection acts on traits through a threshold, linkage reduces genetic variation for much more strongly selected sites than existing theory predicts. In contrast, if selection stabilizes trait values toward an optimum, then linkage may actually increase genetic variation. Understanding the fully effect of linkage therefore requires understand how selection acts on traits.</p><p id="P85">references.bib</p></boxed-text></floats-group></article>