<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-06-17T16:33:20.382Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Promot Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Promot Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">heapro</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health Promotion International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0957-4824</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2245</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40498767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12154208</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/heapro/daaf077</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">daaf077</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Health Policy</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Maximizing older people&#x02019;s access to primary health care centers in Lebanon: a co-design approach</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0426-8835</contrib-id><name><surname>Dableh</surname><given-names>Saydeh</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Nursing, Midwifery, and Health Systems, Health Sciences Centre, University College Dublin</institution>, <addr-line>Belfield, DO4 V1W8 Dublin 4</addr-line>, <country country="IE">Ireland</country></aff><xref rid="daaf077-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--Saydeh.dableh@ucdconnect.ie--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6703-266X</contrib-id><name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>Kate</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Nursing, Midwifery, and Health Systems, Health Sciences Centre, University College Dublin</institution>, <addr-line>Belfield, DO4 V1W8 Dublin 4</addr-line>, <country country="IE">Ireland</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azar</surname><given-names>Mathilde</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Nursing Program, University of Balamand</institution>, <addr-line>Rond Point Saloumeh, Dekouaneh, 55251 Beirut</addr-line>, <country country="LB">Lebanon</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamadeh</surname><given-names>Randa</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Primary Health Care Department, Ministry of Public Health</institution>, <addr-line>Bir Hassan, Jnah, Next to Ogero, 2063 Beirut</addr-line>, <country country="LB">Lebanon</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>Thilo</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>School of Nursing, Midwifery, and Health Systems, Health Sciences Centre, University College Dublin</institution>, <addr-line>Belfield, DO4 V1W8 Dublin 4</addr-line>, <country country="IE">Ireland</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="daaf077-cor1">Corresponding author. School of Nursing, Midwifery, and Health Systems, Health Sciences Centre, University College Dublin, Belfield, DO4 V1W8 Dublin 4, Ireland. E-mail: <email>Saydeh.dableh@ucdconnect.ie</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-06-11"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>daaf077</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact reprints@oup.com for reprints and translation rights for reprints. All other permissions can be obtained through our RightsLink service via the Permissions link on the article page on our site&#x02014;for further information please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="daaf077.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Limited access of older people to primary health care is a pressing issue in resource-constrained countries, particularly in Lebanon, amid the ongoing crisis. The co-design research approach is instrumental in addressing this problem, as it draws on people&#x02019;s experiences to generate practical and sustainable solutions. Using the design thinking framework, this co-design study involved 13 older people, family members, and primary healthcare service providers in co-designing solutions to maximize older people&#x02019;s access to primary healthcare centers in Lebanon. The design thinking process was implemented through seven in-person workshops, complemented by three individual interviews with older people involved as advisors. Co-designers identified the lack of preventive strategies for mental health and cognitive abilities as a key access barrier and a co-design challenge. The process resulted in two solution prototypes: (i) a plan to implement screenings for depression and cognitive problems, as a new service to be delivered at the primary health care center, and (ii) a creative brief for a social media campaign to raise awareness about the importance of preventive strategies to promote mental health and abilities among older people. This study suggests that enhancing preventive care to promote mental health and cognitive abilities can improve access by fostering the approachability, acceptability, appropriateness, and availability of services, as well as individuals&#x02019; ability to perceive the need for care, seek, pay, and engage with care. Further research is needed to support the implementation of suggested solutions, to replicate this work in different settings across regions, and to address other identified challenges.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>co-design</kwd><kwd>design thinking</kwd><kwd>older people</kwd><kwd>primary health care</kwd><kwd>access</kwd><kwd>healthcare accessibility</kwd><kwd>low- and middle-income countries</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="daaf077-box1" position="anchor"><label>Contribution to Health Promotion</label><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Access to primary healthcare improves older people&#x02019;s health outcomes and well-being, achieves universal health coverage, and reduces health inequities.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Aligned with health promotion principles, the adopted co-design approach empowers different partners and actively engages them in the decision-making for service improvement.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The findings of this study advocate for reorienting health services to center on preventive care, which is a main pillar of health promotion. Focusing on mental health and abilities promotes successful aging, thus enhancing social welfare.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The findings inform policymakers to generate supportive policies and approaches that adopt the age-friendly primary healthcare agenda.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="daaf077-s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Access to primary health care (PHC) is essential to ensure universal health coverage and improve health outcomes, health equity, and health system efficiency (<xref rid="daaf077-B3" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2023</xref>). Investing in PHC is particularly fundamental during economic changes and demographic transitions (<xref rid="daaf077-B55" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2018</xref>). This was also emphasized after the COVID-19 pandemic, to enhance health system preparedness for epidemics, particularly for the benefit of older people (<xref rid="daaf077-B22" ref-type="bibr">Ibsen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>), considering their health, social, and financial possible vulnerabilities (<xref rid="daaf077-B46" ref-type="bibr">Schr&#x000f6;der-Butterfill and Marianti 2006</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B29" ref-type="bibr">Langmann 2023</xref>). Available systematic reviews summarizing the literature on access to PHC for older people report several barriers impeding this right, especially in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs) (<xref rid="daaf077-B32" ref-type="bibr">Lubenow <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2016</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B10" ref-type="bibr">da Silva <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2018</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>). Barriers were mapped across five dimensions characterizing the delivery of PHC services and five corresponding abilities representing the older population attributes (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2024</xref>).</p><p>Older people living in Lebanon are at higher risk because of compounded crises, including the COVID-19 pandemic, the Beirut blast, and the financial crisis marked by severe currency devaluation in addition to the collapse of the economy, banking system, social insurance systems, and mutual funds (<xref rid="daaf077-B20" ref-type="bibr">HelpAge 2022</xref>). Around 80% of older people do not benefit from any social protection system and are currently unable to afford services provided by the private sector. This explains their changing health-seeking behavior, relying more on services delivered through PHCCs (<xref rid="daaf077-B58" ref-type="bibr">Yaacoub <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>) by 125% in 2021 compared with 2019 (<xref rid="daaf077-B50" ref-type="bibr">UNICEF 2023</xref>). This changing situation highlights the need to strengthen the PHC sector nowadays more than ever to respond to the population&#x02019;s emerging needs.</p><p>Culturally, older people in Lebanon are not active in decision-making related to their health (<xref rid="daaf077-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chemali <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Moreover, evidence from LMICs underscores the lack of patient and public involvement (PPI) in research on this topic (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>), highlighting the need for participatory approaches. PPI in research is increasingly advocated to align researchers&#x02019; aims with research users&#x02019; needs (<xref rid="daaf077-B53" ref-type="bibr">Wilson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). PPI varies from consultation to active collaboration, then co-led projects (<xref rid="daaf077-B4" ref-type="bibr">NIHR 2024</xref>). Co-creation describes a range of collaborative approaches with partners throughout different project stages. Co-creation, co-production, and co-design have been conceptualized differently in the literature. In this study, we view co-design as defining problems and generating solutions; co-production as implementing co-designed solutions; and co-creation as doing both phases through active PPI (<xref rid="daaf077-B18" ref-type="bibr">Giolitto 2017</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B36" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Donnell <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2025</xref>).</p><p>Co-design is an approach grounded in participatory practices and user-centered methods, dating back to 1960&#x02013;1970 (<xref rid="daaf077-B42" ref-type="bibr">Sanders and Stappers 2008</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B11" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>). It evolved into a collaborative approach allowing end-users, who are not trained in design, to participate in the design process as equal partners with expert designers (<xref rid="daaf077-B42" ref-type="bibr">Sanders and Stappers 2008</xref>). The co-design process uses partners&#x02019; experiential knowledge and perception to define problems and generate solutions, facilitating the transformation of complex adaptive systems (<xref rid="daaf077-B36" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Donnell <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2025</xref>). By emphasizing inclusivity, active involvement, and knowledge sharing, co-design ensures a close alignment between users&#x02019; needs and co-designed products and services, which increases their acceptability, applicability, accessibility, and sustainability (<xref rid="daaf077-B38" ref-type="bibr">Palmer <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2019</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B21" ref-type="bibr">Hyett <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2020</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B36" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Donnell <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2025</xref>). At first, co-design was used to create products and business values (<xref rid="daaf077-B42" ref-type="bibr">Sanders and Stappers 2008</xref>). Then, with the global shift toward service-oriented economies, especially in Western countries, co-design has been used to develop services, improve experiences, and find solutions for complex problems in various fields (<xref rid="daaf077-B42" ref-type="bibr">Sanders and Stappers 2008</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B11" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B39" ref-type="bibr">Pi&#x00142;at 2024</xref>), including primary healthcare systems (<xref rid="daaf077-B57" ref-type="bibr">Xiong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>). The use of co-design in health research has resulted in sustainable innovation in healthcare delivery models, relevant health system improvements, and enhanced user experiences (<xref rid="daaf077-B51" ref-type="bibr">White <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023a</xref>).</p><p>The involvement of non-designers in design necessitates preparation and structured processes with careful consideration of cultural and disciplinary differences (<xref rid="daaf077-B52" ref-type="bibr">White <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023b</xref>). In this context, the design thinking framework offers a structured problem-solving and innovation process anchored in two core principles: human-centeredness and creativity (<xref rid="daaf077-B28" ref-type="bibr">Ku and Lupton 2020</xref>). It is a user-oriented method that prioritizes understanding (<xref rid="daaf077-B39" ref-type="bibr">Pi&#x00142;at 2024</xref>) by involving empathy. Empathy is a foundational stage that consists of understanding users&#x02019; experiences, needs, and challenges to generate innovative and context-sensitive ideas (<xref rid="daaf077-B28" ref-type="bibr">Ku and Lupton 2020</xref>). Design experts can immerse themselves in the users&#x02019; world through different methods such as interviewing and observation, without involving end-users in all design stages. Despite being essential, this approach limits end-users&#x02019; contribution to the understanding phase only and may involve biased knowledge. Fortunately, the versatile nature of design thinking allows for co-design integration to maximize effectiveness (<xref rid="daaf077-B28" ref-type="bibr">Ku and Lupton 2020</xref>). This means that end-users can directly infuse their expertise into the whole design process (<xref rid="daaf077-B28" ref-type="bibr">Ku and Lupton 2020</xref>) and collaborate as partners, in understanding complex issues while generating a broad spectrum of innovative ideas and solutions (<xref rid="daaf077-B39" ref-type="bibr">Pi&#x00142;at 2024</xref>). Design thinking, which was initially used to develop corporate businesses, has also been recognized as a unique problem-solving tool to drive social and healthcare innovation (<xref rid="daaf077-B28" ref-type="bibr">Ku and Lupton 2020</xref>).</p><p>Involving older people in the co-design process is extremely important (<xref rid="daaf077-B25" ref-type="bibr">James and Buffel 2023</xref>) but requires specific considerations to avoid possible challenges mainly related to relationships among involved partners, familiarity with the co-design process, and accessibility to places, information, and adapted communication (<xref rid="daaf077-B44" ref-type="bibr">Schilling and Gerhardus 2017</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B45" ref-type="bibr">Schouten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2022</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B19" ref-type="bibr">Goodwin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>).</p><p>This co-design research is informed by findings from a foundational qualitative study that identified barriers and enablers for older people&#x02019;s access to primary health care centers (PHCCs) in Lebanon (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2025</xref>). It showed that access barriers relate to service delivery characteristics and to the attributes of older people. This subsequent research phase aims to co-design solutions to maximize older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs in Lebanon. Specific objectives are to (i) engage older people and their family members in prioritizing one access barrier among those identified through the foundational study and (ii) co-design, with older people, family members, and PHC providers, solutions that address the selected access barrier.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="daaf077-s2.1"><title>Study design</title><p>This study involves co-design research conducted through the lens of pragmatism, a paradigm that focuses on practical solutions that shape future practice to solve real-world problems (<xref rid="daaf077-B43" ref-type="bibr">Saunders <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2019</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B5" ref-type="bibr">Allemang Sitter and Dimitropoulos 2022</xref>). The use of co-design is relevant for this study as it is linked to a deep understanding of people&#x02019;s needs (<xref rid="daaf077-B52" ref-type="bibr">White <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023b</xref>), sustainable adoption of created solutions within the resource-constrained Lebanese community (<xref rid="daaf077-B12" ref-type="bibr">Donaldson 2006</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B24" ref-type="bibr">Jagtap 2022</xref>), and increased accessibility to services with enhanced health outcomes (<xref rid="daaf077-B47" ref-type="bibr">Sumner <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2021</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B33" ref-type="bibr">Mirza Brown and Hulko 2022</xref>).</p><p>The principal investigator (PI) involved older people, family members, and service providers (physicians, nurses, and PHCC administrators) as experts by experience and equal partners (<xref rid="daaf077-B42" ref-type="bibr">Sanders and Stappers 2008</xref>) in the co-design process to account for different perspectives. A design thinking approach was adopted. In addition to deep problem understanding, creativity, and innovation potentials, design thinking is recognized for its adaptability to diverse contexts and fields, its ability to address complex issues, and for facilitating teamwork through an iterative process to reach innovative and sustainable solutions (<xref rid="daaf077-B39" ref-type="bibr">Pi&#x00142;at 2024</xref>). The design thinking process, as envisioned by the Stanford D School, encompasses five stages: empathize, define, ideate, prototype, and test (<xref rid="daaf077-B13" ref-type="bibr">Doorley <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). The empathize phase is dedicated to understanding the problem perceived by people with lived experiences. During the define phase, co-designers turn findings into insights with a clear definition of the main co-design challenge by focusing on core problems. The ideation phase allows creative idea generation and innovative solutions. The prototyping phase consists of realizing actionable solutions in a simple and low-cost format, while testing consists of getting feedback on prototyped solutions and iteratively refining them.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.2"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the University of Balamand (IRB-REC/o/024-25/0624 on 1 July 2024) and the Human Research Ethics Committee of University College Dublin (LS-C-24-250-Dableh-Kroll on 19 July 2024). Approval to access PHCC was also granted by the Lebanese Ministry of Public Health&#x02014;Primary Healthcare Department on 4 July 2024. All participants provided a written consent based on the information leaflets communicated by the PI. They were informed about the confidentiality of shared information and data security measures such as limited access to personal data, safe storage on PI&#x02019;s devices, and abstinence from information sharing with third parties.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.3"><title>Specific considerations for co-designing with older people</title><p>Co-designing with older people is reported as an effective and enriching experience (<xref rid="daaf077-B41" ref-type="bibr">Sakaguchi-Tang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2021</xref>). Based on the available literature suggesting barriers and facilitators to this process (<xref rid="daaf077-B41" ref-type="bibr">Sakaguchi-Tang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2021</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B47" ref-type="bibr">Sumner <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2021</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B45" ref-type="bibr">Schouten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2022</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B48" ref-type="bibr">Terkelsen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2022</xref>), we implemented measures that facilitate the active involvement of older people along with other partners. These measures revolve around fostering a comfortable environment; establishing power balance; promoting value, interest, and commitment; as well as empowering the co-designers.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.4"><title>Participants and recruitment</title><p>The team of 13 co-designers and 3 advisors constituted a subset of participants who took part in the foundational qualitative study and agreed to be contacted for involvement in future research steps. The PI recruited participants for the co-design with the purpose of ensuring maximum variation in terms of gender, age groups, and socioeconomic level, in addition to the following eligibility criteria:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Availability to attend all workshops, which ensures meaningful participation in the iterative design thinking process.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ability to read and write, as workshops include interactive methods requiring a minimum literacy level to facilitate the process.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ability to reach the workshop venue.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of advanced sensory limitations.</p></list-item></list><p>It is pertinent to point out that, for the foundational study, two PHCCs were chosen to recruit service users and providers, while non-users were selected through municipalities. Findings from this study suggested that practices and challenges vary across centers depending on financial resources. Therefore, for the co-design study, we focused on the PHCC that presented more funding challenges to ensure specificity when discussing access barriers and solutions. Service users and providers from this PHCC were only eligible to participate in the co-design study.</p><p>Besides the PI, the co-design team operated in two groups to avoid power imbalances, as it included both service users and providers:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The first group (Group 1 or G1) consisted of 10 participants: three older people who use services delivered by the PHCC, three older people who do not use services delivered by the PHCC, and four family members of users and non-users. The number of participants for this group was agreed upon based on the typical number of participants in focus group discussions (FGDs), which allows for interaction and idea generation (<xref rid="daaf077-B17" ref-type="bibr">George 2013</xref>). Moreover, we learned from the foundational qualitative study that smaller groups ensure that older people have sufficient time to express their ideas.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The second group (Group 2 or G2) included the three service providers from the selected PHCC team who participated in the foundational study.</p></list-item></list><p>Since advanced motor and sensory limitations were an exclusion factor for participating in the co-design workshops, three older people living with such limitations were included as advisors and shared their insights through individual interviews during the ideation and testing stages.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.5"><title>Data collection</title><p>Data collected from participants included the following:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Sociodemographic information: All needed data were collected during the foundational study; the PI asked participants to update their demographic data including (i) age, gender, occupation, education, and socioeconomic status for older people and family members and (ii) age, education, and occupational role at the PHCC for service providers.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Participants&#x02019; experiences with the co-design process: methods and findings related to this component will be reported in a separate paper.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Participants&#x02019; perspective on a priority barrier to accessing PHCCs and potential solutions to address it: data were collected during co-design workshops, supplemented by three structured interviews, as described in the next section.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.6"><title>Co-design workshops</title><p>Guided by the Stanford D School approach for design thinking (<xref rid="daaf077-B13" ref-type="bibr">Doorley <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2018</xref>), seven weekly workshops were conducted in person, between October and November 2024, in an accessible venue for all participants: four with older people and family members and two with service providers. These workshops ran in parallel. A final additional workshop brought the two groups together, as shown in <xref rid="daaf077-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Since this paper focuses on older people&#x02019;s experiences with access to PHCCs, they were exclusively involved in defining the co-design challenge, which reflects their concerns and priorities. Then, all partners actively participated in a thorough analysis of the identified challenge and proposed solutions that presented their diverse perspectives. All workshops lasted 3&#x02005;h except for G1W4, which ran over 4&#x02005;h, in response to the participants&#x02019; request to finalize the prototype. Detailed workshop plans are available in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File S1</xref>. The PI (SD) facilitated all workshops in Arabic and audio-recorded them as consented. All participants received reimbursement for travel costs to support their sustained commitment. Participants were invited to provide their feedback at the end of each workshop through &#x02018;like&#x02019; and &#x02018;dislike&#x02019; display boards that feature, respectively, aspects they appreciate along with those they would like to modify. Their feedback was instrumental in planning for subsequent workshops.</p><fig position="float" id="daaf077-F1" fig-type="figure"><label>
Figure 1.
</label><caption><p>The application of the design thinking process through co-design workshops.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf077f1" position="float"/></fig><p>
<xref rid="daaf077-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the workshops objectives, methods employed, and outcomes. Most methods were adapted from available toolkits on design thinking (<xref rid="daaf077-B23" ref-type="bibr">IDEO 2015</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B18" ref-type="bibr">Giolitto 2017</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B13" ref-type="bibr">Doorley <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). A table justifying and explaining their use in this study is available in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File S2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="daaf077-T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary of workshops objectives, methods, and outcomes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workshop</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Objectives</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methods</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Researcher input</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tangible outcomes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1W1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introducing participants to each other;<break/>Nurturing bonds and team spirit;<break/>Explaining the research objectives and process, and agreeing on ground rules;<break/>Introducing key results from the qualitative study;<break/>Empathizing through further discussion of barriers to older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs;<break/>Evaluating the workshop.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Icebreaker: Salt &#x00026; Pepper;<break/>Discussion;<break/>Brainstorming;<break/>Interactive presentation;<break/>Storytelling;<break/>Exercise: &#x02018;To what extent does this story tell mine?&#x02019;;<break/>Like and dislike display boards.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explaining and facilitating the activities;<break/>Providing information about the study;<break/>Explaining the design thinking process;<break/>Discussing roles and responsibilities;<break/>Presenting findings from the qualitative study through the story.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signed consent forms;<break/>List of expectations and concerns;<break/>Five ground rules for the group;<break/>Agreed schedule for workshops;<break/>Individual lists of identified barriers based on the story;<break/>Feedback on the workshop.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summarizing and translating findings, then sharing a detailed report with the research team.<break/>Planning for the next workshop.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1W2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creating a comfortable environment;<break/>Presenting the full qualitative study findings;<break/>Selecting one priority barrier as a co-design challenge;<break/>Elaborating the problem statement;<break/>Evaluating the workshop.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Game: personal object;<break/>Game: puzzle (<xref rid="daaf077-B31" ref-type="bibr">Levesque <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.&#x02019;s</xref> framework);<break/>Brainstorming;<break/>Nominal voting;<break/>Interactive presentation;<break/>Group work;<break/>Like and dislike display boards.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussing objectives;<break/>Introducing Levesque&#x02019;s framework;<break/>Explaining and facilitating the activities;<break/>Explaining essentials for problem statement elaboration.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Completed puzzle: access barriers mapped according to Levesque <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>&#x02019;s framework (<xref rid="daaf077-B31" ref-type="bibr">Levesque <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).<break/>The co-design challenge: one selected barrier;<break/>A draft of the co-design problem statement;<break/>Feedback on the workshop.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summarizing and translating findings, then sharing a detailed report with the research team.<break/>Discussing findings and planning for the next workshop.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2W1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explaining the research objectives and process;<break/>Presenting the full qualitative study findings;<break/>Empathizing through further discussion of barriers to older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs;<break/>Introducing the problem statement defined by Group 1;<break/>Identifying the problem (barrier) root causes and consequences;<break/>Selecting three modifiable and relevant root causes;<break/>Formulating three &#x02018;HMW&#x02019; questions based on root causes;<break/>Evaluating the workshop.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brainstorming;<break/>Interactive presentation;<break/>Discussions;<break/>Storytelling;<break/>Nominal voting;<break/>Like and dislike display boards.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explaining and facilitating the activities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signed consent forms;<break/>Problem tree;<break/>Three &#x02018;HMW&#x02019; questions;<break/>Feedback on the workshop.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summarizing and translating findings, then sharing a detailed report with the research team.<break/>Discussing findings and planning for the next workshop.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1W3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identifying the problem (barrier) root causes and consequences;<break/>Selecting one root cause and considering its underlying factors;<break/>Formulating three &#x02018;HMW&#x02019; questions based on underlying factors;<break/>Generating solution ideas;<break/>Evaluating the workshop.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem tree analysis;<break/>Brainstorming;<break/>Discussions;<break/>Voting;<break/>Ideation Exercise #1: worst, grounded, and blue-sky ideas;<break/>Ideation Exercise #2: 10 ideas in 10&#x02005;min;<break/>Like and dislike display boards.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussing different prevention levels;<break/>Discussing objectives;<break/>Explaining and facilitating the activities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem tree;<break/>Three &#x02018;HMW&#x02019; questions;<break/>List of solution ideas (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 98);<break/>Feedback on the workshop.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summarizing and translating findings, then sharing a detailed report with the research team.<break/>Discussing findings and planning for the next workshop.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2W2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generating solution ideas;<break/>Mapping ideas on the 2*2 solution matrix;<break/>Voting for the solution that is most relevant and practical;<break/>Prototyping the solution idea;<break/>Evaluating the workshop.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presentation;<break/>Ideation exercise: grounded and blue-sky ideas;<break/>Brainstorming;<break/>Discussion;<break/>Voting;<break/>Like and dislike display boards.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussing objectives;<break/>Explaining and facilitating the activities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">List of solution ideas (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 14);<break/>Solution map;<break/>Selected solution idea;<break/>Prototype: plan to implement the screening for depression and memory problems as a new service for older people at the PHCC;<break/>Feedback on the workshop.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summarizing and translating findings, then sharing a detailed report with the research team.<break/>Planning for the next workshop.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1W4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brainstorm further ideas;<break/>Discussing and adding advisors&#x02019; ideas;<break/>Mapping ideas on the 2*2 solution matrix;<break/>Voting for the solution that is most relevant and practical;<break/>Prototyping the solution idea;<break/>Evaluating the workshop.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presentation;<break/>Brainstorming;<break/>Discussion;<break/>Voting;<break/>Like and dislike display boards.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussing objectives;<break/>Explaining and facilitating the activities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">List of solution ideas;<break/>Solution map;<break/>Selected solution idea;<break/>Prototype: campaign creative brief;<break/>Feedback on the workshop.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Summarizing and translating findings, then sharing a detailed report with the research team.<break/>Communicating back the prototype draft for feedback.<break/>Discussing findings and planning for the next workshop.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final common workshop</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presenting G1 and G2 prototypes;<break/>Getting feedback;<break/>Refining current prototypes;<break/>Discussing participants&#x02019; experiences with co-design.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presentations;<break/>Discussions;<break/>Survey and focus group discussion.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discussing objectives;<break/>Explaining and facilitating the activities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feedback on prototypes;<break/>Completed exit survey forms;<break/>Shared experiences regarding participation in the co-design workshops.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Collecting and summarizing results.<break/>Sharing a detailed report with the research team.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>&#x02018;G&#x02019; stands for Group, &#x02018;W&#x02019; stands for Workshop, and the numbers indicate the designated group (1 or 2) and workshop (1&#x02013;4 for Group 1 and 1&#x02013;2 for Group 2).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.7"><title>Workshops for older people and family members (Group 1)</title><sec id="daaf077-s2.7.1"><title>Workshop 1 (G1W1): empathize</title><p>The introduction included an icebreaker to establish relationships among team members and ensure a comfortable environment; an agreement on roles, responsibilities, ground rules, schedules, and communication means to establish clarity and trust between the PI and the co-design team; and an explanation of the design thinking stages to familiarize participants with the process and objectives. Participants&#x02019; expectations and concerns were discussed, and then, informed signed consent was obtained.</p><p>The empathy phase was informed by findings from the qualitative foundational study, presented through storytelling. Story sharing is an effective tool to communicate gathered insights while engaging listeners&#x02019; ideas and emotions (<xref rid="daaf077-B13" ref-type="bibr">Doorley <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2018</xref>). The PI created the story featuring a persona and summarizing barriers constraining older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs. Participants explored challenges highlighted in the story and identified commonalities with their own experiences.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.7.2"><title>Workshop 2 (G1W2): define</title><p>The full list of identified barriers from the foundational study was introduced through a puzzle game, ensuring the active participants&#x02019; engagement while exploring results. Based on the empathy phase discussions, each participant nominated two barriers according to two criteria: relevance to older people&#x02019;s needs and feasibility to address with limited funding. Duplicates and ideas that did not meet the selection criteria were removed. Nominal voting was then used to select one barrier, from the 10 shortlisted ones, constituting the co-design challenge. With the facilitator&#x02019;s guidance, participants collaboratively developed the problem statement.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.7.3"><title>Workshop 3 (G1W3): ideate</title><p>Ideation was facilitated by following these steps: (i) using the problem tree analysis (<xref rid="daaf077-B1" ref-type="bibr">ODI Global 2009</xref>) to uncover the root causes and consequences associated with the selected barrier; (ii) voting to select one root cause; (iii) considering the factors underlying this root cause to formulate three &#x02018;how might we?&#x02019; (HMW) questions (<xref rid="daaf077-B13" ref-type="bibr">Doorley <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2018</xref>); (iv) answering the HMW questions by providing blue-sky, grounded, and worst solution ideas (<xref rid="daaf077-B49" ref-type="bibr">R&#x000e9;amonn and Kane 2024</xref>); and (v) applying the 10 ideas in a 10-min exercise (<xref rid="daaf077-B49" ref-type="bibr">R&#x000e9;amonn and Kane 2024</xref>) to yield more ideas.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.7.4"><title>Workshop 4 (G1W4): prototype</title><p>To finalize the ideation phase, participants were grouped into two teams, each completing the following tasks: (i) discussing a random selection of solution ideas generated during the ideation phase; (ii) mapping them according to their importance and applicability on the 2*2 solution matrix; and (iii) nominating one idea from the quadrant featuring the most important and applicable solutions. This activity yielded two solution ideas. The team assessed their advantages and limitations and then agreed on one for prototyping. By using brainstorming and open discussion methods, participants identified necessary elements to conceptualize and present their solution, thereafter elaborated on each to finalize their prototype. As agreed with participants, the PI submitted a brief summary to them using the messenger service via WhatsApp.</p></sec></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.8"><title>Workshops for service providers (Group 2)</title><p>Speeding up the design process was possible with this group composed of a small number of service providers who work together at the same PHCC. During the first workshop, the same methods used with the first group were employed to complete the introduction and empathy phase. After introducing the problem defined by Group 1, the tree analysis was applied to analyze it, choose one root cause, and formulate three HMW questions. The second workshop focused on the ideation and prototyping stages. Participants (i) individually generated blue-sky and grounded ideas for each HMW question; (ii) selected the top three solutions for each HMW question; (iii) mapped the selected solutions on an importance/applicability matrix; and (iv) reached a consensus on the most relevant and applicable idea to prototype.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.9"><title>Joint workshop: test</title><p>This workshop focused on collaboratively presenting both prototypes developed by the two co-design teams and gathering feedback on them. All participants were involved in presenting a section of their prototype. Constructive feedback was provided using (i) one idea the participant liked; (ii) one idea the participant did not like; and (iii) one suggestion. Comments were discussed before asking each group to vote on necessary refinements to finalize their prototypes. A closing ceremony took place to thank participants for their commitment and acknowledge their contribution to the final outcome. The last part of the workshop included a discussion with participants and feedback on their participation, and the co-design process was noted.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.10"><title>Interviews with advisors</title><p>During the ideation phase, the PI conducted three individual interviews (30&#x02013;45&#x02005;min) with three older people living with motor and sensory limitations. The structured interviews took place at the advisors&#x02019; places and were audio-recorded. The PI obtained participants&#x02019; signed consent, briefed them on the work accomplished in the co-design workshops, collected their suggested solutions, and then added them to Group 1 discussions. The advisors provided feedback on the prototype using WhatsApp, as a preferred mode of communication.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.11"><title>Data analysis and interpretation of results</title><p>Co-design workshops and advisory structured interviews were audio-recorded. The PI used the recordings and the outputs from each workshop to summarize and compile key ideas in text or tables. Content analysis, as described by <xref rid="daaf077-B14" ref-type="bibr">Erlingsson and Brysiewicz (2017)</xref>, was applied to analyze the generated data. Meaning units were highlighted and coded. Codes were revisited iteratively and grouped under different categories and themes (<xref rid="daaf077-B14" ref-type="bibr">Erlingsson and Brysiewicz 2017</xref>). The PI, who is bilingual, analyzed the data in Arabic to preserve the meaning carried by the participants&#x02019; language. After each workshop, the PI translated the summarized data into English for discussion with co-authors. The back translation methods of some summarized research outputs (co-design challenge, problem trees, and prototypes) were verified by an expert.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s2.12"><title>Trustworthiness</title><p>Several strategies were employed to ensure the criteria of rigor (<xref rid="daaf077-B35" ref-type="bibr">Nowell <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2017</xref>). &#x02018;Credibility&#x02019; was enhanced through member checking to ensure participants&#x02019; perspectives are authentically represented. Peer debriefing was ensured via timely reporting and discussions of all study steps with the co-authors. &#x02018;Transferability&#x02019; was promoted by providing a thick description of the context and participants. To increase &#x02018;dependability,&#x02019; research methods, including analysis procedures, were explained comprehensively and documented. An audit trail tailing the data collection process and documenting the flow of the decision-making process was used to establish &#x02018;confirmability.&#x02019; Reflexivity was also practiced by using after each workshop Rolfe et al.&#x02019;s reflective tool &#x02018;What, So what, Now what&#x02019; (What&#x02014;describes the situation; So What&#x02014;discusses key learning and understanding; and Now What&#x02014;identifies the need for specific actions) (<xref rid="daaf077-B40" ref-type="bibr">Rolfe Freshwater and Jasper 2001</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="daaf077-s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>All participants attended all co-designed workshops. <xref rid="daaf077-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> outlines the participants&#x02019; characteristics and highlights the group diversity in terms of age, gender, and socioeconomic status.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="daaf077-T2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Participants&#x02019; characteristics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Older people(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9: workshops <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 and advisors <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family members(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Service providers(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60&#x02013;70: 50%<break/>70&#x02013;80: 50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;50: 75%<break/>50&#x02013;60: 25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;40: 67%<break/>40&#x02013;60: 33%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: 44.5%<break/>Male: 55.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: 75%<break/>Male: 25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: 100%<break/>Male: 0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes: 22%<break/>No: 78%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes: 100%<break/>No: 0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes: 100%<break/>No: 0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary: 22%<break/>Secondary: 34%<break/>University: 44%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary: 0%<break/>Secondary: 25%<break/>University: 75%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary: 0%<break/>Secondary: 33%<break/>University: 67%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status (self-rated)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low: 44%<break/>Medium: 56%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low: 50%<break/>Medium: 50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low: 33%<break/>Medium: 67%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role at the PHCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02013;</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02013;</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrative: 33%<break/>Nurse/nurse-aid: 67%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>This section presents results generated throughout each design thinking stage culminating in the final co-design outcome.</p><sec id="daaf077-s3.1"><title>Empathize</title><p>This phase allowed participants to discuss barriers constraining older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs, based on findings from the foundational qualitative study, presented through storytelling. Older people stated that the story truly resonated with their reality, mirroring and reflecting their own lived experiences.<disp-quote><p>I am really impressed, this story reflects our own reality (G1 participant, female, age 76).</p></disp-quote></p><p>The key access barriers identified by older people and family members fall into three categories: service delivery, individual attributes, and social factors. Regarding the delivery side, participants emphasized the shortage of physicians, which leads to overcrowding, long waiting time at facilities, and superficial medical examinations. They stated that physicians&#x02019; attendance at PHCCs is very limited, prompting them to examine a large number of patients within a narrow time frame. This makes them focus on the patients&#x02019; chief complaints at the expense of preventive care. The lack of training on geriatric care, in addition to the influx of displaced people after the Syrian crisis, has exacerbated this problem.<disp-quote><p>Older people wait for a long time to be examined for ten minutes; physicians are rushed and can barely examine the patient quickly and prescribe medications (G1 participant, female, age 41).</p></disp-quote></p><p>At the individual level, the lack of family support was reported as an essential factor that significantly impacts older people&#x02019;s care journey. Limited financial resources were a paramount factor increasing older people&#x02019;s dependency, jeopardizing their health, and undermining their dignity.<disp-quote><p>Older people definitely need someone to help them seek care, reach centers, and ensure that they are receiving needed care (G1 participant, male, age 49).</p></disp-quote><disp-quote><p>Older people do not feel comfortable asking for help; they hide their symptoms (G1 participant, male, age 71).</p></disp-quote></p><p>Labeling PHCC users as &#x02018;disadvantaged&#x02019; was considered as one of the social factors limiting the use of PHCC services.</p><p>While one service provider regarded the results as exaggerated and unfair considering the efforts deployed by the team, the other two explicitly indicated that these results were expected. The PI clarified that the results summarize findings from different centers and the presented ones focus particularly on barriers to meet the co-design objectives. From the delivery side, care providers highlighted the lack of information about services and funding as significant challenges, which leads to users&#x02019; negative experiences. The shortage of personnel, particularly geriatric professionals, the increasing demand for chronic medications, and the short clinical examination time were also highlighted.<disp-quote><p>Short funds underlie most of the problems concerning service organization and delivery. (G2 participant, female, age 48).</p></disp-quote></p><p>On the social level, service providers discussed the non-acceptance of low-cost services, often correlated with low quality.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s3.2"><title>Define</title><p>After exploring the full list of barriers identified throughout the foundational study, participants emphasized the importance of lacking social pension plans and health coverage as a critical issue.<disp-quote><p>Fair pension plans are key to enable older people&#x02019;s access to health care (G1 participant, male, age 74).</p></disp-quote></p><p>However, participants agreed on selection criteria that prioritize the need to reach relevant yet practical solutions that are PHCC-based and actionable within available funds. A nominal voting system produced a list of ten shortlisted barriers related to service delivery. The top three barriers included (i) the lack of focus on preventive care, (ii) inconsistent application of patient preparation as part of the medical examination, and (iii) poor organization of services and favoritism. The final agreed topic, as voted by participants, was a lack of focus on preventive care.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s3.3"><title>Ideate</title><p>Explaining prevention levels at the beginning of the workshop was instrumental in narrowing down the co-design challenge and refining the problem statement. Participants identified the decline in cognitive abilities and mental health among older adults as a significant concern, particularly for retired individuals living alone due to increased life stressors.</p><p>Accordingly, older people and family members elaborated the following problem statement based on &#x02018;(the user) need (what), because (insight from the empathy phase)&#x02019; model (<xref rid="daaf077-B49" ref-type="bibr">R&#x000e9;amonn and Kane 2024</xref>):<disp-quote><p>Retired older people who live alone need preventive strategies to promote their cognitive abilities and mental health because they expressed that they live with psychological distress and memory problems, and they seek care at advanced stages, while care providers at PHCCs do not assess these conditions systematically.</p></disp-quote></p><p>The problem tree analysis of both groups revealed a consensus that the lack of preventive strategies to promote mental health and cognitive abilities in older adults can negatively impact their emotional well-being, physical health, and care delivery, potentially resulting in fatal consequences (<xref rid="daaf077-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). According to all participants, the root cause of this problem relate to clients, providers, service organization, and policies. The main client-related factors included a lack of awareness regarding the importance of preventive care and the inability of some older people to provide accurate answers, especially when they are unaccompanied, present cognitive problems, or when their companion cannot wait. Provider-related factors included the lack of competence, training, empathy, and geriatric professionals, in addition to overload. Service-related factors were the lack of home care, inconsistent application of patient preparation, lack of focus on preventive care, and limited funds. Policy-related factors encompassed the lack of investment in preventive care and the reduced attention to geriatric care compared with maternal and child health.</p><fig position="float" id="daaf077-F2" fig-type="figure"><label>
Figure 2.
</label><caption><p>Results of the problem tree analysis completed by older people and family members.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf077f2" position="float"/></fig><p>Among root causes, older people and family members chose to address the lack of awareness about the importance of preventive care among people and providers, while service providers focused on the providers&#x02019; lack of competence.</p><p>Considering the underlying factors that contributed to the lack of awareness about the importance of preventive care, older people and family members formulated the following three HMW questions:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>HMW prioritize preventive care despite the current situation?</p></list-item><list-item><p>HMW emphasize preventive care through school and university curricula?</p></list-item><list-item><p>HMW empower providers to apply preventive measures?</p></list-item></list><p>To answer the HMW questions, advisors&#x02019; interviews and ideation exercises with Group 1 generated 98 solution ideas, including: (i) empowering providers through capacity-building activities facilitated by national and international experts and fund-raising activities to empower providers and launch specialized preventive centers and (ii) raising people&#x02019;s awareness on preventive care through media campaigns, university- and school-based activities and curricula, community and home-based activities, and PHCC-based activities to be implemented during waiting time.</p><p>To address the providers&#x02019; lack of competence, service providers developed the following three HMW questions:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>How can we organize the implementation of preventive strategies?</p></list-item><list-item><p>How can we empower providers to apply preventive strategies?</p></list-item><list-item><p>How can we plan for the implementation of preventive strategies?</p></list-item></list><p>Through ideation exercises, 14 ideas were generated, and finally, three solution ideas for each HMW were achieved. Objectives were (i) selecting and using validated screening tools for mental health and cognitive abilities, (ii) capacity-building activities, and (iii) actions to implement preventive strategies.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s3.4"><title>Prototype</title><p>Older people and family members mapped their suggested solutions in a 2*2 matrix and nominated two solution ideas which were judged to be most important and applicable, to raise awareness about preventive care to promote mental health and cognitive abilities:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Gathering older people informally after prayer time to discuss prevention practices;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Social media awareness campaign.</p></list-item></list><p>The whole group discussed the advantages and limitations of each idea and agreed on the final solution outlined below:<disp-quote><p>&#x02018;Campaign on social media to raise awareness about preventive strategies to promote mental health and cognitive abilities among older people.&#x02019;</p></disp-quote></p><p>Despite inclusivity challenges, particularly for people with limited access to mobile phones and technology, this solution was selected for its potential to reach a larger number of older people who can engage through their phones; its use of unified messages shared by experts; and its cost-effectiveness.</p><p>The solution idea consisted of a piloting phase targeting up to 30 users of the PHCC services aged over 64 years who live alone. This campaign, designed to be launched through the PHCC, directs weekly text messages or short video messages via WhatsApp or by means of a booklet to the target group, inviting them to apply practical preventive activities to enhance their mental health and cognitive abilities. The brainstorming activity with participants resulted in a list of elements to be elaborated to prototype their idea, including an introduction, objectives, target audience, communication channels, deliverables, and evaluation. The PI asked specific questions and, through open discussion with participants, developed a first draft of the prototype, which is a social media campaign creative brief (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File S3</xref>&#x02014;Prototype 1).</p><p>The service providers mapped prioritized solutions in a 2*2 matrix and selected the following most important and applicable idea:<disp-quote><p>&#x02018;Elaborate a plan to implement screening for depression and memory problems, as part of the services delivered by the PHCC for older people.&#x02019;</p></disp-quote></p><p>The participants suggested a pilot phase targeting 10 older people aged 80 years and above. The key elements required to prototype the service implementation plan included defining the target audience, choosing and adapting screening tools, training care providers, scheduling the service, reaching out to the target audience, setting referral systems, and evaluating the pilot phase. This plan was developed using the 5Ws 1H framework (<xref rid="daaf077-B2" ref-type="bibr">International Project Management Association 2018</xref>). The detailed plan prototype is available in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File S3</xref>&#x02014;Prototype 2.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s3.5"><title>Test</title><p>As part of the feedback shared with service providers, older people and family members expressed appreciation for collaborating with specialists to use scientific tools for assessment, the capacity building for the PHCC team, and the evaluation component. However, they questioned the age of the target population as service providers explained that they chose to commence the testing phase with individuals aged 80 years and above because they could be at higher risk. The group of older people and family members insisted on lowering the age of the target population, as they believed that prevention should start earlier. The suggestion of increasing the number of target people for the piloting phase was also discussed for evaluation purposes, to obtain sufficient feedback about the service. After the workshop, suggestions were summarized and shared with Group 2 members, who agreed to increase the target audience to 25 and lower the age to 70 years.</p><p>Regarding the feedback for Group 1, providers appreciated the suggestion to reach out to beneficiaries of services delivered through the PHCC and share videos, voice messages, practical exercises, and games. However, they raised concerns about the applicability of the idea and expressed that producing the resources is time-consuming. Additional discussions with older people and family members suggested the prototype was achievable and provided further ideas for development. Group 1 members suggested collaborating with a geriatrician, as refinement to their prototype, and highlighted the importance of undertaking screenings newly added to PHCC services and collaborating with specialist practitioners.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="daaf077-s4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This co-design research was informed by a foundational study that identified enablers and barriers to older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs in Lebanon. This current study engaged older people, family members, and service providers to co-design solutions that maximize access to PHCC. Beyond the definition limiting &#x02018;access&#x02019; to the reach and use of services delivered by PHCCs, the qualitative and co-design studies adopted Levesque <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>&#x02019;s (<xref rid="daaf077-B31" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) definition of healthcare access. Access is viewed as a set of opportunities starting with the perception of a need for care and ending with appropriate services that fit the users&#x02019; needs, a process enabling acceptable economic and health outcomes. According to the patient-centered access to healthcare framework, access is achieved when services are available, acceptable, affordable, and appropriate for people&#x02019;s needs; but also, when people are able to perceive the need for care, to seek, to reach, to pay for care, and engage with it (<xref rid="daaf077-B31" ref-type="bibr">Levesque <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Discussions during the empathy phase allowed older people to highlight several problems perceived as priority, including their limited ability to afford PHC services, aggravated by the currency devaluation, dysfunctional insurance schemes, and absence of social security plans. Limited resources impede people&#x02019;s access to healthcare services, especially preventive care, as they primarily seek medical assistance only at advanced stages of disease, a pattern that the <xref rid="daaf077-B30" ref-type="bibr">Lebanese Ministry of Social Affairs (2021)</xref> has also noted on the national level. They also acknowledged the shortage of geriatric professionals, the overcrowding at PHCCs, and the lack of geriatric care training for care providers, contributing to superficial medical examination. For practical purposes, the team agreed to select a barrier that can be addressed within the available funds.</p><p>Older people and family members identified &#x02018;the lack of focus on preventive care&#x02019; as a barrier to the appropriateness dimension of services (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2025</xref>) and a constraint to their access to quality care that meets their health needs. Although this problem denotes a gap in the delivery of services which are majorly focused on therapeutic care (<xref rid="daaf077-B30" ref-type="bibr">Lebanese Ministry of Social Affairs 2021</xref>), it also relates to older people and their families&#x02019; inability to afford preventive care, which makes them answer urgent issues only, especially amidst the dire economic crisis (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2025</xref>). Older people with comorbidities demonstrate increasing needs for integrated care that includes health promotion and disease prevention strategies (<xref rid="daaf077-B54" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2017</xref>). The call for greater emphasis on preventive care aligns with international guidelines for successful and healthy aging (<xref rid="daaf077-B56" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2020</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B37" ref-type="bibr">Palapar <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>). To narrow down the co-design challenge, older people chose to highlight &#x02018;the lack of preventive strategies that promote mental health and cognitive abilities among older people,&#x02019; viewed as pressing needs for Lebanese older people according to the available literature (<xref rid="daaf077-B20" ref-type="bibr">HelpAge 2022</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B8" ref-type="bibr">Cherfane <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>). Based on their lived experiences, they recognize the evidence-based connection between mental health and cognitive abilities (<xref rid="daaf077-B27" ref-type="bibr">Kobayashi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2022</xref>, <xref rid="daaf077-B6" ref-type="bibr">Bai <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>). Focusing on mental health is also one of the main pillars noted in the Lebanese national strategy to enhance older people&#x02019;s well-being (<xref rid="daaf077-B30" ref-type="bibr">Lebanese Ministry of Social Affairs 2021</xref>).</p><p>Older people and family members collaborated in a group working in parallel to service providers, on the same problem defined by older people. The problem analysis conducted by these two groups provided different perspectives to comprehensively understand the root causes contributing to this gap. The lack of governmental interest in preventive care, sensitivity surrounding mental health issues, overload and incompetence among care providers, and the population&#x02019;s lack of awareness regarding the importance of preventive care were common themes. While the service providers&#x02019; group focused on the delivery aspect, the group of older people and family members emphasized the lack of awareness about preventive strategies that promote mental health and cognitive abilities among older people, resulting in a low demand for such services.</p><p>The design thinking process run in parallel with both co-design teams resulted in two complementary solution ideas: (i) the service providers prototyped a plan to launch screenings for depression and cognitive abilities as a new service that adds to the PHCC package of services and (ii) older people and family members prototyped a creative brief for a social media campaign to raise awareness about the importance of practical preventive measures to enhance mental health and cognitive abilities, including the uptake of screenings offered at the PHCC. The first prototype details the plan for screening implementation, which includes defining and reaching out to the target population, choosing and validating the screening tools, training health professionals, dedicating specific days and providers to implement the screening, creating referral systems, and evaluating the pilot phase. The second prototype outlines the pilot phase of a 6-month social media campaign to be launched through the PHCC, targeting a group of older people who use its services. It consists of sending weekly messages&#x02014;via WhatsApp&#x02014;to highlight the importance of preventive measures in promoting mental health and cognitive abilities, and their impact on improving health and economic outcomes, with practical tips and activities to apply.</p><p>Suggested solutions, addressing one root cause of only one barrier, could maximize older people&#x02019;s access to the PHCC by improving one or more service dimensions or population&#x02019;s ability (<xref rid="daaf077-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). In fact, service providers&#x02019; solution constitutes a step toward implementing the comprehensive geriatric assessment at the PHCC level, which increases the adequacy and appropriateness of services (<xref rid="daaf077-B34" ref-type="bibr">Nord <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2021</xref>). It also encompasses the training of care providers on geriatric care and features the proactive role of nurses in conducting this assessment, as advocated throughout the available literature (<xref rid="daaf077-B16" ref-type="bibr">Garrard <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2020</xref>). It constitutes a pioneering step at the level of PHC delivery in general, since such screenings are not applied even in private clinics, in Lebanon, except for the few centralized geriatric clinics (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>). Training care providers and expanding geriatric services refine the availability and accommodation of services. Enhancing the quality of services at PHCCs, notably the clinical examination along with integrated care and appropriate referral systems, fosters the population&#x02019;s trust, thereby increasing service acceptability and appropriateness and boosting the ability to seek them. Moreover, the solution provided by older people and family members ameliorates the approachability of services by raising awareness about available services at the PHCC. Promoting mental health and cognitive abilities using practical activities also boosts health outcomes, thus contributing to decreased demand for services, less overcrowding, and waiting time at PHCCs, which increases the quality of delivered care and fosters the accommodation of services. Enhanced mental health is also related to a better quality of life (<xref rid="daaf077-B6" ref-type="bibr">Bai <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2023</xref>), satisfaction (<xref rid="daaf077-B26" ref-type="bibr">Jokela 2022</xref>), and reduced expenditure for health (<xref rid="daaf077-B15" ref-type="bibr">Figueroa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2020</xref>), denoting a better ability to pay for preventive services. People with sound cognitive abilities can better perceive the need for care, seek services, and engage with care thoughtfully (<xref rid="daaf077-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dableh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2024</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="daaf077-F3" fig-type="figure"><label>
Figure 3.
</label><caption><p>Solutions maximizing older people&#x02019;s access to PHCCs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="daaf077f3" position="float"/></fig><sec id="daaf077-s4.1"><title>Co-design strengths and challenges</title><p>This study brings evidence that older people are valuable informants and excellent collaborators to the improvement of geriatric services, mainly because of their lived experiences, cumulative knowledge, and their dedication and availability to participate in co-design workshops. Engaging different partners in the co-design process ensures a comprehensive understanding of the problem and generates solutions that account for different perspectives. Dividing the co-design team into two groups was instrumental in managing power imbalances, which was appreciated and approved during the last workshop by all participants. It enriched the process by generating two complementary solution ideas accounting for delivery and demand perspectives. It also allowed the two teams to share mutual feedback, leading to grounded solutions that genuinely address older people&#x02019;s needs. Attending workshops in person offered an invaluable opportunity to engage co-designers, especially Lebanese older people who may not be able to engage with virtual workshops, considering their potential limited digital literacy and restricted accessibility to smartphones and internet connection. Other factors contributing to the success of the co-design process included the authors&#x02019; expertise in co-design, the shared cultural background between the PI and participants, and the use of a structured process with evidence-based, interactive, and user-friendly methods.</p><p>Challenging factors were addressed as follows:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The insecure situation and limited financial resources restricted the number of workshops (one for each phase of the design thinking process); however, insights from the foundational study and structured activities facilitated the fulfillment of the co-design objectives. A shift to weekly workshops instead of planned biweekly ones was necessary to speed up the process for security reasons; this turned out to be an advantage as it maintained the momentum, facilitated the full commitment of older people, and ensured the retention of key discussion ideas over the workshops.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The need to run several workshops over a short period required the PI&#x02019;s full dedication and advanced time management skills. Advanced group management and facilitation skills were vital to fulfill the co-design objectives, and secure a safe and comfortable co-design environment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The lack of technical assistance during workshops for data protection purposes, required thorough preparation and task delegation to participants when relevant.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The exclusion of people lacking literacy and presenting sensory and motor limitations was alleviated by representing their views through the advisory group. The commitment of physicians to workshops was not feasible, but they provided their input on the main problem through the qualitative study.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="daaf077-s5"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>In line with international recommendations, this study addresses one of the vital needs and rights for older people, which is accessing appropriate PHC services and promoting active and healthy ageing. Amidst the alarming economic situation, access to PHCCs is essential for preserving older people&#x02019;s dignity and promoting their autonomy and well-being. The co-design approach amplified the voices of service providers, older people, and families who are current or potential users, allowing them to express their challenges and participate actively in designing solutions. Results inform policymakers and service providers to redesign services to better meet the needs of older people. The detailed process serves as footprints for other researchers who are willing to adopt participatory research approaches, especially toward an active involvement of older people in defining research problems and innovating user-centered solutions. Findings from the foundational qualitative study highlight several barriers mapped across all service dimensions and population abilities; however, this co-design process focused on only one barrier to address. This highlights the need for more research to tackle other issues across varying PHCCs and contexts, support the implementation of co-designed solutions, and involve end-users in re-shaping services.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>daaf077_Supplementary_Data</label><media xlink:href="daaf077_supplementary_data.zip"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Ms. Gladys Abi Said Dib for offering the GladDays Happiness Spot venue to host all co-design workshops along with all participants involved in this co-design study.</p></ack><sec id="daaf077-s6"><title>Authors contributions</title><p>S.D., T.K., and K.F. assisted in the conception of the study, and all co-authors contributed to the study design and methodology development. S.D., along with R.H., provided resources. Then, S.D. collected and analyzed the data with support from T.K. and K.F. T.K. and K.F. supervised the project. S.D. wrote the first manuscript draft, which was revised and edited by all co-authors who validated the results and approved the final manuscript version.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s7"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">Health Promotion International</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="daaf077-s8"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec id="daaf077-s9"><title>Funding</title><p>External funds were not received for this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="daaf077-s10"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data underlying this article are available in the article and in its online <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>. However, due to the nature of research and in compliance with GDPR requirements for data privacy, raw data, including audio-recording and identifiers of participants, are not available.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="daaf077-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Allemang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sitter</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimitropoulos</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pragmatism as a paradigm for patient-oriented research</article-title>. <source>Health Expect</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hex.13384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34748689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Inter-relationship between cognitive performance and depressive symptoms and their association with quality of life in older adults: a network analysis based on the 2017-2018 wave of Chinese Longitudinal Healthy Longevity Survey (CLHLS)</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>320</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.09.159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36206885</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chemali</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chahine</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sibai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Older adult care in Lebanon: towards stronger and sustainable reforms</article-title>. <source>East Mediterr Health J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2008</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19161123</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cherfane</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boueri</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Issa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Unveiling the unseen toll: exploring the impact of the Lebanese economic crisis on the health-seeking behaviors in a sample of patients with diabetes and hypertension</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-18116-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38413883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dableh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frazer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokes</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Access of older people to primary health care in low and middle-income countries: a systematic scoping review</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>e0298973</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0298973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38640096</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dableh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frazer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azar</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> Barriers and enablers to the access of older people to primary health care centers in Lebanon: A qualitative inquiry. Paper submitted for publication, 2025.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>da Silva</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pucci</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>VR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>O acesso do idoso na aten&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o prim&#x000e1;ria &#x000e0; sa&#x000fa;de: uma revis&#x000e3;o integrativa</article-title>. <source>Rev de APS</source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.34019/1809-8363.2018.v21.15911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Davis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tuckey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gwilt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Understanding co-design practice as a process of &#x0201c;welldoing&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Int J Art Des Educ</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jade.12459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Donaldson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Product design in less industrialized economies: constraints and opportunities in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Res Eng Des</source> &#x000a0;<year>2006</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00163-006-0017-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Doorley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holcomb</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klebahn</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<italic toggle="yes">Design thinking Bootleg: Stanford D. School</italic>. 2018. <ext-link xlink:href="https://dschool.stanford.edu/resources/design-thinking-bootleg" ext-link-type="uri">https://dschool.stanford.edu/resources/design-thinking-bootleg</ext-link> (26 April 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Erlingsson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brysiewicz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A hands-on guide to doing content analysis</article-title>. <source>Afr J Emerg Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.afjem.2017.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30456117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Figueroa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phelan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orav</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Association of mental health disorders with health care spending in the medicare population</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e201210</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.1210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191329</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Garrard</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cox</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dodds</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Comprehensive geriatric assessment in primary care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40520-019-01183-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30968287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>George</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Teaching focus group interviewing: benefits and challenges</article-title>. <source>Teach Sociol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092055X12465295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Giolitto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">The WACOSS Co-Design Toolkit.</italic> 2017. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.wacoss.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/co-design-toolkit-combined-2-1.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wacoss.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/co-design-toolkit-combined-2-1.pdf</ext-link> (12 April 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Goodwin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Low</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MSA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quinn</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Including older people in health and social care research: best practice recommendations based on the INCLUDE framework</article-title>. <source>Age Ageing</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>afad082</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afad082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37261448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>HelpAge</collab>
</person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">A glimmer of Hope amidst the Pain</italic>. 2022. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ilo.org/publications/glimmer-hope-amidst-pain" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ilo.org/publications/glimmer-hope-amidst-pain</ext-link> (25 April 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hyett</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bagley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lacono</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Evaluation of a codesign method used to support the inclusion of children with disability in mainstream schools</article-title>. <source>Int J Qual Methods</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>e1609406920924982</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1609406920924982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ibsen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strand</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A longitudinal cohort study on the use of health and care services by older adults living at home with/without dementia before and during the COVID-19 pandemic: the HUNT study</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>485</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-024-10846-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38641570</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<ext-link xlink:href="https://IDEO.org" ext-link-type="uri">IDEO.org</ext-link>. <italic toggle="yes">The Field Guide to Human-Centered Design</italic>. 2015. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.designkit.org/resources/1.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.designkit.org/resources/1.html</ext-link> (12 April 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">International Project Management Association. <italic toggle="yes">5Ws 1H: A Technique to Improve Project Management Efficiencies</italic>. <year>2018</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://ipma.world/5ws-1h-a-technique-to-improve-project-management-efficiencies/" ext-link-type="uri">https://ipma.world/5ws-1h-a-technique-to-improve-project-management-efficiencies/</ext-link> (20 August 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jagtap</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Codesign in resource-limited societies: theoretical perspectives, inputs, outputs and influencing factors</article-title>. <source>Res Eng Des</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00163-022-00384-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>James</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buffel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Co-research with older people: a systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Ageing Soc</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>2930</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0144686X21002014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jokela</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Why is cognitive ability associated with psychological distress and wellbeing? Exploring psychological, biological, and social mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Pers Individ Dif</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>192</volume>:<fpage>111592</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.paid.2022.111592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kobayashi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O'Shea</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joseph</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Acute relationships between mental health and cognitive function during the COVID-19 pandemic: longitudinal evidence from middle-aged and older US adults</article-title>. <source>SSM Ment Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>100097</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssmmh.2022.100097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35434675</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ku</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lupton</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Health Design Thinking: Creating Products and Services for Better Health</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, Cooper Hewitt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Langmann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Vulnerability, ageism, and health: is it helpful to label older adults as a vulnerable group in health care?</article-title> &#x000a0;<source>Med Health Care Philos</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11019-022-10129-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36402852</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Lebanese ministry of social affairs</collab>
</person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">The National Strategy for Older Persons in Lebanon 2020-</italic>2030. 2021. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.unescwa.org/sites/default/files/news/docs/online_-_final_english_strategy_for_online_use_1.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.unescwa.org/wsites/default/files/news/docs/online_-_final_english_strategy_for_online_use_1.pdf</ext-link> (20 September 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Levesque</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Russell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Patient-centred access to health care: conceptualising access at the interface of health systems and populations</article-title>. <source>Int J Equity Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-9276-12-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23496984</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lubenow</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JAM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barr&#x000ea;to</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AJR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nogueira</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Access for the elderly to primary health care services: an integrative review</article-title>. <source>Int Arch Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>9</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3823/1917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mirza</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hulko</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Service users&#x02019; views on the restructuring of primary and community care services for older adults: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>J Rural Community Dev</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://journals.brandonu.ca/jrcd/article/view/2037/585" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.brandonu.ca/jrcd/article/view/2037/585</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Institute for Health and Care Research&#x02014;NIHR. <italic toggle="yes">Briefing Notes for Researchers &#x02013; Public Involvement in NHS, Health and Social Care Research</italic>. <year>2024</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nihr.ac.uk/briefing-notes-researchers-public-involvement-nhs-health-and-social-care-research#tab-256881" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nihr.ac.uk/briefing-notes-researchers-public-involvement-nhs-health-and-social-care-research#tab-256881</ext-link> (12 February 2025, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nord</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lyth</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alwin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Costs and effects of comprehensive geriatric assessment in primary care for older adults with high risk for hospitalisation</article-title>. <source>BMC Geriatr</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-021-02166-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33882862</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nowell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norris</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Thematic analysis: striving to meet the trustworthiness criteria</article-title>. <source>Int J Qual Methods</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1609406917733847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>O&#x02019;Donnell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collier</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pineda-Pinto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Redefining co-design for social-ecological research and practice: a systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Policy</source> &#x000a0;<year>2025</year>;<volume>164</volume>:<fpage>103998</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsci.2025.103998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Overseas Development Institute&#x02014;ODIGlobal. <italic toggle="yes">Planning Tools: Problem Tree Analysis</italic>. <year>2009</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://odi.org/en/publications/planning-tools-problem-tree-analysis/" ext-link-type="uri">https://odi.org/en/publications/planning-tools-problem-tree-analysis/</ext-link> (25 September 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Palapar</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blom</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkinson-Meyers</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Preventive interventions to improve older people&#x02019;s health outcomes: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>e208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/BJGP.2023.0180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38499364</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Palmer</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weavell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Callander</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The participatory zeitgeist: an explanatory theoretical model of change in an era of coproduction and codesign in healthcare improvement</article-title>. <source>Med Humanit</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/medhum-2017-011398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29954854</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Pi&#x00142;at</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Designing the design. Application of design thinking to social innovation planning</article-title>. <source>Sci Pap Silesian Univ Technol Organiz Manage Ser</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.29119/1641-3466.2024.193.18</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R&#x000e9;amonn D, Kane RL. <italic toggle="yes">Design Thinking</italic>. University College Dublin-Innovation Academy (unpublished course). <year>2024</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rolfe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freshwater</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jasper</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Critical Reflection for Nursing and the Helping Professions: A User's Guide</italic>. 2001. <ext-link xlink:href="https://philpapers.org/rec/ROLCRF" ext-link-type="uri">https://philpapers.org/rec/ROLCRF</ext-link> (29 April 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sakaguchi-Tang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cunningham</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roldan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Co-design with older adults: examining and reflecting on collaboration with aging communities</article-title>. <source>Proc ACM Hum Comput Interact</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3479506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36644216</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sanders</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stappers</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Co-creation and the new landscapes of design</article-title>. <source>CoDesign</source> &#x000a0;<year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15710880701875068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Saunders</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornhill</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <part-title>Understanding research philosophy and approaches to theory development</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Saunders</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornhill</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds.), <source>Research Methods for Business Students</source>. <edition>8</edition>th edn, chapter 4. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>, <year>2019</year>, <fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schilling</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerhardus</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for involving older people in health research&#x02014;a review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1476</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph14121476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schouten</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kip</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dekkers</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Best-practices for co-design processes involving people with severe mental illness for eMental health interventions: a qualitative multi-method approach</article-title>. <source>Des Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/24735132.2022.2145814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schr&#x000f6;der-Butterfill</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marianti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A framework for understanding old-age vulnerabilities</article-title>. <source>Ageing Soc</source> &#x000a0;<year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0144686X05004423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23750062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sumner</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bundele</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Co-designing technology for aging in place: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Gerontologist</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>e395</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>409</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geront/gnaa064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32506136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Terkelsen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wester</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Co-creation and co-production of health promoting activities addressing older people&#x02014;a scoping review</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>13043</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph192013043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36293629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Children&#x02019;s Fund&#x02014;UNICEF. <italic toggle="yes">Integrating Primary Healthcare and Outreach to Communities and Households in Lebanon</italic>. <comment>Unpublished report</comment>. <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>White</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cleary</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Co-design with integrated care teams: establishing information needs</article-title>. <source>Int J Integr Care</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023a</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/ijic.7618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>White</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okello</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Co-designing with engineers for community engagement in rural Uganda</article-title>. <source>Des Sci</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023b</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e12</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/dsj.2023.10</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keenan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Research with patient and public involvement: a realist evaluation&#x02014;the RAPPORT study</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Deliv Res</source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3310/hsdr03380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>
</person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Integrated care for older people: guidelines on community-level interventions to manage declines in intrinsic capacity</italic>. 2017. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241550109" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241550109</ext-link> (3 October 2022, date last accessed)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>
</person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Building the economic case for primary health care: a scoping review</italic>. 2018. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-HIS-SDS-2018.48" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-HIS-SDS-2018.48</ext-link> (20 August 2021, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>
</person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">UN Decade of Healthy Ageing: Plan of Action</italic>. 2020. <ext-link xlink:href="https://cdn.who.int/media/docs/default-source/decade-of-healthy-ageing/decade-proposal-final-apr2020-en.pdf?sfvrsn=b4b75ebc_28" ext-link-type="uri">https://cdn.who.int/media/docs/default-source/decade-of-healthy-ageing/decade-proposal-final-apr2020-en.pdf?sfvrsn=b4b75ebc_28</ext-link> (25 September 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. <italic toggle="yes">Primary Health Care</italic>. <year>2023</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/primary-health-care" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/primary-health-care</ext-link> (25 April 2024, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Xiong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Co-designing interventions to strengthen the primary health care system for the management of hypertension and type 2 diabetes in China</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg Health West Pac</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>101131</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2024.101131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39056090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="daaf077-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yaacoub</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group> S, Zmeter C, Abbas LA <etal>et al</etal> &#x000a0;<article-title>Has the COVID-19 pandemic changed the utilization and provision of essential health care services from 2019 to 2020 in the primary health care network in Lebanon? Results from a nationwide representative cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e0288387</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0288387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37440540</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>