<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WJC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>World Journal of Cardiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-8462</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Baishideng Publishing Group Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12186132</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jWJC.v17.i6.eid107114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4330/wjc.v17.i6.107114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-manuscript">107114</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mood alteration and heart rate variability in patients with cancer on treatment</article-title><alt-title>Chang YC <italic>et al</italic>. Mood alteration and HRV in cancer</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Yun-Chen</given-names></name><aff>School of Nursing and Graduate Institute of Nursing, China Medical University, Taichung 406, Taiwan</aff><aff>Department of Nursing, China Medical University Hospital, Taichung 404, Taiwan</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Wei-Nung</given-names></name><aff>Department of Medicine, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center, Taipei 114, Taiwan</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Felicia</given-names></name><aff>Community Care, Minnesota Oncology, Minneapolis, MN 55404, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Gen-Min</given-names></name><aff>Department of Medicine, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center, Taipei 114, Taiwan</aff><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Hualien Armed Forces General Hospital, Hualien City 970, Taiwan. <email>farmer507@yahoo.com.tw</email></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Author contributions: Chang YC wrote the article; Liu WN, Lin F and Lin GM made critical revisions related to important content of the manuscript; and all authors provided approval of the final version of the article to be published.</p><p>Corresponding author: Gen-Min Lin, Director, FACC, FAHA, FESC, Department of Medicine, Hualien Armed Forces General Hospital, No. 100 Jinfeng Street, Hualien City 970, Taiwan. <email>farmer507@yahoo.com.tw</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>107114</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;The Author(s) 2025. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is an open-access article that was selected by an in-house editor and fully peer-reviewed by external reviewers. It is distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/Licenses/by-nc/4.0/</uri></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>In this article, Deng and Song showed compelling evidence on the connection between heart rate variability (HRV) alterations and cancer in 127 cancer patients compared with healthy reference individuals, highlighting autonomic nervous system dysfunction as a significant physiological manifestation in cancer patients. We discussed that the reduced HRV may be associated with cancer treatments, <italic>e.g.</italic>, operation, chemotherapy and pain control and psychological response such as depression and anxiety related to the affected cancer. A management such as medicine to mood disturbances related to cancer has been shown a benefit to improve HRV in cancer patients.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cancer</kwd><kwd>Chemotherapy</kwd><kwd>Heart rate variability</kwd><kwd>Mental stress</kwd><kwd>Heart</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>
<bold>Core Tip:</bold> We discussed that the reduced heart rate variability may be associated with cancer treatments, <italic>e.g.</italic>, operation, chemotherapy and pain control and psychological response such as depression and anxiety related to the affected cancer. A management such as medicine to mood disturbances related to cancer has been shown a benefit to improve heart rate variability in cancer patients.</p><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Deng and Song[<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] presented compelling evidence on the connection between heart rate variability (HRV) alterations and cancer, highlighting autonomic nervous system dysfunction as a significant physiological manifestation in cancer patients. Their observational study of 127 cancer patients demonstrated that HRV, a non-invasive measure of autonomic function, is significantly abnormal in cancer patients compared to reference individuals, with pronounced reductions especially evident in advanced disease stages.</p></sec><sec><title>MECAHNISMS FOR REDUCED HRV IN CANCER AND MANAGEMENTS</title><p>Cancer treatments, including surgical interventions, chemotherapy, and pain management protocols, have substantial impacts on HRV patterns, reflecting treatment-induced autonomic modulation. Surgical procedures often trigger profound autonomic responses characterized by immediate sympathetic activation followed by gradual recovery, with HRV parameters frequently showing substantial reductions during the perioperative period[<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These alterations can persist beyond the immediate recovery phase, indicating prolonged autonomic dysfunction. Chemotherapeutic agents, particularly anthracyclines, platinum compounds, and taxanes, have been associated with significant reductions in both time-domain and frequency-domain HRV parameters, suggesting these treatments may directly affect cardiac autonomic innervation[<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The cardiotoxic effects of chemotherapy not only manifest as structural cardiac damage but also as functional autonomic dysregulation, potentially contributing to increased cardiovascular morbidity in cancer survivors. Furthermore, adequate pain control has emerged as a crucial factor influencing autonomic function in cancer patients. Uncontrolled pain triggers sympathetic hyperactivity, resulting in reduced HRV, while effective analgesic interventions can partially restore autonomic balance[<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Notably, opioid analgesics demonstrate complex effects on HRV, with initial parasympathetic enhancement often followed by adaptation and potential long-term alterations in autonomic tone. These treatment-related autonomic changes highlight the importance of comprehensive cardiovascular monitoring throughout cancer treatment trajectories, with HRV assessment potentially serving as a valuable tool for early detection of treatment-induced cardiovascular complications.</p><p>Emerging evidence highlights the critical relationship between mood alterations in cancer patients and their impact on HRV, underscoring the complex interplay between psychological distress and autonomic nervous system regulation. A cancer diagnosis and subsequent treatments are frequently associated with heightened emotional stress, anxiety, and depression, which directly influence autonomic function, often manifesting as increased sympathetic activity and diminished parasympathetic tone, resulting in decreased HRV[<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Chronic stress activation perpetuates autonomic imbalance, negatively affecting cardiovascular health, immune function, and potentially reducing overall prognosis and quality of life for cancer patients[<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Given these implications, integrating psychological interventions into comprehensive cancer care has become increasingly critical. Mindfulness-based stress reduction[<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], cognitive-behavioral therapy[<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], supportive counseling[<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and structured psycho-oncological support have all demonstrated potential in modulating autonomic function, enhancing parasympathetic activity, and consequently improving HRV[<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Mindfulness interventions, specifically, have shown promising results in reducing anxiety and depression, thereby attenuating sympathetic dominance and facilitating autonomic recovery[<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Furthermore, relaxation techniques including yoga, meditation, and guided breathing exercises have proven effective in improving emotional well-being and autonomic regulation in cancer populations[<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Pharmacological treatments, when indicated clinically, can complement psychological interventions, particularly in managing severe mood disturbances and their physiological consequences[<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additionally, adjunctive strategies such as music therapy and social support programs provide supplementary benefits, contributing significantly to emotional stabilization and physiological resilience, thereby supporting enhanced HRV outcomes[<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Future research directions should aim at elucidating precise neurophysiological and psychological mechanisms linking mood disturbances to autonomic dysfunction, identifying potential patient-specific moderators, and rigorously evaluating intervention efficacy in long-term HRV improvement and cardiovascular risk mitigation. Embracing a biopsychosocial framework in oncology care can promote comprehensive patient management, fostering both emotional and physiological resilience, ultimately enhancing cancer patient outcomes and quality of life.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The intricate relationship between psychological distress and autonomic nervous system dysfunction underscores the importance of addressing mood alterations in cancer patients as a critical component of comprehensive oncology care. Persistent mood disturbances, such as anxiety and depression, significantly influence HRV, highlighting the necessity for integrative therapeutic approaches aimed at enhancing autonomic balance. Evidence-based psychological interventions, including mindfulness-based stress reduction, cognitive-behavioral therapy, and supportive counseling, demonstrate promising efficacy in restoring parasympathetic activity and mitigating sympathetic over activation. Additionally, complementary practices such as meditation, yoga, guided breathing exercises, and structured psycho-oncological support programs contribute substantially to emotional and physiological resilience. To optimize clinical outcomes, future research should further elucidate the mechanistic pathways linking psychological states to autonomic regulation, refine intervention modalities, and identify personalized factors that enhance responsiveness to these treatments. By recognizing and incorporating psychological well-being into cancer management, clinicians can foster a holistic, patient-centered approach that improves both cardiovascular function and overall quality of life for individuals affected by cancer.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflict-of-interest statement:</bold> All the authors report no relevant conflicts of interest for this article.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Invited article; Externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Peer-review model:</bold> Single blind</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Specialty type:</bold> Cardiac and cardiovascular systems</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Country of origin:</bold> Taiwan</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Peer-review report&#x02019;s classification</bold>
</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Scientific Quality:</bold> Grade B</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Novelty:</bold> Grade B</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Creativity or Innovation:</bold> Grade B</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Scientific Significance:</bold> Grade B</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>P-Reviewer:</bold> Sato T <bold>S-Editor:</bold> Bai Y <bold>L-Editor:</bold> A <bold>P-Editor:</bold> Guo X</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Connection between heart rate variability alterations and cancer in tumor patients</article-title><source>World J Cardiol</source><year>2025</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>102999</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40161569</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehlsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kehlet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Preoperative heart rate variability as a predictor of perioperative outcomes: a systematic review without meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Clin Monit Comput</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35092527</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caspani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tralongo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campiotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asteggiano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guasti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Squizzato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Prevention of anthracycline-induced cardiotoxicity: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Intern Emerg Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33011930</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeyaprakash</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sangha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sivapathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pathan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Negishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cardiotoxic Effect of Modern Anthracycline Dosing on Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Placebo Arms From Randomized Controlled Trials</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e018802</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33660514</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Troisi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pazzaglia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pascalis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casagrande</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Heart Rate Variability and Pain: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>Brain Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35203917</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callendar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shakeshaft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St</surname><given-names>Ours S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lucero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>High-trait anxious individuals show positive relationship between HRV and threat vigilance</article-title><source>Psychophysiology</source><year>2023</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>e14282</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36869018</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thayer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brosschot</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The relationship of autonomic imbalance, heart rate variability and cardiovascular disease risk factors</article-title><source>Int J Cardiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910061</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheon</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Stress and Heart Rate Variability: A Meta-Analysis and Review of the Literature</article-title><source>Psychiatry Investig</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>245</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Experience of Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction on Menopausal Symptoms, Sleep Disturbance, and Body Image among Patients with Breast Cancer-A Qualitative Study</article-title><source>Curr Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36661746</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Redeker</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohsenin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia on Sleep, Symptoms, Stress, and Autonomic Function Among Patients With Heart Failure</article-title><source>Behav Sleep Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30461315</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edebol-Carlman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schrooten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lj&#x000f3;tsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brummer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cognitive behavioral therapy for irritable bowel syndrome: the effects on state and trait anxiety and the autonomic nervous system during induced rectal distensions - An uncontrolled trial</article-title><source>Scand J Pain</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29794287</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahorsu</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of Baduanjin Exercise on Depression Severity and Heart Rate Variability in Adults with Major Depressive Disorder: A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial</article-title><source>Psychol Res Behav Manag</source><year>2025</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40060106</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Investigating the effect of mindfulness training for stress management in military training: the relationship between the autonomic nervous system and emotional regulation</article-title><source>BMC Psychol</source><year>2025</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39773484</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coplan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aaronson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panthangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Treating comorbid anxiety and depression: Psychosocial and pharmacological approaches</article-title><source>World J Psychiatry</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26740928</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zambonini</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group><comment>Music Therapy Interventions for Resilience and Hope in Adolescents With Psychiatric Emergencies: A Non-Randomized Feasibility Trial. M.Sc. Thesis, Temple University. 2024. Available from: <uri xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.12613/10673">http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.12613/10673</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaudreuil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nordstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Degraba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pasquina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The role of technology in music therapy, occupational therapy, and co-treatment of an injured United States service member</article-title><source>Nord J Music Ther</source><year>2025</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>