<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Immunol Immunother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Immunol Immunother</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Immunology, Immunotherapy : CII</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0340-7004</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0851</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40358726</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12075072</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3991</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00262-025-03991-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>KLF12 as a potential biomarker for lateral pelvic lymph node metastases in advanced rectal cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Tianxian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Fangze</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Sicheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Fuqiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Liu</given-names></name><address><email>fcwpumch@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02drdmm93</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.506261.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0706 7839</institution-id><institution>Department of Colorectal Surgery, </institution><institution>National Cancer Center / National Clinical Research Center for Cancer/Cancer Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100021 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02z1vqm45</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411472.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1764 1621</institution-id><institution>Breast Disease Center, </institution><institution>Peking University First Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100034 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>74</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>199</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Rectal cancer accounts for approximately 40% of colorectal cancer cases, and lateral pelvic lymph node (LPLN) metastasis in rectal cancer significantly increases the local recurrence rate. Despite its clinical significance, studies on the molecular biology of LPLN metastasis are relatively scarce. In this study, we aimed to elucidate the underlying mechanisms by identifying hub regulatory genes in LPLN tissues and analyzing differentially expressed genes shared between tumor and pericarcinomatous tissues within our clinical cohort. To investigate the biological functions of these hub regulatory genes, we performed GSEA, GO, and KEGG pathway analyses on mRNA-Seq data. Among the identified hub genes, KLF12 emerged as a pivotal regulatory gene in rectal cancer. We further explored its clinical relevance and biological function. Our findings, validated using public databases, clinical cohort data, and immunohistochemistry (IHC), identified KLF12 as a specific marker for LPLN. Additionally, KLF12 expression exhibited a strong correlation with disease-free survival (DFS). According to clinical data, significant differences in KLF12 expression exist between groups based on factors such as age, gender, tumor location, pathological N stage, and postoperative tumor residue. Both treatment outcomes (DFS) and&#x000a0;receiver operating characteristic curves (AUCs) were significantly&#x000a0;associated with KLF12 expression. Furthermore, KLF12 demonstrated a strong association with immune cell infiltration, immune checkpoint expression, and immunophenoscore (IPS), indicating its potential regulatory role in immunotherapy. Functional molecular experiments revealed that KLF12 overexpression inhibited the proliferation, migration, and invasion of SW620 cells. In conclusion, leveraging mRNA-Seq data, TCGA database analysis, immune infiltration data, and biological function assessments, we confirmed that KLF12 could serve as an effective predictive marker and potential therapeutic target for LPLN metastasis. These findings suggest that KLF12 may be instrumental in assessing predictive risk and identifying novel therapeutic targets for patients with rectal cancer.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s00262-025-03991-8.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Rectal cancer</kwd><kwd>Lateral pelvic lymph node</kwd><kwd>KLF12</kwd><kwd>Marker</kwd><kwd>Target</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>CAMS Innovation Fund for Medical Sciences</institution></funding-source><award-id>No.2022-I2M-C&#x00026;T-B-057</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Liu</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100012166</institution-id><institution>National Key Research and Development Program of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>No. 2022YFC2505003</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Liu</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">In 2022, there were 1,926,118 newly diagnosed colorectal cancer cases worldwide, with rectal cancer accounting for nearly 40% of these cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The lateral pelvic lymph node (LPLN) is a typical site for rectal cancer metastasis, playing a crucial role in local recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, treatment approaches for lateral pelvic lymph node metastases (LPLN-M) in rectal cancer vary considerably between Eastern and Western nations. Western researchers generally consider LPLN-M a systemic disease and prefer neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy (nCRT) over lateral pelvic lymph node dissection (LPLND) to manage local recurrence in advanced low rectal cancer. Despite this approach, studies have demonstrated that nCRT alone is insufficient to control local recurrence, with a substantial proportion of patients still presenting with LPLN metastases post-treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In contrast, Japanese researchers advocate a proactive strategy, recommending prophylactic LPLND for patients with stage T3/T4 rectal cancer located below the peritoneal reflection. The Japanese Clinical Oncology Group (JCOG) 0212 trial revealed that while prophylactic LPLND significantly reduces local recurrence in the lateral pelvic region, the pathological LPLN-M rate is only 7%. This low rate suggests that the strategy could result in overtreatment, leading to unnecessary surgical trauma for patients with pathologically LPLN-negative (LPLN-N) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Consequently, both Eastern and Western treatment paradigms for LPLN-M exhibit notable limitations and shortcomings.</p><p id="Par3">To address these challenges, Chinese researchers have adopted a more selective approach, limiting LPLND to patients with clinically confirmed LPLN-M. However, current diagnostic methods that depend exclusively on imaging characteristics and clinicopathological parameters have demonstrated limited accuracy in identifying LPLN-M [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. This diagnostic uncertainty often results in either missed diagnoses or unnecessary surgical interventions, highlighting a critical need for more precise molecular markers. Despite extensive research on various cancers, the molecular mechanisms underlying LPLN-M remain largely unexplored, highlighting a critical gap in our knowledge of rectal cancer progression.</p><p id="Par4">Utilizing comprehensive transcriptome analysis of our clinical cohort and The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) database, we identified KLF12 as a promising candidate gene based on several key findings. First, KLF12 exhibited a consistently distinct expression profile between LPLN-M and non-LPLN-M tissues. Second, previous studies have implicated KLF12 in cancer metastasis by modulating epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) and cellular invasion, though its role in LPLN-M remains unexamined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Utilizing RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) for comprehensive transcriptome profiling, we analyzed mRNA expression in rectal cancer tissues, pericarcinomatous tissues, and LPLN tissues from our clinical cohort. We integrated these findings with public data from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) to identify differentially expressed genes (DEGs). Among these DEGs, KLF12 emerged as a hub gene with a potentially significant role in LPLN-M, as supported by clinical feature analysis and immune infiltration studies.</p><p id="Par5">To further investigate the clinical and molecular significance of KLF12, we conducted quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR), immunohistochemistry, colony formation, and transwell assays to assess its expression and biological functions in rectal cancer. Our results demonstrate that KLF12 is a promising biomarker for predicting LPLN-M and plays a regulatory role in rectal cancer progression, suggesting potential applications in both diagnosis and targeted therapy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Tissue sample collection</title><p id="Par6">Freshly excised rectal cancer and lateral pelvic lymph node (LPLN) tissues were obtained from the Colorectal Surgery Department at the Cancer Hospital affiliated with the Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences. Prior to sample collection, all patients provided informed consent, as officially recorded by the hospital administration. Notably, no patients received treatment before surgery. The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Cancer Hospital affiliated with the Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (NCC 2017-YZ-026, Oct 17, 2017) and registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT04850027).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>RNA sequencing</title><p id="Par7">RNA sequencing was performed by mapping the reads to the GENCODE (human-hg19, mouse-mm10) or Ensembl gene annotations using Bowtie2 version 2.1.0. Gene expression levels were quantified using RSEM v1.2.28 and normalized using the TMM (trimmed mean of M-values) method. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified using the R package "edgeR," based on the threshold criteria of <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and |logFC|&#x02265;&#x02009;1. The significance of canonical pathways was assessed using Fisher's exact test with the false discovery rate (FDR) correction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data gathering and preparation</title><p id="Par8">Data from the TCGA-READ adenocarcinoma project were downloaded and processed, including STAR-processed RNA sequencing data and clinical information extracted from the TCGA database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://portal.gdc.cancer.gov">https://portal.gdc.cancer.gov</ext-link>). Data filtering involved the removal of non-essential clinical and redundant metadata, and the processed data were log-transformed using the log2(value&#x02009;+&#x02009;1) method.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Estimation of immune score and immune-infiltrating cell percentage</title><p id="Par9">The expression profile of the TCGA-READ dataset was analyzed using the R packages GSVA, CIBERSORT, and GSEABase to estimate the percentage of immune-infiltrating cells. The CIBERSORT algorithm was applied to determine cell composition in complex tissues based on gene expression profiles.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Drug sensitivity analysis</title><p id="Par10">The R package pRRophetic, along with gene expression data from the READ cohort, was used to predict the IC50 values of 138 drugs from the Genomics of Drug Sensitivity in Cancer (GDSC) database. Statistical tests were performed to assess the significance of IC50 differences among subtypes, and drugs with significant variations were selected for visualization using IC50 heatmaps and distribution box plots.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>IHC staining examination</title><p id="Par11">Immunohistochemistry (IHC) was performed using an SP kit (No. SP-9000, ZSGB-BIO, China) following established protocols. The anti-KLF12 antibody (1:200) was purchased from ABclonal (No. A20469, China). IHC images were magnified 20&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;for detailed examination.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par12">The human colorectal cancer (CRC) cell line SW620 was obtained from the ATCC Cell Bank in the USA. Cells were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) (Sigma, Beijing, China) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) and 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml streptomycin (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Cultivation was conducted in an incubator maintained at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under ambient CO&#x02082;-free conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Lentiviral transduction and transfection</title><p id="Par13">To overexpress KLF12 in the SW620 cell line, recombinant lentiviral vectors (pRP[Exp]-EGFP-CMV or pRP[Exp]-EGFP-CMV-KLF12) and packaging plasmids (psPAX2 and pMD2.G) were utilized (Supplementary File <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The transfection of cells with these overexpression plasmids was performed using Lipofectamine 2000 (12,566,014, Invitrogen, Shanghai, China), following the manufacturer's protocol (Supplementary File <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) and colony formation assay</title><p id="Par14">The sequences of the KLF12 primers were as follows: Forward: CCTTTCCATAGCCAGAGCAGTAC, Reverse: CTGGCGTCTTGTGCTCTCAATAC. For tissue samples, 1&#x000a0;ml of RNA extraction buffer (Servicebio, G3013) was added and homogenized using a high-speed microtherm homogenizer (Servicebio, KZ-III-F) until no visible tissue mass remained. For tumor cells, Trizol reagent was used for RNA extraction, followed by chloroform, isopropanol, and 75% ethanol treatment (Chemical Reagent Co. Ltd). Servicebio&#x000ae; RT Enzyme Mix Strand cDNA Synthesis and SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix (Servicebio, G3320) were used for qPCR. For the colony formation assay, cells were seeded at a density of 10<sup>3</sup> cells per well in 6-well plates and cultured for 10&#x000a0;days in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS. Colonies containing fewer than 30 cells were excluded from analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Transwell assay</title><p id="Par15">The invasive and migratory capabilities of SW620 cells were evaluated using Transwell assays. For the migration assay, 700&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of DMEM containing 20% serum was added to the lower chamber of a Transwell plate (Corning, NY, USA), while 1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells suspended in 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of serum-free DMEM were seeded in the upper chamber. After a 24-h incubation at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the Transwell chamber was removed, washed with PBS, fixed for 30&#x000a0;min, and stained with 0.5% crystal violet. Cells on the upper side of the filter were gently detached before the chamber was washed with PBS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par16">All statistical analyses were performed using R software (v3.5.3) and GraphPad Prism (v8.01, GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA, USA). Student's t test was used for comparisons, with statistical significance set at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Tumor microenvironment and immune infiltration in tumor and lymph node tissues between LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups</title><p id="Par17">We investigated the tumor microenvironment by assessing the ESTIMATE score, stromal score, and tumor purity. As depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, immune and stromal scores were significantly higher in lymph node tissues from the LPLN-N group compared to the LPLN-M group. Conversely, tumor purity was elevated in LPLN-N tumor tissues compared to LPLN-M tumor tissues.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Single-sample Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (ssGSEA) and Tumor Microenvironment (TME) analysis of rectal cancer and lymph node tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups. <bold>A</bold> Heatmap of tumor tissues. <bold>B</bold> Heatmap of lymph node tissues</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">To further explore immune infiltration, we employed single-sample Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (ssGSEA). In tumor tissues, inflammation-promoting factors, type I interferon (IFN) response, and chemokine receptor (CCR) signaling were significantly enriched in the LPLN-M group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). In lymph node tissues, CCR signaling, human leukocyte antigen (HLA) expression, type II IFN response, and macrophage-related pathways were significantly enriched in the LPLN-M group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Differential expression genes between LPLN-M and LPLN-N</title><p id="Par19">We analyzed mRNA expression profiles in rectal cancer, adjacent tissues, and LPLN tissues using mRNA sequencing (mRNA-Seq). Initially, 2,633 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified between tumor and adjacent tissues. To investigate gene expression patterns associated with LPLN metastasis status, patients were classified into LPLN-M-positive and LPLN-M-negative groups. A total of 1,951 DEGs were identified between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups. Additionally, 1,671 DEGs were detected in tumor tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups.</p><p id="Par20">The functional significance of DEGs was explored using Gene Ontology (GO) enrichment analysis. In DEGs between tumor and adjacent tissues, significant enrichment was observed in biological process (BP) terms related to mitotic cell cycle phase transition, sister chromatid segregation, RNA catabolism, DNA replication, and chromosome segregation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Cellular component (CC) terms such as chromosomal region, chromosome centromeric region, spindle, and kinetochore were enriched, while molecular function (MF) terms included ATPase activity, ubiquitin-like protein ligase binding, and DNA-dependent ATPase activity.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Biological enrichment analysis of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) across various tissue types. Gene Ontology (GO) enrichment bubble plots of DEGs: <bold>A</bold> GO enrichment of DEGs between tumor and adjacent tissues. <bold>B</bold> GO enrichment of DEGs in tumor tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups. <bold>C</bold> GO enrichment of DEGs in lymph node tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups. Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) enrichment bubble plots of DEGs: <bold>D</bold> KEGG enrichment of DEGs between tumor and adjacent tissues. <bold>E</bold> KEGG enrichment of DEGs in tumor tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups. <bold>F</bold> KEGG enrichment of DEGs in lymph node tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">For DEGs between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M tumor groups, enrichment was observed in protein targeting and ribosome biogenesis (BP), ribosomal subunit and ribosome-related structures (CC), and structural constituents of ribosomes and cadherin binding (MF) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). In lymph node tissues between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups, DEGs were enriched in DNA-templated transcription initiation and chromosome organization (BP), lipid droplet and lysosomal membrane (CC), and carbohydrate kinase activity and transcription coregulator activity (MF) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C).</p><p id="Par22">Pathway enrichment analysis using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database revealed that DEGs between tumor and adjacent tissues were significantly enriched in pathways related to cell cycle regulation and RNA transport (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D). In tumors between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups, DEGs were enriched in metabolic pathways, ribosomal activity, and oxidative phosphorylation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). In lymph nodes between the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups, DEGs were significantly associated with metabolic pathways, carbon metabolism, and 2-oxocarboxylic acid metabolism (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>F).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Biological function of hub DEGs between metastatic and non-metastatic LPLN</title><p id="Par23">In this study, we analyzed differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between tumor and adjacent tissues, as well as between metastatic and non-metastatic groups, to identify shared DEGs. As illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A, 52 genes were found to be overlapping among all three comparisons. To elucidate the functional characteristics of these genes, we performed Gene Ontology (GO) enrichment analysis. These genes were significantly enriched in biological process (BP) terms related to DNA replication and transcription-coupled nucleotide excision repair. Regarding cellular component (CC) terms, they were associated with the replication fork and nuclear replication machinery. For molecular function (MF) terms, significant enrichment was observed in &#x003b2;-tubulin binding and drug binding (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Identification of hub genes and biological enrichment analysis. <bold>A</bold> Venn diagram displaying commonly expressed genes among rectal cancer tissues, adjacent tissues, and lymph node tissues in the LPLN-N and LPLN-M groups. <bold>B</bold> GO enrichment circular plot of hub genes. <bold>C</bold> KEGG enrichment lollipop plot of hub genes. T: tumor tissues, N: adjacent tissues</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">Additionally, KEGG pathway analysis revealed that these genes were involved in cellular senescence, the mTOR signaling pathway, and DNA replication (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C), suggesting their potential role in tumor progression and metastasis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>KLF12 clinical characteristics in rectal cancer</title><p id="Par25">Among the 52 identified genes, KLF12 emerged as a key hub gene. We assessed its prognostic significance in lymphatic invasion using data from the TCGA database. As depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, KLF12 expression was significantly associated with overall survival (OS), where higher expression correlated with a more favorable prognosis in rectal cancer cases involving lymphatic invasion. However, no significant difference in OS was observed between rectal cancer patients with high and low KLF12 expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Clinical significance of KLF12 in rectal cancer. <bold>A</bold> Kaplan&#x02013;Meier survival curve illustrating the relationship between KLF12 expression and overall survival in rectal cancer with lymphatic invasion. <bold>B</bold> No statistically significant difference in overall survival (OS) was observed between patients with high and low KLF12 expression. <bold>C</bold> Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curve showing the predictive efficacy of KLF12, with an area under the curve (AUC) of 0.726. KLF12 expression was significantly lower in <bold>D</bold> older colorectal cancer (CRC) patients and <bold>E</bold> male patients. KLF12 expression effectively differentiated between high and low groups based on <bold>F</bold> anatomic neoplasm subdivision, <bold>G</bold> pathologic N stage, <bold>H</bold> residual tumor status, and <bold>I</bold> disease-specific survival (DSS)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">To further investigate KLF12 expression in relation to clinical features, we analyzed TCGA rectal cancer datasets. The area under the time-dependent receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve (AUC) was calculated to evaluate the diagnostic performance of KLF12, yielding an AUC of 0.726 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). Our analysis revealed that patients aged&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;65&#x000a0;years (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D), male patients (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E), and those with rectal cancer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>F) exhibited significantly lower KLF12 expression.</p><p id="Par27">Furthermore, KLF12 expression was able to distinguish between high- and low-expression groups based on anatomic neoplasm subdivision (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>G), pathologic N stage (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>H), and residual tumor status (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>I). Disease-free survival (DSS) analysis demonstrated that KLF12 expression was significantly associated with treatment outcomes, further supporting its potential clinical relevance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>J).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Immune infiltration of KLF12 expression in rectal cancer</title><p id="Par28">To investigate the relationship between KLF12 expression and the tumor immune microenvironment, we used the CIBERSORT method to assess the infiltration patterns of 24 immune cell types in the rectal cancer TCGA dataset. The results revealed notable variations in immune cell infiltration associated with KLF12 expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). Specifically, KLF12 expression was significantly correlated with the infiltration levels of T helper cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B), macrophages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C), TFH cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>D), NK cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>E), Tgd cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>F), Th17 cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>G), Tem cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>H), Tcm cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>I), and CD56 bright cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>J).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Correlation between KLF12 expression and immune cell infiltration in rectal cancer. <bold>A</bold> Overview of significant differences in immune cell infiltration associated with KLF12 expression. KLF12 expression was significantly correlated with the infiltration of <bold>B</bold> T helper cells, <bold>C</bold> macrophages, <bold>D</bold> TFH cells, <bold>E</bold> NK cells, <bold>F</bold> Tgd cells, <bold>G</bold> Th17 cells, <bold>H</bold> Tem cells, <bold>I</bold> Tcm cells, and <bold>J</bold> CD56 bright cells. <bold>K</bold> KLF12 expression was able to effectively differentiate stromal score, immune score, and ESTIMATE score</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">Additionally, we used the ESTIMATE program to predict the tumor microenvironment (TME) score. KLF12 expression significantly differentiated stromal score, immune score, and ESTIMATE score (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>K), suggesting a potential role in shaping the TME.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>KLF12's relationship with immunotherapy and chemotherapy</title><p id="Par30">We evaluated the potential of KLF12 as a predictor of immunotherapy response by analyzing immune checkpoint expression and the immunophenoscore (IPS) in rectal cancer samples from the TCGA database, as accessed through the TCIA database. Immune checkpoints regulate immune activation to maintain self-tolerance and prevent autoimmunity. Our findings indicate that KLF12 expression correlates with the expression levels of multiple immune checkpoints, including NRP1, TNFSF4, TNFRSF14, CD28, and TIGIT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Association between KLF12 expression and the tumor immune microenvironment. <bold>A</bold> KLF12 expression was correlated with multiple immune checkpoint molecules, including NRP1, TNFSF4, TNFRSF14, CD28, and TIGIT. <bold>B</bold>&#x02013;<bold>E</bold> Immunophenoscore (IPS) analysis revealed that tumors with low KLF12 expression exhibited significantly lower IPS values across four categories: ips_ctla4_neg_pd1_neg, ips_ctla4_neg_pd1_pos, ips_ctla4_pos_pd1_neg, and ips_ctla4_pos_pd1_pos. <bold>F</bold>&#x02013;<bold>I</bold> Scatter plots displaying correlations between KLF12 risk scores and IC50 values of chemotherapy drugs, with four drugs randomly selected for visualization</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">The IPS is an indicator of tumor immunogenicity and potential response to immunotherapy. Notably, IPS scores for the categories ips_ctla4_neg_pd1_neg, ips_ctla4_neg_pd1_pos, and ips_ctla4_pos_pd1_neg were significantly lower in the high KLF12 group compared to the low KLF12 group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B&#x02013;E), indicating that high KLF12 expression may be predictive of enhanced immunotherapy response.</p><p id="Par32">Furthermore, we investigated KLF12-associated chemosensitivity by calculating IC50 values for 138 chemotherapy drugs from the GDSC database, using the rectal cancer TCGA expression profile. Our analysis revealed a notable association between KLF12 risk scores and the IC50 values of 28 drugs. To illustrate this relationship, we selected four representative drugs for scatter plot visualization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>F&#x02013;I).</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Biological role of KLF12 in rectal cancer expression</title><p id="Par33">To further investigate the biological role of KLF12 in rectal cancer, we examined fresh cancer tissues and utilized immunohistochemistry (IHC) to compare its expression between the LPLN-M and LPLN-N groups. The results revealed that KLF12 expression was significantly elevated in the LPLN-M positive group relative to the LPLN-M negative group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, Supplementary Material <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Expression and biological function of KLF12 in rectal cancer. <bold>A</bold> Immunohistochemistry (IHC) staining and positive percentage analysis demonstrated significantly higher KLF12 expression in the LPLN-M positive group compared to the LPLN-M negative group. <bold>B</bold> Higher KLF12 expression was significantly associated with improved disease-free survival (DFS), <bold>C</bold> but not with overall survival (OS). Functional experiments showed that KLF12 overexpression significantly suppressed <bold>D</bold> cell proliferation, <bold>E</bold> migration, and <bold>F</bold> invasion in SW620 cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2025_3991_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">Based on these IHC findings, we performed disease-free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) analyses for patients in the LPLN-M positive group. The analysis demonstrated a significant association between KLF12 expression and DFS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B), whereas no statistically significant correlation was observed with OS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C) in rectal cancer patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Clinical characteristics of KLF12 in the LPLN-M positive group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Characteristic</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>N</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="2">KLF12</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Low (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;28)</th><th align="left">High (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sex</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.490</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Male</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">13 (46.4)</td><td align="left">7 (58.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Female</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">15 (53.6)</td><td align="left">5 (41.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.629</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;60</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">14 (50.0)</td><td align="left">5 (41.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;60</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">14 (50.0)</td><td align="left">7 (58.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Tumor location</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.418</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Low rectum</td><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">20 (71.4)</td><td align="left">7 (58.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Middle rectum</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">8 (28.6)</td><td align="left">5 (41.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Tumor differentiation</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.411</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Moderate</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">5 (17.9)</td><td align="left">4 (33.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Poor</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">23 (82.1)</td><td align="left">8 (66.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Tumor stage</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.341</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;T1&#x02013;T2</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">3 (10.7)</td><td align="left">3 (25.0)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;T3&#x02013;T4</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">25 (89.3)</td><td align="left">9 (75.0)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Nodal stage</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.124</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;N0</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">10 (35.7)</td><td align="left">1 (8.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;N1&#x02013;N2</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">18 (64.3)</td><td align="left">11 (91.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">LLN metastasis</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.209</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Unilateral</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">27 (96.4)</td><td align="left">10 (83.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Bilateral</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">1 (3.6)</td><td align="left">2 (16.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">LLN locations</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Internal iliac and obturator metastases</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">24 (85.7)</td><td align="left">11 (91.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;External or common iliac metastases</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">4 (14.3)</td><td align="left">1 (8.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Perineural invasion</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.157</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">16 (57.1)</td><td align="left">10 (83.3)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">12 (42.9)</td><td align="left">2 (16.7)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Lymphatic invasion</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">16 (57.1)</td><td align="left">12 (100.0)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">12 (42.9)</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par35">To elucidate the functional roles of KLF12 in rectal cancer cells, we conducted colony formation assays to examine cell proliferation and transwell assays to assess invasion and migration potential. Our experimental findings demonstrated that KLF12 overexpression inhibited the proliferation, migration, and invasion of SW620 cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D&#x02013;F).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par36">Lateral pelvic lymph node metastasis (LPLN-M) in rectal cancer is a key determinant in treatment strategies, as its presence significantly increases the risk of local recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Current diagnostic approaches predominantly rely on imaging; however, molecular markers offer a novel avenue for enhancing LPLN-M detection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. However, LPLN dissection is associated with potential complications, including nerve injury, bleeding, and lymphorrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Neoadjuvant therapy is the standard first-line treatment for patients with lymph node metastasis. Indeed, in rare cases where rectal cancer complications like obstruction or perforation occur, direct surgical intervention becomes necessary, and LPLN dissection can be performed simultaneously. However, accurately locating and clearing the metastatic lymph nodes during dissection itself is quite challenging. As critical immune organs responsible for lymphocyte differentiation and maturation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], metastatic lymph nodes play a key role in guiding surgical decisions, emphasizing the importance of precise LPLN diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Thus, developing a simple and reliable diagnostic method for lymph node metastasis is of paramount importance.</p><p id="Par37">Our study reveals that lymph node metastasis is marked by increased immune cell infiltration but diminished antigen-presenting capacity, potentially weakening anti-tumor immunity and promoting further metastasis. For the first time, we identify potential biomarkers in primary rectal tumor tissues that are associated with LPLN-M, offering novel biopsy indicators for its diagnosis. Integrating these biomarkers with imaging techniques could significantly improve the diagnostic accuracy of lymph node metastasis.</p><p id="Par38">In this study, we first analyzed differences in immune cell infiltration between metastatic and non-metastatic lymph nodes, as well as between tumor tissues with and without lymph node metastasis. To identify predictive biomarkers for lymph node metastasis, we conducted mRNA sequencing (mRNA-seq) on tumor, adjacent, and lymph node tissues. Initially, we identified differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between tumor and adjacent tissues, followed by an analysis of DEGs in tumor and lymph node tissues between LPLN-N and LPLN-positive (LPLN-M) cases. The biological functions of these DEGs primarily involve DNA transcription, thereby influencing gene expression and protein synthesis. From these DEGs, we identified a shared gene set, termed the hub gene set, and highlighted KLF12 as a potential biomarker for predicting LPLN-M.</p><p id="Par39">The Kruppel-like factor (KLF) family of transcription factors regulates key oncogenic processes, including proliferation, survival, therapy resistance, motility, and invasiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. KLF12, originally identified as a transcriptional repressor of AP-2, has been implicated in multiple malignancies. Studies suggest that KLF12 promotes breast cancer cell proliferation by downregulating p21 transcription through both p53-dependent and independent pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Conversely, in bladder cancer, KLF12 functions as a tumor suppressor by downregulating ENO2, a potential therapeutic target [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. KLF12 also plays a critical role in poorly differentiated gastric cancer, highlighting its potential as a therapeutic target [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par40">In our study, KLF12 exhibited robust diagnostic performance for LPLN-M, with an area under the curve (AUC) of 0.726. Analysis of disease-specific survival (DSS) events revealed a strong correlation between KLF12 expression and therapeutic response. Moreover, immunohistochemistry (IHC) findings demonstrated a significant association between KLF12 expression and disease-free survival (DFS) in rectal cancer patients. These findings indicate that KLF12 serves as a reliable biomarker for predicting rectal cancer prognosis and DFS in LPLN-M patients. However, KLF12 expression does not show a strong correlation with overall survival (OS), likely due to the multifactorial nature of OS, which is influenced by factors such as distant metastasis, treatment response, and comorbidities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Additionally, the availability of effective salvage therapies for recurrence may reduce the impact of LPLN-M on OS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">Subsequent analyses of mRNA sequencing (mRNA-Seq) data, including Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA), Gene Ontology (GO), and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway analysis, revealed a strong association between immune infiltration, immunotherapy, and LPLN-M, particularly regarding PD-L1 expression and the PD-1 checkpoint mechanism in cancer. We further examined the relationship between KLF12 expression and the tumor immune microenvironment. Our correlation analysis identified statistically significant associations between KLF12 expression and immune cell infiltration (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). However, many correlation coefficients were below 0.3, suggesting that KLF12 functions within a broader regulatory network. Despite these modest correlations, we observed significant differences in immune cell infiltration, immune checkpoint expression, and immunophenoscore (IPS) between high and low KLF12 expression groups, suggesting that patients with high KLF12 expression may derive greater benefit from immunotherapy. These findings align with previous studies associating KLFs with immune cell regulation in cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">Functional assays demonstrated that KLF12 overexpression suppressed the proliferation, migration, and invasion of SW620 cells, highlighting its previously unrecognized potential as a therapeutic target for rectal cancer. However, our study has certain limitations. Due to the rarity of these specimens, our sample size is limited. In future studies, we aim to expand the sample size and develop a predictive model to validate KLF12's diagnostic performance. Additionally, since our study primarily focuses on immune infiltration and KLF12 function, we plan to refine experimental approaches and further investigate the molecular mechanisms underlying KLF12's role.</p><p id="Par43">In conclusion, our study provides the first comprehensive molecular-level analysis of LPLN-M in rectal cancer, identifying KLF12 as a potential biomarker for predicting LPLN-M.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="262_2025_3991_MOESM1_ESM.txt"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (TXT 9 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="262_2025_3991_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (DOCX 78 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="262_2025_3991_MOESM3_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file3 (TIF 70 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="262_2025_3991_MOESM4_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file4 (TIF 72 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Tianxian Xiao and Fangze Wei have contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>6/25/2025</p><p>A Correction to this paper has been published: 10.1007/s00262-025-04114-z</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Authors thank staff at Department of Colorectal Surgery, National Cancer Center/National Clinical Research Center for Cancer/Cancer Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College (Beijing, China) for providing support to this study. Authors also thank patients and their families for participating in this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Tianxian Xiao contributed to writing&#x02014;original draft, software, resources, methodology, investigation, formal analysis, and data curation. Fangze Wei contributed to writing&#x02014;original draft, software, resources, methodology, investigation, formal analysis, and data curation. Sicheng Zhou contributed to writing&#x02014;original draft, software, resources, methodology, investigation, and formal analysis. Fuqiang Zhao contributed to resources, investigation, and data curation. Fei Huang contributed to resources and investigation. Liu Qian contributed to writing&#x02014;review and editing, visualization, validation, supervision, project administration, methodology, funding acquisition, and conceptualization. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the CAMS Innovation Fund for Medical Sciences (CIFMS) (No.2022-I2M-C&#x00026;T-B-057) and the National Key Research and Development Program (No. 2022YFC2505003).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analyzed during the current study.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par44">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par45">None.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par46">All&#x000a0;authors&#x000a0;consented&#x000a0;to&#x000a0;the&#x000a0;publication&#x000a0;of&#x000a0;the&#x000a0;paper.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Laversanne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Soerjomataram</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics 2022: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2024</year><volume>74</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38572751</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Bray F, Laversanne M, Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Soerjomataram I et al (2024) Global cancer statistics 2022: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin 74(3):229&#x02013;263<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38572751</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yojiro</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yutaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshinori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoichi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetsuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Japanese society for cancer of the colon and rectum (JSCCR) guidelines 2019 for the treatment of colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Int J Clin Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31203527</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Yojiro H, Kei M, Yutaka S, Yoshinori I, Yoichi A, Tetsuya H et al (2019) Japanese society for cancer of the colon and rectum (JSCCR) guidelines 2019 for the treatment of colorectal cancer. Int J Clin Oncol 25(1):1&#x02013;42<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31203527</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atsushi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuyoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Julio</surname><given-names>G-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigeo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neoadjuvant (Chemo)radiotherapy with total mesorectal excision only is not sufficient to prevent lateral local recurrence in enlarged nodes: results of the multicenter lateral node study of patients with low cT3/4 rectal cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.18.00032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30403572</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Atsushi O, Tsuyoshi K, Chris C, Julio G-A, Henrik I, Shigeo T et al (2019) Neoadjuvant (Chemo)radiotherapy with total mesorectal excision only is not sufficient to prevent lateral local recurrence in enlarged nodes: results of the multicenter lateral node study of patients with low cT3/4 rectal cancer. J Clin Oncol 37(1):33&#x02013;43<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30403572</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Junki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Norio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusuke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yukihide</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postoperative morbidity and mortality after mesorectal excision with and without lateral lymph node dissection for clinical stage II or stage III lower rectal cancer (JCOG0212): results from a multicentre, randomised controlled, non-inferiority trial</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(12)70158-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22591948</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Shin F, Takayuki A, Junki M, Norio S, Yusuke K, Yukihide K et al (2012) Postoperative morbidity and mortality after mesorectal excision with and without lateral lymph node dissection for clinical stage II or stage III lower rectal cancer (JCOG0212): results from a multicentre, randomised controlled, non-inferiority trial. Lancet Oncol 13(6):616&#x02013;621<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22591948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazushige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroshi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Keisuke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Toshiaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimal size criteria for lateral lymph node dissection after neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy for rectal cancer</article-title><source>Dis Colon Rectum</source><year>2021</year><volume>64</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCR.0000000000001866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33395141</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Kazushige K, Hiroshi S, Keisuke H, Hiroaki N, Toshiaki T, Takeshi N et al (2021) Optimal size criteria for lateral lymph node dissection after neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy for rectal cancer. Dis Colon Rectum 64(3):274&#x02013;283<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33395141</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heung-Kwon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung-Bum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung-Min</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Soo Young</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Myoung Hun</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Duck-Woo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy affects the indications for lateral pelvic node dissection in mid/low rectal cancer with clinically suspected lateral node involvement: a multicenter retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2280</fpage><lpage>2287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-014-3559-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24604580</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Heung-Kwon O, Sung-Bum K, Sung-Min L, Soo Young L, Myoung Hun I, Duck-Woo K et al (2014) Neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy affects the indications for lateral pelvic node dissection in mid/low rectal cancer with clinically suspected lateral node involvement: a multicenter retrospective cohort study. Ann Surg Oncol 21(7):2280&#x02013;2287<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24604580</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating predictive factors for determining the presence of lateral pelvic node metastasis in rectal cancer patients following neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy</article-title><source>Colorectal Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>21</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/codi.14595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30801862</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Wang P, Zhou S, Zhou H, Liang J, Zhou Z (2019) Evaluating predictive factors for determining the presence of lateral pelvic node metastasis in rectal cancer patients following neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy. Colorectal Dis 21(7):791&#x02013;796<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30801862</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-141 enhances anoikis resistance in metastatic progression of ovarian cancer through targeting KLF12/Sp1/survivin axis</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12943-017-0582-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28095864</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Mak CS, Yung MM, Hui LM, Leung LL, Liang R, Chen K et al (2017) MicroRNA-141 enhances anoikis resistance in metastatic progression of ovarian cancer through targeting KLF12/Sp1/survivin axis. Mol Cancer 16(1):11<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28095864</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KLF12 transcriptionally regulates PD-L1 expression in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Mol Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2659</fpage><lpage>2674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1878-0261.13512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37606530</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Pan X, Zhang W, Wang L, Guo H, Zheng M, Wu H et al (2023) KLF12 transcriptionally regulates PD-L1 expression in non-small cell lung cancer. Mol Oncol 17(12):2659&#x02013;2674<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37606530</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA NEAT1 transported by extracellular vesicles contributes to breast cancer development by sponging microRNA-141-3p and regulating KLF12</article-title><source>Cell Biosci</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>68</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13578-021-00556-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33820555</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Zhou D, Gu J, Wang Y, Wu H, Cheng W, Wang Q et al (2021) Long non-coding RNA NEAT1 transported by extracellular vesicles contributes to breast cancer development by sponging microRNA-141-3p and regulating KLF12. Cell Biosci 11(1):68<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33820555</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation of Kruppel-like factor 12 in the development of endometrial cancer</article-title><source>Gynecol Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>152</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2018.10.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482501</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Ding L, Ding Y, Kong X, Wu J, Fu J, Yan G et al (2019) Dysregulation of Kruppel-like factor 12 in the development of endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 152(1):177&#x02013;184<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482501</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell and WGCNA uncover a prognostic model and potential oncogenes in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Biolo Proced Online</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12575-022-00175-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Di Z, Zhou S, Xu G, Ren L, Li C, Ding Z et al (2022) Single-cell and WGCNA uncover a prognostic model and potential oncogenes in colorectal cancer. Biolo Proced Online 24(1):13</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyoshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsueda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiratsuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Unno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indications for lateral pelvic lymph node dissection based on magnetic resonance imaging before and after preoperative chemoradiotherapy in patients with advanced low-rectal cancer</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>S614</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-015-4565-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25896145</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Akiyoshi T, Matsueda K, Hiratsuka M, Unno T, Nagata J, Nagasaki T et al (2015) Indications for lateral pelvic lymph node dissection based on magnetic resonance imaging before and after preoperative chemoradiotherapy in patients with advanced low-rectal cancer. Ann Surg Oncol 22(Suppl 3):S614-620<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25896145</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for complications following lateral pelvic lymph node dissection for rectal cancer</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>41</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5599</fpage><lpage>5604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21873/anticanres.15374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34732431</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Okamoto D, Matsuda T, Sawada R, Hasegawa H, Yamashita K, Harada H et al (2021) Risk factors for complications following lateral pelvic lymph node dissection for rectal cancer. Anticancer Res 41(11):5599&#x02013;5604<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34732431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors and prognostic significance of postoperative complications following lateral pelvic lymph node dissection for rectal cancer: results of the multicenter lateral node study in China</article-title><source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source><year>2022</year><volume>52</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35858237</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Zhou S, Tang J, Mei S, Lou Z, Fu W, Feng B et al (2022) Risk factors and prognostic significance of postoperative complications following lateral pelvic lymph node dissection for rectal cancer: results of the multicenter lateral node study in China. Jpn J Clin Oncol 52(10):1150&#x02013;1158<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35858237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinselmeyer</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scallan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lymphatic system: integral roles in immunity</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2017</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-041015-055354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27860528</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Randolph GJ, Ivanov S, Zinselmeyer BH, Scallan JP (2017) The lymphatic system: integral roles in immunity. Annu Rev Immunol 35:31&#x02013;52<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27860528</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of internal iliac and obturator lymph nodes in mid-low rectal cancer</article-title><source>World J Surg Oncol</source><year>2024</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12957-024-03427-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38863003</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Xiao T, Chen J, Liu Q (2024) Management of internal iliac and obturator lymph nodes in mid-low rectal cancer. World J Surg Oncol 22(1):153<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38863003</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyakita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadahiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors and histological effects of preoperative chemoradiotherapy for rectal cancer and control of lateral lymph node metastasis</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>334</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12876-022-02414-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35804299</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Miyakita H, Chan L, Okada K, Kayano H, Mori M, Sadahiro S et al (2022) Predictors and histological effects of preoperative chemoradiotherapy for rectal cancer and control of lateral lymph node metastasis. BMC Gastroenterol 22(1):334<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35804299</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialkowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SP and KLF transcription factors in digestive physiology and diseases</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2017</year><volume>152</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1845</fpage><lpage>1875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2017.03.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366734</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Kim C, He P, Bialkowska A, Yang V (2017) SP and KLF transcription factors in digestive physiology and diseases. Gastroenterology 152(8):1845&#x02013;1875<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366734</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factors in health and diseases</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>90</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1337</fpage><lpage>1381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00058.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20959618</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">McConnell B, Yang V (2010) Mammalian Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factors in health and diseases. Physiol Rev 90(4):1337&#x02013;1381<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20959618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuierer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of the AP-2alpha promoter by BTEB-1 and AP-2rep, a novel wt-1/egr-related zinc finger repressor</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.19.1.194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858544</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Imhof A, Schuierer M, Werner O, Moser M, Roth C, Bauer R et al (1999) Transcriptional regulation of the AP-2alpha promoter by BTEB-1 and AP-2rep, a novel wt-1/egr-related zinc finger repressor. Mol Cell Biol 19(1):194&#x02013;204<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858544</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KLF12 promotes the proliferation of breast cancer cells by reducing the transcription of p21 in a p53-dependent and p53-independent manner</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>313</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-023-05824-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37156774</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Li Y, Li S, Shi X, Xin Z, Yang Y, Zhao B et al (2023) KLF12 promotes the proliferation of breast cancer cells by reducing the transcription of p21 in a p53-dependent and p53-independent manner. Cell Death Dis 14(5):313<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37156774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factor 12 suppresses bladder cancer growth through transcriptionally inhibition of enolase 2</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2021</year><volume>769</volume><fpage>145338</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2020.145338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33279628</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Tang C, Wang M, Dai Y, Wei X (2021) Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factor 12 suppresses bladder cancer growth through transcriptionally inhibition of enolase 2. Gene 769:145338<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33279628</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biju</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahyoun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Safar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Atallah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of treatment coordination on overall survival in rectal cancer</article-title><source>Clin Colorectal Cancer</source><year>2021</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clcc.2021.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33618972</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Biju K, Zhang GQ, Stem M, Sahyoun R, Safar B, Atallah C et al (2021) Impact of treatment coordination on overall survival in rectal cancer. Clin Colorectal Cancer 20(3):187&#x02013;196<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33618972</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habr-Gama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gama-Rodrigues</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sao Juliao</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Proscurshim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabbagh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Local recurrence after complete clinical response and watch and wait in rectal cancer after neoadjuvant chemoradiation: impact of salvage therapy on local disease control</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2014</year><volume>88</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2013.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24495589</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Habr-Gama A, Gama-Rodrigues J, Sao Juliao GP, Proscurshim I, Sabbagh C, Lynn PB et al (2014) Local recurrence after complete clinical response and watch and wait in rectal cancer after neoadjuvant chemoradiation: impact of salvage therapy on local disease control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 88(4):822&#x02013;828<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24495589</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Migita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factor 12 plays a significant role in poorly differentiated gastric cancer progression</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2009</year><volume>125</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>1867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.24538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19588488</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Nakamura Y, Migita T, Hosoda F, Okada N, Gotoh M, Arai Y et al (2009) Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like factor 12 plays a significant role in poorly differentiated gastric cancer progression. Int J Cancer 125(8):1859&#x02013;1867<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19588488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhongting</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haibin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and prognosis value of the KLF family members in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>J Oncol</source><year>2022</year><volume>2022</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Zhongting H, Haibin H, Feng Q, Hailong Q (2022) Expression and prognosis value of the KLF family members in colorectal cancer. J Oncol 2022:1&#x02013;13</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirofumi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Atsushi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Taku</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazuyoshi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidetoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohru</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profiling reveals distinct molecular signatures associated with the rupture of intracranial aneurysm</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2014</year><volume>45</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2239</fpage><lpage>2245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.114.005851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24938844</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Hirofumi N, Atsushi T, Taku Y, Kazuyoshi H, Hidetoshi K, Tohru M et al (2014) Gene expression profiling reveals distinct molecular signatures associated with the rupture of intracranial aneurysm. Stroke 45(8):2239&#x02013;2245<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24938844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>