<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neuroimage: Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-9560</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36969093</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10038095</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-9560(22)00077-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynirp.2022.100153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100153</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Polygenic indices for cognition in healthy aging; the role of brain measures</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Tsapanou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Mourtzi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Habeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Belsky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><email>ys11@columbia.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Cognitive Neuroscience Division, Department of Neurology, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, NY, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>1st Department of Neurology, Aiginition Hospital, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens Medical School, Athens, Greece</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Epidemiology, Columbia University Mailman School of Public Health, New York, USA</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Robert N Butler Columbia Aging Center, Columbia University, New York, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Cognitive Neuroscience Division, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, NY, 10032, USA. <email>ys11@columbia.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>100153</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2022 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have identified large numbers of genetic variants associated with cognition. However, little is known about how these genetic discoveries impact cognitive aging.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted polygenic-index (PGI) analysis of cognitive performance in n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;168 European-ancestry adults aged 20&#x02013;80. We computed PGIs based on GWAS of cognitive performance in young/middle-aged and older adults. We tested associations of the PGI with cognitive performance, as measured through neuropsychological evaluation. We explored whether these associations were accounted for by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) measures of brain-aging phenotypes: total gray matter volume (GM), cortical thickness (CT), and white matter hyperintensities burden (WMH).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Participants with higher PGI values performed better on cognitive tests (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.627, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.196, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002) (age, sex, and principal components as covariates). Associations remained significant with inclusion of covariates for MRI measures of brain aging; B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.439, SE: 0.198, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.028). PGI associations were stronger in young and middle-aged (age&#x0003c;65) as compared to older adults. For further validation, linear regression for Cog PGI and cognition in the fully adjusted model and adding the interaction between age group and Cog PGI, showed significant results (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.892, SE: 0.325, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.007) driven by young and middle-aged adults (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.403, SE: 0.193, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.039). In ancillary analysis, the Cognitive PGI was not associated with any of the brain measures.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Genetics discovered in GWAS of cognition are associated with cognitive performance in healthy adults across age, but most strongly in young and middle-aged adults. Associations were not explained by brain-structural markers of brain aging. Genetics uncovered in GWAS of cognitive performance may contribute to individual differences established relatively early in life and may not reflect genetic mechanisms of cognitive aging.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Polygenic indices</kwd><kwd>Cognition</kwd><kwd>Brain morphometry</kwd><kwd>Cognitive aging</kwd><kwd>Neural phenotypes</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0015">Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have identified many genetic variants associated with global cognitive functioning. However, the biology of these associations is mostly unknown, in part because GWAS-discovered variants are rarely located in or near genes with known functions in cognition and in part because effect-sizes of individual variants are very small. One approach to following-up GWAS discoveries to investigate their mechanisms of action is to combine information across the genome in polygenic indices (PGIs). PGIs summarize the results of GWAS and enable tests of how the combined set of genetic influences relates to intermediate phenotypes thought to contribute to differences between people in cognitive functioning (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Belsky and Harden, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">PGIs are constructed as a weighted average of phenotype-associated alleles across thousands of genetic variants called Single-Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs) (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Torkamani et al., 2018</xref>). Because GWAS designs are correlational, the mechanisms linking the genetic information captured in polygenic indices with phenotypes may be diverse, encompassing direct biological causation and processes mediated by behavior and environmental factors (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Dudbridge, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Sugrue and Desikan, 2019</xref>). Moreover, because genetic variation is established at conception and remains fixed across the life course, it is uncertain when in development GWAS-discovered genetic risks become manifest (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Belsky et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">Bioinformatics analyses of results from GWAS of cognitive phenotypes suggest features of brain structure and function as key mediators of genetic associations (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Demange et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Savage et al., 2018</xref>). In contrast, GWAS of cognitive performance and brain structure have identified different SNPs (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Thompson et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Davies et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Deary et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2022</xref>). Most participants in brain-imaging GWAS come from older individuals. Therefore, a possible explanation of the discordance between bioinformatic analysis and comparison of GWAS results is that genetic contributions to cognition reflect processes of neurodevelopment whereas mid and later life brain imaging data reflect processes of cognitive aging. Smaller datasets that include genetic, Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), and cognitive test data can help clarify how genetics, brain-structural markers, and cognition are connected. Specifically, studies are needed to test if genetic associations with cognitive test performance are accounted for by brain-structural markers of brain aging.</p><p id="p0030">Elucidating underlying mechanisms and life-course timing of effects for GWAS discoveries for cognition is needed to clarify their relevance to understanding the etiology of cognitive aging and informing development of interventions to prevent and/or treat dementing illness. Although many studies report associations between either cognitive performance and brain markers (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cheryl, 2000</xref>), or genetics and cognition (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Greenwood and Parasuraman, 2003</xref>), we are not aware of a study that examines the potential role of brain markers in the relationship between cognitive PGI and cognitive performance. We conducted analysis of a cognitive performance PGI, brain-structural markers of cognitive aging, and cognitive test performance in two cross-sectional databases of cognitively normal adults aged 20 to 80. We tested PGI associations with cognitive test performance and the extent to which these associations were accounted for by brain-structural markers of cognitive aging. We further explored heterogeneity in PGI associations with cognition across the adult age-range from the third to the ninth decades of life. Findings contribute to our emerging understanding of the meaning of GWAS discoveries for cognitive performance.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods and materials</title><p id="p0035">Participants were recruited for two studies: the Reference Ability Neural Network (RANN) and the Cognitive Reserve (CR) study. Both studies share similar recruitment procedure and data collection. All participants were native English speakers, right-handed, with at least a fourth-grade reading level. To be included in the study, participants had to also be free of any major neurological or psychiatric condition that could affect their cognitive status. Careful screening excluded participants with mild cognitive impairment or dementia. A score equal or greater than 130 was required on the Mattis Dementia Rating Scale (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Mattis, 1988</xref>) for the inclusion in the study. Moreover, participants had to have no or minimal complaints on a questionnaire about their functionality (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Blessed et al., 1968</xref>). Both studies have been approved by the Institutional Review Board of Columbia University. Detailed information can be found in previous publications (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Habeck et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Stern, 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Stern et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Razlighi et al., 2017</xref>). All participants have a written informed consent to perform the study. For the purposes of the current analyses, we included participants who had complete data on the measures used for our hypothesis.</p><p id="p0040">The GWAS used for PGI calculation included participants of European ancestry, and previous studies have shown that PGIs perform worse when applied to other ancestry groups due to differences in Linkage-disequilibrium (LD) and allele frequencies between different populations (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Duncan et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Prive et al., 2022</xref>). Thus, we restricted our analysis to self-reported white participants.</p><p id="p0045"><underline>Genotyping</underline>: Each participant had a venous blood drawn during their visit at Columbia University. DNA samples were obtained through whole blood extraction. Genotyping was performed using Omni 1M chips, according to Illumina procedures. Genotype calling was performed using GenomeStudio v.1.0. Quality control was applied to both DNA samples and SNPs. Specifically, samples were removed from further analysis if they had call rates below 95%, sex discrepancies and relatedness (kinship coefficient more than 0.125). To account for population structure-ancestry, we computed the top 20 Principal Components (PCs) of the whole sample using Plink software and we used the 20&#x000a0;PCs as covariates in our analysis (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Purcell et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p id="p0050"><underline>GWAS imputation</underline>: GWAS data for all study participants was imputed using the Haplotype Reference Consortium (HRC v1.1) panel through the Michigan Imputation online server (Das, Forer et al., 2016). The HRC is a reference panel of 64,976 human haplotypes at 39,235,157 SNPs constructed using whole genome sequence data from 20 studies of predominantly European ancestry (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">McCarthy et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">Imputed dosages for a total of 6,280,331 SNPs with MAF &#x0003e;0.05, HWE <italic>p</italic> value &#x0003e; 1e&#x02013;6 and a missing rate &#x0003c;10% were used for PGI computation. PGI scoring was performed using PRSice software (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Choi and O'Reilly, 2019</xref>) following the clumping and thresholding (C&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;T) approach, as originally described by the International Schizophrenia Consortium (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Prive et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0060"><underline>Polygenic Index</underline>: We composed the PGI from summary statistics from a recent GWAS metanalysis of cognitive performance including n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;269,867 participants, from 14 independent European cohorts (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Savage et al., 2018</xref>). Different measures of intelligence were assessed in each cohort but were all operationalized to index a common latent <italic>g</italic> factor, the general intelligence factor or Spearman's <italic>g</italic>, representing multiple cognitive functioning dimensions. The majority of the samples were adults, 18&#x02013;60 years old (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;204,228), and when they stratified the participants according to age-groups (children, young adults, older adults, adults), results did not show any specific age-dependent effect suggesting that the same SNPs are important across age-groups.</p><p id="p0065">In our analyses, we included all SNPs, regardless of <italic>p</italic>-value. To ensure that only independent markers were included in the computed PGI, we conducted LD clumping using an R<sup>2</sup> threshold of 0.1 and a 250&#x000a0;kb sliding window. Markers within the Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC) LD region on chromosome 6 (chr6:27&#x02013;33&#x000a0;Mb, hg19) were also excluded from the PGI due to the presence of complex patterns of long-range linkage disequilibrium within this region. For each remaining SNP, we computed the weighted count of cognition-associated alleles (0, 1, or 2), with the weights determined by the coefficient estimated in the GWAS. We then computed the average weighted count across all SNPs to form the PGI. The PGI computation was performed using the PRSice software (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Choi and O'Reilly, 2019</xref>). For interpretation reasons, PGI values were normalized by z-transformed.</p><p id="p0070"><underline>Structural MRI scan and image processing</underline>: MRI images were acquired on a 3.0T Philips Achieva Magnet. Each scan used 240&#x000a0;mm field of view. The parameters for Echo-Planar Imaging (EPI) acquisition were echo time/repetition time (TE/TR) (ms) 20/2000; Flip Angle 72&#x000b0;; In-plane resolution (voxels) 112&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;112; Slice thickness/gap (mm) 3/0; Slices 41. T1 scans for each participant were reconstructed with FreeSurfer (v5.1.0) software for human brain imaging analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu" id="intref0010">http://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu</ext-link>). The accuracy of FreeSurfer's subcortical segmentation and cortical parcellation (31, 32) has been reported to be comparable to manual labeling. Each participant's white and gray matter boundaries, as well as gray matter and cerebral-spinal-fluid boundaries, were visually inspected slice by slice, and manual control points were added in case of any visible discrepancy. Boundary reconstruction was repeated until satisfactory results for every participant were reached. The subcortical structure borders were plotted by TkMedit visualization tools and compared against the actual brain regions. In case of discrepancy, they were corrected manually.</p><p id="p0075">We selected three brain-structural markers for analysis based on existing literature establishing association with cognitive test performance: Gray Matter volume (GM) (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Yoon et al., 2017</xref>), Cortical Thickness (CT) (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Tuladhar et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Ehrlich et al., 2012</xref>), and White Matter Hyperintensities (WMH) (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kloppenborg et al., 2014</xref>). We measured GM based on the total gray-matter volume reported by FreeSurfer. We measured regional CT from values computed by standard FreeSurfer parcellation (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Desikan et al., 2006</xref>). We measured total CT as the average of values across both hemispheres. FreeSurfer's subcortical segmentation and cortical parcellation has been shown to have comparable accuracy to manual labeling (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Fischl, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fischl et al., 2002</xref>). Reconstructions were checked and, if needed, manual control points and repeated reconstruction were used. WMH were measured as follows. First, WMH were segmented by the Lesion Segmentation Tool algorithm (LST) (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt et al., 2012</xref>) as implemented in the LST toolbox version 2.0.15 (June 2017) for Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.statistical-modelling.de/lst.html" id="intref0015">www.statistical-modelling.de/lst.html</ext-link>). Next, to extract lobar WMH values, we registered the T1 sequence of each participant in FreeSurfer and then co-registered the Fluid-Attenuaded Inversion Recovery (FLAIR) sequence. We lastly log transformed global WMH burden (log(WMH+1)) derived from the FMRIB software library (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Jenkinson et al., 2012</xref>). Frontal, parietal, temporal, cingulate, and occipital regions were defined as the lobes in FreeSurfer. Finally, the volumes of WMH in each of the five lobes were automatically extracted and their sum was used here. One participant was excluded due to technical problems in extracting the regional WMH map (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Moura et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0080"><underline>Cognitive evaluation</underline>: Each participant underwent an extensive neuropsychological evaluation. From that battery, we derived four cognitive domains: memory, fluid reasoning, speed of processing, and language. The following tests were used: for <italic>memory</italic>: Selective Reminding Test (SRT) (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Buschke and Fuld, 1974</xref>), Long-Term Storage, Consistent Long Term Retrieval, Total words recalled on the last trial; for <italic>fluid reasoning</italic>: Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS-III) matrix reasoning raw score, WASI-III letter-number sequencing raw score, and Block design test, total correct (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">W, 1997</xref>); for <italic>speed of processing</italic>: WAIS-III digit-symbol total correct, Trail Making Test (TMT-A) total time (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Reitan, 1955</xref>), and Stroop Word Raw Score (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Stroop, 1935</xref>); and for <italic>language</italic>: WAIS-III language test, the Wechsler Test of Adult Reading (WTAR) (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">W, 2001</xref>), and the American National Adult Reading Test (AMNART) errors (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Grober and Sliwinski, 1991</xref>). Z-scores were computed for each cognitive task, and each participant, based on the means and standard deviations (SD) of all participants. Scores for TMT-A time and AMNART errors were transformed so that higher score indicates better performance, following the directionality of the other tests. Lastly, for the purposes of the current analysis, we created a global cognitive score, using the sum of all the four cognitive domains together. Similar to the PGI, global cognitive performance, and the brain measures were also transformed into z-scores.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0085">We computed Pearson correlations among the PGI for Cognition (Cog PGI), brain measures, and cognitive test scores.</p><p id="p0090">We used linear regression to test associations between the Cog PGI and cognitive performance. The initial model included the covariates of the first 20 SNP PCs, age, and sex. In the second model, the three brain measures (GM, CT, WMH) were added as covariates. In order to examine whether any of these measures is highly associated with the Cog PGI, we also performed bivariate correlation analysis between the Cog PGI and each of the brain measures separately, without adding any covariate.</p><p id="p0095">To investigate potential differences in associations between younger and older participants, we created two age-groups (young and middle-aged adults: 20&#x02013;64 y.o., and older adults: 65&#x02013;80 y.o.), and repeated our analysis within these two groups. We conducted formal tests of differences in associations between younger and older participants by including an indicator variable for age group and a product term for the interaction of age group with PGI in our original regression specifications.</p><p id="p0100">Education has been linked to differences in brain structure, cognition and cognitive PGIs. Polygenic scores for education have also been associated with other polygenic scores including cognitive PGIs (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Gen&#x000e7; et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Ritchie et al., 2020</xref>). Thus, we further provide supplementary analyses results, adding in the linear regression models education as a covariate.</p><p id="p0105">Analyses were performed using SPSS 26 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Nominally significant alpha values were defined as <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0110">Our sample consisted of 168 cognitively healthy participants aged 20-80 years - old (48.8% women), who self-reported White ethnicity. The mean educational level - was 16 years (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). When split by age-group, young and middle-aged adults had a mean age of 48 years, while older adults of 70 years, with similar education in both groups (M: 16 years) (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sample characteristics.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2">Characteristics<hr/></th><th rowspan="2">Young and middle-aged adults</th><th rowspan="2">Older adults</th></tr><tr><th/><th>Total sample</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age, years, Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">56.9 (15.5)</td><td align="left">47.6 (13.9)</td><td align="left">69.9 (3.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Education, years, Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">16.4 (2.27)</td><td align="left">16.3 (2.1)</td><td align="left">16.7 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex, women, N (%)</td><td align="left">82 (48.8)</td><td align="left">51 (52)</td><td align="left">31 (44.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Global cognitive score, Mean (SD)</td><td align="left">0.66 (2.3)</td><td align="left">0.33 (1)</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.47 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GM</td><td align="left">6.25 (0.59)</td><td align="left">6.46 (0.58)</td><td align="left">5.9 (0.45)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT</td><td align="left">0.63 (0.24)</td><td align="left">0.72 (0.22)</td><td align="left">0.59 (0.45)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">WMHlog</td><td align="left">7.41 (0.64)</td><td align="left">7.16 (0.5)</td><td align="left">7.8 (0.65)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total, N</td><td align="left">168</td><td align="left">98</td><td align="left">70</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0115">In the correlation analyses, participants with higher PGIs also performed better on cognitive tests (global cognitive score) (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.244, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001) (unadjusted model). In parallel, all three brain-structural markers showed the expected patterns of association with cognitive test performance; participants with more gray matter, thicker cortices, and fewer white matter hyperintensities performed better on cognitive tests (global cognitive score) (GM: r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.385, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001; CT: r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.559, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001; WMH: r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.240, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002).</p><p id="p0120">Results showed no significant association between the Cog PGI and any of the three brain measures, (GM: r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.127, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.104, CT: r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.123, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.117, WMH: B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.039, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.618) (unadjusted models) (see <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Similarly, there was no significant association when all the three measures were added in a linear regression model together (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.133).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Bivariate correlations between Brain measures and Cognitive performance, Cog PGI, and Linear regression analysis' results for the association between Cognitive performance and Cog PGI.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Cognition (NP performance)</th><th>Cog PGI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><bold>Brain measures</bold> (Bivariate correlations)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GM</td><td align="left"><bold>r</bold><sup><bold>2</bold></sup><bold>=&#x000a0;0.148, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.653, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.0001</bold></td><td align="left">r<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.016, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.217, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.104</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT</td><td align="left"><bold>r</bold><sup><bold>2</bold></sup><bold>=&#x000a0;0.312, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.288, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.0001</bold></td><td align="left">r<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.015, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.429, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.117</td></tr><tr><td align="left">WMHlog</td><td align="left"><bold>r</bold><sup><bold>2</bold></sup><bold>=&#x000a0;-0.057, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;-0.372, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002</bold></td><td align="left">r<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.061, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.618</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left"><bold>Cognition (NP performance)</bold> (Linear regression models)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total sample (age, sex, PCs)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left"><bold>r</bold><sup><bold>2</bold></sup><bold>=&#x000a0;0.443, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.627, SE:0.196, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total sample (age, sex, PCs, brain measures)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left"><bold>r</bold><sup><bold>2</bold></sup><bold>=&#x000a0;0.513, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.439, SE: 0.198, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.028</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Young and middle-aged adults (age, sex, PCs, brain measures)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left"><bold>r</bold><sup><bold>2</bold></sup><bold>=&#x000a0;0.579, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.704, SE: 0.263, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Older adults (age, sex, PCs, brain measures)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">r<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.523, B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.401, SE: 0.334, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.238</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0125">We then investigated the role of brain-structural markers in PGI associations with cognitive - performance using a series of linear regression models. The base model included the PGI and the covariates of age, sex, and the 20&#x000a0;PCs. In this model, the magnitude of the Cog PGI association with cognitive test performance was B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.627 (SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.196, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002). Next, we added the three neural phenotype measures to the model, where the association between Cog PGI and cognitive - performance was still significant: B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.439 (SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.198, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.028) (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Scatterplot for the association between Cog PGI and Cognition, after adding PCs, age, sex, gray matter, cortical thickness, and white matter hyperintensities as covariates.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0130">In an analysis stratified by age group, results indicated significant association between the Cog PGI and cognition after adding the above-mentioned covariates (age, sex, PCs, brain measures) for the young group (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.704, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.263, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.009), while the association was not significant for the older adults (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.401, SE:0.334, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.238 (see <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In a further analysis combining the age groups and examining the interaction test, results remained significant for the relationship of Cog PGI with cognition (fully adjusted model; sex, age dichotomous, PCs, brain measures) (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.892, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.325, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.007), with the relationship being driven by the young and middle-aged group: age-interaction term (B&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.403, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.193, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.039) (see <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Scatterplot for the interaction test between age groups (young and middle-aged, older adults) and Cog PGI for Cognition, after adding PCs, sex, age groups, gray matter volume, cortical thickness, and white matter hyperintensities as covariates.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0135"><xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 1</xref> provides all the associations mentioned above (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), but further adding education as a covariate, while <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 2</xref> provides the association between Cog PGI and each of the brain markers for each age group, adjusted for sex, education, and PCs.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0140">We analyzed genetic, brain-imaging, and cognitive test data in a sample of healthy adults representing the full age range from young adulthood to old age. To our knowledge, there is a gap on research integrating genetics, brain imaging, and cognitive test data, in cognitively healthy adults across age. Consistent with prior GWAS and PGI studies, we found that participants with higher PGIs also performed better on cognitive tests. However, this genetic gradient in cognitive test performance was only partly explained by documented brain-structure phenotypes of cognitive aging (GM, CT, WMH). Moreover, participants&#x02019; PGIs were not associated with these brain-structure phenotypes. In a sensitivity analysis, we found that PGI associations with cognition were stronger in young and middle-aged as compared to older adults. In sum, our findings suggest genetics uncovered in GWAS of cognitive performance reflect genetics that contribute to individual differences and may not reflect genetic mechanisms of cognitive aging.</p><p id="p0145">Normal aging is accompanied by structural changes in brain anatomy including region-specific gray matter atrophy (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Raz and Rodrigue, 2006</xref>), cortical thinning that is more pronounced in parts of the association cortex (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hurtz et al., 2014</xref>), and white matter lesions that constitute biomarkers of cognitive decline even before its appearance (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">d'Arbeloff et al., 2019</xref>). These age-related changes in structural brain features are strongly associated with cognition among healthy older adults (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hurtz et al., 2014</xref>), and therefore represent one potential pathway through which genetics could influence individual differences in cognitive performance. Thus, we tested if the association between PGI and cognitive performance may be confounded by a set of age-related brain markers known to be associated with cognitive performance (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Choi and O'Reilly, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Prive et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Yoon et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Tuladhar et al., 2015</xref>). The relationship between the PGI and cognition remained strong beyond brain markers, and such results do not support brain-structure phenotypes associated with cognitive aging as a mechanism through which genetic variation influences cognitive performance. Instead, they point to pathways and mechanisms earlier in life-course development. Following a PGI approach, it might be possible to identify individuals with a higher risk of developing more severe age-related cognitive decline, independent of the effects of Alzheimer's pathology. Early identification of such a high-risk group could aid in the testing and implementation of preventive strategies. Genetic data could be more closely linked to performance early in life since the association weakens by adding more noise as we grow, and further, age-related pathology accumulates. Cognition-related genetic variation may contribute to cognitive reserve by modifying the relationship between neurodegenerative processes and cognitive performance (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Lee, 2003</xref>). However, testing this hypothesis will require longitudinal cognitive evaluation and neuroimaging data. Further, it is noteworthy that the brain measures used in the current analysis are comprised of trait and state effects, i.e., they are the product of both trait endowment of good brain structure at the beginning of life and maintenance over the life course. Because of the cross-sectional study design such trait and state effects cannot be disentangled.</p><p id="p0150">We also are careful to avoid asserting that brain-structural markers are not related to cognition: our study only has a small sample size and might be underpowered to discover such associations. However, our data do suggest that PGI associations with cognition are not fully explained by brain structure markers of cognitive aging. Further, we conducted a supplementary analysis where association strength (as measured by the T-statistic) of the PGI with cognition was compared to the associations of the brain-structural markers with cognition in a two-tailed permutation test of 100,000 iterations, where we repeated the linear regression for null conditions by randomizing the cognition endpoint. We found that across combined age groups, the association of the PGI and cognition was significantly larger than between CT and cognition (T-stat difference&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.9252, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0413); it was also significantly larger than between WMHlog and cognition (T-stat difference&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.8776, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0476) while offering no significant difference to the association between cognition and TGM (T-stat difference&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.7607, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.6182).</p><p id="p0155">It is noteworthy that cognitive PGI was not directly associated with GM, CT, or WMH brain measures, suggesting that cognition-associated genetics do not affect cognitive performance via their influence on phenotypes of the brain. Environmental factors such as brain injury or aging could indeed affect brain areas (e.g., increase in WMH) and this in turn affect cognitive performance. However, under normal state of cognition, our data suggest that Cog PGI influences cognition independently of brain structure. An alternate hypothesis could be that cognition-associated genes influence changes in brain structure over time, especially during aging, and these brain alterations in turn impact cognition. Addressing this possibility will require longitudinal studies.</p><p id="p0160">We acknowledge some limitations of the study; foremost, the PGI we analyzed remains a work in progress. We used results from the largest-scale GWAS of cognition available and employed a well-established and robust pipeline for computing our PGI. However, methods in this area continue to develop (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, more sophisticated sample designs in GWAS may also clarify and refine our understanding of genetic influences on individual differences in cognition (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Howe et al., 2022</xref>). Our sample size was powered to detect only medium-effect-size or larger associations. Thus, while we were able to rule out these substantial genetic associations with structural brain imaging parameters; repeating analysis in larger samples is required to test for potential smaller effects. Like other neuroimaging cohorts, our sample tends to be somewhat higher-educated as compared to the general population. Our results apply to White-ethnicity participants only, which can limit the generalizability of our results in other cohorts, however, no GWAS of cognitive functioning in non-European cohorts has been conducted until now that we could use to replicate our findings in other ancestry groups. Overall, this difference should reduce variation in cognitive performance and related brain characteristics and therefore render our analysis more conservative. Follow-up of our findings in more diverse, population-representative samples is needed. Finally, longitudinal analysis would be valuable to better characterize the chronology of the influence of the PGI on cognitive aging.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0170">The authors have nothing to disclose.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale</part-title><edition>third ed.</edition><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Harcourt Assessment</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc><fpage>684</fpage><lpage>690</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The Wechsler Test of Adult Reading (WTAR): Test Manual</part-title><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belsky</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harden</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic annotation: using polygenic scores to translate discoveries from genome-wide association studies from the top down</article-title><source>Curr. Dir. Psychol. Sci.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38736689</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belsky</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffitt</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caspi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics in population health science: strategies and opportunities</article-title><comment>Suppl 1</comment><source>Am. J. Publ. Health</source><volume>103</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>S73</fpage><lpage>S83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blessed</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between quantitative measures of dementia and of senile change in the cerebral grey matter of elderly subjects</article-title><source>Br. J. Psychiatry</source><volume>114</volume><issue>512</issue><year>1968</year><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5662937</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buschke</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuld</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating storage, retention, and retrieval in disordered memory and learning</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>24</volume><issue>11</issue><year>1974</year><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4473151</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheryl</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional brain imaging and age-related changes in cognition</article-title><source>Biol. Psychol.</source><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035226</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PRSice-2: polygenic Risk Score software for biobank-scale data</article-title><source>GigaScience</source><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>T.S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tutorial: a guide to performing polygenic risk score analyses</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2759</fpage><lpage>2772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32709988</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>d'Arbeloff</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>White matter hyperintensities are common in midlife and already associated with cognitive decline</article-title><source>Brain Commun.</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">fcz041</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Study of 300,486 individuals identifies 148 independent genetic loci influencing general cognitive function</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2098</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844566</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deary</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation, brain, and intelligence differences</article-title><source>Mol. Psychiatr.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>353</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demange</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigating the genetic architecture of noncognitive skills using GWAS-by-subtraction</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>53</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33414549</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desikan</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An automated labeling system for subdividing the human cerebral cortex on MRI scans into gyral based regions of interest</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16530430</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudbridge</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Power and predictive accuracy of polygenic risk scores</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1003348</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of polygenic risk score usage and performance in diverse human populations</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>3328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31346163</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations of cortical thickness and cognition in patients with schizophrenia and healthy controls</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1050</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436318</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FreeSurfer</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>62</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22248573</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole brain segmentation: automated labeling of neuroanatomical structures in the human brain</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832223</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gen&#x000e7;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polygenic scores for cognitive abilities and their association with different aspects of general intelligence-A deep phenotyping approach</article-title><source>Mol. Neurobiol.</source><volume>58</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>4145</fpage><lpage>4156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33954905</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parasuraman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal genetic variation, cognition, and aging</article-title><source>Behav. Cognit. Neurosci. Rev.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15006290</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grober</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sliwinski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a model for estimating premorbid verbal intelligence in the elderly</article-title><source>J. Clin. Exp. Neuropsychol.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><year>1991</year><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1779032</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Reference Ability Neural Network Study: life-time stability of reference-ability neural networks derived from task maps of young adults</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>125</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26522424</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cognitive reserve and brain maintenance: orthogonal concepts in theory and practice</article-title><source>Cerebr. Cortex</source><volume>27</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>3962</fpage><lpage>3969</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Within-sibship genome-wide association analyses decrease bias in estimates of direct genetic effects</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35534559</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurtz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age effects on cortical thickness in cognitively normal elderly individuals</article-title><source>Dement. Geriatr. Cogn. Dis. Extra.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25177330</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fsl</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>62</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21979382</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kloppenborg</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Presence and progression of white matter hyperintensities and cognition: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>82</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>2127</fpage><lpage>2138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24814849</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic evidence for cognitive reserve: variations in memory and related cognitive functions</article-title><source>J. Clin. Exp. Neuropsychol.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815498</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene discovery and polygenic prediction from a genome-wide association study of educational attainment in 1.1 million individuals</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1112</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30038396</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brain structure and function show distinct relations with genetic predispositions to mental health and cognition</article-title><source>Biol. Psychiatr. Cogn. Neurosci. Neuroimag.</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical use of current polygenic risk scores may exacerbate health disparities</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>51</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30926966</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Dementia Rating Scale (DRS)</part-title><year>1988</year><publisher-name>Psychological Assessment Resources</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Odessa, FL</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A reference panel of 64,976 haplotypes for genotype imputation</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>48</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27548312</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The relationship between white matter hyperintensities and cognitive reference abilities across the life span</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Aging</source><volume>83</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31585365</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prive</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Making the most of clumping and thresholding for polygenic scores</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source><volume>105</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31761295</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prive</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Portability of 245 polygenic scores when derived from the UK Biobank and applied to 9 ancestry groups from the same cohort</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source><volume>109</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>373</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35120604</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source><volume>81</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential aging of the brain: patterns, cognitive correlates and modifiers</article-title><source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16919333</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razlighi</surname><given-names>Q.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cognitive neuroscience neuroimaging repository for the adult lifespan</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>144</volume><issue>Pt B</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26311605</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reitan</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relation of the trail making test to organic brain damage</article-title><source>J. Consult. Psychol.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1955</year><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13263471</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polygenic predictors of age-related decline in cognitive ability</article-title><source>Mol. Psychiatr.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2584</fpage><lpage>2598</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association meta-analysis in 269,867 individuals identifies new genetic and functional links to intelligence</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942086</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An automated tool for detection of FLAIR-hyperintense white-matter lesions in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>59</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>3774</fpage><lpage>3783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22119648</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive reserve</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>47</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>2028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19467352</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive reserve in ageing and Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1006</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23079557</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Reference Ability Neural Network Study: motivation, design, and initial feasibility analyses</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>103</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25245813</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stroop</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies of interference in serial verbal reactions</article-title><source>J. Exp. Psychol.</source><volume>18</volume><year>1935</year><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>662</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugrue</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desikan</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What are polygenic scores and why are they important?</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>321</volume><issue>18</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30958510</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic influences on brain structure</article-title><source>Nat. Neurosci.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>1253</fpage><lpage>1258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11694885</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torkamani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wineinger</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The personal and clinical utility of polygenic risk scores</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29789686</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuladhar</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between white matter hyperintensities, cortical thickness, and cognition</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25572411</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>Y.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brain structural networks associated with intelligence and visuomotor ability</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>2177</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28526888</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0180">The following is the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0010"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0010">Data will be made available on request.</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0175">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1">National Institute of Aging</funding-source> (grant numbers <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">K01AG051777</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">R01AG026158</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">R01AG038465</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">R01AG062578</award-id>, and <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">K99AG071930</award-id>), and the <funding-source id="gs2">Bodossaki foundation</funding-source>.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0185">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ynirp.2022.100153" id="intref0020">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ynirp.2022.100153</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>