<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40442596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12123810</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6722</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-025-06722-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Enhancing alfalfa and sorghum silage quality using agricultural wastes: fermentation dynamics, microbial communities, and functional insights</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Dianpeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yulian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Maoya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jiachuhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Xiangjiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xinyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Shengnan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaoqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name><address><email>429845801@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chao</given-names></name><address><email>chenc@gzu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02wmsc916</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.443382.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1804 268X</institution-id><institution>College of Animal Science, </institution><institution>Guizhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guiyang, 550025 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/024d3p373</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.464485.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1777 7975</institution-id><institution>Tongliao Academy of Agriculture and Animal Husbandry Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Tongliao, 028000 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Inner Mongolia Forestry and Grassland Monitoring and Planning Institute, Hohhot, 010020 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Grassland Research of the Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hohhot, 010013 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><elocation-id>728</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025, corrected publication 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">At present, there are many researches on the nutritional quality and fermentation quality of forage silage by adding distillers&#x02019; grain and fruit residue, but few researches on the succession and function prediction of microbiotic community. In this study, the potential of Moutai distillers' grain (MDG), <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace (RP) and <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> (LAB) to improve silage quality during anaerobic storage of alfalfa and sorghum was investigated. Harvested alfalfa and sorghum were ensiled without (CK) or with MDG, RP, LAB, LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG or LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP for 45 days at 21&#x02013;25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Compared with the uninoculated control, alfalfa silage inoculated with LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG presented better nutrient retention, where the lactic acid (LA) content was increased by 84.62% and the ammonia nitrogen (AN) content was reduced by 38.52%. Similarly, in sorghum silage, both inoculation with LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG and inoculation with LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP effectively increased nutrient retention, increased the LA content and reduced the AN content. The proportion of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> increased in sorghum and alfalfa silage after 45 days of fermentation. Inoculation of alfalfa and sorghum with RP or LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG significantly increased the relative abundance of lactic acid bacteria in silage, especially <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>, which was the main dominant strain. The addition of MDG to the feeds not only effectively retained the crude protein (CP) content of the feeds for better retention of their nutritional value but also significantly reduced the contents of neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and acid detergent fiber (ADF), which improved the digestibility and utilization of the feeds. In addition, the addition of MDG further promoted the proliferation of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and increased their abundance in the silage, thus contributing to the improvement of fermentation quality and preservation of silage. In summary, MDG, LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, and RP&#x02009;+&#x02009;LAB resulted in higher-quality silage, but the addition of MDG was more cost effective and therefore is recommended for application in production.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace</kwd><kwd>Alfalfa</kwd><kwd>Bacterial community</kwd><kwd>Moutai distillers' grain</kwd><kwd>Sorghum</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Youth Science Fund Projects of the National Natural Science Foundation</institution></funding-source><award-id>32401494</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Key Research and Development Subject</institution></funding-source><award-id>2021YFD1300302</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Project</institution></funding-source><award-id>Qiankehe Chengguo [2022]005</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Guizhou University Cultivation Project</institution></funding-source><award-id>Guida Peiyu [2020]9</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Projects</institution></funding-source><award-id>QKHPTRC-GCC[2023]012</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">China, the world&#x02019;s second most populous country, generates substantial agricultural waste annually, posing environmental risks if improperly managed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Meanwhile, rapid growth in animal husbandry since the 21st century has intensified feed grain shortages, a key constraint on agricultural development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. To address these challenges, we propose enhancing forage quality through silage combined with agricultural byproducts.</p><p id="Par3"><italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> (Roxburgh rose), a thorny, nutrient-rich plant endemic to China, has seen significant cultivation expansion in Guizhou Province, reaching 140,000 hectares and producing over 300,000 tons of fruit annually by 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Its fruit, valued for active compounds, is primarily processed into juice, generating large amounts of <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace (RP) with 50% water content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This pomace is often disposed of by simple piling, landfilling or incineration, which not only results in a large amount of unused natural resources but also raises serious ecological pollution problems. While studies show RP&#x02019;s potential as dietary fiber [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and livestock feed (improving protein efficiency in Hu sheep at 30% inclusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] ), its application in silage remains underexplored. The present study shows that the quality of alfalfa silage can be improved by adding astragalus and hawthorn residues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] or grape pomace [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Distillers&#x02019; grain (DG), a byproduct of alcohol production, contains residual grains, yeast, sugars, crude protein (CP), fiber, and micronutrients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. China generates about 35&#x000a0;million tons of DG annually from liquor production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], with Guizhou being a major contributor. Due to its high moisture content, DG spoils easily, posing environmental risks if not disposed of promptly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. While most research focuses on using dried DG as animal feed, excessive heat during drying can degrade proteins and amino acids, limiting the utilization of its bioactive components and economic value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Although RP and MDG have silage application potential, most of the existing studies are limited to nutritional analysis, and the specific mechanisms of their regulation of fermentation microbial communities and inhibition of spoilage are not clear, and need to be further analyzed through pairing experiments and microbiomes. Therefore, we propose that RP and DG be added to forage silage to improve its quality, thus increasing waste utilization and reducing environmental pollution.</p><p id="Par4">Alfalfa (<italic>Medicago sativa</italic> L.) is a nutrient-rich perennial legume forage, high in protein, minerals, and vitamins, making it ideal for ruminants like cattle and sheep. In southern China, it is often preserved as silage due to hot, humid summers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. However, alfalfa silage typically has poor quality due to high buffering capacity, low water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC), and harmful microbes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Studies show that adding byproducts like sea buckthorn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], lemon pomace [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], grape residue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] improves silage quality by reducing harmful microorganisms. Therefore, incorporating other bioactive byproducts, such as RP and DG, may similarly enhance alfalfa silage quality, extending shelf-life and boosting nutritional value. Sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> L.), an annual grass native to Africa, is cultivated globally for its nutritional and high-sugar stalks, making it valuable for feed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Sorghum grows vigorously in summer, with excess amounts of fresh grass produced, and southern China is humid and rainy, so fresh grass is not easy to preserve. Ensiling whole sorghum helps retain nutrients and extend storage, addressing seasonal forage shortages. However, direct sorghum silage has poor fermentation quality, though lactic acid bacteria can improve it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The impact of RP and DG on alfalfa and sorghum silage remains unstudied, and their mechanisms on different forages are unclear.</p><p id="Par5">Silage preserves fresh feed via lactic acid bacteria fermentation, where organic acids (mainly lactic acid (LA)) lower pH, ensuring long-term stability. However, alfalfa and sorghum are unsuitable for solo ensiling, while RP and Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain (MDG) spoil easily due to high moisture. This study investigates how RP, MDG, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> (LAB), LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG influence silage quality, microbial diversity, and functional profiles in Leguminosae (alfalfa) and Poaceae (sorghum).</p><p id="Par6">By analyzing these interactions, we aim to demonstrate how agricultural byproducts can optimize fermentation by suppressing harmful microbes, improving forage quality. This research supports sustainable waste utilization and advances silage technology innovation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Preparation of alfalfa and sorghum before silage</title><p id="Par7">Whole plants of alfalfa and sorghum were artificially harvested from Anshun city, Guizhou Province, on August 15, 2022. The samples were cut into 10&#x02013;20&#x000a0;mm lengths before silage. <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace was obtained from Guizhou Hengliyuan Natural Biological Technology Co., Ltd., in Guiyang city, Guizhou Province, China. The MDG was acquired from the Kweichow Moutai Group in Moutai town, Renhuai city, Guizhou Province, China. The chemical compositions of alfalfa, sorghum, MDG and RP are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Each bag contains 330&#x000a0;g of chopped samples, which were then vacuumed and sealed with a vacuum packaging machine (Mag, DZ-400/2S, Qingdao). This process was repeated for alfalfa. (1) CK (without additives), applied as 5% fresh weight (FW) distilled water; (2) LAB, applied as <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> (Sourced from Guangzhou Hua Microbial Technology Co., Ltd., Guangzhou, China, the effective microbial count is 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>CFU/g) at 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/g FW; (3) RP, applied as 25% FW RP (Guizhou Hengliyuan Natural Biological Technology Co., Ltd., Guizhou, China); (4) MDG, applied as 25% FW MDG; (5) LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, combined with the application of 25% FW RP with LAB at 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/g FW (Guangzhou Hua Microbial Technology Co., Ltd., Guangzhou, China); and (6) LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, combined with the application of 25% FW MDG with LAB at 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/g FW. Three replicates are set for per treatment. In this work, S is used to represent sorghum, and A is used for alfalfa. Based on the findings of Dai et al. (2022), we selected 25% FW MDG and RP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. All bags containing silage were stored at 21&#x02013;25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 45 days, after which the fermentation indicators, nutritional indicators, microbial communities, and functional predictions of the silage were determined.</p><p id="Par8">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical compositions of fresh Alfalfa, Sorghum, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain and <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Item</th><th align="left">Fresh alfalfa</th><th align="left">Sorghum</th><th align="left">Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain</th><th align="left">Rosa roxburghii pomace</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">DM (%FM)</td><td align="left">27.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.32</td><td align="left">38.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td><td align="left">44.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td align="left">29.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CP (%DM)</td><td align="left">26.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.57</td><td align="left">5.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td align="left">28.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td align="left">6.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NDF (%DM)</td><td align="left">43.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.00</td><td align="left">57.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td align="left">43.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.68</td><td align="left">46.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ADF (%DM)</td><td align="left">29.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td><td align="left">32.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.00</td><td align="left">30.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.71</td><td align="left">25.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">WSC (%DM)</td><td align="left">4.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td><td align="left">12.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td align="left">0.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24</td><td align="left">5.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data are expressed as the means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard errors. DM, dry matter; CP, crude protein; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; WSC, water soluble carbohydrate; FM, fresh matter</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Chemical composition analysis of sorghum and alfalfa silage samples</title><p id="Par9">A total of 10&#x000a0;g of each sample was added to 90 mL of water, mixed well, allowed to stand for 24&#x000a0;h, and filtered with cheesecloth. Organic acids, ammonia nitrogen (AN), and pH were measured in the supernatant. The pH was measured via a glass electrode pH meter. The content of AN was determined by the phenol-sodium hypochlorite method of Broderick &#x00026; Kang (1980) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. LA, acetic acid (AA), propionic acid (PA) and butyric acid (BA) levels were determined via high-performance liquid chromatography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Each sample, weighing approximately 200&#x000a0;g, was dried at 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until a constant weight was achieved to determine the dry matter (DM) content. Afterward, the samples were ground through a 1&#x000a0;mm mesh sieve for chemical component analysis. The CP content was examined with a Kjeldahl analyzer in accordance with the Association of Official Analytical Chemists (AOAC) procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Using an Ankom 2000 fiber analyzer, the neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and acid detergent fiber (ADF) concentrations were determined following the Van Soest method, as detailed in Van et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. WSC content was determined by anthrone - sulfuric acid colorimetric method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Microbial population analysis</title><p id="Par10">Total genomic DNA from each sample was extracted via the CTAB method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The full-length 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) gene was amplified via PCR for SMRT sequencing via the forward primer 27F (5&#x02019;-GAGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3&#x02019;) and the reverse primer 1541R (5&#x02019;-AAGGAGGTGATCCAGCCGCA-3&#x02019;), which contained a set of 16-nucleotide barcodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. DNA libraries were generated with the SMRTbell Template Prep Kit (PacBio, Menlo Park, 135 CA, USA) and sequenced via the PacBio Sequel system. The processing of the raw sequences was performed by Novogene Bio Technology 136 Co., Ltd. (Beijing, China). The data were analyzed via the Novogene Magic Cloud Platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://magic.novogene.com">https://magic.novogene.com</ext-link>). Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) functional prediction analysis was used to predict bacterial community function in sorghum and alfalfa silage via the Tax4fun tool.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par11">Two-factor ANOVA was performed via SPSS 19 software to analyze chemical composition and fermentation quality data, and multiple comparisons were subsequently performed via Duncan&#x02019;s test to determine the significance of differences between treatments. Data on microbial communities were analyzed and plotted via GraphPad Prism. 8.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Chemical composition of fresh samples</title><p id="Par12">The chemical compositions of the fresh samples were shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The DM levels of alfalfa, sorghum, MDG and RP were 27.83%, 38.45%, 44.92% and 29.57%, respectively, before ensiling. The CP contents of the fresh alfalfa and sorghum samples were 26.64% and 5.20%, respectively. The NDF and ADF contents of alfalfa were 43.51% and 29.21%, respectively, whereas the NDF and ADF contents of sorghum were 57.33% and 32.23%, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Chemical composition of alfalfa and sorghum silage</title><p id="Par13">For sorghum silage, the DM content in the CK treatment was significantly lower than that in the LAB and MDG treatments; for alfalfa silage, the DM content was significantly greater in the LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG treatments than in the CK treatment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Higher CP contents (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) were clearly observed for sorghum silage with the addition of MDG and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG than for S-CK. Compared with the LAB and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG treatments, the CK treatment resulted in significantly lower levels of WSC in sorghum silage. In contrast, in alfalfa silage, we found a similar trend. Specifically, all the treatment groups with different substances added, except the MDG treatment group, presented significantly greater WSC contents than did the control group without any substances added.</p><p id="Par14">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Chemical composition of silage</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Forage species (F)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Treatment (T)</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Items</th></tr><tr><th align="left">DM%FM</th><th align="left">CP%DM</th><th align="left">NDF%DM</th><th align="left">ADF%DM</th><th align="left">WSC%DM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Sorghum silage</td><td align="left">S-CK</td><td align="left">36.48<sup>cd</sup></td><td align="left">5.82<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">61.33<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">32.69<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">2.05<sup>ef</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB</td><td align="left">41.19<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="left">6.69<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">46.07<sup>cde</sup></td><td align="left">32.24<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">4.03<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-RP</td><td align="left">40.13<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">7.12<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">49.00<sup>bcd</sup></td><td align="left">29.00<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">1.80<sup>f</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-MDG</td><td align="left">44.02<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">8.85<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">45.01<sup>de</sup></td><td align="left">26.50<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">2.07<sup>ef</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP</td><td align="left">38.37<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">6.14<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">54.00<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">32.67<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">2.07<sup>ef</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG</td><td align="left">39.46<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">9.32<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">52.51<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">29.33<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">3.06<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Alfalfa silage</td><td align="left">A-CK</td><td align="left">28.45<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">24.89<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">43.33<sup>de</sup></td><td align="left">30.67<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">2.09<sup>ef</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB</td><td align="left">28.75<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">25.64<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">42.00<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">29.33<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">3.20<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-RP</td><td align="left">28.68<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">21.37<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">51.66<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">35.74<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.90<sup>bcd</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-MDG</td><td align="left">32.10<sup>ef</sup></td><td align="left">25.71<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">45.63<sup>de</sup></td><td align="left">33.56<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="left">2.41<sup>de</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP</td><td align="left">33.25<sup>de</sup></td><td align="left">22.76<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">42.00<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">29.33<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="left">2.67<sup>bcd</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG</td><td align="left">32.84<sup>de</sup></td><td align="left">25.18<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">40.67<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">28.00<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">2.63<sup>cd</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><italic>P</italic> value</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">0.006</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.003</td><td align="left">0.710</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.558</td><td align="left">0.168</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T&#x000d7;F</td><td align="left">0.022</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.030</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between different treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; DM, dry matter; CP, crude protein; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; WSC, water-soluble carbohydrate; FM, fresh matter; T, treatment; F, forage species; T &#x000d7; F, interaction of treatments and forage species</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Fermentation quality of alfalfa and sorghum silage</title><p id="Par15">The silage fermentation quality results are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The pH values measured for sorghum silage were generally lower than those for alfalfa silage in the treatment groups where the same types and amounts of additives were added. For both sorghum silage and alfalfa silage, the pH values were significantly lower in the LAB treatment than in the other treatments. In both the alfalfa and sorghum silages, the LA contents in the LAB, LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG treatments were significantly greater than those in the other treatments. All the alfalfa treatments presented significantly greater AA contents than did the sorghum treatments. In contrast, for sorghum, the AA content did not significantly differ after the different treatments. The LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP treatment stood out among the other treatments in terms of alfalfa silage, with a noticeably higher AA content. the PA levels were significantly greater in all the sorghum treatment groups than in the alfalfa treatment groups, Interestingly, we found that PA was not detected in alfalfa silage in the MDG and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG treatments. In our exploration, alfalfa silage was found to produce significantly higher levels of AN than sorghum silage. For both the alfalfa and sorghum silages, all the additive treatments led to a lower AN content than did the CK.</p><p id="Par16">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Fermentation characteristics of silage</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Forage species (F)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Treatment (T)</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Items</th><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">pH</th><th align="left">LA%DM</th><th align="left">AA%DM</th><th align="left">PA%DM</th><th align="left">BA%DM</th><th align="left">AN%DM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Sorghum silage</td><td align="left">S-CK</td><td align="left">4.82<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.71<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">0.47</td><td align="left">2.15<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.16<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.08<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB</td><td align="left">3.87<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.26<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.38</td><td align="left">1.35<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.09<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.41<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-RP</td><td align="left">4.89<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.39<sup>f</sup></td><td align="left">0.44</td><td align="left">1.64<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.00<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">0.78<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-MDG</td><td align="left">4.78<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.83<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left">1.18<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.28<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.55<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP</td><td align="left">4.46<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">1.07<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.46</td><td align="left">1.49<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.03<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">0.79<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG</td><td align="left">4.51<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">1.73<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.47</td><td align="left">2.30<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.23<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.48<sup>cd</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Alfalfa silage</td><td align="left">A-CK</td><td align="left">5.56<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.39<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.83<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.65<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.00<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">3.08<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB</td><td align="left">4.83<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.51<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.96<sup>bcd</sup></td><td align="left">0.73<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">2.55<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-RP</td><td align="left">5.49<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.17<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">1.04<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.50<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.16<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.41<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-MDG</td><td align="left">4.96<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.14<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.89c<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.03<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.21<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.12<sup>cd</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP</td><td align="left">5.09<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.63<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">1.19<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.69<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="left">0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">2.63<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG</td><td align="left">4.70<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">0.72<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">1.03<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">0.05<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.00<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.77<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><italic>P</italic> value</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T&#x000d7;F</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.016</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between different treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LA, Lactic acid; AA, Acetic acid; PA, Propionic acid; BA, Butyric acid; AN, Ammonia nitrogen; DM, dry matter; T, treatment; F, forage species; T &#x000d7; F, interaction of treatments and forage species</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Changes in the microbial communities of sorghum and alfalfa during silage</title><p id="Par17">The bacterial alpha diversity of the alfalfa samples during ensiling is illustrated in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The lowest number of strains was observed under the A-LAB treatment, which resulted in a decrease in bacterial diversity indices such as the ACE and Shannon indices. Compared with the S-CK treatment, the S-MDG treatment resulted in the greatest decrease in the ACE index. Compared with sorghum, the addition of LAB and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP to alfalfa resulted in a greater Shannon index, which indicates a significant difference in alpha diversity between sorghum and alfalfa. The bacterial communities at the phylum level in the alfalfa and sorghum raw materials after 45 days of ensiling are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A. Fresh alfalfa and fresh sorghum were found to be teeming with a diverse array of bacterial communities, with Cyanobacteria and Proteobacteria being predominant at the phylum level, and sorghum contained small amounts of Bacteroidetes. Prior to silage, the dominant phylum in sorghum was Proteobacteria (66.97%). The relative abundance of Firmicutes increased to 57.29% after 45 d of silage in the S-CK treatment. After 45 days of alfalfa silage, Firmicutes replaced Cyanobacteria as the dominant phylum, and its relative abundance reached 78.81%. After fermentation of both materials, the dominant phylum was Firmicutes. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, <italic>Sphingomona</italic>s, unidentified <italic>Cyanobacteria</italic> and <italic>Asaia</italic> were dominant in fresh sorghum, and unidentified <italic>Cyanobacteria</italic> (80.51%), <italic>Kosakonia</italic> (5.46%) and others (11.51%) were dominant in fresh alfalfa. The dominant genus in sorghum and alfalfa after ensiling was <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Kosakonia</italic> (26.75%) and unidentified <italic>Clostridiales</italic> (23.63%) were more abundant in sorghum silage without additives, and <italic>Kosakonia</italic> (14.51%) and <italic>Enterococcus</italic> (29.9%) were more abundant in alfalfa silage without additives. The bacterial species present in the alfalfa and sorghum samples during anaerobic storage are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C. The main bacterial species treated with S-CK were <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>, <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic>, and <italic>Kosakonia cowanii</italic>. The A-CK treatment resulted in relatively greater abundances of <italic>Lactobacillus acidipiscis</italic>, <italic>Kosakonia cowanii</italic>, and <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic>. All the treatments (A-MDG, A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, S-MDG and S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG) with the addition of MDG contained high levels of <italic>Lactobacillus homohiochii</italic>. After 45 days of sorghum ensiling, the abundances of <italic>Kosakonia cowanii</italic> and <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> were greater in the S-CK control. With the addition of LAB, RP, and MDG, the harmful microorganisms <italic>Kosakonia cowanii</italic> and <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> were replaced by beneficial <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> species. In S-RP, nine groups of bacterial species were enriched, and <italic>Lactobacillus agilis</italic> had the highest LDA score. However, there were no significantly enriched bacteria in either the S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG or the S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP treatment. According to the data presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B, it is evident that following a 45-day period of alfalfa ensiling, the silage produced under the A-RP treatment presented an increase in <italic>Tatumella citrea</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> and <italic>Weissella paramesenteroides</italic> were more abundant in the A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP-treated silage, whereas <italic>Lactobacillus panis</italic> was more abundant in the A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP-treated silage. The addition of RP and MDG to both sorghum and alfalfa significantly increased the content of lactic acid bacteria.</p><p id="Par18">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The bacterial alpha diversity indices of sorghum and alfalfa</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Forage species (F)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Treatment (T)</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Items</th></tr><tr><th align="left">observed species number</th><th align="left">ACE index</th><th align="left">shannon index</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">S-Fresh</td><td align="left">73.00<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">113.14<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">3.29<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Sorghum silage</td><td align="left">S-CK</td><td align="left">92.00<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">105.49<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.65<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB</td><td align="left">33.67<sup>e</sup></td><td align="left">53.47<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">0.75<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-RP</td><td align="left">64.00<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">85.45<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">2.79<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-MDG</td><td align="left">51.33<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">68.81<sup>cd</sup></td><td align="left">1.80<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP</td><td align="left">49.00<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">65.48<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">1.72<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG</td><td align="left">58.00<sup>cd</sup></td><td align="left">84.00<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="left">1.96<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">A-Fresh</td><td align="left">81.33<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">131.99<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">1.31<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Alfalfa silage</td><td align="left">A-CK</td><td align="left">84.00<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">129.53<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.69<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB</td><td align="left">68.00<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">89.14<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">2.04<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-RP</td><td align="left">95.33<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">126.58<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">2.72<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-MDG</td><td align="left">38.00<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left">55.58<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.76<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP</td><td align="left">65.00<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">84.47<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">2.45<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG</td><td align="left">44.67d</td><td align="left">63.43<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.85<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><italic>P</italic> value</td><td align="left">T</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T&#x000d7;F</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between different treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; T, treatment; F, forage species; T &#x000d7; F, interaction of treatments and forage species</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Relative abundances of bacteria at the phylum level (<bold>A</bold>), genus level (<bold>B</bold>) and species level (<bold>C</bold>) in alfalfa and sorghum after 45 days of anaerobic storage. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e1809"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The identified differentially abundant bacteria (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and linear discriminant analysis [LDA] score&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3) among the silage groups. (<bold>A</bold>) Differentially abundant bacteria identified in sorghum after 45 days of anaerobic storage. (<bold>B</bold>) Differentially abundant bacteria identified in alfalfa after 45 days of anaerobic storage. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e1844"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Changes in the correlations of microbial communities with the ensiling characteristics of silage</title><p id="Par21">According to the PCoA results (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A), at 45 days of sorghum ensiling, the contributions of PC1 and PC2 were 44.9% and 18.04%, respectively. According to the PCoA results (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B), at 45 days of alfalfa ensiling, the contributions of PC1 and PC2 were 29.69% and 25.17%, respectively. For sorghum, the ADF, AA and LA levels were positively correlated with the S-LAB and S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP treatment levels; the pH and CP levels were positively correlated with the S-MDG treatment level; the WSC, NDF and AN levels were positively correlated with the S-CK treatment level; and the S-LAB and S-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP treatment levels were negatively correlated with both the pH and CP levels. The contents of ADF, NDF, and AN in alfalfa, as well as pH, were positively correlated with those in treatments A-CK. Moreover, the contents of WSC and AA were positively correlated with those in the A-LAB and A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP treatments. On the other hand, the contents of CP and LA were positively correlated with treatment A-MDG. Notably, the A-MDG and A-LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG treatments, on the other hand, presented negative correlations with pH and AN levels. Through Spearman correlation analysis, we found that the pH of the silage samples was positively correlated with the abundance of <italic>Kosakonia</italic>, <italic>Enterobacter</italic>, <italic>Enterococcus</italic>, and unidentified <italic>Enterobacteraceae</italic> bacteria, whereas a significant negative correlation was observed with the abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). The concentration of AN was positively correlated with the abundances of <italic>Kosakonia</italic>, <italic>Enterococcus</italic>, unidentified <italic>Rhizobiaceae</italic>, and <italic>Enterobacter</italic> but negatively correlated with the abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> was negatively correlated with pH and the AN concentration (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B).</p><p id="Par22">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) plot at the bacterial operational taxonomic unit (OTU) level in sorghum (<bold>A</bold>) and alfalfa (<bold>B</bold>) after 45 days of anaerobic storage. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e1938"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par23">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Spearman correlation heatmap between silage parameters and bacterial genera (<bold>A</bold>) and species (<bold>B</bold>) in sorghum and alfalfa after 45 days of anaerobic storage. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; CP, crude protein; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; WSC, water-soluble carbohydrate; LA, lactic acid; AA, acetic acid; AN, ammonia nitrogen; *, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01. Red squares represent positive correlations, whereas blue squares represent negative correlations</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig5_HTML" id="d33e1977"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Function prediction and genomic metabolic pathways of the bacterial community in the silages</title><p id="Par24">Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the functional prediction of bacterial communities in silage. The functions of the bacterial community in fresh sorghum were &#x0201c;chemoheterotrophy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aerobic_chemoheterotrophy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;phototrophy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;oxygenic_photoautotrophy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cyanobacteria&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;photoautotrophy&#x0201d;. The functions of the bacterial community in fresh alfalfa were &#x0201c;phototrophy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;oxygenic_photoautotrophy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cyanobacteria&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;photoautotrophy&#x0201d;. The main function of the bacterial community in silage was &#x0201c;chemoheterotrophy&#x0201d;, followed by &#x0201c;fermentation&#x0201d;. The functional prediction of bacterial communities enabled us to evaluate how these communities influence the alterations in the metabolic pathways involved in silage formation.</p><p id="Par25">
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Functional prediction for the bacterial community in fresh materials and silages. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig6_HTML" id="d33e2009"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par26">As shown in Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a, both the sorghum and alfalfa metabolic pathways presented significantly greater relative abundances of &#x0201c;metabolism&#x0201d; than did the other pathways. As shown in Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b, in the metabolic network of sorghum and alfalfa, the relative abundance of the two pathways &#x0201c;amino acid metabolism&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;carbohydrate metabolism&#x0201d; clearly occupied absolute dominance, which far exceeded all other metabolic pathways. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> shows &#x0201c;amino acid metabolism&#x0201d; (a) and &#x0201c;carbohydrate metabolism&#x0201d; (b) at the tertiary pathway level before and after sorghum silage. The levels of &#x0201c;histidine metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;tyrosine metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;phenylalanine metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;tryptophan metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;arginine metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;proline metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;lysine degradation,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;valine metabolism,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;glycine metabolism,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;alanine metabolism&#x0201d; were lower in the additive-treated group than in the CK and fresh samples; however, &#x0201c;cysteine metabolism&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;methionine metabolism&#x0201d; were increased. Moreover, the level of &#x0201c;amino acid-related enzymes&#x0201d; increased in all the treatment groups except S-RP. Ensiling and additives had no effect on the metabolism of &#x0201c;inositol phosphate&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;ascorbate and aldarate&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;C5 branched dibasic acid&#x0201d;. The addition of RP significantly promoted only the &#x0201c;interconversion of pentose and glucuronate&#x0201d;. The addition of RP and MDG promoted the metabolism of &#x0201c;fructose&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mannose&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;galactose&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;starch&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sucrose&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;amino sugars and nucleotide sugars&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;pentose phosphate pathway&#x0201d;.Ensiling inhibited &#x0201c;lysine degradation&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;alanine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;glycine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;alanine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;histidine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tyrosine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;phenylalanine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tryptophan metabolism&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;arginine and proline metabolism&#x0201d;, as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>(a). As demonstrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>(b), silage significantly increased the activity of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> in &#x0201c;carbohydrate metabolism&#x0201d;, which includes &#x0201c;fructose and mannose metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;starch and sucrose metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;galactose metabolism&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;pentose phosphate pathway&#x0201d; (PPP), strongly confirming the ability of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> to utilize multiple different carbon sources for its own proliferation.</p><p id="Par27">
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Bar graphs showing 16&#x000a0;S rRNA gene-predicted functional profiles of the level 1 metabolic pathways (<bold>a</bold>) and level 2 metabolic pathways (<bold>b</bold>) obtained with Tax4Fun for sorghum silage after 45 days of ensiling. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig7_HTML" id="d33e2071"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par28">
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Bar graphs showing 16&#x000a0;S rRNA gene-predicted functional profiles of the level 1 metabolic pathways (<bold>a</bold>) and level 2 metabolic pathways (<bold>b</bold>) obtained with Tax4Fun for alfalfa silages after 45 days of ensiling. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig8_HTML" id="d33e2103"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par29">
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Bar graphs showing 16&#x000a0;S rRNA gene-predicted functional profiles for amino acids metabolism (<bold>a</bold>) and carbohydrate metabolism (<bold>b</bold>) in the level 3 metabolic pathways obtained with Tax4Fun for sorghum silages after 45 days of ensiling. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig9_HTML" id="d33e2135"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par30">
<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Bar graphs showing 16&#x000a0;S rRNA gene-predicted functional profiles for amino acids metabolism (<bold>a</bold>) and carbohydrate metabolism (<bold>b</bold>) in the level 3 metabolic pathways obtained with Tax4Fun for alfalfa silages after 45 days of ensiling. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig10_HTML" id="d33e2167"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Chemical composition of alfalfa and sorghum</title><p id="Par31">The addition of MDG (28.47%) or RP (6.21%) increased the CP content of sorghum. The MDG and RP treatments resulted in lower NDF and ADF contents, and these two ingredients could reduce the fiber content of sorghum. One study has shown that when the WSC content is &#x0003e;&#x02009;5% DM, high-quality silage can be obtained [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The WSC content of sorghum (12.28%) was sufficient for <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> fermentation, whereas alfalfa had a low WSC content (4.62%) and required silage additives to improve its fermentation quality, which is in accordance with the research of Jiang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, adding RP can enhance the fermentation effect of alfalfa because the WSC content of RP is &#x0003e;&#x02009;5%. In conclusion, the addition of RP and MDG may improve the nutritional quality and fermentation quality of alfalfa and sorghum to some extent.</p><p id="Par32">(T&#x000d7;F) indicates that the effects of treatments and forage species on each index were not independent, but act together. The addition of lactic acid bacteria significantly increased the concentration of LA in silage, which in turn effectively lowered its pH and significantly reduced DM loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The low-pH (3.76) environment in the MDG inhibited protease activity, directly reducing protein hydrolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG did not improve CP in alfalfa because the CP content of alfalfa itself was high, and the CP content of MDG was not different. After comparing alfalfa silage under different treatments, we found that alfalfa silage under two treatments, RP and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, presented significantly lower CP contents than those in all the other treatments. The potential reason for this phenomenon may be the relatively high abundance of <italic>Enterobacter</italic> contained in RP, which leads to increased hydrolysis of CP. As the NDF and ADF contents continue to increase, the texture or acceptability of the feeds tends to decrease and become less palatable, which tends to result in a corresponding decrease in the amount of food consumed by the animals, while the digestion and absorption process of the feeds becomes slower as a result. When we examined alfalfa silage under the RP treatment alone, we found that its NDF content was significantly greater than that under all the other treatments, possibly because RP itself contains a relatively high proportion of NDF, with a specific value of 46.65% (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This significant difference was attributed to the fact that LAB effectively inhibited the multiplication of harmful microorganisms, leading to a reduction in the consumption of WSC by these harmful bacteria. These results suggest that LAB or other types of additives work effectively in alfalfa silage to inhibit the activity of harmful microorganisms that may consume WSC. Therefore, we can reasonably infer that appropriate additive use strategies are of great practical importance in protecting the WSC content in alfalfa silage from being overconsumed by harmful microorganisms, which is in accordance with the research of Tao et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The inclusion of MDG and RP enhanced the nutritional quality of alfalfa and sorghum to some degree, although their effects were driven by different mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Fermentation quality of alfalfa and sorghum silage</title><p id="Par33">Chen et al. (2020) added sea buckthorn pomace to alfalfa to improve its silage quality, and this experiment also showed similar results when RP and MDG were added [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. pH is one of the key indicators of silage quality, which is influenced by two main factors: the organic acids naturally produced during fermentation, which inhibit the activity of undesirable microorganisms by lowering the pH of the environment, and the buffering capacity of the silage material itself, which resists, to a certain extent, the lowering of the pH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The pH values measured for sorghum silage were generally lower than those for alfalfa silage. The reason for the lower pH of sorghum is its high WSC content, as well as having higher nutrients to control the bacterial population that produces LA and LA production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Specifically, alfalfa has a relatively low WSC content, which means that during fermentation, it has limited substrate availability for microorganisms such as lactic acid bacteria to utilize and produces relatively little organic acid, which has a less significant effect on pH reduction than sorghum does. On the other hand, alfalfa has a strong buffering capacity, which is due mainly to its rich chemical composition, such as cellulose, protein and other substances with acid&#x02012;base neutralizing effects, which are able to resist, to a certain extent, the pH-lowering effect of organic acids produced, resulting in a relatively high pH value in alfalfa silage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. This makes fermentation more difficult, resulting in low LA production. This phenomenon strongly suggests that the addition of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> to silage is extremely effective at increasing the number of lactic acid bacteria during fermentation, which further promotes the proliferation of lactic acid bacteria and the production of abundant LA. This biochemical process not only accelerated the silage fermentation process but also significantly improved the overall quality of fermentation, resulting in optimized silage quality, which is in accordance with the results of Xu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The content of LA treated with LAB is higher, which effectively lowered the pH of the silage by promoting the high production of LA, which in turn enhanced the fermentation quality and preservation stability of the silage. These findings indicate that LAB increased LA production in alfalfa and sorghum, which is in accordance with the findings of Feng et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Initially, silage is dominated by <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> homofermentation, but at later stages, fermentation is dominated by <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> heterofermentation, which leads to an increase in the AA content. The AA content of alfalfa was higher, which is most likely due to the relatively low DM content of alfalfa and its high buffering capacity, which together result in the further conversion of LA and PA already produced during silage to AA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The addition of LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP to alfalfa silage significantly increased its aerobic stability because of the remarkable ability of AA. Notably, the PA content of sorghum was higher, indicating the stronger antifungal resistance and superior nutrient retention potential of sorghum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], which was attributed to the presence of <italic>Clostridium</italic> in sorghum postsilage fermentation. We speculate that the addition of MDG to alfalfa may have resulted in the production of new chemicals, thereby blocking PA production. The presence of BA in silage can exacerbate DM loss, and unfortunately, trace amounts of BA were detected in some silage samples. During the early stages of silage fermentation, the pH in the system decreases more slowly, providing a longer period for the sugars to undergo incomplete fermentation, which in turn encourages the conversion of some of the sugars to BA or the conversion of LA under unfavorable conditions, which results in the production of more BA. An increase in the BA content is usually detrimental to maintaining the quality of silage. However, BA production can be significantly inhibited by the addition of RP to sorghum silage; this may have occurred because some active substances in the RP inhibited the growth of <italic>C. perfringens</italic>.</p><p id="Par34">The AN content is used to indicate the degree of breakdown of crude protein in silage, with lower levels representing less protein breakdown and better fermentation quality. During ensiling, the gradual accumulation of AN occurs as a result of microbial deamidation of amino acids, while the decrease in AN content is due to the formation of polyphenol&#x02012;protein complexes and the inhibitory effect of such complexes on plant or bacterial protein hydrolysis enzymes, which in turn results in a decrease in CP effectiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The AN content of alfalfa was significantly higher than that of sorghum because of the relatively high buffered capacity and CP content of leguminous forage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The content of AN in additive treatment is lower, suggesting that the additives reduce proteolysis and the action of plant enzymes or respiratory enzymes by lowering pH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Changes in the microbial communities of sorghum and alfalfa during silage</title><p id="Par35">The lowest number of strains was observed under the A-LAB treatment. This is because LAB effectively inhibit the growth and reproduction of harmful and stray bacteria through their metabolic activities, thus enabling lactic acid bacteria to rapidly dominate the silage process in a short period and become the dominant strain in the silage process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The results of the present study suggested that inoculation with <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> and sea buckthorn pomace reduced bacterial alpha diversity in alfalfa samples, and the same results were obtained in the present study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par36">Research has revealed that large amounts of Cyanobacteria are also present in other fresh grasses, such as barley, mulberry leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] and tea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], which may be due to the presence of soil inclusions in alfalfa. All the silage treatments resulted in a significant increase in Firmicutes because Firmicutes are suitable for growth under anaerobic and low pH conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. which indicates that fermentation was relatively successful, suggesting that MDG may favor the growth of Firmicutes during ensiling.</p><p id="Par37">The dominant genus in sorghum and alfalfa after ensiling was <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, which indicates better fermentation, which is in accordance with the findings of Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. In general, <italic>Clostridiales</italic> were considered harmful bacteria in silage fermentation because they cause high levels of protein degradation, DM loss and production of ammonia and BA and hinder pH reduction; moreover, feeding with silage enriched with <italic>Clostridiales</italic> may lead to reduced feed intake and increased incidence of ketosis in dairy cows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. <italic>Kosakonia</italic> has plant growth-promoting properties, and through its metabolic activity, it reduces the contents of AN and volatile chemicals in silage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Excessive levels of these substances in silage can adversely affect feed quality and animal health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Alfalfa and sorghum, when silage alone, contain <italic>Kosakonia</italic> and <italic>Clostridiales</italic>, which indicates that conventional ensiling of sorghum and alfalfa is not easy. <italic>Kosakonia</italic> was detected in all the alfalfa silages (6.74-25.96%), which is in accordance with the results of Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. This study suggested that <italic>Kosakonia</italic> was isolated mainly from legumes and soybean plants or from alfalfa rhizomes. Interestingly, sorghum and alfalfa silage treated with RP contained significant amounts of <italic>Enterobacter</italic>. The overgrowth and undesirable metabolic activities of <italic>Enterobacter</italic>, particularly their ability to compete with lactic acid bacteria for the production of AA and the conversion of nitrate to nitric oxide, can have detrimental effects on feed quality and animal health and may affect the content and form of AN in silage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. These findings suggest that RP may contain high levels of <italic>Enterobacter</italic> and that care should be taken to eliminate <italic>Enterobacter</italic> when RP is used as an additive at a later stage. In our study, compared with the RP treatment, the LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP treatment suppressed <italic>Enterobacter</italic> levels in the alfalfa and sorghum silages. These findings suggest that RP can be coapplied with LAB when it is used at later stages as an additive. The dominant genus in sorghum and alfalfa silage from the other treatments was <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, suggesting that the addition of LAB, MDG or each should inhibit the growth of <italic>Kosakonia</italic> and <italic>Clostridiales</italic>, further rapidly promoting the dominance of beneficial bacteria (<italic>Lactobacillus</italic>) and thus improving the fermentation quality of sorghum and alfalfa. Our results suggest that MDG and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP can be used as silage additives.</p><p id="Par38"><italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> produces LA to rapidly establish an acidic environment, promoting rapid fermentation and inhibiting the increase of different unsafe bacteria, for this reason, stopping the degradation of proteins and sugars in crops [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. <italic>Lactobacillus homohiochii</italic> is more common in sauce-flavor baijiu and can grow in media supplemented with up to 15% ethanol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>, a beneficial bacterial species, can be effectively enhanced by the combined addition of LAB and RP during anaerobic fermentation. This combination can reduce the abundance of other potentially competing bacteria, thus creating a more favorable environment for the anaerobic fermentation process, which strongly promotes and ensures silage success. <italic>Lactobacillus buchneri</italic> increased in S-MDG, so it was hypothesized that the addition of MDG to pastoral grass forage might increase its aerobic stability. <italic>Lactobacillus panis</italic> is an anaerobic, specialized heterogeneous lactic acid-fermenting lactic acid bacterium belonging to type III <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, whose fermentation end products are LA, AA, ethanol and CO<sub>2</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. <italic>L. panis</italic> is the main producer of LA in the microbiota during Maotai brewing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. This explains the greater relative abundance of <italic>L. panis</italic> in this experiment when LAB was applied in combination with MDG. Interestingly, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>, which was added during the experiment, was not detected after ensiling, probably because it is not acid tolerant and was replaced by other acid-tolerant microorganisms.</p><p id="Par39">To reveal and elucidate in greater depth the differences in microbial community composition experienced by the two crops, alfalfa and sorghum, during silage fermentation under different treatment conditions, we specifically used LEfSe, a state-of-the-art bioinformatics tool, to carry out systematic analyses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). <italic>Lactobacillus buchneri</italic> and <italic>Bacillus coagulans</italic> were more abundant in the S-MDG-treated silage. This was due to the large amount of <italic>Bacillus</italic> and a certain percentage of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> in Moutai Daqu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. <italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> was more abundant in the S-LAB- and A-LAB-treated groups, which is in accordance with the findings of Guo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. <italic>L. rhamnosus</italic> enhances the quality of fermented foods by producing bacteriocins that inhibit harmful microorganisms (e.g., mold and enterobacteria) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Changes in the correlations of microbial communities with the ensiling characteristics of silage</title><p id="Par40">Figure&#x000a0; <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>(A-B) shows the results of principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) performed at the level of microbial operational taxonomic units (OTUs) in sorghum and alfalfa silage to further assess differences in the distribution of bacterial communities across treatments. The findings revealed distinct variations in the bacterial populations among the groups treated with various additives. Two principal components of sorghum together explained more than 60% of the variation in the distribution of the bacterial community, with PC1 dominating, suggesting the presence of certain specific bacterial taxa that play a decisive role in the composition and changes in the overall bacterial community during sorghum silage fermentation. The contributions of these two principal components were relatively balanced in the alfalfa silage. The effects of different additive treatments on alfalfa silage bacterial communities were more dispersed than those on sorghum silage bacterial communities.</p><p id="Par41">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> (A-B) shows the results of the canonical correlation analysis (CCA) used to investigate the associations between the six treatment groups (CK, MDG, RP, LAB, LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP) and eight environmental parameters (NDF, ADF, CP, WSC, LA, AA, and AN contents and pH) for sorghum and alfalfa. In the prolonged anaerobic preservation environment, all alfalfa plants subjected to different treatments produced high amounts of LAB, a biological process that promotes the production of LA and AA. This series of changes is a normal and expected trend during silage fermentation, reflecting the successful establishment of fermentation conditions and the efficient accumulation of fermentation products. In addition, the CCA results indicated that the addition of RP to both legumes and grasses increased the WSC content, and the combination of <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> and RP may have played an important role in increasing LA and AA levels as well as in maintaining CP levels; these consequences are consistent with those of Yang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">
<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Canonical correlation analysis (CCA) at the bacterial operational taxonomic unit (OTU) level in sorghum (<bold>A</bold>) and alfalfa (<bold>B</bold>) after 45 days of anaerobic storage. CK, without additives; RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace; LAB, <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP, <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> pomace combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG, Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain combined with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>; CP, crude protein; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; WSC, water-soluble carbohydrate; LA, lactic acid; AA, acetic acid; AN, ammonia nitrogen</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2025_6722_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e2491"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par43"><italic>Enterococcus</italic>, unidentified <italic>Rhizobiaceae</italic> and <italic>Enterobacter</italic> species are all gram-negative bacteria, a common group of bacteria, leading to protein hydrolysis and increased AN concentrations due to the high buffering capacity and low WSC content of alfalfa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. However, the negative correlation between <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and AN levels was attributed to the presence of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, resulting in increased environmental acidity, which prevents the growth of AN-producing bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Ogunade et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] concluded that microbial activity and plant enzymes work together to produce AN and that the rapid acidification of the overall environment by the plant <italic>L. plantarum</italic> reduces microbial activity, leading to lower AN levels in silage. <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> begins lactic acid fermentation during the early phase of ensiling but cannot thrive in acidic conditions because it is sensitive to relatively low pH levels. In contrast, the growth and viability of <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> decline quickly as the pH decreases.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Function prediction and genomic metabolic pathways of the bacterial community in the silages</title><p id="Par44">The carbon sequestration of most bacteria, which uses carbon and energy to oxidize organic components, leads to an increase in &#x0201c;chemoheterotrophy&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;fermentation&#x0201d;. Li et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] reported that &#x0201c;nitrogen respiration&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nitrite ammonification&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;nitrite respiration&#x0201d; can lead to sustained AN production. Therefore, &#x0201c;nitrite respiration&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;nitrogen respiration&#x0201d; increased in both materials after ensiling in this experiment, explaining the continued production of AN after ensiling.</p><p id="Par45">The relative abundances of &#x0201c;metabolism&#x0201d; are higher, which suggests that the core regulatory mechanism of the silage fermentation process lies in the activity of bacteria, which successfully convert fermentable substrates into a wide range of metabolites via a series of different metabolic pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].The metabolic pathways that determine fermentation quality at the secondary pathway level are mainly the metabolic pathways for &#x0201c;amino acids&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;carbohydrates&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;energy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nucleotides&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;vitamins and cofactors&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Amino acids, as essential nutrients in living organisms, play crucial roles in promoting plant primary metabolism and protein synthesis. Notably, most amino acid metabolic pathways were inhibited by the silage process, most likely due to the low levels of AN in sorghum silage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Furthermore, the silage process also inhibits the metabolism of &#x0201c;inositol phosphate&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;propanoate&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;glyoxylate and dicarboxylate&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;citrate cycle&#x0201d; (TCA cycle). This inhibitory effect is closely related to the anoxic environment, as the normal progression of the TCA cycle is dependent on aerobic conditions. In the absence of oxygen, those removed hydrogen ions cannot successfully enter the respiratory chain for a thorough oxidation reaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In this study, the relative abundance of the &#x0201c;TCA cycle&#x0201d; was lower in the LAB and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG groups of sorghum and alfalfa than in the treatment without additives, suggesting that LA production was greater in these two groups. In conclusion, LAB treatment and LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG treatment improved forage silage quality by reducing the abundance of the &#x0201c;TCA cycle&#x0201d; and inhibiting &#x0201c;tyrosine metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;tryptophan metabolism&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;alanine metabolism&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;lysine degradation&#x0201d;.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par46">Adding MDG and RP to alfalfa silage or sorghum silage could improve their nutritional quality and fermentation quality to varying degrees. Comprehensive analyses revealed that the addition of LAB, MDG and a combination of the two could inhibit the growth of <italic>Kosakonia</italic> and <italic>Clostridiales</italic> and rapidly promote the dominance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, thus improving the fermentation quality of sorghum and alfalfa. These findings indicate that MDG can be applied as an additive to other forage silages. If RP is developed as a silage additive, care needs to be taken to control <italic>Enterobacter</italic> production, and coapplication with <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> is recommended. After ensiling, the metabolism of &#x0201c;nucleotides&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;carbohydrates&#x0201d; is enhanced, and the metabolism of &#x0201c;amino acids&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;energy&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;cofactors and vitamins&#x0201d; decreases. We recommend that farmers apply 25% FW MDG to their production. This study revealed that MDG, LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;MDG or LAB&#x02009;+&#x02009;RP are good silage additives that improve the quality of silage, thereby increasing the utilization rate of waste and reducing environmental pollution.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>The original online version of this article was revised: Fig. 1c was unintentionally cut off.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Yuanyuan Zhao and Dianpeng Liu contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>6/24/2025</p><p id="Par501">The original online version of this article was revised: Fig. 1c was unintentionally cut off.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>6/25/2025</p><p>A Correction to this paper has been published: 10.1186/s12870-025-06846-7</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Yuanyuan Zhao: Data curation, Formal analysis, Visualization, Writing&#x02013; original draft. Dianpeng Liu: Investigation. Yulian Chen: Investigation. Yao Lei: Investigation, Resources. Maoya Li: Investigation, Resources. Jiachuhan Wang: Investigation, Resources. Xiangjiang He: Investigation, Resources. Yu Yang: Investigation, Resources. Xinyi Zhang: Investigation, Resources. Shengnan Liu: Investigation. Xiaoqing Zhang: Investigation, Methodology. Qiming Cheng: Conceptualization, methodology, validation, writing&#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, supervision, funding acquisition. Chao Chen: Project administration, Funding acquisition.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This project was supported by the Youth Science Fund Projects of the National Natural Science Foundation (32401494), National Key Research and Development Subject (2021YFD1300302), Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Project (Qiankehe Chengguo [2022]005), Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Project (Qiankehe Jichu-ZK [2023]120), Guizhou University Cultivation Project (Guida Peiyu [2020]9), Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Projects (QKHPTRC-GCC[2023]012) and Guizhou Provincial Science and Technology Project (QKHPTRC-CXTD [2022]011).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated during the current study are available in the [NCBI] repository, [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>, PRJNA1234378].</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par47">This research project was conducted in strict accordance with ethical guidelines. We respected and protected the rights and privacy of the participants and ensured the confidentiality of their personal information.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par48">We, the undersigned, confirm that we have read and approved the manuscript entitled " Regulation of silage fermentation in alfalfa and sorghum by different wastes: Silage characteristics, bacterial community composition and their predicted functional characteristics&#x0201d; and agree to its submission to BMC plant biology. We also confirm that this manuscript has not been published elsewhere and is not under consideration by another journal.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par49">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resource utilization of agricultural solid waste</article-title><source>J Integr Agric</source><year>2021</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2095-3119(21)63648-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Li Z. Resource utilization of agricultural solid waste. J Integr Agric. 2021;20:1119&#x02013;20.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Muralidharan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruvenkadan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of cotton gin trash supplementation as unconventional feedstuff on feed intake and production characteristics of mecheri sheep of India</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>10500</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su151310500</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Nagarajan SB, Ramakrishnan S, Muralidharan J, Vasan P, Sivakumar K, Thiruvenkadan AK. Effect of cotton gin trash supplementation as unconventional feedstuff on feed intake and production characteristics of mecheri sheep of India. Sustainability. 2023;15:10500.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical and structural properties of dietary fiber from Rosa roxburghii pomace by steam explosion</article-title><source>J Food Sci Technol</source><year>2021</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2381</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-021-05254-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35602434</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Zhai X, Ao H, Liu W, Zheng J, Li X, Ren D. Physicochemical and structural properties of dietary fiber from Rosa roxburghii pomace by steam explosion. J Food Sci Technol. 2021;59:2381&#x02013;91.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35602434</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of polyphenols from Rosa roxburghii Tratt pomace and evaluation of in vitro and in vivo antioxidant activity</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2022</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>131922</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.131922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34979396</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Huang D, Li C, Chen Q, Xie X, Fu X, Chen C, Huang Q, Huang Z, Dong H. Identification of polyphenols from Rosa roxburghii Tratt pomace and evaluation of in vitro and in vivo antioxidant activity. Food Chem. 2022;377:131922.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34979396</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical profile, bioactivity and prebiotic potential of bound polyphenols released from Rosa roxburghii fruit pomace dietary fiber during in vitro digestion and fermentation</article-title><source>Food Function</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>8880</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D2FO00823H</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35924964</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Su J, Fu X, Huang Q, Liu G, Li C. Phytochemical profile, bioactivity and prebiotic potential of bound polyphenols released from Rosa roxburghii fruit pomace dietary fiber during in vitro digestion and fermentation. Food Function. 2022;13:8880&#x02013;91.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35924964</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue as an alternative feed for improving growth, blood metabolites, rumen fermentation, and slaughter performance in Hu sheep</article-title><source>Front Vet Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1397051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1397051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38962702</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Li H, Song X, Wu W, Zhou C. <italic>Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue as an alternative feed for improving growth, blood metabolites, rumen fermentation, and slaughter performance in Hu sheep. Front Vet Sci. 2024;11:1397051.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38962702</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the silage quality of alfalfa ensiled with the residues of astragalus and Hawthorn</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2020</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>122249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.122249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31761631</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Ni KK, Wang XK, Lu Y, Guo LN, Li XM, Yang FY. Exploring the silage quality of alfalfa ensiled with the residues of astragalus and Hawthorn. Bioresour Technol. 2020;297:122249.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31761631</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial mechanisms of using feruloyl esterase-producing <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> A1 and grape pomace to improve fermentation quality and mitigate ruminal methane emission of ensiled alfalfa for cleaner animal production</article-title><source>J Environ Manage</source><year>2022</year><volume>308</volume><fpage>114637</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2022.114637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35124318</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Zhang X, Ke WC, Ding ZT, Xu DM, Wang MS, Chen MY, Guo XS. Microbial mechanisms of using feruloyl esterase-producing <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> A1 and grape pomace to improve fermentation quality and mitigate ruminal methane emission of ensiled alfalfa for cleaner animal production. J Environ Manage. 2022;308:114637.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35124318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of Fermented-Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain on growth performance, meat quality, and blood metabolites of finishing cattle</article-title><source>Front Vet Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>874453</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.874453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35615251</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Cheng Q, Xu D, Chen Y, Zhu M, Fan X, Li M, Tang X, Liao C, Li P, Chen C. Influence of Fermented-Moutai distillers&#x02019; grain on growth performance, meat quality, and blood metabolites of finishing cattle. Front Vet Sci. 2022;9:874453.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35615251</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ai-Lati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Baijiu Vinasse as a new source of bioactive peptides with antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2021</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>128159</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.128159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33152898</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Peng L, Kong X, Wang Z, Ai-Lati A, Ji Z, Mao J. Baijiu Vinasse as a new source of bioactive peptides with antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity. Food Chem. 2021;339:128159.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33152898</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical characterization and pyrolysis kinetic analysis of Moutai-flavored dried distiller&#x02019;s grains towards its thermochemical conversion for potential applications</article-title><source>J Anal Appl Pyrol</source><year>2021</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>105046</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaap.2021.105046</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Zhang Y, Huang G, Yu S, Gu X, Cai J, Zhang X. Physicochemical characterization and pyrolysis kinetic analysis of Moutai-flavored dried distiller&#x02019;s grains towards its thermochemical conversion for potential applications. J Anal Appl Pyrol. 2021;155:105046.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalscheur</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ruminal degradation and intestinal digestibility of dried or wet distillers grains with increasing concentrations of condensed distillers solubles</article-title><source>J Anim Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>3013</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2009-1894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19502508</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Cao Z, Anderson JL, Kalscheur KF. Ruminal degradation and intestinal digestibility of dried or wet distillers grains with increasing concentrations of condensed distillers solubles. J Anim Sci. 2009;87:3013&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19502508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Desta</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of formic acid and potassium diformate on the fermentation quality, chemical composition and aerobic stability of alfalfa silage</article-title><source>Grass Forage Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gfs.12296</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Yuan X, Wen A, Dong Z, Desta ST, Shao T. Effects of formic acid and potassium diformate on the fermentation quality, chemical composition and aerobic stability of alfalfa silage. Grass Forage Sci. 2017;72:833&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besharati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Aya&#x0015f;an</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving ruminant fermentation characteristics with addition of Apple pulp and essential oil to silage</article-title><source>Mindanao J Sci Technol</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.61310/mndjstea.0961.22</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Besharati M, Palangi V, Aya&#x0015f;an T, Abachi S. Improving ruminant fermentation characteristics with addition of Apple pulp and essential oil to silage. Mindanao J Sci Technol. 2022;20:206&#x02013;26.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Leandro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of lactic acid bacteria with bacteriocinogenic potential on the fermentation profile and chemical composition of alfalfa silage in tropical conditions</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1895</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2015-9792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26774723</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Silva V, Pereira O, Leandro E, Da Silva T, Ribeiro K, Mantovani H, Santos S. Effects of lactic acid bacteria with bacteriocinogenic potential on the fermentation profile and chemical composition of alfalfa silage in tropical conditions. J Dairy Sci. 2016;99:1895&#x02013;902.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26774723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of wet sea Buckthorn pomace utilized as an additive on silage fermentation profile and bacterial community composition of alfalfa</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2020</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>123773</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2020.123773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32645569</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Chen L, Qu H, Bai S, Yan L, You M, Gou W, Li P, Gao F. Effect of wet sea Buckthorn pomace utilized as an additive on silage fermentation profile and bacterial community composition of alfalfa. Bioresour Technol. 2020;314:123773.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32645569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besharati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>AZM</given-names></name><name><surname>De Palo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggiolino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substitution of Raw Lucerne with Raw citrus lemon by-product in silage: <italic>In vitro</italic> apparent digestibility and gas production</article-title><source>Front Veterinary Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1006581</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1006581</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Besharati M, Palangi V, Salem AZM, De Palo P, Lorenzo JM, Maggiolino A. Substitution of Raw Lucerne with Raw citrus lemon by-product in silage: <italic>In vitro</italic> apparent digestibility and gas production. Front Veterinary Sci. 2022;9:1006581.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fermentation weight loss, fermentation quality, and bacterial community of ensiling of sweet sorghum with lactic acid bacteria at different silo densities</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1013913</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1013913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36452921</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Xu H, Wu N, Na N, Sun L, Zhao Y, Ding H, Fang Y, Wang T, Xue Y, Zhong J. Fermentation weight loss, fermentation quality, and bacterial community of ensiling of sweet sorghum with lactic acid bacteria at different silo densities. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:1013913.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36452921</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of wet brewers grains on fermentation quality and in vitro ruminal digestibility of mixed silage prepared with corn stalk, sweet potato Peel and dried Apple pomace in Southeast China</article-title><source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source><year>2022</year><volume>107</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13716</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Dai T, Dong D, Wang J, Yin X, Zong C, Jia Y, Shao T. Effects of wet brewers grains on fermentation quality and in vitro ruminal digestibility of mixed silage prepared with corn stalk, sweet potato Peel and dried Apple pomace in Southeast China. J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr. 2022;107(2):340&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broderick</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated simultaneous determination of ammonia and total amino acids in ruminal fluid and in vitro media</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>1980</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(80)82888-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7372898</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Broderick GA, Kang JH. Automated simultaneous determination of ammonia and total amino acids in ruminal fluid and in vitro media. J Dairy Sci. 1980;63:64&#x02013;75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7372898</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myrna</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisperos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buslig</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous detection of dehydroascorbic, ascorbic, and some organic acids in fruits and vegetables by HPLC</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Myrna O, Nisperos C, Bela S, Buslig PE, Shaw. Simultaneous detection of dehydroascorbic, ascorbic, and some organic acids in fruits and vegetables by HPLC. J Agric Food Chem. 2002;40(7):1127&#x02013;30.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AOAC. 2016. Association of Official Analytical Chemists: Official Methods of Analysis.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>1991</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>3583</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Van Soest PJ, Robertson JB, Lewis BA. Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition. J Dairy Sci. 1991;74:3583&#x02013;97.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Muck</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein degradation and fermentation characteristics of red clover and alfalfa silage harvested with varying levels of total nonstructural carbohydrates</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1873</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1999.3961873x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Owens V, Albrecht KA, Muck RE, Duke SH. Protein degradation and fermentation characteristics of red clover and alfalfa silage harvested with varying levels of total nonstructural carbohydrates. Crop Sci. 1999;39:1873&#x02013;80.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA extraction of Birch leaves by improved CTAB method and optimization of its ISSR system</article-title><source>J Forestry Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11676-006-0068-3</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Pan H, Yang C, Wei Z, Jiang J. DNA extraction of Birch leaves by improved CTAB method and optimization of its ISSR system. J Forestry Res. 2006;17(4):298&#x02013;300.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial community and fermentation characteristic of Italian ryegrass silage prepared with corn Stover and lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2019</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.01.107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30721817</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Yan YH, Li XM, Guan H, Huang LK, Ma X, Peng Y, Li Z, Nie G, Zhou JQ, Yang WY, Cai Y, Zhang X. Microbial community and fermentation characteristic of Italian ryegrass silage prepared with corn Stover and lactic acid bacteria. Bioresour Technol. 2019;279:166&#x02013;73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30721817</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naturally occurring lactic acid bacteria isolated from tomato pomace silage</article-title><source>Asian-Australasian J Anim Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2013.13670</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Wu JJ, Du RP, Gao M, Sui YQ, Xiu L, Wang X. Naturally occurring lactic acid bacteria isolated from tomato pomace silage. Asian-Australasian J Anim Sci. 2014;27(5):648&#x02013;57.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of compound additives on nutritional composition, fermentation quality, and bacterial community of High-Moisture alfalfa silage</article-title><source>Fermentation</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>453</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/fermentation9050453</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Jiang H, Wang H, Bao B, Qu H, Wang J, Sun L, Liu B, Gao F. Effect of compound additives on nutritional composition, fermentation quality, and bacterial community of High-Moisture alfalfa silage. Fermentation. 2023;9:453.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kaewpila C, Gunun P, Kesorn P, Subepang S, Thip-uten S, Cai YM, Pholsen S, Cherdthong A, Khota W. 2021. Improving ensiling characteristics by adding lactic acid bacteria modifies in vitro digestibility and methane production of forage-sorghum mixture silage. Scientific Reports. 11, 1968.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x00131;lmaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baytok</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x00131;lmaz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of fumaric and maleic acids on the fermentation, nutrient composition, proteolysis and in vitro ruminal gas of corn silage</article-title><source>Grassl Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>68</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/grs.12377</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Kara K, Pirci G, Y&#x00131;lmaz S, Baytok E, Y&#x00131;lmaz K. Effects of fumaric and maleic acids on the fermentation, nutrient composition, proteolysis and in vitro ruminal gas of corn silage. Grassl Sci. 2022;68(4):362&#x02013;71.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of viscosity on process stability and microbial community composition during anaerobic mesophilic digestion of Maotai-flavored distiller&#x02019;s grains</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2019</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>122460</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.122460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784250</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Ao T, Ran Y, Chen Y, Li R, Luo Y, Liu X, Li D. Effect of viscosity on process stability and microbial community composition during anaerobic mesophilic digestion of Maotai-flavored distiller&#x02019;s grains. Bioresour Technol. 2019;297:122460.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of citric acid residue and lactic acid bacteria on fermentation quality and aerobic stability of alfalfa silage</article-title><source>Italian J Anim Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1828051X.2020.1789511</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Tao X, Chen S, Zhao J, Wang S, Dong Z, Li J, Sun F, Shao T. Effects of citric acid residue and lactic acid bacteria on fermentation quality and aerobic stability of alfalfa silage. Italian J Anim Sci. 2020;19:744&#x02013;52.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient matter, fatty acids, in vitro gas production and digestion of herbage and silage quality of yellow sweet clover (Melilo-tus officinalis L.) at different phenological stages</article-title><source>J Anim Feed Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22358/jafs/136401/2021</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Kara K. Nutrient matter, fatty acids, in vitro gas production and digestion of herbage and silage quality of yellow sweet clover (Melilo-tus officinalis L.) at different phenological stages. J Anim Feed Sci. 2021;30(2):128&#x02013;40.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gallic acid influencing fermentation quality, nitrogen distribution and bacterial community of high-moisture mulberry leaves and Stylo silage</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2020</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>122255</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.122255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31639626</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">He LW, Chen N, Lv HJ, Wang C, Zhou W, Chen XY, Zhang Q. Gallic acid influencing fermentation quality, nitrogen distribution and bacterial community of high-moisture mulberry leaves and Stylo silage. Bioresour Technol. 2020;295:122255.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31639626</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besharati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nekoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayasan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Lactobacillus Buchneri</italic> inoculation and fresh Whey addition on alfalfa silage quality and fermentation. Kahramanmara&#x0015f; S&#x000fc;t&#x000e7;&#x000fc; &#x00130;mam &#x000dc;niversitesi Tar&#x00131;m ve Do&#x0011f;a</article-title><source>Dergisi</source><year>2021</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Besharati M, Palangi V, Nekoo M, Ayasan T. Effects of <italic>Lactobacillus Buchneri</italic> inoculation and fresh Whey addition on alfalfa silage quality and fermentation. Kahramanmara&#x0015f; S&#x000fc;t&#x000e7;&#x000fc; &#x00130;mam &#x000dc;niversitesi Tar&#x00131;m ve Do&#x0011f;a. Dergisi. 2021;24:671&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro methane production and quality of corn silage treated with maleic acid</article-title><source>Italian J Anim Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/ijas.2015.3994</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Kara K. In vitro methane production and quality of corn silage treated with maleic acid. Italian J Anim Sci. 2015;14:718&#x02013;22.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of lactic acid bacteria inoculants on the nutrient composition, fermentation quality, and microbial diversity of whole-plant soybean-corn mixed silage</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1347293</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1347293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38686105</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Xu J, Ma J, Sa R, Sui H, Wang X, Li Q, Zhu X, Wu B, Hu Z, Niu H. Effects of lactic acid bacteria inoculants on the nutrient composition, fermentation quality, and microbial diversity of whole-plant soybean-corn mixed silage. Front Microbiol. 2024;15:1347293.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38686105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Degen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addition of organic acids and <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> to the leguminous forage <italic>Chamaecrista rotundifolia</italic> improved the quality and decreased harmful Bacteria of the silage</article-title><source>Animals: Open Access J MDPI</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12172260</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Feng Q, Shi W, Chen S, Degen AA, Qi Y, Yang F, Zhou J. Addition of organic acids and <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> to the leguminous forage <italic>Chamaecrista rotundifolia</italic> improved the quality and decreased harmful Bacteria of the silage. Animals: Open Access J MDPI. 2022;12:2260.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pahlow G, Muck RE, Driehuis F, Elferink O, Spoelstra SJWH. S. F., 2003. Microbiology of ensiling.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwan</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva &#x000c1;vila</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of amylases and storage length on losses, nutritional value, fermentation, and microbiology of silages of corn and sorghum kernels</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source><year>2022</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>115227</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2022.115227</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Fernandes T, da Silva KT, Carvalho BF, Schwan RF, Pereira RA, Pereira MN, da Silva &#x000c1;vila CL. Effect of amylases and storage length on losses, nutritional value, fermentation, and microbiology of silages of corn and sorghum kernels. Anim Feed Sci Technol. 2022;285:115227.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Albrecht KA, Muck REJCS. 1991. Proteolysis in Ensiled Forage Legumes That Vary in Tannin Concentration. 31, 464&#x02013;469.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besharati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Niazifar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of dietary lemon seed essential oil to enhance alfalfa silage chemical composition and in vitro degradability</article-title><source>Semina Cienc Agrar</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5433/1679-0359.2021v42n2p891</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Besharati M, Palangi V, Niazifar M, Nemati Z. Optimization of dietary lemon seed essential oil to enhance alfalfa silage chemical composition and in vitro degradability. Semina Cienc Agrar. 2021;42:891&#x02013;906.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Lactiplantibacillus paraplantarum during anaerobic storage of ear-removed corn on biogas production</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2022</year><volume>364</volume><fpage>128061</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2022.128061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36195220</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Sun H, Liao C, Lu G, Zheng Y, Cheng Q, Xie Y, Wang C, Chen C, Li P. Role of Lactiplantibacillus paraplantarum during anaerobic storage of ear-removed corn on biogas production. Bioresour Technol. 2022;364:128061.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36195220</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bacterial community and fermentation quality of mulberry (<italic>Morus alba</italic>) leaf silage with or without <italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic> and sucrose</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2019</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>122059</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.122059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31476563</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Wang Y, Chen XY, Wang C, He LW, Zhou W, Yang FY, Zhang Q. The bacterial community and fermentation quality of mulberry (<italic>Morus alba</italic>) leaf silage with or without <italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic> and sucrose. Bioresour Technol. 2019;293:122059.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31476563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Awasthi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the bacterial community and fermentation characteristics during silage fermentation of abandoned fresh tea leaves</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2021</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>131234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.131234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34153916</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Lin HY, Lin SQ, Awasthi MK, Wang YF, Xu P. Exploring the bacterial community and fermentation characteristics during silage fermentation of abandoned fresh tea leaves. Chemosphere. 2021;283:131234.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34153916</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Da</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bacterial community and metabolome dynamics and their interactions modulate fermentation process of whole crop corn silage prepared with or without inoculants</article-title><source>Microb Biotechnol</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32627363</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Xu DM, Wang N, Rinne M, Ke WC, Weinberg ZG, Da M, Bai J, Zhang YX, Li FH, Guo XS. The bacterial community and metabolome dynamics and their interactions modulate fermentation process of whole crop corn silage prepared with or without inoculants. Microb Biotechnol. 2021;14:561&#x02013;76.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32627363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sena</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000fc;leyman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of plantago species herbage and silage on in vitro ruminal fermentation and Microbiome</article-title><source>Italian J Anim Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1569</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1828051X.2022.2139201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Kanber K, Sena Y, S&#x000fc;leyman E, Abdullah &#x000d6; &#x000d6;. Effects of plantago species herbage and silage on in vitro ruminal fermentation and Microbiome. Italian J Anim Sci. 2022;21(1):1569&#x02013;83.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silage microbiology and its control through additives</article-title><source>Rev Bras Zootec</source><year>2010</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1516-35982010001300021</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Muck R. Silage microbiology and its control through additives. Rev Bras Zootec. 2010;39:183&#x02013;91.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatemeh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Etesami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Najafi</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alishahi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mining alfalfa (<italic>Medicago sativa</italic>, L.) nodules for salinity tolerant non-rhizobial bacteria to improve growth of alfalfa under salinity stress</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf</source><year>2018</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.06.092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29990724</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Fatemeh N, Etesami H, Najafi ZH, Sima K, Hosseini NA, S. G., and, Alishahi F. Mining alfalfa (<italic>Medicago sativa</italic>, L.) nodules for salinity tolerant non-rhizobial bacteria to improve growth of alfalfa under salinity stress. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf. 2018;162:129&#x02013;38.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29990724</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altering microbial communities: a possible way of lactic acid bacteria inoculants changing smell of silage</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Tech</source><year>2021</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>114998</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2021.114998</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Zhang Q, Guo X, Zheng M, Chen D, Chen X. Altering microbial communities: a possible way of lactic acid bacteria inoculants changing smell of silage. Anim Feed Sci Tech. 2021;279:114998.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beneficial effects of Tannic acid on the quality of bacterial communities present in High-Moisture mulberry leaf and Stylo silage</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>586412</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.586412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33224123</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Wang C, Pian R, Chen X, Lv H, Zhou W, Zhang Q. Beneficial effects of Tannic acid on the quality of bacterial communities present in High-Moisture mulberry leaf and Stylo silage. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:586412.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33224123</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duni&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sindou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaucheyras Durand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevallier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000e9;venot Sergentet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silage processing and strategies to prevent persistence of undesirable microorganisms</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2013.04.006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Duni&#x000e8;re L, Sindou J, Chaucheyras Durand F, Chevallier I, Th&#x000e9;venot Sergentet D. Silage processing and strategies to prevent persistence of undesirable microorganisms. Anim Feed Sci Technol. 2013;182:1&#x02013;15.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Lactobacillus homohiochii</italic> is a later heterotypic synonym of <italic>Lactobacillus fructivorans</italic></article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol MicroBiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1720</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.003380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920364</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Zhao W, Gu CT. <italic>Lactobacillus homohiochii</italic> is a later heterotypic synonym of <italic>Lactobacillus fructivorans</italic>. Int J Syst Evol MicroBiol. 2019;69:1720&#x02013;3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920364</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Korber</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contributions of citrate in redox potential maintenance and ATP production: metabolic pathways and their regulation in <italic>Lactobacillus panis</italic> PM1</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>8693</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-013-5108-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23912115</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Kang TS, Korber DR, Tanaka T. Contributions of citrate in redox potential maintenance and ATP production: metabolic pathways and their regulation in <italic>Lactobacillus panis</italic> PM1. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2013;97:8693&#x02013;703.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23912115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of microorganisms producing lactic acid during solid-state fermentation of Maotai flavour liquor</article-title><source>J Inst Brew</source><year>2019</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jib.537</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Yang F, Chen L, Liu Y, Li J, Wang L, Chen J. Identification of microorganisms producing lactic acid during solid-state fermentation of Maotai flavour liquor. J Inst Brew. 2019;125:171&#x02013;7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guo L, Wang X, Lin Y, Yang X, Ni K, Yang F. Microorganisms that are critical for the fermentation quality of paper mulberry silage. Food and Energy Security; 2021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of bacteriocin produced by <italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> zrx01</article-title><source>Food Bioscience</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>100754</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fbio.2020.100754</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Zhao R, Lu Y, Ran J, Li G, Lei S, Zhu Y, Xu B. Purification and characterization of bacteriocin produced by <italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> zrx01. Food Bioscience. 2020;38:100754.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of microbial community and fermentation quality during ensiling of sterile and nonsterile alfalfa with or without <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> inoculant</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2019</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2018.12.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594838</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Yang LL, Yuan XJ, Li JF, Dong ZH, Shao T. Dynamics of microbial community and fermentation quality during ensiling of sterile and nonsterile alfalfa with or without <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> inoculant. Bioresour Technol. 2019;275:280&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594838</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ce</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of lactic acid bacteria inoculants on alfalfa (<italic>Medicago sativa</italic> L.) silage quality: assessment of degradation (<italic>in situ</italic>) and gas production (<italic>in vitro</italic>)</article-title><source>J Integr Agric</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2834</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2095-3119(16)61424-7</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Ce L, Lai YJ, Lu XN, Guo PT, Luo HL. Effect of lactic acid bacteria inoculants on alfalfa (<italic>Medicago sativa</italic> L.) silage quality: assessment of degradation (<italic>in situ</italic>) and gas production (<italic>in vitro</italic>). J Integr Agric. 2016;15:2834&#x02013;41.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>BYL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of inoculation of <italic>Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</italic> and <italic>Lentilactobacillus buchneri</italic> on fermentation quality, aerobic stability, and microbial community dynamics of wilted <italic>Leymus chinensis</italic> silage</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>928731</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.928731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35966710</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Wu BYL, Hu ZF, Wei ML, Yong M, Niu HX. Effects of inoculation of <italic>Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</italic> and <italic>Lentilactobacillus buchneri</italic> on fermentation quality, aerobic stability, and microbial community dynamics of wilted <italic>Leymus chinensis</italic> silage. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:928731.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35966710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogunade</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervantes</surname><given-names>AAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesogan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial diversity and composition of alfalfa silage as analyzed by illumina miseq sequencing: effects of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and silage additives</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>2048</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-12876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29274960</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Ogunade IM, Jiang Y, Cervantes AAP, Kim DH, Oliveira AS, Vyas D, Weinberg ZG, Jeong KC, Adesogan AT. Bacterial diversity and composition of alfalfa silage as analyzed by illumina miseq sequencing: effects of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and silage additives. J Dairy Sci. 2018;101:2048&#x02013;59.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29274960</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>NQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanism of ethanol-H<sub>2</sub> co-production fermentation in anaerobic acidogenesis: challenges and perspectives</article-title><source>Biotechnol Adv</source><year>2021</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>107679</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2020.107679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33316366</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Li Z, Gu JY, Ding J, Ren NQ, Xing DF. Molecular mechanism of ethanol-H<sub>2</sub> co-production fermentation in anaerobic acidogenesis: challenges and perspectives. Biotechnol Adv. 2021;46:107679.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33316366</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of fermentation parameters, bacterial community compositions and their metabolic pathways during the ensiling of sorghum</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>3563</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.15484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35152522</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Wang S, Shao T, Li J, Zhao J, Dong Z. A survey of fermentation parameters, bacterial community compositions and their metabolic pathways during the ensiling of sorghum. J Appl Microbiol. 2022;132:3563&#x02013;77.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35152522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different lactic acid bacteria and their combinations regulated the fermentation process of ensiled Alfalfa: ensiling characteristics, dynamics of bacterial community and their functional shifts</article-title><source>Microb Biotechnol</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33666350</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Bai J, Ding Z, Ke W, Xu D, Wang M, Huang W, Zhang Y, Liu F, Guo X. Different lactic acid bacteria and their combinations regulated the fermentation process of ensiled Alfalfa: ensiling characteristics, dynamics of bacterial community and their functional shifts. Microb Biotechnol. 2021;14:1171&#x02013;82.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33666350</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring microbial community structure and metabolic gene clusters during silage fermentation of paper Mulberry, a high-protein Woody plant</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source><year>2021</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>114766</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2020.114766</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Du Z, Sun L, Chen C, Lin J, Yang F, Cai Y. Exploring microbial community structure and metabolic gene clusters during silage fermentation of paper Mulberry, a high-protein Woody plant. Anim Feed Sci Technol. 2021;275:114766.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banfalvi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conversion of oxidative energy to reductive power in the citrate cycle</article-title><source>Biochem Mol Biol Edu</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Banfalvi G. Conversion of oxidative energy to reductive power in the citrate cycle. Biochem Mol Biol Edu. 2010;19:24&#x02013;6.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>