<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-06-26T05:45:51.613Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evol Lett</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Evol Lett</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">evlett</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evolution Letters</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2056-3744</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40191414</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11968184</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/evlett/qrae066</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">qrae066</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letters</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00010</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00960</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01130</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sex-specific immunocompetence: resistance and tolerance can both be futile but not under the same circumstances</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1794-0536</contrib-id><name><surname>Brenninger</surname><given-names>Franziska A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Evolutionary Biology and Environmental Studies, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><xref rid="fn-0001" ref-type="author-notes"/><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--franziska.brenninger@ieu.uzh.ch--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalov</surname><given-names>Viktor</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Evolutionary Biology and Environmental Studies, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><xref rid="fn-0001" ref-type="author-notes"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>Hanna</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Institute for Organismic and Molecular Evolution, Johannes Gutenberg University of Mainz</institution>, <addr-line>Mainz</addr-line>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Institute of Quantitative and Computational Biology, Johannes Gutenberg University of Mainz</institution>, <addr-line>Mainz</addr-line>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn-0001"><p>Franziska A. Brenninger and Viktor Kovalov Shared first coauthor.</p></fn><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author: Department of Evolutionary Biology and Environmental Studies, University of Zurich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, 8057 Zurich, Switzerland. E-mail: <email>franziska.brenninger@ieu.uzh.ch</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-12-16"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of The Society for the Study of Evolution (SSE) and European Society for Evolutionary Biology (ESEB).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact reprints@oup.com for reprints and translation rights for reprints. All other permissions can be obtained through our RightsLink service via the Permissions link on the article page on our site&#x02014;for further information please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="qrae066.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Immunocompetence evolution can involve a &#x0201c;resistance is futile&#x0201d; scenario if parasite encounter rates are so high that high investment in resistance only marginally delays infection. Here, we investigate two understudied aspects of &#x0201c;futility&#x0201d;: the mode of immunocompetence and sexual selection. First, immunocompetence is usefully categorized as reducing the rate of becoming infected (resistance) or reducing the negative fitness consequences of infection once it happened (tolerance). We compare the prospects of futility for resistance, tolerance, and their joint occurrence, showing that resistance futility arises with respect to parasite encounter rates, while tolerance futility arises with respect to parasite virulence. However, if the same host trait improves pleiotropically both resistance and tolerance, futility disappears altogether and immunity investment remains profitable when increasing parasite encounter rates, virulence, or both. Second, we examine how sexual selection strength impacts these findings. If one sex (typically males) is near the faster end of a fast-slow continuum of life histories, then life history patterns reflecting futility can evolve sex-specificity. The solutions often feature sexual dimorphism in immunocompetence, but not always in the direction of strong sexual selection yielding low immunity: sexual selection can select for faster and &#x0201c;sicker&#x0201d; lives, but if sexual selection also favors traits that impact parasite encounter rates, the results are strongly dependent on whether futility (along any axis) plays a role.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Sexual selection</kwd><kwd>parasites</kwd><kwd>resistance</kwd><kwd>tolerance</kwd><kwd>virulence</kwd><kwd>sex-specific immunocompetence</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>University of Zurich</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100006447</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Alexander von Humboldt Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100005156</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>GenEvo graduate school</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hosts employ various strategies to fend off parasites, ranging from behavioral avoidance (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Gibson &#x00026; Amoroso, 2022</xref>), to a variety of physiological mechanisms summarized as the immune system (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Nicholson, 2016</xref>). Immunocompetence, i.e., the ability of a host to resist the establishment of a parasite and/or to limit and possibly eradicate parasite growth once infected, can be broadly divided into resistance and tolerance. The former improves host fitness by limiting parasitism (perhaps by preventing infection altogether or by reducing parasite loads). The latter keeps host fitness intact (or partially intact) without diminishing the presence or abundance of the parasite (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Martins et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">R&#x000e5;berg et al., 2009</xref>). Note, however, that terminology varies between authors: <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al. (2007)</xref> define tolerance as above but consider it a subcategory of resistance. <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Jokela et al. (2000)</xref> use tolerance to refer to a scenario where any type of defense has evolved to be low, and <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Best et al. (2010)</xref> use resistance and tolerance to model two different traits that both take effect in infected hosts only, excluding the possibility that resistance may prevent infection in the first place.</p><p>An interesting theoretical finding is a scenario where &#x0201c;resistance is futile,&#x0201d; typically discussed with respect to resistance. The &#x0201c;futility&#x0201d; cases are a counterexample to the intuition that more abundant parasites lead to stronger host immune defenses (see <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Lindstr&#x000f6;m et al., 2004</xref> for an example of the said intuition). If parasite encounter rates are so high that strongly resistant hosts still become infected, then, assuming a trade-off between resistance and current reproduction, reduced investment into resistance, i.e., futility, is selected for (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Jokela et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Walsman et al., 2023</xref>). This may involve &#x0201c;classical&#x0201d; resistance via animal immunocompetence, but also any behavioral avoidance of parasites (<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Walsman &#x00026; Cressler, 2022</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Walsman et al., 2023</xref>; see also <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Kokko et al., 2002</xref> for a sexually transmitted context), as well as plant resistance against plant pathogens (<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Thrall &#x00026; Burdon, 2000</xref>). Theoretical findings of &#x0201c;resistance is futile&#x0201d; are supported by experimental data and field observations in animals (<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Walsman et al., 2023</xref>) and plants (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Ericson &#x00026; Burdon, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Laine, 2004</xref>). Whether futility can also apply to tolerance is rarely discussed, though it is known that tolerance can be lost under certain conditions, such as short host lifespans (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p>A host that has given up immunity when it is futile makes the most of its (potentially brief) time being still parasite-free and/or still living despite being infected. This yields a connection between futility and sex-specific life histories. Strong sexual selection can make males invest in a &#x0201c;live fast, die young&#x0201d; manner (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Kokko, 2025</xref>). Whether this creates sex-specific prospects for futility is unknown, even though sexually dimorphic immunocompetence (<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Zuk et al., 2004</xref>) has been reported in a wide variety of taxa: birds (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000f8;ller et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Sauer et al., 2024</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Vincze et al., 2022</xref>), mammals (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Guerra-Silveira &#x00026; Abad-Franch, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Klein, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Moore &#x00026; Wilson, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Wilkinson et al., 2022</xref>), fishes (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Shepherd et al., 2012</xref>), and insects (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Belmonte et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Kurtz et al., 2000</xref>); for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Kelly et al. (2018)</xref>. Although males are not always the &#x0201c;sicker sex&#x0201d; (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Hillegass et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sanchez et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Sheridan et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Stoehr &#x00026; Kokko, 2006</xref>), there is a general expectation that strong sexual selection should make males favor high mating success even if it comes with a shortened lifespan. The links to futility, however, remain unexplored.</p><p>Here, we investigate two understudied aspects of &#x0201c;futility&#x0201d;: (1) types of immune mechanisms (resistance or tolerance) that hosts employ as their defense traits, and (2) varying levels of sexual selection strength. In our study, we operationally define resistance as any immune mechanism reducing the infection probability after encountering a parasite (thus we do not model varying parasite loads), while tolerance captures the host&#x02019;s ability to minimize parasite-imposed harm once infected. We develop a model that assumes a trade-off between immunity and reproduction and solve it numerically for varying levels of sexual selection strength, parasite encounter rate, and virulence. We do this for two defense mechanisms&#x02014;resistance and tolerance, whose impact is assessed separately as well as jointly, to examine whether either of them, or both, can become futile.</p><sec id="s2"><title>Model</title><p>Our continuous-time model optimizes the allocation of resources <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> (0&#x02005;&#x02264;&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>&#x02005;&#x02264;&#x02005;1) into immunity that trades off with reproduction. Resources not allocated towards immunity, 1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, are invested into reproduction. All hosts are assumed to reproduce continually, whether infected or not. Since the rate of reproduction is 1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, host fitness in a stationary population is (1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>), where <italic toggle="yes">L</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>) denotes the expected lifespan. Most of the modeling effort below deals with deriving <italic toggle="yes">L</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>). After the expression for the lifespan expectation is known, the numerical search for the fitness-maximizing value of (1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>) is simple to conduct.</p><p>To work towards <italic toggle="yes">L</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>), we assume that each host starts its life in a susceptible state (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>) with baseline mortality <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> and a constant parasite encounter rate <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003e;&#x02005;0. The method follows continuous-time rates impacting fitness (see <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kokko, 2024</xref> for an extensive tutorial; for the current model, we visualize a high rate of transitioning away from the current state&#x02014;by dying or by becoming infected&#x02014;as many parallel arrows in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>; low rates have few arrows). Not every parasite encounter leads to the host becoming infected (state I), as infections can be fended off by high resistance (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>: resistant hosts have some parasite encounters where the arrow does not &#x0201c;work&#x0201d; to create an infected individual, but one of the many encounters still does result in infection). Once infected, parasite virulence <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003e;&#x02005;1 elevates multiplicatively the mortality of their hosts, shortening the expected lifespan (more arrows in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> leading to death once infected), but this effect may be counteracted by tolerance (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref> has fewer death-inducing arrows from the infected state than <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1A</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). Our choice of a multiplicative effect makes the interpretation of <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> easy across wide ranges of mortality <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;1.2 always increases mortality by 20%, regardless of <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>). All parameters are listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The list of parameters and notions used in the model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symbol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Values (when applicable)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strength of sexual selection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See Figure captions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistance investment payoff</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See Figure captions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tolerance investment payoff</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See Figure captions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline mortality</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See Figure captions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasite virulence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See Figure captions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">k</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasite encounter rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See Figure captions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immunity investment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model outcome</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">x*</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Optimal immunity investment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model outcome</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>
<sub>SR</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifespan of susceptible individuals, &#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pleiotropic&#x0201d; scenarios</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IN0001">
<mml:math id="m7" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>
<sub>ST</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifespan of susceptible individuals, &#x0201c;tolerance&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IN0002">
<mml:math id="m8" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>
<sub>IR</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifespan of infected individuals, &#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IN0003">
<mml:math id="m9" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>
<sub>IT</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifespan of infected individuals, &#x0201c;tolerance&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pleiotropic&#x0201d; scenarios</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>
<sub>IT</sub>
<inline-formula id="IN0004">
<mml:math id="m10" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thinmathspace"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>SR</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitness of susceptible individuals, &#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pleiotropic&#x0201d; scenarios</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>SR</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">L</italic><sub>SR</sub>(1 &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>ST</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitness of susceptible individuals, &#x0201c;tolerance&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>ST</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">L</italic><sub>S</sub>(1 &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>IR</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitness of infected individuals, &#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>IR</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">L</italic><sub>IR</sub>(1 &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>IT</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitness of infected individuals, &#x0201c;tolerance&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pleiotropic&#x0201d; scenarios</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>IT</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">L</italic><sub>IT</sub>(1 &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>R</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total fitness of individuals, &#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>R</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub>SR</sub>&#x02005;+&#x02005;<inline-formula id="IN0005"><mml:math id="m11" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub>IR</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>T</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total fitness of individuals, &#x0201c;tolerance&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>T</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub>ST</sub>&#x02005;+&#x02005;<inline-formula id="IN0006"><mml:math id="m12" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub>IT</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>P</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total fitness of individuals, &#x0201c;pleiotropic&#x0201d; scenario</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">W</italic>
<sub>P</sub>&#x02005;=&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub>SR</sub>&#x02005;+&#x02005;<inline-formula id="IN0007"><mml:math id="m13" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub>IT</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Susceptible state</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infected state</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic of the model. In our continuous-time model, a susceptible individual (orange butterfly) encounters parasites continually, which may or may not lead to infection: curved arrows are all capable of causing infection in (A) where there is no resistance, but some contacts do not cause this transition in (B) where there is investment in resistance. Both susceptible (orange) and infected (blue) hosts can die, but the latter do so at a higher rate (more black arrows impacting the infected host); this increase in death rate can, however, be mitigated by tolerance (fewer black arrows in C than in B for infected hosts). An individual can reproduce regardless of infection status, as symbolized by egg-laying (dark gray arrows).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="qrae066_fig1" position="float"/></fig><p>We consider three scenarios. In the <italic toggle="yes">resistance</italic> scenario, investment into immunity&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic> reduces infection probability upon parasite encounter (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). In the <italic toggle="yes">tolerance</italic> scenario, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> instead mitigates harm imposed by parasites after infection (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). Finally, in the <italic toggle="yes">pleiotropic</italic> scenario, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> feeds into both immunity mechanisms simultaneously.</p><p>Solving the model requires deriving expectations of times spent in different states when different types of events (becoming infected, or death) &#x0201c;compete to happen&#x0201d; to an individual (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kokko, 2024</xref>). We derive the expected lifespan <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> of a host capable of resistance (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>), tolerance (<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>), or both (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>, for pleiotropy) as the sum of the time a host is expected to spend in the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> states:</p><disp-formula id="M1">
<mml:math id="m1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0fe38;</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0fe38;</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>transition&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>probability</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0fe38;</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RI</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:math>
<label>[1]</label>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="M2">
<mml:math id="m2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x023df;</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x023df;</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x023df;</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
<label>[2]</label>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="M3">
<mml:math id="m3" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x023df;</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x023df;</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x023df;</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
<label>[3]</label>
</disp-formula><p>In scenarios involving resistance (Equations 1 and 3), the probability of infection upon each parasite encounter equals 1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic></sup>, where lower values of <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic> imply more efficient reduction in risk (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1B</xref>). If <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic> is high, substantial allocation (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>) is required to yield a considerable reduction. These assumptions translate into a transition rate <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>(1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic></sup>) from <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>.</p><p>An individual remains in the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> state as long as it avoids both infection and death. In cases where immunocompetence&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><italic toggle="yes">&#x02005;</italic>improves resistance, the expected time spent in S is longer if&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>&#x02005;is high (Equations 1 and 3), while if&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>&#x02005;only confers tolerance (Equation 2), the time to infection depends on <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> without involving <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>. In all settings, the expected time spent in an <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> state is also limited by death rates <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>.</p><p>The expected time spent in the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> state depends on the lifetime probability of transitioning from <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> state to <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> state in the first place (second term in Equations 1, 2, and 3), multiplied by the expected lifespan conditional on ever entering that state (the last terms in Equations 1, 2, and 3). Since we do not include recovery in our model, the only way to leave the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> state is through death. In scenarios with no tolerance, virulence <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> elevates multiplicatively the death rate from <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;&#x003bc;</italic> and thus the expected lifespan from the point of infection onwards is 1/(<italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;&#x003bc;</italic>).</p><p>In scenarios including tolerance (Equations 2 and 3), immunity investment <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> mitigates the mortality changes caused by virulence: we assume it diminishes the difference between mortality rates while infected and uninfected (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;&#x003bc;</italic> &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> in the absence of tolerance) through a multiplication by 1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic></sup>, where <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic> modulates how allocation <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> translates into longer lifespan once infected (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic> &#x0003e; 0) (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1C</xref>). Thus, mortality changes from <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;+</italic>(1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic></sup>)(<italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;&#x003bc;</italic>&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>) upon infection. Note that even with mortality reduction through tolerance, mortality in the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> state does not fall below mortality in the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> state. Immunity investment <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> into both resistance and/or tolerance leads to a proportional reduction of the chance of infection and/or mortality in the infected state, respectively, regardless of the absolute parasite encounter rate or virulence.</p><p>We assume that host reproductive success is contingent on the fraction of resources invested into reproduction (1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>), both in the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> and in the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> states. Reproductive output per time unit equals (1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>)<sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic></sup>, where <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> describes the strength of sexual selection (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003e;&#x02005;0) (see, e.g., <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Stoehr &#x00026; Kokko, 2006</xref>, for this way of modulating the strength of sexual selection, though in their notation this was <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b4;</italic>). High values of <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> indicate that a small marginal investment difference creates little marginal change in reproductive success when investment into reproduction (1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>) is low to begin with, while the improvement in reproductive success is considerable if the investment has already reached high levels. A biological example for this are males that need to invest heavily into reproduction before achieving any meaningful mating success. Small values of <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> behave in the opposite way to the above statements (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1A</xref>). In species that are not sex role reversed, low <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> fits female life history, where modest investment into reproduction is required, but ever-higher investment leads to diminishing returns.</p><p>The expected fitness of a host of a specific sex is a product of reproductive output per time unit, 1&#x02013;<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, multiplied with the expected lifespan. For each scenario, &#x0201c;resistance,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;tolerance,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;pleiotropic,&#x0201d; this yields the following equations describing the expected lifetime fitness:</p><disp-formula id="M4">
<mml:math id="m4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
<label>[4]</label>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="M5">
<mml:math id="m5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
<label>[5]</label>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="M6">
<mml:math id="m6" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
<label>[6]</label>
</disp-formula><p>We numerically derive the optimal immunity investment <italic toggle="yes">x*</italic> that maximizes fitness for a host, and then interpret the resulting dependencies on <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s4"><title>Futility in response to parasite encounter rate, virulence, or neither?</title><p>When reproduction trades off with resistance only, the lowest and highest parasite encounter rates <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> produce similar outcomes, where investment into immunity remains low (red line, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). It is easy to understand why immunity is neglected with low parasite encounter rates&#x02014;most lives end without entering the infected state, yielding little incentive to invest into immunity. However, immunity remains low at a high parasite encounter rate, with lifespans evolving to be short. This is a classic example of a &#x0201c;resistance is futile&#x0201d; situation: when parasitic encounters are so frequent that even high immunity cannot prevent infection for any substantial amount of time, it becomes optimal to neglect immunity and maximize offspring production before death. Substantial immunity investment in the resistance scenario thus evolves at intermediate values of parasite encounter rate <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Optimal investment <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>* (A, B) and resulting expected lifespan <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> (sum of expected lifespan in two states, susceptible and infected) (C, D), as a function of (A, C) parasite encounter rates <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and (B, D) parasite virulence <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> under the three immunity mechanisms scenarios. Line color and shape indicate immunity mechanisms included into a given model scenario: red line&#x02014;&#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; scenario; yellow dashed line&#x02014;&#x0201c;tolerance&#x0201d; scenario; blue dotted line&#x02014;&#x0201c;pleiotropy&#x0201d; scenario where immunocompetence improves both resistance and tolerance. Other model parameters: <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;2; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.2; in (A, C) <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;1,000; in (B, D) <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="qrae066_fig2" position="float"/></fig><p>With tolerance, benefits from immunity investment are based on decreasing the additional mortality induced by parasites. There is no futility pattern for tolerance with respect to parasite encounter rates; instead, allocation into tolerance-conferring immunity increases with parasite encounter rate (yellow dashed line, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Note that this increase only mitigates and does not prevent the lifespan loss associated with parasitism (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>). Tolerance, however, produces futility with respect to parasite virulence: immunity investment first grows, then shrinks, along the virulence axis (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>), showing a similar effect as parasite encounter rates had for the resistance scenario.</p><p>When the same investment improves both resistance and tolerance (pleiotropy), futility disappears and optimal immunity investment increases with parasite encounter rate as well as with parasite virulence (blue dotted lines, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). Despite pleiotropic benefits, the investment once again is not sufficient to keep lifespan as long as in the absence of the parasite (blue dotted lines, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). Note that as a whole, conditions that lead to maximal immunity investment, such as high parasite encounter rate or virulence, associate with either short or intermediate expected lifespans <italic toggle="yes">L</italic>. The &#x0201c;short life&#x0201d; cases arise because difficulties to cope with abundant, virulent parasites can simultaneously shorten life while also selecting for high immunity. This co-occurrence between shortest lives and strongest immunity is broken under conditions where there is futility: now immunity investment is maximal at intermediate parasite encounter rates and virulence, and lifespans are accordingly at the intermediate range too.</p><p>While the above examples show interesting patterns, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> varies parasite encounter rate <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> while keeping virulence <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> constant, or vice versa; nor is baseline mortality <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> varied. Broadening the view to other combinations of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> is necessary to infer generality, while <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> merely scales the lifespan outcomes and its precise value is less important.</p><p>Exploring solutions across varying parasite encounter rates <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and virulence <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> allows asking whether either parameter promotes futility. Along the encounter rate axis, allocation into resistance-promoting immunity first grows (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>: colors become lighter) when moving horizontally, in the direction of increasing <italic toggle="yes">k,</italic> declining thereafter (colors become darker again), such that the optimal investment <italic toggle="yes">x*</italic> reaches the highest values at intermediate values of <italic toggle="yes">k.</italic> Moving vertically, in the direction of increasing virulence, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic>, does not show futility in resistance: investment either stays unchanged or increases (moving upwards means moving into lighter-colored regions).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The effect of parasite virulence and parasite encounter rate on (A, C, E) optimal immunity investment and (B, D, F) expected lifespan. Immunocompetence is assumed to improve resistance (A, B), tolerance (C, D), or both (E, F). The investment heatmaps (A, C, E) show the optimal immunity investment <italic toggle="yes">x*</italic> for each combination of parasite encounter rate <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis, log scaled) and parasite virulence <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis). The lifespan heatmaps (B, D, F) assume individuals invest according to the optimal value <italic toggle="yes">x*</italic>. Parameter values: <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;2; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5;<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="qrae066_fig3" position="float"/></fig><p>The statements can be reversed for tolerance (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>): moving along the horizontal axis (increasing <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>) only leads to lighter colors (increasing investment), while movement along the vertical axis yields futility, where increasing virulence selects for giving up tolerance. To sum up, while resistance futility requires highly abundant parasites, tolerance futility occurs with highly virulent parasites. If parasites significantly shorten life and significant mitigation via tolerance is unachievable, the optimal strategy maximizes fitness with a short life and fast reproduction rather than prolonging it through tolerance.</p><p>Finally, when immunity investment improves both tolerance and resistance, the question is whether the system combines both types of &#x0201c;futility,&#x0201d; only one, or none. The answer was &#x0201c;none&#x0201d; in the single example of <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, and this also generalizes to <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>. Since Equations (4, 5, and 6) do not yield closed-form solutions for the optimal <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>*, the result that futility disappears with pleiotropy deserves an even stronger investigation with respect to its generality. A broad search across parameter values shows this is the case for all 10,000 tested parameter sets (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary information</xref>).</p><p>The lifespan results of <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> generalize as well: the adaptive responses by the hosts do not fully compensate for the burden of parasitism. The different immunity scenarios yield almost identical results for the expected host lifespan (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">D</xref>, and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">F</xref>). Total lifespan diminishes with increasing parasite encounter rate as well as with virulence (dark blue areas at the top-right side of <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">D</xref>, and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">F</xref>), despite adaptive changes in immunocompetence that differ between resistance, tolerance, and pleiotropic scenarios (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">E</xref>). Note also that, should one compare two species differing in their ecologies, it is possible to have little difference in predicted immunity despite widely differing encounter rates and/or virulence of their (potentially species-specific) parasites; this applies whenever the two parameter combinations are within a zone of the same color in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Stronger sexual selection leads to weaker immunity, but the net effect depends on parasite encounter rates</title><p>Sexual selection strength interplays with parasite abundance to influence optimal immunocompetence (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). In general, whenever it is beneficial for a host to invest into immunity (at moderate and/or high parasite encounter rates depending on the immunity mechanism), the relationship between sexual selection strength and investment into immunity is negative (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">E</xref>: colors darken when sexual selection increases). This is logical: relaxed sexual selection (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;1) implies diminishing returns of reproductive success with ever-higher investment in reproductive traits, rendering the lifespan-extending trait of immunocompetence relatively more beneficial. However, at very low parasite encounter rates, irrespective of the immunity mechanisms in focus, immunity investment remains low regardless of sexual selection strength, as infection risk remains minimal. This is also true when varying the relationship between immunity investment and resistance and tolerance payoffs <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic> (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures S2 and S3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>The effect of strength of sexual selection and parasite encounter rate on optimal immunity investment. Immunocompetence is assumed to improve resistance (A, B), tolerance (C, D), or both (E, F). The optimal investment <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>* heatmaps (A, C, E) show the nonlinearity of <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>* with respect to parasite encounter rate <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and strength of sexual selection <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>. The lifespan heatmaps (B, D, F) assume individuals invest according to the optimal value <italic toggle="yes">x*</italic>. Symbols inside the heatmaps point out locations referred to in the main text, with numbers indicating immunity investment <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>*. Within each plot, the square and triangle mark higher levels of sexual selection as well as parasite encounter rate compared to the respective circle; triangles have the highest investment, circles medium, and squares the lowest. Other model parameters: <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b3;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;0.5; <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02005;=&#x02005;30.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="qrae066_fig4" position="float"/></fig><p>We do not explicitly specify &#x0201c;males&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;females&#x0201d; in our model. Instead, we consider their situation to differ in two ways: the sex experiencing stronger sexual selection (often males) is located higher up along the <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> axis (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">E</xref>); additionally, some sexually selected traits, e.g., fighting (with the possibility of injuries) and increased mobility, may elevate the parasite encounter rate, shifting a given sex towards the right in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">E</xref>. The optimal investment changes accordingly. While increasing <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic> lowers optimal investment, the effect of increased parasite encounter rate is mechanism-specific, as explained in previous findings (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><p>Consequently, what matters for the final prediction is the location of a sex in the parameter space. The effects may be subtle: if moving a female to a male life history involves an increase in both <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">&#x003b1;</italic>, then in some cases (large areas of similar color, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>) not much changes, while in other situations there is much subtlety in predictions. Examples (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>) occur when moving from circles (&#x0201c;female&#x0201d;) to either triangles or squares (&#x0201c;male&#x0201d;), and in both cases (triangles and squares), males experience a higher <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and are more strongly sexually selected than females are. In the triangle locations, the shift along the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> axis is relatively stronger than the shift along the sexual selection axis, and the result is a strengthening of immunity in males relative to females as a result of an increased parasite encounter rate; the square shows the opposite (male <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>*&#x02005;&#x0003c;&#x02005;female <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>*) as the difference in sexual selection strength, promoting fast life histories in males, predominates the pattern.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Discussion</title><p>The concept of &#x0201c;futility&#x0201d; explains a counterintuitive phenomenon where a host neglects immunocompetence when intuitively it would be most needed. Typically, the axis in question is parasite abundance; futility means a negative relationship between (some values of) abundance and evolved resistance (<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Walsman et al., 2023</xref>). Broadly speaking, a &#x0201c;resistance-is-futile&#x0201d; strategy applies to ineffective defense mechanisms, predicting weaker or possibly abandoned investments into defense (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Jokela et al., 2000</xref>). In our study, we showed that resistance and tolerance differ in the conditions that create futility.</p><p>While our results align with earlier work, showing that resistance can sometimes diminish with very high parasite abundance, our study identifies another axis of futility. With tolerance as the defense trait, parasite virulence&#x02014;not abundance&#x02014;serves as the axis of futility. Interestingly, ours is not the first to show futility as a response to parasite traits beyond abundance. <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Best et al. (2010)</xref> modeled a special case of castrating parasites, distinguishing between two traits termed &#x0201c;resistance&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;tolerance,&#x0201d; but with important terminological differences between their study and ours. Their resistance does not prevent infection; instead, it is assumed to lower the parasite growth rate, influencing virulence. Thus, once the terminology is accounted for, their finding of &#x0201c;futile resistance&#x0201d; aligns well with virulence-tolerance futility from our model.</p><p>Intriguingly, if we assume that immunocompetence aids both resistance and tolerance, neither axis of futility remains. This holds even if immune investment strengthens one immune mechanism more than the other (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary information</xref>). Thus, we make the prediction that if the same trait can often help in both contexts, futility should not be observed. Thus, when futility is found, our model suggests that researchers should find little pleiotropy where one trait helps in both contexts&#x02014;or perhaps even an actual trade-off between resistance and tolerance, should they compete for resources within an organism (see discussion in the context of birds, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Arriero et al., 2018</xref>; or fruit flies: <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">Vincent &#x00026; Sharp, 2014</xref>). Modeling this scenario explicitly appears a fruitful research avenue.</p><p>Our model also has some other limitations. To keep the causalities maximally clear, we made the choice of building an &#x0201c;open&#x0201d; model (<italic toggle="yes">sensu</italic> &#x000a0;<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2018</xref>) where parasite encounter rates can take any value regardless of host traits. While this makes detecting futility clearer, it also prevents us from making predictions on the role that feedbacks take in host-parasite dynamics (see a review by <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Boots et al., 2008</xref> for several examples of how the coevolution of a host-parasite system can be modeled). Interestingly, since resistance and tolerance differ starkly in their effects on parasite fitness, we can conjecture that high tolerance can increase parasite abundance, with knock-on effects on the evolution of resistance, a potential outcome resembling results of a coevolutionary model (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Baalen, 1998</xref>) where hosts lose their resistance under abundant but avirulent parasites. Likewise, we did not consider evolving parasite traits (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Cousineau &#x00026; Alizon, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Gipson &#x00026; Hall, 2016</xref>), creating potentially more complex settings and promising avenues for future models.</p><p>We assume a trade-off between reproduction and immunity with the potential for sex-specific optima. There are extreme examples in nature: male semelparity in <italic toggle="yes">Antechinus</italic> is caused by the collapse of male immunocompetence after one intense mating season (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Fisher et al., 2013</xref>). More generally, fighting off infection negatively impacts a host&#x02019;s reproductive success (as suggested by host traits (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Manjerovic &#x00026; Waterman, 2012</xref>) and exposure to infectious agents (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Hogg &#x00026; Hurd, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Fellowes et al., 1999</xref>; for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Schwenke et al., 2016</xref>). In turn, higher reproductive investment may also suppress immunocompetence (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Adamo et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Ardia et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Fedorka et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Uller et al., 2020</xref>). Our model, where sexual selection decreases optimal immunity investment, goes in line with previous studies (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Sheldon &#x00026; Verhulst, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Zuk, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Zuk &#x00026; Stoehr, 2002</xref>).</p><p>We add, however, new examples to the set of known theoretical counterexamples, such as the known theoretical finding that if a male needs very good condition to have appreciable mating success, and parasites are a major determinant of condition, males may remain the more immunocompetent sex (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Stoehr &#x00026; Kokko, 2006</xref>). In our case, sex differences in optimal immunity levels occur when sexes differ in the strength of sexual selection and/or the parasite encounter rate. If parasites are not abundant enough for futility to emerge, the more sexually selected sex is predicted to have lower immunocompetence when sexual selection is the sole difference between sexes, but this sex can switch to higher immunocompetence if sexual selection comes with behaviors increasing parasite encounter rates. In &#x0201c;futile&#x0201d; scenarios, the sexually selected sex is much more clearly predicted to have lower immunocompetence, regardless of parasite encounter rate.</p><p>A higher parasite burden in males (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Poulin, 1996</xref>) may stem either from sex-specific parasite behavior (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Duneau &#x00026; Ebert, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Duneau et al., 2012</xref>) or from males offering an easier habitat for the parasites, reflecting sexually divergent immunocompetence (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Bacelar et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Foo et al., 2017</xref>). Documenting parasite encounter rates is probably easier than sex-specific virulence (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Hall &#x00026; Mideo, 2018</xref>). Note, however, that while we might expect higher parasite encounter rates for males (e.g., with male-biased mate-searching, <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Li &#x00026; Kokko, 2019</xref>), females face unique challenges too, e.g., pregnancy-associated transmission risk (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2022</xref>), traumatic insemination (<xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Reinhardt et al., 2003</xref>), or diet differences (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">De Lisle &#x00026; Bolnick, 2021</xref>).</p><p>We did not consider any specific form of sexual selection, where favorable sexually selected traits correlate with superior resistance genes (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Dunn et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Taskinen &#x00026; Kortet, 2002</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Stoehr and Kokko (2006)</xref> considered immunity investment&#x02019;s potential to increase mating success yet without an explicit focus on females preferring resistant males. If females mate preferably with males resisting infection, or tolerant males simply persist longer in the mating pool (an idea akin to &#x0201c;stamina,&#x0201d; <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Kovalov &#x00026; Kokko, 2022</xref>), dynamics are likely to become more complicated; parental care (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Venkateswaran et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Wittman &#x00026; Cox, 2021</xref>) and sexually transmitted disease (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Keiser et al., 2020</xref>) offer further challenges.</p><p>Overall, we have shown an interesting nonadditivity: two axes of futility both disappear if the same immunity trait can help uninfected hosts avoid infection and improve the performance (here, survival) of infected hosts. Hence, an immune system with pleiotropic effects may avoid scenarios where immune defense becomes futile. Since it is conceivable that mechanisms conferring resistance can also help tolerate the infection once it exists, this may help explain why organisms rarely &#x0201c;capitulate&#x0201d; in the presence of frequently encountered parasites.</p></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>Supplementary material is available online at <italic toggle="yes">Evolution Letters</italic>.</p><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>qrae066_suppl_Supplementary_Material</label><media xlink:href="qrae066_suppl_supplementary_material.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="a1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>V.K. thanks members of the L&#x000fc;pold&#x02019;s group at UZH for their valuable comments at different stages of the work on this project.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s8"><title>Data and code availability</title><p>MATLAB files with the model code and scripts used to generate data and figures are available under the following link: <ext-link xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/14139445" ext-link-type="uri">https://zenodo.org/records/14139445</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization&#x02014;all the authors; building and investigating the model&#x02014;all the authors; writing original draft&#x02014;F.A.B. and V.K.; reviewing and editing&#x02014;all the authors; supervision&#x02014;H.K. All the authors read the final version of the manuscript and approved it for the publication.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Funding</title><p>F.A.B. and V.K. were funded by University of Zurich, H.K. acknowledges funding by the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation and the GenEvo graduate school.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest</italic>: The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><ref-list id="r1"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Adamo</surname>, <given-names>S. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Younger</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Changes in lifetime immunocompetence in male and female <italic toggle="yes">Gryllus texensis</italic> (formerly <italic toggle="yes">G. integer</italic>): Trade-offs between immunity and reproduction</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source>, <volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.2001.1786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ardia</surname>, <given-names>D. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schat</surname>, <given-names>K. A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Winkler</surname>, <given-names>D. W.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Reproductive effort reduces long-term immune function in breeding tree swallows (<italic toggle="yes">Tachycineta bicolor</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>270</volume>(<issue>1525</issue>), <fpage>1679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1683</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2003.2424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12964994</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Arriero</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez-Tris</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramirez</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Remacha</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Trade&#x02011;off between tolerance and resistance to infections: An experimental approach with malaria parasites in a passerine bird</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>, <volume>188</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1010</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-018-4290-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30377770</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Baalen</surname>, <given-names>M. V.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Coevolution of recovery ability and virulence</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London. Series B: Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>265</volume>(<issue>1393</issue>), <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.1998.0298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bacelar</surname>, <given-names>F. S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Boots</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Life history and mating systems select for male biased parasitism mediated through natural selection and ecological feedbacks</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source>, <volume>269</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20946902</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Belmonte</surname>, <given-names>R. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corbally</surname>, <given-names>M. K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duneau</surname>, <given-names>D. F.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Regan</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Sexual Dimorphisms in innate immunity and responses to infection in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Immunology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Best</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Boots</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Resistance is futile but tolerance can explain why parasites do not always castrate their hosts</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>, <volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>357</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2009.00819.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19686267</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Boots</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Best</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>White</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The role of ecological feedbacks in the evolution of host defence: What does theory tell us</article-title>? <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>364</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>, <given-names>G. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levin</surname>, <given-names>S. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wild</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>West</surname>, <given-names>S. A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Modeling relatedness and demography in social evolution</article-title>. <source>Evolution Letters</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Cousineau</surname>, <given-names>S. V.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Alizon</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Parasite evolution in response to sex-based host heterogeneity in resistance and tolerance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>2753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2766</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jeb.12541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25376168</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>De Lisle</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Bolnick</surname>, <given-names>D. I.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Male and female reproductive fitness costs of an immune response in natural populations</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>2509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2523</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33991339</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dong</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seemann</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humble</surname>, <given-names>J. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>, <given-names>D. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>, <given-names>H. -S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J. -S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Au</surname>, <given-names>D. W. T.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>, <given-names>Y. W.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Modification of the plasma complement protein profile by exogenous estrogens is indicative of a compromised immune competence in marine medaka (<italic toggle="yes">Oryzias melastigma</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Fish and Shellfish Immunology</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>269</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2017.09.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28882797</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Duneau</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Ebert</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Host sexual dimorphism and parasite adaptation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biology</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>e1001271</fpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22389630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Duneau</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luijckx</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruder</surname>, <given-names>L. F.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Ebert</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Sex-specific effects of a parasite evolving in a female-biased host population</article-title>. <source>BMC Biology</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22214525</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dunn</surname>, <given-names>P. O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bollmer</surname>, <given-names>J. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freeman-Gallant</surname>, <given-names>C. R.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Whittingham</surname>, <given-names>L. A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>MHC variation is related to a sexually selected ornament, survival, and parasite resistance in common yellowthroats</article-title>. <source>Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution</source>, <volume>67</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>687</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01799.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23461319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ericson</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Burdon</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Linking field epidemiological and individual plant resistance patterns in the <italic toggle="yes">Betula pubescens&#x02013;Melampsoridium betulinum</italic> host&#x02013;pathogen interaction</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>, <volume>118</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>232</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0706.2008.16988.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fedorka</surname>, <given-names>K. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zuk</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Mousseau</surname>, <given-names>T. A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Immune suppression and the cost of reproduction in the ground cricket, <italic toggle="yes">Allonemobius socius</italic></article-title>. <source>Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution</source>, <volume>58</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>2478</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2485</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0014-3820.2004.tb00877.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15612291</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fellowes</surname>, <given-names>M. D. E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kraaijeveld</surname>, <given-names>A. R.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Godfray</surname>, <given-names>H. C. J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The relative fitness of Drosophila melanogaster (Diptera, Drosophilidae) that have successfully defended themselves against the parasitoid <italic toggle="yes">Asobara tabida</italic> (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>, <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1420-9101.1999.00018.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>, <given-names>D. O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dickman</surname>, <given-names>C. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>, <given-names>M. E.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Blomberg</surname>, <given-names>S. P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Sperm competition drives the evolution of suicidal reproduction in mammals</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the USA</source>, <volume>110</volume>(<issue>44</issue>), <fpage>17910</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17914</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1310691110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24101455</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Foo</surname>, <given-names>Y. Z.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakagawa</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhodes</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Simmons</surname>, <given-names>L. W.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The effects of sex hormones on immune function: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Biological Reviews of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</source>, <volume>92</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>571</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26800512</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Amoroso</surname>, <given-names>C. R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Evolution and ecology of parasite avoidance</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-102220-020636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Gipson</surname>, <given-names>S. A. Y.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Hall</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The evolution of sexual dimorphism and its potential impact on host&#x02013;pathogen coevolution</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>, <volume>70</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>959</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>968</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/evo.12922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27076194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Guerra-Silveira</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Abad-Franch</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Sex bias in infectious disease epidemiology: Patterns and processes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>e62390</fpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23638062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hall</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Mideo</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Linking sex differences to the evolution of infectious disease life-histories</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, Series B: Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>373</volume>(<issue>1757</issue>), <fpage>20170431</fpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2017.0431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30150228</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hillegass</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waterman</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Roth</surname>, <given-names>J. D.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The influence of sex and sociality on parasite loads in an African ground squirrel</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Ecology</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1006</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1011</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hogg</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Hurd</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Plasmodium yoelii nigeriensis</italic>: The effect of high and low intensity of infection upon the egg production and bloodmeal size of <italic toggle="yes">Anopheles stephensi</italic> during three gonotrophic cycles</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>, <volume>111</volume>(<issue>Pt 5</issue>), <fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0031182000077027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8559587</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Jokela</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Rigby</surname>, <given-names>M. C.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Dr. Pangloss restrained by the Red Queen - Steps towards a unified defence theory</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>, <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Keiser</surname>, <given-names>C. N.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rudolf</surname>, <given-names>V. H. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luksik</surname>, <given-names>M. C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Saltz</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Sex differences in disease avoidance behavior vary across modes of pathogen exposure</article-title>. <source>Ethology</source>, <volume>126</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>, <given-names>C. D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoehr</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nunn</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smyth</surname>, <given-names>K. N.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Prokop</surname>, <given-names>Z. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in immunity across animals: A meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title>. <source>Ecology Letters</source>, <volume>21</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1885</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1894</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ele.13164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30288910</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Klein</surname>, <given-names>S. L.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Sex influences immune responses to viruses, and efficacy of prophylaxis and treatments for viral diseases</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1050</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1059</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.201200099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23012250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kokko</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Who is afraid of modelling time as a continuous variable</article-title>? <source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1756</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210x.14394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kokko</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>2025</year>). <article-title>Sex-specific life histories</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><given-names>M</given-names> &#x000a0;<surname>Segoli</surname></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><given-names>E.</given-names> &#x000a0;<surname>Wajnberg</surname></string-name></person-group>, (Eds.), <source>Life history evolution: Traits, interactions, and applications</source>. <publisher-name>Wiley (in press)</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kokko</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranta</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruxton</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Lundberg</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Sexually transmitted disease and the evolution of mating systems</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>, <volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1091</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1100</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0014-3820.2002.tb01423.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12144011</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kovalov</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Kokko</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Selection for male stamina can help explain costly displays with cost-minimizing female choice</article-title>. <source>Behavior, Ecology and Sociobiology</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kurtz</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiesner</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Sauer</surname>, <given-names>K. P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Gender differences and individual variation in the immune system of the scorpionfly <italic toggle="yes">Panorpa vulgaris</italic> (Insecta: Mecoptera)</article-title>. <source>Developmental and Comparative Immunology</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0145-305x(99)00057-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10689094</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Laine</surname>, <given-names>A. -L.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Resistance variation within and among host populations in a plant&#x02013;pathogen metapopulation: Implications for regional pathogen dynamics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source>, <volume>92</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>990</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1000</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0022-0477.2004.00925.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>X. Y.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Kokko</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Sex-biased dispersal: A review of the theory</article-title>. <source>Biological Reviews of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</source>, <volume>94</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>736</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30353655</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lindstr&#x000f6;m</surname>, <given-names>K. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foufopoulos</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>P&#x000e4;rn</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Wikelski</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Immunological investments reflect parasite abundance in island populations of Darwin&#x02019;s finches</article-title>. <source>Proceedings Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>271</volume>(<issue>1547</issue>), <fpage>1513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1519</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2004.2752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Manjerovic</surname>, <given-names>M. B.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Waterman</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Immunological sex differences in socially promiscuous African ground squirrels</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>e38524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e38525</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22715391</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Martins</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carlos</surname>, <given-names>A. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braza</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bastos-Amador</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramos</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Soares</surname>, <given-names>M. P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Disease tolerance as an inherent component of immunity</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Immunology</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-042718-041739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Boots</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Host life span and the evolution of resistance characteristics</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>, <volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2007.00001.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17300423</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname>, <given-names>A. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>&#x000da;beda</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Wild</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>On maternity and the stronger immune response in women</article-title>. <source>Nature Communications</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname>, <given-names>A. P.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sorci</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Erritz&#x000f8;e</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in immune defense</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>, <volume>152</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>619</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/286193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Moore</surname>, <given-names>S. L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Parasites as a viability cost of sexual selection in natural populations of mammals</article-title>. <source>Science (New York, N.Y.)</source>, <volume>297</volume>(<issue>5589</issue>), <fpage>2015</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2018</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1074196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nicholson</surname>, <given-names>L. B.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The immune system</article-title>. <source>Essays in Biochemistry</source>, <volume>60</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/EBC20160017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27784777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Poulin</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Sexual inequalities in helminth infections: A cost of being a male</article-title>? <source>American Naturalist</source>, <volume>147</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/285851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>R&#x000e5;berg</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname>, <given-names>A. L.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Read</surname>, <given-names>A. F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Decomposing health: Tolerance and resistance to parasites in animals</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, Series B: Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>364</volume>(<issue>1513</issue>), <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2008.0184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18926971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Reinhardt</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naylor</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Siva&#x02013;Jothy</surname>, <given-names>M. T.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Reducing a cost of traumatic insemination: Female bedbugs evolve a unique organ</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London. Series B: Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>270</volume>(<issue>1531</issue>), <fpage>2371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2375</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2003.2515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sanchez</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devevey</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Bize</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Female-biased infection and transmission of the gastrointestinal nematode <italic toggle="yes">Trichuris arvicolae</italic> infecting the common vole, <italic toggle="yes">Microtus arvalis</italic></article-title>. <source>International Journal for Parasitology</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>13&#x02013;14</issue>), <fpage>1397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1402</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2011.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22056297</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sauer</surname>, <given-names>E. L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connelly</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perrine</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Love</surname>, <given-names>A. C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>DuRant</surname>, <given-names>S. E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Male pathology regardless of behaviour drives transmission in an avian host&#x02013;pathogen system</article-title>. <source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source>, <volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2656.14026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38044497</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Schwenke</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazzaro</surname>, <given-names>B. P.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Wolfner</surname>, <given-names>M. F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Reproduction-immunity trade-offs in insects</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Entomology</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-010715-023924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sheldon</surname>, <given-names>B. C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Verhulst</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Ecological immunology: Costly parasite defences and trade-offs in evolutionary ecology</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>321</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0169-5347(96)10039-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237861</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Shepherd</surname>, <given-names>B. S.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rees</surname>, <given-names>C. B.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Binkowski</surname>, <given-names>F. P.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Goetz</surname>, <given-names>F. W.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Characterization and evaluation of sex-specific expression of suppressors of cytokine signaling (SOCS)-1 and -3 in juvenile yellow perch (<italic toggle="yes">Perca flavescens</italic>) treated with lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Fish and Shellfish Immunology</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>481</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2012.05.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22634749</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sheridan</surname>, <given-names>L. A. D.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poulin</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>, <given-names>D. F.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Zuk</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Sex differences in parasitic infections among arthropod hosts: Is there a male bias</article-title>? <source>Oikos</source>, <volume>88</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>334</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2000.880211.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Stoehr</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Kokko</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in immunocompetence: What does life-history theory predict</article-title>? <source>Behavioral Ecology</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>756</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Taskinen</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Kortet</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Dead and alive parasites: Sexual ornaments signal resistance in the male fish, <italic toggle="yes">Rutilus rutilus</italic></article-title>. <source>Evolutionary Ecology Research</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>919</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>929</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Thrall</surname>, <given-names>P. H.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Burdon</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Effect of resistance variation in a natural plant host&#x02013;pathogen metapopulation on disease dynamics</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathology</source>, <volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>773</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3059.2000.00523.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Uller</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isakssont</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Olsson</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Immune challenge reduces reproductive output and growth in a lizard</article-title>. <source>Functional Ecology</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>879</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Venkateswaran</surname>, <given-names>V. R.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roth</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Gokhale</surname>, <given-names>C. S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Consequences of combining sex-specific traits</article-title>. <source>Evolution (N. Y)</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>1274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1287</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Vincent</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Sharp</surname>, <given-names>N. P.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Sexual antagonism for resistance and tolerance to infection in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Proceedings Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>281</volume>(<issue>1788</issue>), <fpage>20140987</fpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2014.0987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24966317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Vincze</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>V&#x000e1;g&#x000e1;si</surname>, <given-names>C. I.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>P&#x000e9;nzes</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szab&#x000f3;</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magonyi</surname>, <given-names>N. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czirj&#x000e1;k</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Pap</surname>, <given-names>P.L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in immune function and oxidative physiology across birds: The role of sexual selection</article-title>. <source>Ecology Letters</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>970</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35106902</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Walsman</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Cressler</surname>, <given-names>C. E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Predation shifts coevolution toward higher host contact rate and parasite virulence</article-title>. <source>Proceedings Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>289</volume>(<issue>1978</issue>), <fpage>20212800</fpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2021.2800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35858064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Walsman</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>C&#x000e1;ceres</surname>, <given-names>C. E.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Hall</surname>, <given-names>S. R.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Resistance is futile&#x0201d;: Weaker selection for resistance by abundant parasites increases prevalence and depresses host density</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>, <volume>201</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>879</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilkinson</surname>, <given-names>N. M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>H. C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lechner</surname>, <given-names>M. G.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Su</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Sex differences in immunity</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Immunology</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-101320-125133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wittman</surname>, <given-names>T. N.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Cox</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>The evolution of monogamy is associated with reversals from male to female bias in the survival cost of parasitism</article-title>. <source>Proceedings Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>288</volume>(<issue>1950</issue>), <fpage>20210421</fpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2021.0421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33977790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zuk</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Reproductive strategies and disease susceptibility: An evolutionary viewpoint</article-title>. <source>Parasitology Today</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>233</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0169-4758(90)90202-f</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15463350</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zuk</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simmons</surname>, <given-names>L. W.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rotenberry</surname>, <given-names>J. T.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Stoehr</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Sex differences in immunity in two species of field crickets</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zuk</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Stoehr</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Immune defense and host life history</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>, <volume>160</volume>(<issue>Suppl 4</issue>), <fpage>S9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S22</lpage>. https://doi.org/<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/342131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>