<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WJC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>World Journal of Cardiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-8462</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Baishideng Publishing Group Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12186126</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jWJC.v17.i6.eid105330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4330/wjc.v17.i6.105330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-manuscript">105330</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Retrospective Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Incidence, risk factors and clinical outcomes of pericardial effusion in left ventricular assist device patients</article-title><alt-title>Khan MZ <italic>et al.</italic> Risk of pericardial effusion in LVAD</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Muhammad Zubair</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Thomas Jefferson University Hospital, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States. <email>muhammad.khan2@jefferson.edu</email></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brailovsky</surname><given-names>Yevgeniy</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Sidney Kimmel School of Medicine, Jefferson Heart Institute, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuiyan</surname><given-names>Mohammad Alfrad Nobel</given-names></name><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Louisiana State University Health Shreveport, Shreveport, LA 71103, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marhefka</surname><given-names>Gregary</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Thomas Jefferson University Hospital, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Faisal</surname><given-names>Abu S M</given-names></name><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Louisiana State University Health Shreveport, Shreveport, LA 71103, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sircar</surname><given-names>Adrija</given-names></name><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>Parker</given-names></name><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rame</surname><given-names>J Eduardo</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>Sona</given-names></name><aff>Department of Medicine, Jefferson Abington Hospital, Abington, PA 19001, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Waqas</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><aff>Department of Medicine and Surgery, Saidu Medical College Swat, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Hadia</given-names></name><aff>Department of Medicine and Surgery, Saidu Medical College Swat, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rajapreyar</surname><given-names>Indranee</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>Rene J</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Author contributions: Franklin S, Shah H were involved in the graphical abstract; Khan MZ, Brailovsky Y, Alvarez RJ contributed to the conceptualization of this manuscript; Khan MZ, Sircar A, O'Neill P, Waqas M, Brailovsky Y participated in the writing and review; Marhefka G, Alvarez RJ, Rajapreyar I, Rame JE contributed to the review and supervision of this manuscript; Franklin S, Shah H and Waqas M participated to make graphs and tables; Bhuiyan MAN and Faisal ASM did stastictics; all authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p><p>Corresponding author: Muhammad Zubair Khan, MD, Department of Cardiology, Thomas Jefferson University Hospital, 111 S 11th St, Philadelphia, PA 19107, United States. <email>muhammad.khan2@jefferson.edu</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>105330</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;The Author(s) 2025. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is an open-access article that was selected by an in-house editor and fully peer-reviewed by external reviewers. It is distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/Licenses/by-nc/4.0/</uri></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>BACKGROUND</title><p>Development of pericardial effusion in patients with left ventricular assist devices (LVADs) can be detrimental to health outcomes. This study aims to elucidate the prevalence and risk factors for pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs.</p></sec><sec><title>AIM</title><p>To elucidate risk factors associated with the presence of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs and compare the clinical outcomes of those with and without pericardial effusion. The secondary goal is to determine the incidence of pericardiocentesis and pericardial window placement in patients with LVADs experiencing pericardial effusion.</p></sec><sec><title>METHODS</title><p>Data were obtained from the National Inpatient Sample database between 2016 and 2018. Statistical analysis was performed using Pearson <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test and multivariate logistic regression analysis to determine clinical outcomes of pericardial effusion and to identify variables associated with pericardial effusion in LVAD patients, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>The prevalence of LVAD was 9850 (0.01%) among total study patients (<italic>n</italic> = 98112095). The incidence of pericardial effusion among LVAD patients was 640 (6.5%). The prevalence of liver disease (26.6% <italic>vs</italic> 17.4%), chronic kidney disease (CKD; 54.6% <italic>vs</italic> 49.4%), hypothyroidism (21.9% <italic>vs</italic> 18.1%), congestive heart failure (98.4% <italic>vs</italic> 96.5%), atrial fibrillation (Afib; 58.59% <italic>vs</italic> 50.5%), coronary artery disease (CAD; 11.7% <italic>vs</italic> 4.4%), dyslipidemia (31.3% <italic>vs</italic> 39.3%), and having undergone percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI; 1.6% <italic>vs</italic> 0.7%) was higher in the pericardial effusion cohort <italic>vs</italic> the non-pericardial effusion cohort. Multivariate regression analysis demonstrated that CAD (OR = 2.89) and PCI (OR = 2.2) had the greatest association with pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs. These were followed by liver disease (OR = 1.72), hypothyroidism (OR = 1.2), electrolyte derangement (OR = 1.2), Afib (OR = 1.1), and CKD (OR = 1.05). Among patients with LVADs, the median length of stay (33 days <italic>vs</italic> 27 days) and hospitalization cost (847525 USD <italic>vs</italic> 792616 USD) were significantly higher in the pericardial effusion cohort compared to the non-pericardial effusion cohort. There was no significant difference in mortality between cohorts. The prevalence of cardiac tamponade was 109 (17.9% of LVAD patients with pericardial effusion). Ten (9.2% of LVAD patients with cardiac tamponade) patients underwent pericardiocentesis and 44 (40.3%) received a pericardial window.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>This study shows that liver disease, CKD, PCI, hypothyroidism, electrolyte derangement, Afib, and CAD had a significant association with pericardial effusion in LVAD patients. Hospitalization cost and length of stay were higher in the pericardial effusion group, but mortality was the same.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Left ventricular assist device</kwd><kwd>Pericardial effusion</kwd><kwd>Cardiac tamponade</kwd><kwd>Pericardial window</kwd><kwd>Pericardiocentesis</kwd><kwd>Risk factors and clinical outcomes of pericardial effusion</kwd><kwd>Older age</kwd><kwd>Diabetes</kwd><kwd>Larger body mass index</kwd><kwd>Renal failure</kwd><kwd>malnutrition</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>
<bold>Core Tip:</bold> Pericardial effusions in patients with left ventricular assist devices (LVADs) can lead to prolonged hospitalization and increased healthcare costs. Risk factors associated with the development of pericardial effusions include: Liver disease, chronic kidney disease (CAD), hypothyroidism, electrolyte derangement, atrial fibrillation, with the highest association found with CAD and percutaneous coronary intervention. While the presence of pericardial effusions did not have significant impact on mortality in our study, further studies are needed to elucidate whether the optimization of these co-morbidities would reduce the incidence of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs.</p><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Patients suffering from advanced end-stage heart failure who do not meet the criteria for heart transplantation can now benefit from mechanical circulatory support therapies such as left ventricular assist devices (LVADs). These devices improve quality of life and delay end-organ dysfunction; they can be used as bridging therapy until transplantation, or as destination therapy for patients who are ineligible for transplantation[<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In the recent years, the use of LVADs as destination therapy has vastly increased, accounting for about 46% of all LVAD placements[<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In the United States, the amount of LVAD implants is now approaching the number heart transplants[<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As a result, the prevalence of LVADs and their associated complications are rapidly increasing. Topilsky <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] found that up to 60% of patients receiving LVADs experience an LVAD-related complication within 6 months of implantation, and 80% experience an adverse event within 2 years of implantation. Another study by Hillebrand <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] found that on average, patients were re-admitted 2.2 times in 11 months post-implant, with the median time to re-admission being just 35 days after initial discharge.</p><p>The most common LVAD-related complications include bleeding, device thrombosis, ischemic and hemorrhagic strokes, renal impairment, multi-organ failure and infection[<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. An equally important, but less studied complication of LVAD implantation, is the development of pericardial effusion which frequently requires pericardiocentesis or pericardial window placement.</p><p>Pericardial effusions can be found in patients with an initial myocardial infarction (MI) and are more often found in patients with an anterior ST segment MI, larger infarctions and congestive heart failure[<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Pericardial effusions usually present within the first 5 days and slowly resolve over weeks to months[<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In patients with acute MI or percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), hemorrhagic pericardial effusions and cardiac tamponade may develop from coronary artery perforation during PCI, as well as hemorrhagic pericarditis, and cardiac rupture due to left ventricular free wall rupture.</p><p>Pericardial effusion is the abnormal accumulation of fluid within the pericardial cavity, and may be classified according to etiology, size, composition, duration, distribution and associated hemodynamics[<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. An effusion considered trivial is &#x0003c; 50 mL, effusions with an end-diastolic diameter less than 1 cm are considered mild (approximately 100 mL), effusions with a diameter &#x0003e; 1 cm and &#x0003c; 2 cm is considered moderate (100-500 mL), and those exceeding 2 cm are considered large[<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>-<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>LVAD placement carries a high risk of pericardial bleeding and cardiac tamponade[<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Furthermore, LVADs confer a greater risk of bleed due to acquired von Willebrand syndrome, platelet dysfunction, arteriovenous malformation and angiodysplasia[<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additional risk of bleed is secondary to aggressive anticoagulation that is administered for the risk of pump thrombosis.</p><p>This study aims to elucidate risk factors associated with the presence of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs and compare the clinical outcomes of those with and without pericardial effusion. The secondary goal is to determine the incidence of pericardiocentesis and pericardial window placement in patients with LVADs experiencing pericardial effusion.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Data source</title><p>This study was conducted using the National Inpatient Sample (NIS) database which is part of the Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project, developed by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality[<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The NIS is representative of over 97% of the human population, and the data encompasses an average of 7-8 million discharges per year, spanning 48 states. NIS data estimates more than 35 million hospitalizations nationally. Each of these admissions contain a myriad of patient information, including demographics, comorbidities, complications, the primary and secondary discharge diagnosis, and charge-to-cost ratio. The charges listed in the database represent the amount the hospital bills for services while the cost listed represents how much the service costs, including the utilities cost, supplies, and wages.</p></sec><sec><title>Study design</title><p>This study uses the International Classification of Disease (ICD), 10<sup>th</sup> revision, and Clinical Modification (ICD 10-CM) codes to identify diagnoses in the NIS database and included data obtained between January 2016 and December 2018. Only patients over the age of 18 years with were included in the study. Subjects excluded were patients under the age of 18 years, those heart transplant, intra-aortic balloon pump, and Impella device. ICD 10-CM codes were utilized to extract patients with LVAD from the NIS database. From within this subset of patients, ICD codes were again utilized to delineate those who had pericardial effusion and no pericardial effusion, as well as to identify those with specific comorbidities and baseline characteristics. This study was considered exempt from the formal approval of the Institutional Review Board, as the study cohort was derived from a publicly available database containing non-identifiable patient information.</p><p>Diagnosis code for LVAD, pericardial effusion, and other co-morbidities: The NIS data provides up to 30 Clinical Classifications Software (CCS) diagnoses for each inpatient visit. The CCS codes used for this study were: LVAD, pericardial effusion, cardiac tamponade, pericardial window, and pericardiocentesis (<uri xlink:href="https://f6publishing.blob.core.windows.net/643d97d4-0108-4ef8-8c36-82927633f493/105330-supplementary-material.pdf">Supplementary Table 1</uri>). Patients were excluded if they were under 18 years old, had received heart transplants, intra-aortic balloon pumps, and/or Impella heart pumps.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The data analysis and extraction were done using SAS statistical software version 9.4. All continuous variables were compared using Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. These variables were presented as a mean &#x000b1; SD for normally distributed variables. Median and interquartile ranges were used for non-Gaussian distributed variables. Categorical variables were analyzed using the Pearson <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test. These variables were presented as a weighted frequency in percentages. A <italic>P</italic> value of &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. In the Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, age was analyzed using the Student's <italic>t</italic>-test, while the rest of variables in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> were analyzed using the Pearson&#x02019;s <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test. In Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, mortality was analyzed using Pearson&#x02019;s <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test while length of stay and hospitalization cost were analyzed using the Student's <italic>t</italic>-test.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient-level characteristics of pericardial effusion <italic>vs</italic> no pericardial effusion in left ventricular assist device, <italic>n</italic> (%)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Characteristics</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pericardial effusion</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No pericardial effusion</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">640.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9210.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (69.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7245 (78.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (30.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1965 (21.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.57 &#x000b1; 2.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.03 &#x000b1; 3.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">345 (57.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5365 (62.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (27.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2135 (24.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (15.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1125 (13.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Co-morbidities</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Liver disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (26.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1600 (17.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Obesity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (23.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1910 (20.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Chronic kidney disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350 (54.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4550 (49.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (14.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1480 (16.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotid artery disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1020 (11.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.978</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percutaneous coronary intervention</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (0.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CABG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (1.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (10.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1020 (11.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.514</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peripheral vascular disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (2.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">370 (4.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothyroidism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (21.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1665 (18.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus types 1&#x00026;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (29.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3555 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congestive heart failure </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">630 (98.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8890 (96.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electrolyte derangement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">455 (71.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6040 (65.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (3.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">520 (5.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">505 (78.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7055 (76.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afib</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">375 (58.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4650 (50.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (11.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (4.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyslipidemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (31.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3620 (39.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CABG: Coronary artery bypass graft surgery; CAD: Coronary artery disease; Afib: Atrial fibrillation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Multivariate regression analysis for pericardial effusion group in left ventricular assist device</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Comorbidity</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Odds ratio (95%CI)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.721 (1.429- 2.063)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic kidney disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.235 (1.052- 1.452)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percutaneous coronary intervention</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.263 (1.083 -4.232)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peripheral vascular disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.579 (0.328 -0.942)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothyroidism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.269 (1.041- 1.538)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus types 1&#x00026;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.671 (0.563 -0.798)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congestive heart failure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.232 (1.249 -4.523)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electrolyte derangement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.290 (1.083-1.541)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afib</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.387 (1.179-1.633)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.890 (2.212-3.729)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyslipidemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702 (0.590- 0.833)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CAD: Coronary artery disease; Afib: Atrial fibrillation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>Between 2016 and 2018, there was a total of 115882699 hospitalizations in the United States. After excluding patients under 18 years (<italic>n</italic> = 17515974), patients with heart transplants (<italic>n</italic> = 67295), patients with intra-aortic balloon pumps (<italic>n</italic> = 139090) and patients with Impella heart pumps (<italic>n</italic> = 48245), 98112095 patients were eligible to be included in the study. Of the included patients, 9850 had LVADs with 640 (6.5%) patients having experienced a pericardial effusion (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Flow chart of the study selection process.</bold> LVAD: Left ventricular assist device; IABP: Intra-Aortic Balloon Pump.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="wjc-17-6-105330-g001" position="float"/></fig><sec><title>Factors associated with the presence of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs</title><p>Our results demonstrated a statistically significant correlation between multiple co-morbidities and the presence of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>These co-morbidities (percentage of pericardial effusion cohort <italic>vs</italic> percentage of no pericardial effusion cohort) included liver disease (26.56% <italic>vs</italic> 17.37%), chronic kidney disease (CKD; 54.69% <italic>vs</italic> 49.41%), hypothyroidism (21.88% <italic>vs</italic> 18.01%), congestive heart failure (98.44% <italic>vs</italic> 96.53%), atrial fibrillation (Afib; 58.59% <italic>vs</italic> 50.5%), coronary artery disease (CAD; 11.72% <italic>vs</italic> 4.41%), dyslipidemia (31.25% <italic>vs</italic> 39.31%), and having undergone PCI (1.56% <italic>vs</italic> 0.71%).</p><p>Multivariate regression analysis demonstrated that CAD (OR = 2.89, 95%CI = 2.21-3.72) and PCI (OR = 2.2, 95%CI = 1.08-4.23) had the greatest association with pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs. These were followed by liver disease (OR = 1.72, 95%CI = 1.42-2.06), hypothyroidism (OR = 1.26, 95%CI = 1.04-1.53), electrolyte derangement (OR = 1.2, 95%CI = 1.08-1.54), Afib (OR = 1.38, 95%CI = 1.17 -1.63), and CKD (OR = 1.23, 95%CI = 1.08-1.45; Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical outcomes</title><p>Patients with LVADs who developed pericardial effusion experienced longer durations of hospitalization and higher hospitalization costs than patients without pericardial effusions. The median length of stay in LVAD patients with a pericardial effusion was 33 days compared to 27 days in those without a pericardial effusion (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The average hospitalization cost of LVAD patients with pericardial effusion was 847525 USD compared to 792616 USD in patients without pericardial effusion. Interestingly, there was no significant difference in mortality with a mortality of 9.38% in patients with pericardial effusion compared to 9.34% of patients without pericardial effusion. The annual trends of mean hospitalization cost and length of stay in the hospital were compared between pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs <italic>vs</italic> no pericardial effusion (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>The annual trends of mean hospitalization cost and length of stay in the hospital were compared between pericardial effusion in patients with left ventricular assist devices <italic>vs</italic> no pericardial effusion.</bold> A: Trend in cost of care for left ventricular assist device with pericardial effusion and no pericardial effusion. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 for the cost of care among pericardial effusion <italic>vs</italic> no pericardial effusion in 2016, 2017 and 2018; B: Trends in length of stay for left ventricular assist device with pericardial effusion and no pericardial effusion. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 for length of stay among pericardial effusion <italic>vs</italic> no pericardial effusion in 2016, 2017 and 2018. LVAD: Left ventricular assist device.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="wjc-17-6-105330-g002" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Clinical outcomes pericardial effusion <italic>vs</italic> no pericardial effusion in left ventricular assist device</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pericardial effusion</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No pericardial effusion</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.52 &#x000b1; 6.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.08 &#x000b1; 1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalization cost (USD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">847525 &#x000b1; 93380</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">792616 &#x000b1; 37959</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.38 &#x000b1; 2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.34% &#x000b1; 0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Cardiac tamponade and pericardiocentesis</title><p>Of the 9850 patients with implanted LVADs, 640 (6.5%) experienced a pericardial effusion. Within the pericardial effusion cohort, 109 (17.0%) patients developed cardiac tamponade. Ten of these patients (9.2%) underwent pericardiocentesis and 45 patients (40.3%) received pericardial windows. Five-hundred and thirty-one patients experienced pericardial effusion without tamponade, of which 5 (0.9%) underwent pericardiocentesis, and 85 (16.3%) received pericardial windows.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study demonstrates that LVAD patients with pericardial effusion experience longer hospitalization courses and higher hospitalization costs, however, there is no significant effect on mortality. Additionally, our results highlight a significant association between pericardial effusion and the presence of liver disease, CKD, hypothyroidism, electrolyte derangement, Afib, and CAD in LVAD patients.</p><p>To date, there are no large trials detailing the rate at which patients with LVADs develop pericardial effusion, however, several case studies over the years have attempted to quantify its prevalence. One Singaporean study analyzed the outcomes of 100 patients who underwent LVAD implantation and found that 14% developed pericardial effusions[<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Topilsky <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] summarized that cardiac tamponade was a complication that occurred in 20% of patients receiving an LVAD, and Hillebrand <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] highlighted that 1 in 4 patients receiving LVAD implantation may develop pericardial effusion requiring re-exploration. Our study included 9850 patients with LVADs and found the prevalence of pericardial effusion to be 6.5%. The lower prevalence of pericardial effusion in our study may be due to our relatively large sample size, compared to previous case reports and may more accurately represent the prevalence of pericardial effusion in the general population.</p><p>One of the major concerns with developing pericardial effusion in a patient with an LVAD is that the device can mask the symptoms associated with cardiac effusion and tamponade, such as jugular venous distension, pulsus paradoxus, hypotension, and rest dyspnea[<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. This may be due to the set values of the LVAD preventing tachycardia or pulsus paradoxus, and is further complicated by the blurred echocardiogram windows in patients due to the LVAD flow, making rapid diagnosis difficult[<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Both factors increase the risk of delayed diagnosis and management, leading to worse clinical outcomes. This was demonstrated by Al Shakaki <italic>et al</italic>&#x02019;s case report of a patient with a ventricular assist device who suffered a massive pericardial effusion that was initially misdiagnosed as a thrombus of the outflow graft due to flow-limiting formation seen on CT. The patient received lysis therapy and subsequently clinically deteriorated, requiring emergent re-sternotomy and pericardiocentesis[<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Our study relied upon ICD-10 coding of pericardial effusion and cardiac tamponade, which may have led to under-reporting of the true prevalence of pericardial effusion due to misdiagnosis.</p><p>This study found statistically significant correlations between a myriad of clinical conditions and the presence of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs, including liver disease, CKD, hypothyroidism, electrolyte derangement, Afib, CAD, dyslipidemia, and those undergoing PCI. This correlation is not isolated to patients with LVADs and has been demonstrated to increase the risk of pericardial effusion in patients without mechanical circulatory support. Ashikhmina <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] found that patients who underwent cardiac surgery were at increased risk of developing a pericardial effusion if they had a history of a high body mass index, pulmonary thromboembolism, hypertension, immunosuppression, or renal failure. Further research is required to determine whether optimization of these co-morbidities can reduce the incidence of pericardial effusion. It seems likely that a multidisciplinary approach to the management of patients with LVADs would lead to decreased incidence of pericardial effusion and improved clinical outcomes.</p><p>Pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs leads to an increased burden on the healthcare system through prolonging hospitalization and increasing the cost of healthcare delivery. Our study demonstrated that patients with pericardial effusion spent a median of 6 days longer in hospital and cost an additional 54909 USD per hospital stay compared to LVAD patients without pericardial effusion. These findings may be confounded by the fact that many of the co-morbidities associated with the presence of pericardial effusion also tend to prolong hospitalization and increase healthcare costs. This was highlighted by Cotts <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] who found that increased age, non-white race, history of CABG or valve surgery, diabetes, ascites, low albumin, high blood urea nitrogen, high right atrial pressure and concomitant surgery were all variables that increased length of stay and hospitalization costs in LVAD patients. If LVAD patients have co-morbidities that require additional non-cardiac surgery, then they are at very high risk of experiencing severe complications which would prolong their hospital course and increase costs[<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Overall, it is imperative that the multidisciplinary team collaborates to minimize risk factors associated with pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs, and that pericardial effusion is identified appropriately and treated in a timely manner to prevent lengthy and costly hospitalization.</p><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Our study has several limitations. First of all, our data relied upon the correct diagnosis and use of ICD-10 codes by physicians across the country which may have led to some disease misclassification, as we were unable to validate the signs and symptoms experienced by the patients included in this study. Another limitation is that the study population is confined to inpatients and our results may not correlate with outcomes in patients with subclinical pericardial effusion who are managed in an outpatient setting. The NIS database provides information on hospital admissions and not individual patients. As a result, our data may be skewed by patients being admitted multiple times and artificially increasing the prevalence of pericardial effusion in our study population. In addition, LVAD type, implantation duration and anticoagulation therapy were not included in our study, and their inclusion could potentially influence the occurrence of pericardial effusion.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The development of pericardial effusion in patients with LVADs leads to prolonged hospitalization and increased healthcare costs, while the presence of pericardial effusion did not have significant impacts on mortality. The presence of liver disease, CKD, hypothyroidism, electrolyte derangement, Afib, CAD, and undergoing PCI have a significant association with development of pericardial effusion in patients with LVAD. Further research is required to elucidate whether optimization of co-morbidities in patients with LVADs reduces the incidence of pericardial effusion.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>
<bold>Institutional review board statement:</bold> This study, entitled, &#x0201c;Incidence, Risk Factors and Clinical Outcomes of Pericardial Effusion in LVAD Patients,&#x0201d; was considered exempt from the formal approval of the Institutional Review Board, as the study cohort was derived from a publicly available database containing non-identifiable patient information.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Informed consent statement:</bold> Our study meets the definition of Not Human Subject Research, as our study utilized de-identified data obtained from the National Inpatient Sample database between the years 2016 and 2018. We had no access to direct patient identifiers or identifiable information. Prior to obtaining the data from the NIS database utilized in our study, the data had already been de-identified. No data in our study can be used to identify any patients.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflict-of-interest statement:</bold> There are no conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Unsolicited article; Externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Peer-review model:</bold> Single blind</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Specialty type:</bold> Cardiac and cardiovascular systems</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Country of origin:</bold> United States</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Peer-review report&#x02019;s classification</bold>
</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Scientific Quality:</bold> Grade A, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Novelty:</bold> Grade A, Grade A, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade C</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Creativity or Innovation:</bold> Grade A, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade C, Grade C</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Scientific Significance:</bold> Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade B, Grade C</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>P-Reviewer:</bold> Jiang Y; Kong MW; Rafaqat S <bold>S-Editor:</bold> Lin C <bold>L-Editor:</bold> A <bold>P-Editor:</bold> Wang WB</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Left ventricular assist device as destination therapy for end stage heart failure: the right time for the right patients</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cardiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29319565</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Left Ventricular Assist Devices: A Rapidly Evolving Alternative to Transplant</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>2542</fpage><lpage>2555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26065994</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Topilsky</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atchison</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Atypical tamponade hemodynamic in a patient with temporary left ventricular assist device</article-title><source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21303869</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffmeier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Djie</surname><given-names>Tiong Tjan T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sindermann</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Minimally Invasive Implantation of HeartWare Assist Device and Simultaneous Tricuspid Valve Reconstruction Through Partial Upper Sternotomy</article-title><source>Artif Organs</source><year>2017</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27862075</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Acker</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atluri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Dealing with surgical left ventricular assist device complications</article-title><source>J Thorac Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2158</fpage><lpage>2164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26793336</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mega</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group><comment>ST elevation myocardial infarction: management. In: Mann DL, Zipes DP, Libby P, Bonow RO, editors. Braunwald&#x02019;s heart disease: a textbook of cardiovascular medicine. 10<sup>th</sup> ed. Philadelphia: Elsevier Saunders, 2015: 1095&#x02013;1154</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Galve</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garcia-Del-Castillo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evangelista</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Batlle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Permanyer-Miralda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soler-Soler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pericardial effusion in the course of myocardial infarction: incidence, natural history, and clinical relevance</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1986</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3943164</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ajluni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Popma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bittl</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eigler</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Safian</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitlow</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Increased coronary perforation in the new device era. Incidence, classification, management, and outcome</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1994</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>2725</fpage><lpage>2730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7994814</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Widimsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gregor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pericardial involvement during the course of myocardial infarction. A long-term clinical and echocardiographic study</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>1995</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7606999</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Imazio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Management of pericardial effusion</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1186</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23125278</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Imazio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bar&#x000f3;n-Esquivias</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bogaert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brucato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gueret</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klingel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lionis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maisch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayosi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pavie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Risti&#x00107;</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sabat&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Tenas M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seferovic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swedberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomkowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>2015 ESC Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Management of Pericardial Diseases</article-title><source>Rev Esp Cardiol (Engl Ed)</source><year>2015</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26675200</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lazaros</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Imazio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brucato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tousoulis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Untying the Gordian knot of pericardial diseases: A pragmatic approach</article-title><source>Hellenic J Cardiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27894950</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kohmoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Late bleeding from right internal mammary artery after HeartMate left ventricular assist device implantation</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15276550</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>den</surname><given-names>Exter PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beeres</surname><given-names>SLMA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eikenboom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klok</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Anticoagulant treatment and bleeding complications in patients with left ventricular assist devices</article-title><source>Expert Rev Cardiovasc Ther</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32449431</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>AHRQ</surname></name>
</person-group><comment>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. [cited 20 January 2025] Available from: <uri xlink:href="http://www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/nis/nisdbdocumentation.jsp">www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/db/nation/nis/nisdbdocumentation.jsp</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Left Ventricular Assist Device (LVAD) in Singapore: A Nation's 10 Year Experience</article-title><source>J Heart Lung Transpl</source><year>2020</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>S393</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zalawadiya</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindenfeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiSalvo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Rapid diagnosis of cardiac tamponade using pulsatility index variability in a patient with a HeartWare ventricular assist device</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2015</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>e387</fpage><lpage>e388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25825401</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Akin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Struijs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caliskan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Case Report: Early Identification of Subclinical Cardiac Tamponade in a Patient With a Left Ventricular Assist Device by the Use of Sublingual Microcirculatory Imaging: A New Diagnostic Imaging Tool?</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>818063</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402532</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Al</surname><given-names>Shakaki M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dell'Aquila</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rukosujew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Symptoms of massive cardiac tamponade during support of biventricular assist device</article-title><source>Int J Artif Organs</source><year>2018</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29558840</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ashikhmina</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaff</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinak</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dearani</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suri</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orszulak</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundt</surname><given-names>TM 3rd</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Pericardial effusion after cardiac surgery: risk factors, patient profiles, and contemporary management</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20103217</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cotts</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>EC Jr</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naftel</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirklin</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Predictors of hospital length of stay after implantation of a left ventricular assist device: an analysis of the INTERMACS registry</article-title><source>J Heart Lung Transplant</source><year>2014</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24819987</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Briasoulis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chehab</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>In-hospital Outcomes of Left Ventricular Assist Devices (LVAD) Patients Undergoing Noncardiac Surgery</article-title><source>ASAIO J</source><year>2021</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501823</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data sharing statement</title><p>Data was de-identified. No additional data available.</p></sec></back></article>