<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WJC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>World Journal of Cardiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-8462</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Baishideng Publishing Group Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12186171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jWJC.v17.i6.eid106717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4330/wjc.v17.i6.106717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-manuscript">106717</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Retrospective Cohort Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Beyond initial recovery: Heart failure with transient <italic>vs</italic> sustained improvement in left ventricular ejection fraction</article-title><alt-title>Kaddoura R <italic>et al</italic>. Patients with HF and persistent improvement in EF</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaddoura</surname><given-names>Rasha</given-names></name><aff>Department of Pharmacy, Heart Hospital, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar. <email>rasha.kaddoura@gmail.com</email></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chapra</surname><given-names>Ammar</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Heart Hospital, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Jassim</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Heart Hospital, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Izham</surname><given-names>Mohamed</given-names></name><aff>Department of Clinical Pharmacy and Practice College of Pharmacy, QU Health Sector, Qatar University, Doha 2713, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Rajvir</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology Research, Heart Hospital, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alsadi</surname><given-names>Haisam</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Amri</surname><given-names>Maha</given-names></name><aff>Department of Pharmacy, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamamyh</surname><given-names>Tahseen</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fallouh</surname><given-names>Manar</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elasad</surname><given-names>Farras</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelghani</surname><given-names>Mohamed</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alsaadi Alyafei</surname><given-names>Sumaya</given-names></name><aff>Department of Pharmacy, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Badr</surname><given-names>Amr</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Ashfaq</given-names></name><aff>Department of Cardiology, Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha 3050, Qatar</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Co-corresponding authors: Rasha Kaddoura and Ammar Chapra.</p><p>Author contributions: Kaddoura R, Chapra A, Shah J, Izham M, Singh R, Alsadi H, Al-Amri M, Hamamyh T, Fallouh M, Elasad F, Abdelghani M, Alsaadi Alyafei S, Badr A, and Patel A made a substantial, direct, and intellectual contribution to the work and approved it for publication; Kaddoura R and Chapra A contributed equally to this article and are the co-first authors of this manuscript; All authors thoroughly reviewed and endorsed the final manuscript.</p><p>Corresponding author: Rasha Kaddoura, Department of Pharmacy, Heart Hospital, Hamad Medical Corporation, Al-Rumailah, Doha 3050, Qatar. <email>rasha.kaddoura@gmail.com</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>106717</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;The Author(s) 2025. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is an open-access article that was selected by an in-house editor and fully peer-reviewed by external reviewers. It is distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <uri xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/Licenses/by-nc/4.0/</uri></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>BACKGROUND</title><p>There is no available data about the trajectory of heart failure (HF) with improved ejection fraction (EF) and patient clinical outcomes in Qatar.</p></sec><sec><title>AIM</title><p>To explore the difference in characteristics and outcomes between patients with transient and sustained improvement in left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) and to determine the independent predictors for sustained improvement in LVEF.</p></sec><sec><title>METHODS</title><p>This is a retrospective cohort study that was conducted at the advanced HF clinic of a tertiary care hospital in Qatar between January 2017 and December 2018. This study included adult patients with improved LVEF and had at least three echocardiographic studies. The patients were divided into two groups: HF with transient improvement in EF (HFtimpEF) and HF with sustained improvement in EF (HFsimpEF).</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of 175 patients with HF and improved EF were included. Among them 136 (77.7%) patients showed sustained improvement in LVEF. The remaining patients with HFtimpEF were predominantly males [37 (94.9%) <italic>vs</italic> 101 (74.3%), <italic>P</italic> = 0.005] with a higher incidence of ischemic cardiomyopathy [32 (82.1%) <italic>vs</italic> 68 (50.4%), <italic>P</italic> = 0.002], dyslipidemia [24 (61.5%) <italic>vs</italic> 54 (39.7%), <italic>P</italic> = 0.03], and hypertension [34 (87.2%) <italic>vs</italic> 93 (68.4%), <italic>P</italic> = 0.03] than those with HFsimpEF. The latter experienced significantly lower rates of hospitalization [39 (28.7%) <italic>vs</italic> 20 (51.3%), <italic>P</italic> = 0.01] and diagnosis of new cardiovascular conditions during the follow-up (<italic>e.g.</italic>, acute coronary syndrome, stroke, decompensated HF, and atrial fibrillation) [14 (10.3%) <italic>vs</italic> 10 (25.6%), <italic>P</italic> = 0.03] without a difference in emergency department visits or in-hospital death. Sustained improvement in LVEF was positively associated with being female [adjusted odds ratio (aOR) = 6.8, 95% confidence interval (CI): 1.4-32.3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.02], having non-ischemic etiology of HF (aOR = 3.1, 95%CI: 1.03-9.3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04), and using a mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist (aOR = 7.0, 95%CI: 1.50-31.8, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01).</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Patients with HFsimpEF experienced significantly lower rates of hospitalization and diagnosis of new cardiovascular conditions than patients with HFtimpEF. Sustained improvement in LVEF was positively associated with being a female, having non-ischemic etiology of HF, and using a mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Asia</kwd><kwd>Cardiomyopathy</kwd><kwd>Improved ejection fraction</kwd><kwd>Middle East</kwd><kwd>Qatar</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>
<bold>Core Tip:</bold> Our study reported observations from a population with heart failure in Qatar, a Middle Eastern country that is usually underrepresented in major clinical trials. This study was the first in the Middle East to characterize the clinical features and outcomes of patients with heart failure who demonstrate either sustained or temporary improvement in left ventricular ejection fraction.</p><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Heart failure (HF) remains one of the key causes of cardiovascular mortality[<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The current guidelines propose stratifying patients in phenotypes based on left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) to provide individualized care[<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Guideline-directed medical therapy in HF with reduced EF (HFrEF) has resulted in improvements in cardiac function and left ventricular reverse remodeling[<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Several studies have shown that these patients with HF and improved EF (HFimpEF) have a distinct HF phenotype and may carry favorable clinical outcomes[<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Yet this improvement is not always sustained; reverse remodeling is often accompanied by detrimental neurohormonal changes that can precipitate fluctuations in EF[<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This can lead to variations in EF over time and highlights the importance of longitudinal assessment of EF to further sub-stratify patients with HFimpEF into sustained improvement and transient improvement. This distinction has led to the need to further subclassify HFimpEF as HF with sustained improvement in EF (HFsimpEF) or HF with transient improvement in EF (HFtimpEF).</p><p>The factors that determine whether patients with HFrEF go on to become HFsimpEF or HFtimpEF has been an area of interest yet poorly studied. There is also a need to assess the long-term outcomes and prognosis of these patients. There is a lack of available data on the trajectory of HFimpEF and patient clinical outcomes in the Middle East. Hence, this study was conducted to explore several aspects related to patients with HFimpEF and their sustained improvement in LVEF. The hypothesis was that patients with sustained improvement in LVEF would have better clinical outcomes compared with those with transient improvement building on preliminary findings from previous studies exploring outcomes of patients with HFimpEF, who showed a generally favorable prognosis[<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The main objective of this study was to explore the difference in characteristics and outcomes between patients with transient and sustained improvement in LVEF and to determine the independent predictors for sustained improvement in LVEF.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>This was a retrospective cohort study that was conducted at the advanced HF clinic in a tertiary care hospital in Qatar between January 1, 2017 and December 31, 2018. The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Heart Hospital and the Medical Research Center, approval No. MRC-01-20-139. An informed consent was waived due to the retrospective nature of the study. The study was in line with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki, Good Clinical Practice and the laws and regulations of the Ministry of Public Health in Qatar. This study included all adult patients (&#x02265; 18 years) who were initially diagnosed with HFrEF, defined as LVEF &#x0003c; 40.0% at baseline, who demonstrated an initial improvement in LVEF and had at least three echocardiographic studies from their initial visit to the clinic.</p><p>The study population was selected from our previously published study that described the characteristics of patients with HFrEF who had improvement in their LVEF and analyzed the independent predictors of LVEF improvement. Our previous study screened all patients who visited the advanced HF clinic during the study period and included adult patients aged 18 years or older with a diagnosis of HFrEF and who had two echocardiographic examinations performed at least 6 months apart[<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>For the current study, all patients had a first (or baseline) echocardiogram (Echo-1) where the diagnosis of HFrEF was established and showed improvement in LVEF of at least 1.0% on the second echocardiogram (Echo-2) performed at least six months after Echo-1. Hence, Echo-2 would identify the HFimpEF cohort. The specific cutoff values for the improvement in LVEF have not been established yet by the international guidelines[<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and patients with improvement of any magnitude were included. A third echocardiogram (Echo-3) at least 12 months after from Echo-2 was included to distinguish patients with transient or sustained improvement in LVEF. An increase in LVEF by at least 1.0% in both the Echo-2 and the Echo-3 compared to the Echo-1 was defined as sustained improvement in EF (<italic>i.e.</italic> HFsimpEF). An initial improvement in LVEF of at least 1.0% in the Echo-2 followed by any reworsening of LVEF or lack of further improvement in the Echo-3 was defined as having transient improvement in EF (<italic>i.e.</italic> HFtimpEF). Thus, the patients were divided into two groups: HFtimpEF and HFsimpEF.</p><p>Furthermore, the improvement in LVEF was considered large if the increase or change in LVEF (&#x02206; LVEF) was 10.0% or more and modest if &#x02206; LVEF was 1.0%-9.0%[<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. A subgroup analysis for the patients with an initial large LVEF improvement (<italic>i.e.</italic> the difference between Echo-2 and Echo-1 of &#x02265; 10.0%) was conducted to compare the patients with HFtimpEF and HFsimpEF.</p><p>LVEF was measured using the Simpson biplane method, unless the Simpson method was not possible. This study excluded patients with specific cardiomyopathies (<italic>e.g.</italic>, hypertrophic, infiltrative, restrictive, stress-induced, or chemotherapy-induced), primary right-sided disease, congenital heart disease as the etiology of HF, cardiac transplant, left ventricular assist device, or primary valvular disease.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p>Within the specified study duration, 582 patients with HFrEF underwent at least two echocardiograms. Of them, 175 patients (30.1%) showed any improvement in LVEF (<italic>i.e.</italic> &#x02265; 1.0%) between Echo-1 and Echo-2 and who had a second follow-up echocardiogram (<italic>i.e.</italic> Echo-3) performed at least 12 months after Echo-2. Among them, 136 patients (77.7%) showed sustained improvement in LVEF on Echo-3 while the remaining had reworsening of the LVEF (<italic>i.e.</italic> had transient improvement).</p><p>Patients with HFtimpEF were predominantly males (94.9% <italic>vs</italic> 74.3%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.005) with ischemic cardiomyopathy (82.1% <italic>vs</italic> 50.4%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.002). There were no differences between the groups in terms of age, body mass index, or duration of HF diagnosis. Patients with HFtimpEF had a higher incidence of dyslipidemia (61.5% <italic>vs</italic> 39.7%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03) and hypertension (87.2% <italic>vs</italic> 68.4, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03) than those with HFsimpEF.</p><p>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents details of baseline characteristics. At baseline, there were no differences between the groups in terms of blood pressure measurements, heart rate values, and the presence of left bundle branch block.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of the included patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Transient improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 39)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sustained improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 136)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.15 &#x000b1; 11.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.51 &#x000b1; 13.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.36 &#x000b1; 5.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.49 &#x000b1; 7.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (94.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (74.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">HF etiology</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (82.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (50.4)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dilated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (42.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of HF diagnosis, mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05 &#x000b1; 3.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.79 &#x000b1; 4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Comorbidities </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyslipidemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (61.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (39.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (87.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (68.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (71.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (66.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrial fibrillation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (20.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (18.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventricular arrhythmia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (13.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CVA/TIA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal impairment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (43.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (25.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (27.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep apnea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic lung disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (15.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (15.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dementia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothyroidism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperthyroidism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are presented as <italic>n</italic> (%). BMI: Body mass index; CVA: Cerebrovascular accident; HF: Heart failure; PAD: Peripheral artery disease; SD: Standard deviation; TIA: Transient ischemic attack.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Similarly, there was no difference in the previous parameter measurements between the groups at follow-up except for the heart rate, which was significantly lower in patients with HFsimpEF [72.84 &#x000b1; 12.90 <italic>vs</italic> 79.41 &#x000b1; 15.45 beats per minute (bpm), <italic>P</italic> = 0.02] as shown in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Blood test parameters did not differ between the two groups at baseline and follow-up except for the estimated glomerular filtration rate, which was significantly higher in the sustained improvement group at both baseline (79.68 &#x000b1; 33.27 <italic>vs</italic> 66.47 &#x000b1; 27.79 mL/minute, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03) and follow-up (70.35 &#x000b1; 29.24 <italic>vs</italic> 59.89 &#x000b1; 28.49 mL/minute, <italic>P</italic> = 0.05) (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Vital signs and electrocardiographic measures of the included patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Transient improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 39)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sustained improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 136)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Baseline (Echo-1), mean &#x000b1; SD</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systolic BP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.38 &#x000b1; 22.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.30 &#x000b1; 20.1 (<italic>n</italic> = 134)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diastolic BP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.64 &#x000b1; 12.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.97 &#x000b1; 12.99 (<italic>n</italic> = 134)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate (bpm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.43 &#x000b1; 18.02 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.69 &#x000b1; 19.12 (<italic>n</italic> = 132)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Achieved target BP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (64.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sinus rhythm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (90.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (86.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LBBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (14.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (17.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QRS (ms), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.45 &#x000b1; 26.29 (<italic>n</italic> = 29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.43 &#x000b1; 44.04 (<italic>n</italic> = 129)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTc (ms), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">468.86 &#x000b1; 43.48 (<italic>n</italic> = 29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">462.84 &#x000b1; 52.19 (<italic>n</italic> = 109)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Second follow-up (Echo-3), mean &#x000b1; SD</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systolic BP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.87 &#x000b1; 21.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.47 &#x000b1; 98.18 (<italic>n</italic> = 129)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diastolic BP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.85 &#x000b1; 13.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.81 &#x000b1; 11.49 (<italic>n</italic> = 129)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate (bpm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.41 &#x000b1; 15.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.84 &#x000b1; 12.90 (<italic>n</italic> = 128)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Achieved target BP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (69.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sinus rhythm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (89.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (88.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LBBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (17.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QRS (ms), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.00 &#x000b1; 26.87 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.07 &#x000b1; 26.34 (<italic>n</italic> = 120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTc (ms), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">455.08 &#x000b1; 31.57 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">448.91 &#x000b1; 42.92 (<italic>n</italic> = 120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are presented as <italic>n</italic> (%). Echo-1: First (or baseline) echocardiogram; BP: Blood pressure; bpm: Beats per minute; LBBB: Left bundle branch block; QTc: Corrected QT interval; QRS: QRS complex duration; Echo-3: Third echocardiogram; SD: Standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Laboratory blood tests of the included patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Transient improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 39)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sustained improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 136)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Baseline (Echo-1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT-pro-BNP (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5106.63 &#x000b1; 6035.19 (<italic>n</italic> = 27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4730.48 &#x000b1; 6792.82 (<italic>n</italic> = 93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin (g/dL) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.16 &#x000b1; 2.22 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.20 &#x000b1; 12.89 (<italic>n</italic> = 132)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.16 &#x000b1; 4.53 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 &#x000b1; 4.17 (<italic>n</italic> = 133)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.03 &#x000b1; 56.87 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.55 &#x000b1; 114.84 (<italic>n</italic> = 132)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">eGFR (mL/min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.47 &#x000b1; 27.79 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.68 &#x000b1; 33.27 (<italic>n</italic> = 132)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38 &#x000b1; 2.34 (<italic>n</italic> = 26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.54 &#x000b1; 2.19 (<italic>n</italic> = 102)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-C (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69 &#x000b1; 0.92 (<italic>n</italic> = 35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57 &#x000b1; 1.18 (<italic>n</italic> = 120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.87 &#x000b1; 3.69 (<italic>n</italic> = 10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.43 &#x000b1; 6.49 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSAT (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.77 &#x000b1; 5.42 (<italic>n</italic> = 10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37 &#x000b1; 15.74 (<italic>n</italic> = 35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (ug/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325.75 &#x000b1; 347.95 (<italic>n</italic> = 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.50 &#x000b1; 277.71 (<italic>n</italic> = 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSH (pmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#x000b1; 1.51 (<italic>n</italic> = 22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38 &#x000b1; 2.18 (<italic>n</italic> = 92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4 (mIU/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.51 &#x000b1; 1.70 (<italic>n</italic> = 23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.87 &#x000b1; 3.58 (<italic>n</italic> = 87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Second follow-up (Echo-3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT-pro-BNP (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7672.15 &#x000b1; 13459.32 (<italic>n</italic> = 27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3184.52 &#x000b1; 6564.79 (<italic>n</italic> = 81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin (g/dL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.23 &#x000b1; 2.25 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.87 &#x000b1; 2.08 (<italic>n</italic> = 120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.28 &#x000b1; 7.27 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.50 &#x000b1; 8.94 (<italic>n</italic> = 125)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142.84 &#x000b1; 88.49 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.25 &#x000b1; 126.01 (<italic>n</italic> = 128)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">eGFR (mL/min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.89 &#x000b1; 28.49 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.35 &#x000b1; 29.24 (<italic>n</italic> = 127)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.66 &#x000b1; 2.04 (<italic>n</italic> = 33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90 &#x000b1; 4.88 (<italic>n</italic> = 103)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-C (mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 &#x000b1; 0.99 (<italic>n</italic> = 33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03 &#x000b1; 0.93 (<italic>n</italic> = 99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (&#x000b5;mol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.64 &#x000b1; 4.33 (<italic>n</italic> = 18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.23 &#x000b1; 6.24 (<italic>n</italic> = 41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSAT (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.44 &#x000b1; 8.69 (<italic>n</italic> = 18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.48 &#x000b1; 16.53 (<italic>n</italic> = 41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (ug/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276.17 &#x000b1; 489.76 (<italic>n</italic> = 14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244.41 &#x000b1; 429.58 (<italic>n</italic> = 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSH (pmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 &#x000b1; 1.45 (<italic>n</italic> = 22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22 &#x000b1; 3.12 (<italic>n</italic> = 83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4 (mIU/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.73 &#x000b1; 2.23 (<italic>n</italic> = 19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.05 &#x000b1; 3.86 (<italic>n</italic> = 73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SD. Echo-1: First (or baseline) echocardiogram; eGFR: Estimated glomerular filtration rate; HbA1c: Glycated hemoglobin; Echo-3: Third echocardiogram; LDL-C: Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; NT-proBNP: N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide; T4: Thyroxine hormone; TSAT: Transferrin saturation; TSH: Thyroid-stimulating hormone.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Echocardiographic parameters</title><p>Upon initial diagnosis, mean LVEF was significantly lower in the sustained improvement group (26.77 &#x000b1; 7.05% <italic>vs</italic> 30.56 &#x000b1; 6.95%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.003) with no difference in other echocardiographic parameters. At follow-up, LVEF became significantly higher in the sustained improvement group (40.18 &#x000b1; 0.12 <italic>vs</italic> 28.46 &#x000b1; 6.59%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) with significant improvement in other parameters such as lower left atrium volume index (34.30 &#x000b1; 11.26 <italic>vs</italic> 41.41 &#x000b1; 12.92 mL/m<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.003), left ventricular end-systolic diameter (4.50 &#x000b1; 0.95 <italic>vs</italic> 4.99 &#x000b1; 0.75 cm, <italic>P</italic> = 0.004), and right ventricular systolic pressure (RVSP; 33.10 &#x000b1; 11.82 <italic>vs</italic> 38.78 &#x000b1; 14.61 mmHg, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04). The initial improvement in LVEF (between Echo-1 and Echo-2) at almost 20 months of follow-up did not differ in magnitude between the groups (Echo-2 - Echo-1: &#x02206; LVEF: 9.54 &#x000b1; 7.69% <italic>vs</italic> 8.05 &#x000b1; 6.53%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.27). After another 20 months of follow-up, the overall improvement in LVEF differed significantly between the groups (Echo-3 - Echo-1: &#x02206; LVEF: 13.43% &#x000b1; 9.09% <italic>vs</italic> 2.10% &#x000b1; 5.05%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Echocardiographic parameters of the included patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Transient improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 39)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sustained improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 136)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Baseline (Echo-1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVEF (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.56 &#x000b1; 6.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.77 &#x000b1; 7.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average E/e&#x02019;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.01 &#x000b1; 5.88 (<italic>n</italic> = 20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.52 &#x000b1; 5.78 (<italic>n</italic> = 67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA volume index (mL/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.97 &#x000b1; 12.51 (<italic>n</italic> = 25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.09 &#x000b1; 11.35 (<italic>n</italic> = 82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVEDD (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76 &#x000b1; 0.79 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70 &#x000b1; 4.17 (<italic>n</italic> = 130)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVESD (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76 &#x000b1; 0.84 (<italic>n</italic> = 34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.08 &#x000b1; 0.89 (<italic>n</italic> = 115)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RVSP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.46 &#x000b1; 11.06 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.35 &#x000b1; 12.89 (<italic>n</italic> = 130)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Second follow-up (Echo-3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVEF (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.46 &#x000b1; 6.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.18 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average E/e&#x02019;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.12 &#x000b1; 5.46 (<italic>n</italic> = 19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.08 &#x000b1; 5.86 (<italic>n</italic> = 77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA volume index (mL/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.41 &#x000b1; 12.92 (<italic>n</italic> = 31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.30 &#x000b1; 11.26 (<italic>n</italic> = 114)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVEDD (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06 &#x000b1; 0.62 (<italic>n</italic> = 38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81 &#x000b1; 0.89 (<italic>n</italic> = 134)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVESD (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.99 &#x000b1; 0.75 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50 &#x000b1; 0.95 (<italic>n</italic> = 131)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RVSP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.78 &#x000b1; 14.61 (<italic>n</italic> = 37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.10 &#x000b1; 11.82 (<italic>n</italic> = 129)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVEF (Echo-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.59 &#x000b1; 7.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.33 &#x000b1; 7.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02206; LVEF (Echo-2 - Echo-1) (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.05 &#x000b1; 6.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.54 &#x000b1; 7.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration between Echo-1 and Echo-2 (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.82 &#x000b1; 26.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.24 &#x000b1; 21.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02206; LVEF (Echo-3 - Echo-1) (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.10 &#x000b1; 5.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.43 &#x000b1; 9.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration between Echo-2 and Echo-3 (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.49 &#x000b1; 13.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.79 &#x000b1; 23.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SD. Echo-1: First (or baseline) echocardiogram; Echo-2: Second echocardiographic examination at first follow-up; Echo-3: Third echocardiographic; LA: Left atrium/atrial; LVEDD: Left ventricular end-diastolic diameter; LVEF: Left ventricular ejection fraction; LVESD: Left ventricular ejection fraction; RVSP: Right ventricular systolic pressure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Medications</title><p>At the time of diagnosis, more than half of the patients in both groups were on beta-blockers and renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system inhibitors without a difference between the two groups. Significantly more patients in the sustained improvement group were on mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists (MRA; 21.3% <italic>vs</italic> 5.1%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.02). At the second follow-up (Echo 3), the use of guideline-directed medical therapy for HF increased in both groups without a difference between them (Table <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Medications at baseline and at second follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Transient improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 39)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sustained improvement (<italic>n</italic> = 136)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Baseline (Echo-1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta-blockers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (48.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (57.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACEI/ARB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (64.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (59.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (21.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diuretics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (45.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDZ/ISDN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivabradine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digoxin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplatelet therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (61.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (57.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LLA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (61.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (52.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (IV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inotropes (hospital)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Second follow-up (Echo-3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta-blockers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (92.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (95.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACEI/ARB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (76.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (80.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (40.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diuretics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (79.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDZ/ISDN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivabradine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digoxin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplatelet therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (87.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (73.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid-lowering agents</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (92.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (80.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (IV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inotropes (hospital)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Echo-1: First (or baseline) echocardiogram; Echo-3: Third echocardiographic; ACEI: Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors; ARB: Angiotensin receptor blockers; HDZ: Hydralazine; ISDN: Isosorbide dinitrate; IV: Intravenous; MRA: Mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists; LLA: Lipid lowering agents.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Clinical outcomes</title><p>Patients with sustained improvement in LVEF demonstrated a significantly lower rate of all-cause hospitalization compared with those with transient improvement [39 (28.7%) <italic>vs</italic> 20 (51.3%) patients, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01]. Among all the hospitalizations, 28 were specifically due to HF with 16 occurring in the sustained improvement group and 12 in the transient improvement group. The incidence of developing new cardiovascular conditions during follow-up including acute coronary syndrome, stroke, decompensated HF, and atrial fibrillation, was also lower in the sustained improvement group [14 (10.3%) <italic>vs</italic> 10 (25.6%) patients, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03]. However, there was no statistically significant difference in the rates of emergency department visits [38 (27.9%) <italic>vs</italic> 16 (41.0%) patients, <italic>P</italic> = 0.12] or in-hospital deaths [6 (4.4%) <italic>vs</italic> 1 (2.6%) patient(s), <italic>P</italic> = 1.00] between the groups.</p><p>Multivariate nominal logistic regression analysis was performed to identify factors associated with sustained improvement in LVEF. Female sex [adjusted odds ratio (aOR) = 6.8, 95% confidence interval (CI): 1.4-32.3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.02], non-ischemic etiology of HF (aOR = 3.1, 95%CI: 1.03-9.3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04), and the use of MRA (aOR = 7.0, 95%CI: 1.50-31.8, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01) were significantly associated with sustained improvement of LVEF. Other factors such as age, hyperlipidemia, and hypertension did not show a significant association with sustained improvement (Table <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Multivariate nominal logistic regression analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Adjusted OR (95%CI)</bold>
<hr/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic>P</italic> value</bold>
<hr/>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age in years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.95-1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (1.4-32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">HF etiology</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dilated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (1.03-9.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (0.30-9.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.21-1.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.13-1.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRA use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (1.50-31.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CI: Confidence interval; OR: Odds ratio; HF: Heart failure; MRA: Mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Subgroup analysis</title><p>A subgroup analysis was performed to identify the characteristics and outcomes of patients with HFimpEF and a large improvement in LVEF between the baseline (Echo-1) and first follow-up echocardiogram (Echo-2). Seventy-one (40.6%) patients had a large improvement in LVEF (<italic>i.e.</italic> &#x02206; LVEF &#x02265; 10.0%) at Echo-2. Of them, 14 (19.3%) and 57 (80.3%) patients showed transient and sustained improvement in LVEF, respectively. Patients with transient improvement were significantly more dyslipidemic (71.4% <italic>vs</italic> 35.1%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.014) and hypertensive (92.9% <italic>vs</italic> 61.4%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.024) with significantly lower heart rates (79.92 &#x000b1; 19.74 <italic>vs</italic> 94.18 &#x000b1; 21.11 bpm, <italic>P</italic> = 0.030) and RVSP values (29.24 &#x000b1; 7.29 <italic>vs</italic> 38.77 &#x000b1; 12.87 mmHg, <italic>P</italic> = 0.010) at baseline. The heart rate was significantly lower (81.14 &#x000b1; 15.37 <italic>vs</italic> 70.85 &#x000b1; 11.77 bpm, <italic>P</italic> = 0.032) in patients with sustained improvement at the second follow-up.</p><p>Guideline-directed medications for HF did not differ between the sustained and transient improvement subgroups. The clinical outcome findings of the subgroups were in line with the overall study findings. Patients with sustained improvement in LVEF experienced a significantly lower incidence of new cardiovascular conditions (28.6% <italic>vs</italic> 7.0%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.022) without a difference in the emergency department visits (35.7% <italic>vs</italic> 29.8%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.750) or in-hospital deaths (7.1% <italic>vs</italic> 5.3%, <italic>P</italic> = 1.000). However, there was a trend towards lower hospitalizations in those with sustained improvement (50.0% <italic>vs</italic> 22.8%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.054).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study explored the independent predictors for sustained improvement in LVEF at the advanced HF clinic in Qatar. One-quarter of our study population had reworsening in LVEF despite initial improvement. These patients with HFtimpEF were predominantly males with ischemic cardiomyopathy and higher incidence of hypertension and dyslipidemia compared with patients with HFsimpEF. The latter experienced significantly lower rates of hospitalization and diagnosis of new cardiovascular conditions during the follow-up. Sustained improvement of LVEF was positively associated with being a female, having a non-ischemic etiology of HF, and using MRA (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Characteristics and outcomes of patients with improved ejection fraction.</bold> AHFC: Advanced heart failure clinic; aOR: Adjusted odds ratio; Dec: December; ED: Emergency department; Echo 1: First (or baseline) echocardiogram; Echo 2: Second echocardiogram; Echo 3: Third echocardiogram; HF: Heart failure; ICM: Ischemic cardiomyopathy; LVEF: Left ventricular ejection fraction; LVEF1/3: LVEF at first (or baseline) echocardiogram/third echocardiogram; MRA: Mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists; NICM: Non-ischemic cardiomyopathy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="wjc-17-6-106717-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>Although the current diagnosis and management of HF depends on LVEF, it is important to consider that LVEF may vary over time. Many patients may erroneously be managed in the long-term as HFimpEF based on the initial improvement seen on their follow-up echocardiogram when in fact their LVEF may have later reworsened. This misclassification impacts their predicted mortality and hospitalizations. One study found that one-quarter of all patients in their cohort, similar to ours, had subsequent deterioration in their LVEF despite initial improvement[<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This finding likely underpredicts the long-term course of LVEF owing to the lack of routine follow-up echocardiograms conducted in clinical practice once the patient is labelled to have recovered LVEF.</p><p>Currently, there is no consensus in the international guidelines on the exact cutoffs for LVEF improvement to define HFimpEF[<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Due to the small sample size, we included all patients who demonstrated any (rather than large) improvement in LVEF on their first follow-up echocardiogram (Echo-2). However, our study found that the average initial improvement of LVEF was approximately 10.0% (&#x02206; LVEF 8.1%-9.5%). Furthermore, the findings from subgroup analysis of patients who had an initial large improvement in LVEF of 10.0% or more were not different from the findings of the overall population.</p><p>Patients with HFsimpEF made up 77.7% of the total cohort in our study. Similarly, in a study that enrolled patients with dilated cardiomyopathy (<italic>n</italic> = 188), 46.0% of them showed an initial improvement in their LVEF (from 26.0 &#x000b1; 7.0% to 48.0 &#x000b1; 10.0%). At 36 months of follow-up after Echo-2, most patients had Echo-3 (<italic>n</italic> = 183), which also showed sustained EF improvement in 70.0% of patients[<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In contrast the reported frequency of HFtimpEF varies between 11.0% and 38.0% in prior studies[<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This variation is thought to be due to different definitions of LVEF reworsening and variations in the timing and length of the follow-up echocardiograms. This led to increased rates of reported reworsening as the follow-up period was extended.</p><p>In our study patients with HFsimpEF showed concomitant improvement in echocardiographic parameters such as left atrium volume index, left ventricular end-systolic diameter, and RVSP despite having an initially lower LVEF than those with HFtimpEF. Similar findings have been observed in a study by Blechman <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In our study patients with HFsimpEF had a lower mean heart rate than those with HFtimpEF at follow-up, highlighting the continued use of beta-blockers despite initial improvement in patients with HFrEF. However, another study found no significant association between continued beta blocker therapy and sustained improvement in LVEF[<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Hence, further studies are needed to confirm the long-term benefit of beta-blockers in HFsimpEF, especially to determine whether the benefits exist beyond just the lowering of heart rate.</p><p>Understanding the factors that lead to long-term sustained <italic>vs</italic> transient improvement followed by deterioration in LVEF is crucial for individualizing patient care. By recognizing the characteristics of such patients in each group, we can improve risk stratification and identify the vulnerable patients who may benefit from more aggressive treatment approaches. Currently, there is substantial evidence on the characteristics and outcomes of patients with HFimpEF. It is also known that patients with recovered EF have an improved prognosis after recovery[<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, it is not an entirely benign outlook. Despite experiencing improvement in their LVEF, these patients tend to have increased rates of all-cause hospitalizations and hospitalizations for HF[<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Hence, HFimpEF should not be considered recovered. However, data is lacking about whether it is due to reworsening of the LVEF or whether there is a difference in the characteristics and clinical outcomes between those with HFtimpEF and those with HFsimpEF.</p><p>Our patients with HFsimpEF had favorable outcomes in terms of hospitalization rates and diagnosis of new cardiovascular diseases without an impact on mortality. In contrary other studies demonstrated a significant impact on mortality. Park <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] demonstrated that LVEF can be a predictor of mortality and that a declining LVEF was associated with a two-fold higher mortality. Sustained improvement of LVEF was positively associated with being female, having non-ischemic etiology of HF, and using MRA in our study.</p><p>In a recent study by McElderry <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], who recruited 7070 patients with HFimpEF, White race (OR = 1.31, 95%CI: 1.17-1.48) and continued use of renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system inhibitors or angiotensin receptor-neprilysin inhibitor (ARNi) (OR = 1.13, 95%CI: 1.03-1.25) were associated with increased odds of maintaining an improved LVEF. Male sex (OR = 0.84, 95%CI: 0.76-0.93), use of loop diuretics (OR = 0.79, 95%CI: 0.72-0.87), atrial fibrillation (OR = 0.85, 95%CI: 0.77-0.94), and history of myocardial infarction (OR = 0.76, 95%CI: 0.67-0.85) were correlated with a decline in LVEF over time in patients with HFimpEF[<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Another study (<italic>n</italic> = 183) concluded that sustained improvement in LVEF was associated with a favorable long-term prognosis and reported the factors that were associated with the sustained improvement in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy. Pregnancy or chemotherapy-associated cardiomyopathy were associated with sustained improvement, but family history of dilated cardiomyopathy and long-standing disease had worse prognoses. Independent predictors of sustained improvement included pregnancy-associated disease, shorter disease duration, left ventricular hypertrophy by echocardiogram, and baseline LVEF of &#x02264; 25.0%. There was no difference in terms of medical therapy between the groups (HFsimpEF and HFtimpEF). However, beta-blocker dose was significantly higher in those with HFsimpEF. Interestingly, to predict sustained improvement in LVEF, the investigators established a score that assigned one point to each of the following variables: (1) Short disease duration (&#x0003c; 3.0 years) and no familial cardiomyopathy; (2) Baseline LVEF of &#x02264; 25.0%; (3) Pregnancy-associated presentation; and (4) Left ventricular wall thickness of &#x02265; 12.0 mm. A score of &#x02265; 3.0 reliably predicted sustained improvement in LVEF in 91.0% of patients[<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It is important to recognize in our study that patients with pregnancy-associated cardiomyopathy were excluded. Yet most of our patients exhibited sustained improvement underscoring the importance of treatment-related factors in LVEF improvement.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, only a few studies have investigated the factors associated with sustained improvement in LVEF despite the accumulating studies examining the characteristics of patients with HFimpEF[<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Enzan <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] concluded that beta-blocker therapy prevented the deterioration of LVEF (<italic>i.e.</italic> decrease in LVEF &#x02265; 10.0%) in patients with recovered dilated cardiomyopathy (<italic>i.e.</italic> mean LVEF was 49.3 &#x000b1; 8.2%) at the 2-year follow-up (OR = 0.77, 95%CI: 0.63-0.95; <italic>P</italic> = 0.013). Chen <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] prospectively determined the safety of withdrawing spironolactone in patients with idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy with improved LVEF (<italic>i.e.</italic> mean 44.0%-47.0%). Withdrawing spironolactone increased the likelihood of relapse (<italic>i.e.</italic> reduction in LVEF &#x0003c; 10.0%) within 12 months (relative risk = 4.31, 95%CI: 1.67-11.11; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001).</p><p>Halliday <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] in their pilot study concluded that tapering medications gradually can lead to relapses in patients with recovered dilated cardiomyopathy. Additionally, recent research identified echocardiographic parameters, namely global longitudinal strain (GLS), that could predict sustained improvement in LVEF. Adamo <italic>et al</italic>[<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported that a normal GLS was an indicator of maintaining a stable LVEF after its recovery and abnormal GLS was a predictor of a decrease in LVEF during follow-up. However, the authors defined a reduced LVEF as &#x0003c; 50.0%.</p><p>The results of our study should be interpreted in the context of the following potential limitations. Firstly, the retrospective observational design of the study may have introduced confounding by unmeasured variables, potentially affecting the reported associations between baseline characteristics and improvement in LVEF. Secondly, we defined improvement and sustained improvement in LVEF as 1.0% or greater on follow-up echocardiograms regardless of a specific cutoff for the final LVEF. Hence, interpreting the results must account for the inter-echocardiographer variability in the reporting of LVEF on each follow-up and must recognize the limitation of echocardiography as an imaging modality (<italic>i.e.</italic> it may be unable to recognize small improvements in LVEF of 1.0%). This has the potential to misclassify some patients between the two groups. Thirdly, the possibility of survival bias or lead-time bias cannot be fully excluded considering that patients who did not have a second follow-up echocardiogram (Echo-3) were excluded. Fourth, our study did not evaluate subjective measures of improvement to compare quality-of-life differences between HFsimpEF and HFtimpEF patients as such data were not available. It is also important to note that our study period concluded in 2018 when only a few of our patients were on an ARNi or a sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 inhibitors. This may result in potential underestimation of patients with long-term sustained improvement in LVEF considering their proven benefits in patients with HFrEF. Regarding clinical outcomes, our study investigated only the in-hospital death rates. Therefore, potential differences in the overall mortality rates between the groups remains to be elucidated. Finally, we did not evaluate other factors such as adherence to dietary recommendations, medication compliance, alcohol consumption, or smoking cessation, all of which can impact improvement in LVEF[<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>Despite these limitations, the key strength of our study was the inclusion of all patients from the largest tertiary care center for cardiovascular disease in Qatar, a country with a predominantly South East Asian and Middle Eastern/North African populations who are underrepresented in most HF studies. Other peripheral hospitals in Qatar share the same electronic medical records, hence the potential to miss a clinical outcome was reduced. Our study offers further baseline data for long-term longitudinal assessment of HFrEF patients with regular follow-up echocardiograms to prevent lack of recognition of HFtimpEF.</p><p>Further prospective studies are needed for the validation of the associated factors of improvement mentioned in this study to allow the creation of a risk stratification model and to identify patients at risk of reworsening LVEF to intensify their management strategy. In an era marked by extensive research demonstrating the benefits of ARNi and sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 in patients with HF, our study reported favorable outcomes despite the majority of patients not receiving these novel therapies. This highlights the need for future studies focusing on patients with improved LVEF who are treated with contemporary, guideline-directed HF therapies.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Patients with HFsimpEF experienced significantly lower rates of hospitalization and diagnosis of new cardiovascular conditions than patients with HFtimpEF. Sustained improvement in LVEF was positively associated with being female, having non-ischemic etiology of HF, and using an MRA.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>
<bold>Institutional review board statement:</bold> This study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of Hamad Medical Corporation Medical Research Center, approval No. MRC-01-20-139.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Informed consent statement:</bold> Patients were not required to give informed consent to the study because the analysis used anonymous data that were obtained after each patient agreed to treatment with verbal consent according to the usual standard of care.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflict-of-interest statement:</bold> All authors report no relevant conflicts of interest for this article.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>STROBE statement:</bold> The authors have read the STROBE Statement-checklist of items, and the manuscript was prepared and revised according to the STROBE Statement-checklist of items.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Invited article; Externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Peer-review model:</bold> Single blind</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Specialty type:</bold> Cardiac and cardiovascular systems</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Country of origin:</bold> Qatar</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Peer-review report&#x02019;s classification</bold>
</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Scientific Quality:</bold> Grade B</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Novelty:</bold> Grade C</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Creativity or Innovation:</bold> Grade C</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Scientific Significance:</bold> Grade D</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>P-Reviewer:</bold> Jameel ZI <bold>S-Editor:</bold> Bai Y <bold>L-Editor:</bold> Filipodia <bold>P-Editor:</bold> Wang WB</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of Heart Failure: A Contemporary Perspective</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1421</fpage><lpage>1434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33983838</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heidenreich</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bozkurt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colvin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deswal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drazner</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunlay</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fonarow</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayek</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khazanie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kittleson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nnacheta</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vardeny</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vest</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yancy</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group><collab>ACC/AHA Joint Committee Members</collab><article-title>2022 AHA/ACC/HFSA Guideline for the Management of Heart Failure: A Report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Joint Committee on Clinical Practice Guidelines</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2022</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>e895</fpage><lpage>e1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35363499</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mui</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Myocardial Tissue Reverse Remodeling After Guideline-Directed Medical Therapy in Idiopathic Dilated Cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>Circ Heart Fail</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e007944</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33185117</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Savarese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vedin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D'Amario</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Uijl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>CSP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence and Prognostic Implications of Longitudinal Ejection Fraction Change in Heart Failure</article-title><source>JACC Heart Fail</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30852236</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics, predictors, and outcomes of heart failure with improved ejection fraction</article-title><source>Int J Cardiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35339576</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mebazaa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Characteristics, Outcomes, and Treatment of Heart Failure With Improved Ejection Fraction</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e011077</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30845873</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Udelson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Heart Failure With Improved Ejection Fraction: Is it Possible to Escape One's Past?</article-title><source>JACC Heart Fail</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30098965</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Basuray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>French</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vorovich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sweitzer</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cappola</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Heart failure with recovered ejection fraction: clinical description, biomarkers, and outcomes</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2014</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>2380</fpage><lpage>2387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24799515</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartupee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Neurohormonal activation in heart failure with reduced ejection fraction</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cardiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27708278</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Prevalence and Prognosis of HFimpEF Developed From Patients With Heart Failure With Reduced Ejection Fraction: Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>757596</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34901217</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaddoura</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>MIM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alsadi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamamyh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fallouh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elasad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abdelghani</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alyafei</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Characteristics and Outcomes of Heart Failure Outpatients with Improvement in Ejection Fraction in Qatar</article-title><source>Heart Views</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40028242</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oommen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talluri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nizam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kohir</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aviles</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaisankar</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wannakuwatte</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Heart Failure With Improved Ejection Fraction: Prevalence, Predictors, and Guideline-Directed Medical Therapy</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>e61790</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38975458</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heikki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dommasch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>Thomsen PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinnecker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raatikainen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Exner</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Change in Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction Following First Myocardial Infarction and Outcome</article-title><source>JACC Clin Electrophysiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29798797</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de</surname><given-names>Groote P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fertin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duva</surname><given-names>Pentiah A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Go&#x000e9;minne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamblin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauters</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Long-term functional and clinical follow-up of patients with heart failure with recovered left ventricular ejection fraction after &#x003b2;-blocker therapy</article-title><source>Circ Heart Fail</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24563449</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blechman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freimark</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Predictors and outcome of sustained improvement in left ventricular function in dilated cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>Clin Cardiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25236761</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nabeta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inomata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naruke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koitabashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ako</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Dilated cardiomyopathy with re-worsening left ventricular ejection fraction</article-title><source>Heart Vessels</source><year>2019</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942977</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McElderry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalahasti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barzilai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brateanu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Factors Associated With Maintenance of an Improved Ejection Fraction: An Echocardiogram-Based Registry Study</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e031093</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37889194</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>K&#x000f8;ber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abdulla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Characteristics and prognosis of heart failure with improved compared with persistently reduced ejection fraction: A systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title><source>Eur J Prev Cardiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29313369</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mebazaa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Phenotyping Heart Failure According to the Longitudinal Ejection Fraction Change: Myocardial Strain, Predictors, and Outcomes</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e015009</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32519555</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Enzan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ide</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaku</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tohyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Funakoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Beta-Blocker Use Is Associated With Prevention of Left Ventricular Remodeling in Recovered Dilated Cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e019240</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34053244</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Outcomes of Spironolactone Withdrawal in Dilated Cardiomyopathy With Improved Ejection Fraction</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>725399</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34604354</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wassall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lota</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khalique</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newsome</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahneva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wage</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Venneri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tayal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midwinter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whiffin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dungu</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pantazis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baksi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pennell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JGF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Withdrawal of pharmacological treatment for heart failure in patients with recovered dilated cardiomyopathy (TRED-HF): an open-label, pilot, randomised trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2019</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429050</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adamo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Abnormal Global Longitudinal Strain Predicts Future Deterioration of Left Ventricular Function in Heart Failure Patients With a Recovered Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction</article-title><source>Circ Heart Fail</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e003788</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28559418</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Evangelista</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doering</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dracup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Usefulness of a history of tobacco and alcohol use in predicting multiple heart failure readmissions among veterans</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113409</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data sharing statement</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></back></article>