<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neuroimage: Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-9560</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37388455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10310067</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-9560(23)00019-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynirp.2023.100174</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100174</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring interhemispheric connectivity using the directional tract density patterns of the corpus callosum</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>Ali</given-names></name><email>ademir@mgh.harvard.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>H. Diana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Neurology, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Athinoula A. Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Charlestown, MA, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. 149 Thirteenth Street, Suite 10134, Charlestown, MA, 02129, USA. <email>ademir@mgh.harvard.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>100174</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>The corpus callosum (CC) is one of the most important interhemispheric white matter tracts that connects interrelated regions of the cerebral cortex. Its disruption has been investigated in previous studies and has been found to play an important role in several neurodegenerative disorders. Currently available methods to assess the interhemispheric connectivity of the CC have several limitations: i) they require the <italic>a priori</italic> identification of specific cortical regions as targets or seeds, ii) they are limited by the characterization of only small components of the structure, primarily voxels that constitute the mid-sagittal slice, and iii) they use global measures of microstructural integrity, which provide only limited characterization. In order to address some of these limitations, we developed a novel method that enables the characterization of white matter tracts covering the structure of CC, from the mid-sagittal plane to corresponding regions of cortex, using directional tract density patterns (dTDPs). We demonstrate that different regions of CC have distinctive dTDPs that reflect a unique regional topology. We conducted a pilot study using this approach to evaluate two different datasets collected from healthy subjects, and we demonstrate that this method is reliable, reproducible, and independent of diffusion acquisition parameters, suggesting its potential applicability to clinical applications.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0015"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">Novel diffusion-based measure to determine the directional tract density patterns of the corpus callosum (CC).</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">Accurate quantification of the connectivity of the CC to associated brain regions without specifying a priori destinations.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">Reproducible and reliable, supporting its use in evaluating interhemispheric connectivity in health and in disease.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Tract density imaging</kwd><kwd>Interhemispheric connectivity</kwd><kwd>Corpus callosum</kwd><kwd>Directional tract density pattern</kwd><kwd>Diffusion</kwd><kwd>Magnetic resonance imaging</kwd><kwd>Human subjects</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term id="pc_ETS61aDZoz">CC</term><def><p>Corpus callosum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_nJ6uPF8rYR">dTDP</term><def><p>Directional tract density pattern</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_rk6Gxk5EJJ">MRI</term><def><p>Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_IYPGNDjyoh">FA</term><def><p>Fractional anisotropy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_LbzZtjrKul">AD</term><def><p>Axial diffusivity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_KxM29smMAU">RD</term><def><p>Radial diffusivity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_LbZZjRnuLu">QCD</term><def><p>Quartile coefficient of dispersion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_qBoAxtjaNG">HHSD</term><def><p>Healthy human subjects dataset</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_rVMuuvz5DD">CDMD</term><def><p>Comprehensive diffusion MRI dataset</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="pc_pvHSja6doW">FOD</term><def><p>Fiber orientation distribution</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">The integrity of the corpus callosum (CC), the largest of the commissural white matter pathways in the brain, is critical for normal neurological functions. Its disruption has been associated with several neurological diseases, including Alzheimer's, Parkinson's, and Huntington's (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Nir et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Rosas et al., 2010</xref>), but because of its complex architecture, studies of the CC have been technically challenging. For example, anatomical studies have attempted to use distinct parcellation schemes to obtain thickness and/or volume measures of the CC (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Emsell et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Rosas et al., 2010</xref>). The brain-image atlases that have been used to reconstruct the structure, such as the one proposed by Julich (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Amunts et al., 2020</xref>) or the Johns Hopkins University diffusion-based white matter atlas (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mori and Crain, 2005</xref>) represent an average shape of the CC and require non-linear warping of the average shape to individual images, which pose technical challenges. The Hofer-Frahm scheme (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Hofer and Frahm, 2006</xref>) identifies five unique CC regions in humans based on the structural connectivity assessed by the diffusion tractography between cortical regions as the fibers pass through the mid-sagittal section. This approach has been used to evaluate differences in callosal topography (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Rosas et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Stezin et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Rusina et al., 2022</xref>) and has remained the standard for the anatomical evaluation of the CC. Although its applicability has already been established, that can practically be extended well beyond the mid-sagittal section.</p><p id="p0035">Other studies have instead used diffusion metrics, which characterize microstructural tissue properties including fractional anisotropy (FA), axial diffusivity (AD), and radial diffusivity (RD) (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Basser and Pierpaoli, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kingsley, 2006</xref>). In these instances, alterations in microstructural integrity have been typically associated with reductions in FA or increases in RD or AD (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2021</xref>), however, while they provide estimations about microstructural integrity, they primarily provide indirect information about macroscopic connectivity. Newer approaches, including the one proposed by <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al. (2019)</xref>, which uses very high diffusion gradients, enable the evaluation of axon diameter/density and have been suggested to be more sensitive and more closely associated with cognitive measures.</p><p id="p0040">Determining interhemispheric connectivity presents an even greater challenge. The interhemispheric connectivity of the CC has been estimated using cortical regions that have been <italic>a priori</italic> identified (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Rubinov and Sporns, 2010</xref>), but these regions have been defined as both target and source for tractography (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Russo et al., 2022</xref>), thereby limiting its true evaluation. In addition, the magnitude of the number of fibers traversing through the CC interconnecting cortical regions have been very difficult to deconvolve; available tools are primarily unable to adequately characterize interhemispheric fibers because of the magnitude of the connections that travel through CC. Finally, when seeded from a cortical region, traditional tractography can fail to reach the corresponding region of the opposite hemisphere. To overcome some of these limitations, advanced tools and sophisticated ROI definitions are necessary to delineate and subdivide callosal pathways so that the region of a bundle of CC can be used for tract-specific analysis (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Watanabe et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;nch et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="p0045">In this study we developed a novel approach that maintains the information of the orientation and position of fiber trajectories and that allows the quantification of fiber tract density along the entire length of the CC. We hypothesized that anatomically aligned directional tract density patterns were unique for specific regions of the CC and could be used to evaluate regional interhemispheric connectivity without specifying an <italic>a priori</italic> destination. Although more work is needed, our findings using two healthy-subject datasets suggest that this novel analytical algorithm provides an accurate estimation of interhemispheric connectivity that is also reliable, reproducible, independent of diffusion acquisition parameters, and that have the potential to be used to evaluate interhemispheric connectivity in clinical applications.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Datasets</title><sec id="sec2.1.1"><label>2.1.1</label><title>Synthetic dataset</title><p id="p0050">A synthetic dataset using the Phantomas tool (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Caruyer et al., 2014</xref>) was generated to provide a simplified reconstruction to evaluate interhemispheric connections, which are often complex due to their branching nature (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Schilling et al., 2019</xref>). This was intended to evaluate the effect of different acquisition parameters, including angular resolution and gradient strength, on the dTDPs.</p><p id="p0055">The Phantomas tool required inputs of heuristic control points, which were linked in order to form a polynomial trajectory (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a) to create a synthetic diffusion dataset that included information regarding bundle size and diffusion acquisition configurations, such as b-values and uniformly oriented gradient b-vectors. Heuristic control points included a smaller bundle running towards the inferior direction with half the radius size of the main CC bundle.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Synthetic CC data created using a preset multi-shell scheme, 2&#x000a0;mm voxel resolution, and 8&#x000a0;mm bundle radius: (a) Yellow points demarcates control points used to reconstruct a tubular structure of the CC, and (b&#x02013;d) demonstrate orientations of the reconstructed fibers along the structure. Yellow regions A and B showed in (b) are zoomed in (c) and (d). (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0060">We used three diffusion-weighting schemes: i) b700 with 10&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0 and 60 (number of orientations) b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;700 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>] images; ii) b2000 with 3&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0 and 90&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2000 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>] images; and iii) multi-shell scheme with 6&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0, 14&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;500, 48&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1000, and 66&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2000 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>] images. We also used two commonly available diffusion imaging (isotropic) resolutions of 1 and 2&#x000a0;mm to compare the sensitivity of dTDPs to the voxel resolution. In addition, two cross-section bundle sizes (radius of 8 and 12&#x000a0;mm) were used to simulate CC bundles of different sizes. With these input sets, the parameter combination created 12 synthetic diffusion images. A sample output is depicted for the given parameters in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> with reconstructed fiber orientation distributions (FODs).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.1.2"><label>2.1.2</label><title>Human datasets</title><p id="p0065">We used two available human datasets. The first was a publicly available comprehensive diffusion MRI dataset (CDMD), which included healthy human subjects (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24, 15F/9M, mean age 34.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.9) scanned on the MGH-USC (Siemens Skyra) 3T Connectome scanner (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tian et al., 2022</xref>). This dataset also included a subset of repeated scans (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6, 3F/3M, mean age 31.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.1) from the same participants. A second dataset, the healthy human subjects dataset (HHSD), consisted of scans acquired on Siemens Tim Trio 3T MRI scanner at the A.A. Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging. This dataset was further subdivided into HHSD-A, which included subjects (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24, 15F/9M, mean age 34.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.6) that were age-matched to the CDMD, and another group HHSD-B (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;33, 14F/19M, mean age 45.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.7), which allowed us to evaluate the reliability of these measures.</p><p id="p0070"><italic>CDMD imaging parameters</italic> (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tian et al., 2022</xref>): T1-weighted structural MRI data were acquired using an MEMPRAGE sequence with isotropic resolution of 1.0&#x000a0;mm, TR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2530 ms, TE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;{1.15, 3.03, 4.89, 6.75} ms, flip angle&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7<sup><italic>o</italic></sup>, and TI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1100 ms. Diffusion weighted data were acquired using multiple b-value shells (50&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>] and 16 different b values ranging from 50 to 17,800 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>]), each shell having 32 (for b <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2400</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> s/mm<sup>2</sup>) or 64 (for b <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2400</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> s/mm<sup>2</sup>) diffusion encoding directions. Imaging parameters were set with a resolution&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2&#x000a0;mm (isotropic), TR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3800 ms, and TE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;77 ms.</p><p id="p0075"><italic>HHSD imaging parameters</italic>: High resolution MEMPRAGE/T1 image (root-mean-square average of 4 echos) acquired with isotropic resolution of 1.0&#x000a0;mm, TR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2530 ms, TE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;{1.64, 3.5, 5.36, 7.22} ms, flip angle&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7<sup><italic>o</italic></sup>, and TI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1200 ms. The diffusion data used 70 diffusion weighted volumes (10&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>] and 60&#x000a0;b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;700 [s/mm<sup>2</sup>] images), isotropic resolution of 2&#x000a0;mm, TR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7980 ms, and TE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;83 ms.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Data pre-processing framework</title><p id="p0080"><italic>Synthetic dataset</italic>: Diffusion-weighted images were first denoised (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Veraart et al., 2016</xref>) and FODs were reconstructed using a constrained spherical deconvolution model. For single-shell data, we used a Turnier response function estimation, and for the multi-shell data, we used the &#x02018;dhollander&#x02019; option (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dhollander et al., 2019</xref>) for the response function estimation because the 5tt algorithm expects the diffusion data to include brain structures that do not exist in the synthetic dataset. For the two different bundle size configurations, a mid-sagittal cross section of the mean b0 images was used to draw a manual seed region, which imitated the CC cross section segmentation step performed for the human datasets.</p><p id="p0085"><italic>CDMD</italic>: Processing steps were described in <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tian et al. (2022)</xref>. For the diffusion model fitting we used MRtrix3<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref> pipeline using b&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;800, 1500, 2400, 3450&#x000a0;s/mm<sup>2</sup> shells. Since the CDMD was multi-shell diffusion acquisition, we used the multi-shell-multi-tissue options for both the response function estimation and FOD reconstruction steps.</p><p id="p0090"><italic>HHSD</italic>: The diffusion images were denoised (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Veraart et al., 2016</xref>) and corrected for distortion using FSL FUGUE (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Jenkinson et al., 2012</xref>) before correcting for eddy currents and head motions using FSL Eddy (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Andersson and Sotiropoulos, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Andersson et al., 2016</xref>). White matter FODs were obtained using a constrained spherical deconvolution model with a Turnier response function estimation using MRtrix3. Tract density images were reconstructed using (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Calamante et al., 2010</xref>) to evaluate the white matter integrity of CC with <italic>IFOD2</italic> probabilistic tractography (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Tournier et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jeurissen et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0095"><italic>Anatomical reconstruction and registration</italic>: We used FreeSurfer<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref> (version 7) to form an initial mask of the CC for the human datasets. Each individual T1 image was rigidly registered using FSL Flirt (rotation and translation) to the MNI152 (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Mazziotta et al., 2001</xref>) standard space so that all subjects had a unified brain tilt along the AC-PC line. Diffusion weighted images were co-registered to the T1 image using a boundary-based registration (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Greve and Fischl, 2009</xref>). Using the estimated registration matrices, the tract density maps were transformed to MNI152 space.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Segmentation and parcellation of the corpus callosum</title><p id="p0100">The CC labels (251&#x02013;255) from the FreeSurfer reconstruction were binarized to form a CC mask, which served as a boundary condition for the CC segmentation. The principal direction of diffusion (<italic>V</italic>1) and fractional anisotropy (<italic>FA</italic>) maps were utilized as factors for the CC curve evolution and segmentation of CC, for which <italic>V</italic>1 is expected to align in right to left direction ([1, 0, 0]) and <italic>FA</italic> is expected to be lower beyond the CC. The mid-sagittal slice was first located using the user interface along the sagittal slices, and then central voxels of the genu <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the most anterior aspect of the structure (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>a), and the splenium <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at the most posterior aspect (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>b) were identified. Using <xref rid="enun_Algorithm_1" ref-type="statement">Algorithm 1</xref>, we reconstructed a centerline CC curve by following a direction with the maximum metric <italic>&#x003c9;</italic> towards the direction of interest, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> using an adapted version of the Hofer-Frahm CC parcellation scheme to label the arcs of the CC curve as I, IIa, IIb, III, IV, and V in the order starting from the genu (I) to the splenium (V), as shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>d. Neighboring voxels of the curve were included in the parcellation using a modified version of the metric <italic>&#x003c9;</italic> of the <xref rid="enun_Algorithm_1" ref-type="statement">Algorithm 1</xref>, as given in Equation <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>,<xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">3</xref> if a certain threshold criteria (<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02032;&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>) was met. The green regions shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(a, b, and c) depict the voxels which met <italic>&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02032;&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> condition. The threshold parameter <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> was chosen heuristically as 0.15 to include all white matter voxels for seeding the tract.<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg" alttext="Equation 1."><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">recon</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x027e8;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x027e9;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Parcellation of CC for a healthy subject.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Tractography seeding and tract density imaging</title><p id="p0105">The fiber tractography from each CC region was initiated using 50000 seeds to densely cover the entire region, respectively. The <italic>IFOD2</italic> probabilistic tractography algorithm (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Tournier et al., 2010</xref>) was used to reconstruct fiber pathways using the white matter mask obtained from 5ttgen script of the MRtrix as the mask to generate a border at which to terminate the tracts. Track density maps (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Calamante et al., 2010</xref>) were reconstructed to measure the density of interhemispheric bundles traversing through each of the six regions of the CC (shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Volume rendering of tract densities traversing each CC region for a healthy human subject. The 3D directions X shows the right, Y shows the anterior, and Z shows the superior directions.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Definition of a projection plane for tract density images</title><p id="p0110"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was defined as the mapping from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, to show tract density for a voxel coordinate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be the unit vector, which runs as depicted in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a towards the normal vector to the tangent of the CC curve at the centroid of the CC region, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We defined the projection plane, <bold>P</bold>, by rotating the coronal image plane, for which the normal vector was [0, 1, 0], towards the anterior, about the origin point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and fixed axis <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which was to the left of the brain, so that <bold>P</bold> was defined with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the unit vectors <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on the plane, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is normal to the plane as depicted in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. A Cartesian coordinate space defined on <bold>P</bold>, and for each point on <bold>P</bold>, the tract densities, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, were integrated along the depth axis <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02297;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the coordinate point in both towards and the opposite <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> directions to form a projection image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, as depicted in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> for the CC regions, showing the projection sum of the tract density at each point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> sampled on <bold>P</bold>, such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is located at the origin and shows the sum of the tract densities along the direction of the normal vector at the point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Field of view for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was adjusted large enough to include all brain regions.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The CC subdivision given in (a) shows the axis <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on mid-sagittal view, whereas the projection planes, defined using <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (red frame), are shown on upper images of (b&#x02013;h) together with the corresponding projected tract densities, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the bottom images, where the red cross shows <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Directional tract density pattern</title><p id="p0115">Once the tract densities were projected and summed on the plane <bold>P</bold> producing an image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the projection image <italic>I</italic> was subdivided into equal angular pieces centered at the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the integral of the density values for each angular piece formed a two-dimensional polar function, which we named as the directional tract density pattern (dTDP). Let <italic>Q</italic>(<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>) represent the dTDP function showing the sum of tract densities along each <italic>k</italic><sup><italic>th</italic></sup> angular portion, where <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/<italic>K</italic> is the small delta angle, <italic>K</italic> is the number of angular portions, and <italic>k</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02208;&#x000a0;{0, 1, 2, &#x02026;, <italic>K</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;1}. First, <italic>Q</italic>(<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>) was initialized to 0.0 <italic>&#x02200; k</italic>. Then, all the sampled points <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> on the image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were iterated, and each tract density value, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, was added to the sum <italic>Q</italic>(<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>), where <italic>k&#x003b1;</italic> was the corresponding angular portion of (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>) in polar coordinates. For this study we had <italic>K</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;64 angular portions sampled over 2<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>. Ultimately, <italic>Q</italic>(<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>) becomes a polar function showing the directional tract densities along the angular portion (<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>) thereby forming the dTDP of the CC region.</p><p id="p0120">This is shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. In this case, we overlaid the dTDP of CC region III on the projection sum image, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, from a healthy subject. We also defined the surface and side lobe of the dTDP, such that surface lobes represent the total density of fibers that traverse to the cortical regions of the brain as identified by <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Hofer and Frahm (2006)</xref>, whereas the side lobes represent the total density of tracts traversing from the seeded region to the left and right and that then run towards also the inferior brain regions. Note that dTDP provides an indirect quantification for the interhemispheric connectivity of cortical regions.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>dTDP of CC region III from a healthy human subject shows: (a) the angular parcellation of the region (green lines) together with the yellow curve depicting the dTDP, <italic>Q</italic>(<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>), the sum of tract densities along each angular portion (<italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>) of the projection image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is at the origin of the coordinate space (the background is sliced mean b0 image at the projection plane). (b) the dTDP (red curve) on the polar coordinate space in order to demonstrate the directional density magnitudes. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Reliability and variability metrics of dTDPs</title><p id="p0125">To determine the reliability of the dTDPs for the datasets, pairwise dTDPs were evaluated using a Pearson correlation coefficient, and the coefficients of each region was averaged to demonstrate the similarity (score of 1.0 designated that the dTDPs were identical).</p><p id="p0130">In addition, to evaluate between-subject variability between the human datasets, we computed a quartile coefficient of dispersion (QCD) metric (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bonett, 2006</xref>) weighted with the median for the dTDPs using Equation <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, where {<inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>} are the first quartile, median, and the third quartile of the dTDP values for the given angular portion (<italic>k</italic>) respectively.<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si26.svg" alttext="Equation 2."><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0135">For the group analysis, we utilized the quartile statistics plotted on the polar coordinate space, such that each angular portion (<italic>k</italic>) had 25<sup><italic>th</italic></sup> percentile (1<sup><italic>st</italic></sup> quartile), median (50<sup><italic>th</italic></sup> percentile), and 75<sup><italic>th</italic></sup> percentile (3<sup><italic>rd</italic></sup> quartile), and the area between the 1<sup><italic>st</italic></sup> and 3<sup><italic>rd</italic></sup> quartiles was shaded to show the variability of each dataset. We used a paired <italic>t</italic>-test to determine if there were significant differences in the density distributions along each angular portion. Since we were mostly interested in inter-hemispheric cortical connectivity, reflected by metrics along the upper directions, we ignored the lower (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/2 &#x0003c; <italic>k&#x003b1;</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;3<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/2)<italic>K</italic>/2 directions as well as the directions that likely reflect noisy dTDP magnitudes, as observed in central directions (0, <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/2, 3<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/2).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Evaluations of the synthetic dataset: analytical fiber stream</title><p id="p0140">We computed the correlations between pairwise dTDPs obtained for the synthetic CC data, and found that all the pairwise correlations were greater than 0.99, depicted in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>. We depicted 9 of the dTDPs in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, such that each column image represents data from a different gradient orientation scheme. By comparing the first row images to the second row, i.e. <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>a vs. 6d, 6b vs. 6e, and 6c vs. 6f, we observed that changing the voxel resolution did not change the dTDP, irrespective of whether an 8&#x000a0;mm or 12&#x000a0;mm CC radius size was used. The second and third row images (d-i) of <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> were depicted the patterns for different bundle radius sizes, where the voxel resolution was fixed to 1&#x000a0;mm. To summarize the comparisons, we stacked all the dTDPs in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>j, k showing the dTDPs overlaid on the same polar space separately for 8&#x000a0;mm and 12&#x000a0;mm bundle sizes. Here, we can observe for the bundle radius size of 12&#x000a0;mm that the given diffusion scheme and image resolution presets produced a synthetic data which had almost identical dTDPs. However, for the bundle size of 8&#x000a0;mm, the multi-shell scheme produced smaller directional tract density compared to the b700 and b2000 scheme for the left and right side lobes of the dTDP; even in this case, the pairwise correlations were greater than 0.99.<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>dTDPs for different CC bundle size, diffusion scheme, and resolution. (a&#x02013;i) show dTDPs, such that, while resolution and bundle radius are fixed in each row, in columns left to right, dTDPs for b700, b2000, and multi-shell schemes are depicted (background image is the projection of tract densities). The first and second rows compare different resolutions (1 and 2&#x000a0;mm), and the second and third rows compare the bundle radius of 12 and 8&#x000a0;mm. (j&#x02013;h) overlays all dTDPs separately for bundle sizes of 12&#x000a0;mm and 8&#x000a0;mm.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Evaluations of the human datasets</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Variability of dTDPs</title><p id="p0145">In <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, the quartile statistics of dTDP for the CDMD and HHSD-A demonstrated that dTDPs for the two datasets were not significantly different from each other, with the exception of random directions of the CC regions IIa, IIb, III, and IV. The quartile dTDP statistics for the CC regions I and V were also not significantly different for any direction, suggesting that these measures were largely unaffected by the diffusion acquisition parameters.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of directional tract density patterns (dTDPs) between CDMD (blue) and HHSD-A (red) for each CC region. The datasets were not significantly different from each other noting that a few number of &#x0201c;*&#x0201d; symbols demonstrate sparse/inadequate directions of difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) at the end of the radial axis. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="p0150"><xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> depicts the quartile statistics for the HHSD-B dataset providing the normative dTDPs of each CC region. For this dataset, the QCD scores of the CC regions were {0.13, 0.18, 0.17, 0.16, 0.22, 0.17} respectively for the regions I, IIa, IIb, III, IV, and V. The mean dTDP magnitudes for the surface and side lobes, estimated using the heuristically assigned directions as shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, are provided in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<fig id="fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Directional tract density patterns for the CC regions in the HHSD-B cohort, depicting heuristically assigned principal directions for the surface and side lobes (L: Left, R: Right, Surf: surface lobe, Side: side lobe) and the variability in the dataset for each direction (shaded region).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>dTDP variability of HHSD-B: Directional tract densities (mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation) for the side and surface lobes marked in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>. Density values are given on the order of 10<sup>6</sup>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>CC region</th><th>Side-Right</th><th>Surface-Right</th><th>Surface-Left</th><th>Side-Left</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">I</td><td align="left">3.65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.59</td><td align="left">3.40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.58</td><td align="left">3.41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.55</td><td align="left">3.76&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IIa</td><td align="left">4.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.91</td><td align="left">2.97&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.71</td><td align="left">2.89&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.87</td><td align="left">4.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IIb</td><td align="left">3.91&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.91</td><td align="left">2.79&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.60</td><td align="left">2.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.69</td><td align="left">3.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">4.07&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.83</td><td align="left">2.90&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.67</td><td align="left">3.19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.64</td><td align="left">4.16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IV</td><td align="left">4.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.94</td><td align="left">2.89&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.80</td><td align="left">3.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.07</td><td align="left">4.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">V</td><td align="left">4.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.80</td><td align="left">2.24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.51</td><td align="left">2.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.63</td><td align="left">5.11&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.93</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Reliability and reproducibility of dTDPs</title><p id="p0155"><xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> demonstrates the Pearson correlations within and between the CDMD and HHSD. Within group dTDP correlations were greater than 0.75 for 98%, 99%, and 97% of the total number of pairwise correlations respectively for HHSD-A, HHSD-B, and CDMD (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>a&#x02013;c). We also observed that the correlations between the individuals of CDMD and HHSD-A were greater than 0.75 for 97% of the total number of pairwise correlations (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>d).<fig id="fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Correlation matrices of the HHSD and CDMD datasets. (a&#x02013;c) show the between subject correlations of individual dTDPs in the datasets ((a) HSSD-A, (b) HHSD-B, and (c) CDMD). (d) demonstrates the correlation between CDMD and HHSD-A. In all cases, correlation coefficients were greater than 0.75 for at least 97% of total number of pairwise correlations, demonstrating excellent within and between dataset reliability. We used <italic>viridis</italic> color palette: dark blue (&#x02212;1.0) to yellow (1.0) from python matplotlib package in color bar showing high correlations in yellow. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig></p><p id="p0160">In the test-retest analysis, we used scans from six subjects from the CDMD, who had been scanned twice on the same day, to compare the dTDPs of each CC region between the consecutive scan sessions for each subject. Reproducibility was expressed as the respective Pearson correlations as provided in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The test-retest sessions had dTDPs for which the pairwise correlations were greater than 0.97 (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Test-retest reproducibility of the dTDP. S-<italic>#</italic> shows the subject index.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>CC region</th><th>S-1</th><th>S-2</th><th>S-3</th><th>S-4</th><th>S-5</th><th>S-6</th><th><bold>Mean</bold>&#x000a0;<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>&#x000a0;<bold>Std</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">I</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left">0.991</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left">0.997</td><td align="left">0.992</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left"><bold>0.993&#x000b1;0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IIa</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left">0.984</td><td align="left">0.984</td><td align="left">0.982</td><td align="left">0.990</td><td align="left">0.992</td><td align="left"><bold>0.980&#x000b1;0.021</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IIb</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left">0.986</td><td align="left">0.997</td><td align="left">0.979</td><td align="left">0.979</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left"><bold>0.989&#x000b1;0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">0.995</td><td align="left">0.987</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left">0.986</td><td align="left">0.982</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left"><bold>0.990&#x000b1;0.008</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IV</td><td align="left">0.989</td><td align="left">0.985</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left">0.975</td><td align="left">0.988</td><td align="left">0.996</td><td align="left"><bold>0.984&#x000b1;0.014</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">V</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left">0.985</td><td align="left">0.998</td><td align="left">0.988</td><td align="left">0.992</td><td align="left">0.999</td><td align="left"><bold>0.993&#x000b1;0.006</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0165">We also evaluated the test-retest performance results for our CC parcellation scheme using the dice overlap score (2(|<italic>X</italic> &#x02229; <italic>Y</italic>|)/(|<italic>X</italic>|&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;|<italic>Y</italic>|)) between the parcellated CC regions of two scans from the same subject. The dice scores were greater than 0.9 for most of the comparisons (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Dice scores of CC parcellation for the subjects with repeated scans.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>CC region</th><th>S-1</th><th>S-2</th><th>S-3</th><th>S-4</th><th>S-5</th><th>S-6</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">I</td><td align="left">0.968</td><td align="left">0.889</td><td align="left">0.960</td><td align="left">0.914</td><td align="left">0.966</td><td align="left">0.943</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IIa</td><td align="left">0.942</td><td align="left">0.800</td><td align="left">0.964</td><td align="left">0.807</td><td align="left">0.966</td><td align="left">0.939</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IIb</td><td align="left">0.949</td><td align="left">0.867</td><td align="left">0.942</td><td align="left">0.814</td><td align="left">0.924</td><td align="left">0.985</td></tr><tr><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">0.904</td><td align="left">0.900</td><td align="left">0.939</td><td align="left">0.853</td><td align="left">0.926</td><td align="left">0.945</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IV</td><td align="left">0.846</td><td align="left">0.780</td><td align="left">0.969</td><td align="left">0.773</td><td align="left">0.938</td><td align="left">0.939</td></tr><tr><td align="left">V</td><td align="left">0.946</td><td align="left">0.902</td><td align="left">0.981</td><td align="left">0.910</td><td align="left">0.966</td><td align="left">0.955</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.3"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Motion estimations</title><p id="p0170a">We also estimated head motion parameters using the eddy QC, as diffusion imaging measures can be affected by head motion during scanning (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bastiani et al., 2019</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>, both the HHSD-A and the CDMD (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tian et al., 2022</xref>) had less than 1&#x000a0;mm relative average motion, suggesting that the dTDP measures are not affected by subject motion.<fig id="fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Head stability during the diffusion acquisition for all the subjects in HHSD-A: Total outliers were shown to reveal the percentage of dropout slices detected in diffusion data. Individual head motion parameters were also shown with average motion, rotation, and displacement in all dimensions.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Fig. 10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0170">In this study, we used a novel algorithm, dTDP, to evaluate the directional characteristics of tract density patterns of distinct CC regions in healthy subjects. We found that our results provided an unbiased, reliable, and sensitive approach insensitive to variations in acquisition parameters and without the need for <italic>a priori</italic> assumptions of connectivity with topologically selective cortical regions. A major strength of this approach is that, unlike graph-based approaches, which provide a connectivity score between two regions (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Rubinov and Sporns, 2010</xref>), dTDP interprets the interhemispheric connectivity across the entire structure and provides a directional density pattern at the macroscopic scale. dTDP is unique as, unlike orientation-independent shape features, such as the mean length (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Schmied et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Yeh, 2020</xref>), it utilizes probabilistic trajectory of an individual pathway and quantifies the density towards the directions starting from the mid-sagittal center of the CC region. Therefore, dTDP provides an orientation-dependent measure of interhemispheric connectivity.</p><p id="p0175">This study is important for several reasons. As demonstrated, dTDP provides a distinct assessment information measure for interhemispheric connectivity with high reliability both within and across datasets. It also provides information without the need for <italic>a priori</italic> designations of cortical regions of interest, in contrast to prior connectivity studies, which have been considered cortical regions as seeds or targets (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Mars et al., 2018</xref>). We also demonstrated that using an indirect approach, we could obtain information about interhemispheric connectivity representing both the density of fibers able to reach cortical regions (surface lobes) and the density of those that reached only mid-way (side lobes). In this way, our method is able to generate an estimate of the density of CC fibers as they turn/realign and merge with other bundles to run towards the cortical surface. This suggests that, using these dTDPs, it may be possible to monitor the structure of the crossing bending regions within the CC prior to reaching their cortical destination using standard diffusion acquisition parameters, something that cannot be accomplished with the current available methods.</p><p id="p0180">Alterations in the white matter integrity and connectivity have been recognized as both prominent and significant in several neurodegenerative diseases including Alzheimer's, Parkinson's, and Huntington's disease (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Nir et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Rosas et al., 2010</xref>). Our results suggest that the dTDP might provide the needed sensitivity and reliability to be of use in clinical applications, including age- or disease-related changes in interhemispheric architecture, providing opportunities to detect early pathological change. Additional future work will be required to fully explore the applicability of this approach to neurodegeneration in both cross-sectional and longitudinal analyses.</p><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0185">As tractography provides an ill-posed solution to estimate the anatomical structure of the whole-brain white matter fiber trajectories, it may be prone to inconsistent reconstructions, mostly identified as false-positive fibers, which are often discarded when using region sensitive filtering operations (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Maffei et al., 2021</xref>). Since dTDP is reconstructed by carefully seeding the tractography from the mid-sagittal CC, the existence of false-positive connections is a less likely concern. Instead, false positive fibers could instead represent an indicator of damaged connections in clinical applications, but this requires additional evaluation.</p><p id="p0190">Since the dTDP framework does not require identification of a specific cortical target regions, the proposed framework provides a course end region analysis. However, we should note that the uncertainty of the fibers is greatest at target/cortical surface regions (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Behrens et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Friman and Westin, 2005</xref>), which is an issue for all tractography applications. This is because tractography streamlines have branching fibers along the commissural pathway closer to the surface, where tractography is known to be biased (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Schilling et al., 2018</xref>). By projecting the tract densities on an optimal plane to reflect only directional density of the fibers along the dominant directions of CC (left to right), we aimed to partially reduce the branching bias.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0195">In this study, we developed a novel algorithm to evaluate interhemispheric connectivity of regionally selective regions of CC, that provides information about different locations along the callosal trajectory. Variability and reproducibility experiments performed using two human datasets suggest that this method is sensitive, reliable, and reproducible, and support its use in clinical applications to evaluate interhemispheric connectivity.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Data/code availability statement</title><p id="p0200">The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author. The code and compiled binaries including the graphical user interface for dTDP will be made available to public in here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/_ali_demir/dtdp" id="PC_link13XdEVbJn5">https://bitbucket.org/_ali_demir/dtdp</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="p0205">The studies involving human participants were reviewed and approved by Partners Human Research Committee. The patients/participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0210">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohlberg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bludau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Julich-brain: a 3d probabilistic atlas of the human brain's cytoarchitecture</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>369</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb4588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32732281</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotiropoulos</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated approach to correction for off-resonance effects and subject movement in diffusion MR imaging</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>125</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.10.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26481672</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>J.L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zsoldos</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotiropoulos</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporating outlier detection and replacement into a non-parametric framework for movement and distortion correction of diffusion MR images</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>141</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.06.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27393418</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basser</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierpaoli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microstructural and physiological features of tissues elucidated by quantitative-diffusion-tensor MRI</article-title><source>J. Magn. Reson., Ser. B</source><volume>111</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmrb.1996.0086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8661285</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastiani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cottaar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgibbon</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfaro-Almagro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotiropoulos</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jbabdi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated quality control for within and between studies diffusion MRI data using a non-parametric framework for movement and distortion correction</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>184</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2018.09.073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30267859</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen-Berg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and propagation of uncertainty in diffusion-weighted MR imaging</article-title><source>Magn. Reson. Med.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mrm.10609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14587019</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonett</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confidence interval for a coefficient of quartile variation</article-title><source>Comput. Stat. Data Anal.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>2953</fpage><lpage>2957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csda.2005.05.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calamante</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tournier</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Track-density imaging (TDI): super-resolution white matter imaging using whole-brain track-density mapping</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>53</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1233</fpage><lpage>1243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.07.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20643215</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caruyer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daducci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Descoteaux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houde</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiran</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Phantomas: a Flexible Software Library to Simulate Diffusion MR Phantoms</part-title><year>2014</year><publisher-name>ISMRM</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Milan, Italy</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhollander</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mito</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffelt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Improved white matter response function estimation for 3-tissue constrained spherical deconvolution</part-title><source>Proceedings of the International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</source><year>2019</year><comment>Abstract number 555</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Winter</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Billiet</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiaens</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouckaert</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamczuk</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenberghe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sienaert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunaert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenbulcke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corpus callosum macro and microstructure in late-life depression</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><volume>222</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2017.06.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28672181</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friman</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westin</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Uncertainty in white matter fiber tractography</part-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerig</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention &#x02013; MICCAI 2005</source><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/11566465_14</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accurate and robust brain image alignment using boundary-based registration</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>48</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.06.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19573611</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frahm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topography of the human corpus callosum revisited&#x02014;comprehensive fiber tractography using diffusion tensor magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>32</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.05.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16854598</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloyan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bireley</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobyne</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapaport</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nummenmaa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Witzel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klawiter</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corpus callosum axon diameter relates to cognitive impairment in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology</source><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acn3.760</pub-id><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/acn3.760" id="intref0010">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/acn3.760</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31139686</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fsl. NeuroImage</source><volume>62</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21979382</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeurissen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tournier</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhollander</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sijbers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-tissue constrained spherical deconvolution for improved analysis of multi-shell diffusion MRI data</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>103</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.07.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25109526</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingsley</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction to diffusion tensor imaging mathematics: Part II. anisotropy, diffusion-weighting factors, and gradient encoding schemes</article-title><source>Concepts Magn. Reson.</source><volume>28A</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cmr.a.20049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>V.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Group comparison of cortical fiber connectivity map: an application between post-stroke patients and healthy subjects</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><volume>344</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2016.12.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28039039</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Planich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramprasad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trainor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizzagalli</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabrieli</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfield-Gabrieli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yendiki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using diffusion MRI data acquired with ultra-high gradient strength to improve tractography in routine-quality data</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>245</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">118706</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2021.118706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotiropoulos</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Passingham</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhagen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khrapitchev</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sibson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jbabdi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole brain comparative anatomy using connectivity blueprints</article-title><source>Elife</source><volume>7</volume><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e35237</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.35237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazziotta</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toga</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>P.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paus</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacoboni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schormann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomero-Gallagher</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narr</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabani</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goualher</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>D.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazoyer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A probabilistic atlas and reference system for the human brain: international consortium for brain mapping (ICBM)</article-title><source>Phil. Trans. Roy. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci.</source><volume>356</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2001.0915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11545704</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludolph</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassubek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Segmental alterations of the corpus callosum in motor neuron disease: a DTI and texture analysis in 575 patients</article-title><source>Neuroimage: Clinical</source><volume>35</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103061</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2022.103061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>MRI Atlas of Human White Matter</part-title><edition>first ed.</edition><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Amsterdam; Boston</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nir</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahanshad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villalon-Reina</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toga</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of regional DTI measures in distinguishing alzheimer's disease, MCI, and normal aging</article-title><source>Neuroimage: Clinical</source><volume>3</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2013.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179862</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaleta</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vangel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onorato</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salat</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersch</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered white matter microstructure in the corpus callosum in huntington's disease: implications for cortical &#x0201c;disconnection.&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>49</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>2995</fpage><lpage>3004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19850138</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubinov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporns</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex network measures of brain connectivity: uses and interpretations</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>52</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819337</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rusina</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bajtosova</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cs&#x000e9;falvay</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavkova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kukal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matej</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbid neurodegeneration in primary progressive aphasia: clinicopathological correlations in a single-center study</article-title><source>Behav. Neurol.</source><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6075511</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/6075511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stockel</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobyne</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngamsombat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nummenmaa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klawiter</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations between corpus callosum damage, clinical disability, and surface-based homologous inter-hemispheric connectivity in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Brain Struct. Funct.</source><volume>227</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2909</fpage><lpage>2922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-022-02498-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35536387</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janve</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepniewska</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landman</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confirmation of a gyral bias in diffusion MRI fiber tractography</article-title><source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1449</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.23936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29266522</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parvathaneni</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydogan</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ocampo-Pineda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiavi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daducci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barakovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafael-Patino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romascano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rensonnet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizzolato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiran</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canales-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabeen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toga</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rheault</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theaud</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houde</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamberland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westin</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyrby</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irfanoglu</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierpaoli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Descoteaux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landman</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Limits to anatomical accuracy of diffusion tractography using modern approaches</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>185</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2018.10.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30317017</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmied</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerig</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Styner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elison</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinstry</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruett</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botteron</surname><given-names>K.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dager</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazlett</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piven</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences associated with corpus callosum development in human infants: a longitudinal multimodal imaging study</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>215</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">116821</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.116821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stezin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphometric mapping of the macrostructural abnormalities of midsagittal corpus callosum in wilson's disease</article-title><source>Annals of Movement Disorders</source><volume>4</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/AOMD.AOMD_41_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35936213</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Witzel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polackal</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohringer</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngamsombat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Setsompop</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polimeni</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klawiter</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nummenmaa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive diffusion MRI dataset for in vivo human brain microstructure mapping using 300 mT/m gradients</article-title><source>Sci. Data</source><volume>9</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-021-01092-6</pub-id><comment>Article number 7</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tournier</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calamante</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust determination of the fibre orientation distribution in diffusion MRI: non-negativity constrained super-resolved spherical deconvolution</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>35</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.02.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379540</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tournier</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calamante</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gadian</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Improved probabilistic streamlines tractography by 2nd order integration over fibre orientation distributions</part-title><source>Proceedings of the International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</source><year>2010</year><comment>Abstract number 1670</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veraart</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novikov</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiaens</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ades-aron</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sijbers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fieremans</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Denoising of diffusion MRI using random matrix theory</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>142</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.08.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27523449</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamae</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumoto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The detection of white matter alterations in obsessive-compulsive disorder revealed by TRActs Constrained by UnderLying Anatomy (TRACULA)</article-title><source>Neuropsychiatric Dis. Treat.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S164058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal macro/microstructural alterations of different callosal subsections in Parkinson's disease using connectivity-based parcellation</article-title><source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2020.572086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative evaluation of callosal abnormalities in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis using diffusion tensor imaging: a systemic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Clin. Neurol. Neurosurg.</source><volume>201</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">106442</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2020.106442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shape analysis of the human association pathways</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>223</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">117329</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.117329</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1"><label>Appendix A</label><title>CC centerline curve fitting algorithm</title><p id="p0225">
<statement id="enun_Algorithm_1"><label>Algorithm 1</label><p id="p0230">Centerline CC curve reconstruction<fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></p></statement>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0010"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0025">The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article, further inquiries can be directed to the authors. The code and compiled binaries will be available to public.</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0215">Funding for this research provided by: the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> R01:<award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">NS106384</award-id> and R01:<award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">NS114562</award-id>.</p><p id="p0220">We are grateful Dr. Qiyuan Tian and Dr. Susie Y. Huang for providing the demographics information. We also thank Dr. Shahin Nasr for scientific feedback and editorial comments.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">mrtrix.org.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>2</label><p id="ntpara0015">surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>3</label><p id="ntpara0020">For the neighbor inclusion metric, &#x027e8;,&#x027e9; denotes the dot product and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x020d7;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a voxel along the perpendicular direction to the tangent of the curve.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>