<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40502101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12154655</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.21.655404</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>StringTie3 Improves Total RNA-seq Assembly by Resolving Nascent and Mature Transcripts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1651-9347</contrib-id><name><surname>Shinder</surname><given-names>Ida</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3210-7182</contrib-id><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>Geo</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5381-0005</contrib-id><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0004-4883-2305</contrib-id><name><surname>Rudnick</surname><given-names>Zoe</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0762-8637</contrib-id><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>Mihaela</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1.</label>Cross Disciplinary Graduate Program in Biomedical Sciences, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2.</label>Center for Computational Biology, Johns Hopkins University; Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3.</label>Lieber Institute for Brain Development, Johns Hopkins Medical Campus, Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4.</label>Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University; Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5.</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine and Whiting School of Engineering; Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6.</label>Department of Genetic Medicine, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine; Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1">Author Contributions</p><p id="P2">I.S. conceived the study, designed and contributed to the implementation of the software, conducted computational analyses, analyzed and interpreted the results, and wrote the manuscript. Z.R. and R.H. aided in the analysis of results. G.P. assisted with software development. M.P. conceived the study, contributed to software, assisted in writing and editing the manuscript, and supervised the entire project. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence should be addressed to I.S. (<email>ishinde1@jhmi.edu</email>) or M.P (<email>mpertea@jhu.edu</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2025.05.21.655404</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to copy and distribute the material in any medium or format in unadapted form only, for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2025.05.21.655404.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P3">Accurate assembly of rRNA-depleted (total) RNA-seq remains challenging because existing methods often conflate incomplete, nascent RNA with fully processed mature isoforms, leading to misassemblies and quantification errors that skew downstream analyses. Here, we present StringTie3, a major update to the widely used StringTie assembler, specifically designed for total RNA-seq. This new version introduces two key innovations: (1) a nascent mode that models co-transcriptional splicing to separate nascent from mature transcripts, and (2) a refined long-read module that distinguishes genuine polyadenylation sites from poly(A)-priming artifacts. Across short-, long-, and hybrid-read datasets, StringTie3 substantially reduces assembly errors and outperforms existing tools, boosting precision by up to 20% in short-read total RNA-seq and improving sensitivity and precision by as much as 37% and 75%, respectively, in long-read assemblies. In Argonaute knockout experiments, nascent-mode analysis shows that single knockouts predominantly alter nascent transcripts while leaving mature RNA largely unchanged, whereas double or triple knockouts disrupt both fractions. Applying this approach to breast cancer samples shows that, although nascent and mature RNA levels often correlate, certain extracellular matrix and tumor suppressor genes deviate from this pattern, suggesting post-transcriptional regulation. By accurately reconstructing transcriptomes and distinguishing nascent from mature RNA, StringTie3 reveals hidden layers of RNA regulation and provides a powerful framework for investigating transcriptional and post-transcriptional processes in total RNA-seq data.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) has substantially advanced our understanding of gene expression and splicing by enabling transcriptional profiling across diverse biological contexts<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Early applications primarily relied on poly(A)-selected libraries to enrich for mature messenger RNAs (mRNAs), overlooking non-polyadenylated and nascent transcripts. Over time, RNA-seq has evolved into a versatile toolkit, including single-cell analyses that reveal cellular heterogeneity and specialized methods for nascent transcription<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. While these approaches have expanded the scope of RNA-seq, most workflows continue to rely on poly(A) selection for transcript assembly and quantification, thus excluding non-polyadenylated RNA&#x02013;such as histone-encoded transcripts, various non-coding RNAs, and partially processed, nascent RNA. Although specialized nascent RNA assays (e.g., GRO-seq, PRO-seq, 4sU-seq) can capture newly synthesized molecules, they are time- and labor-intensive and require actively transcribing cells, making them impractical for many clinical samples, including biopsies<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">Unlike poly(A)-selected methods, total RNA-seq with rRNA depletion preserves both polyadenylated and non-polyadenylated species<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Although most transcript assemblers include strategies to handle pre-mRNA contamination, they are less accurate when nascent RNA is abundant. In loci with high nascent expression, partially spliced introns are frequently misassembled as exons (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>), obscuring full-length isoforms and confounding downstream analyses such as differential expression. Because nascent transcripts can represent a large share of total RNA, particularly in cells undergoing rapid proliferation or differentiation<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>, ignoring them can obscure essential regulatory events, distort transcriptional dynamics, and introduce quantification biases<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. In addition, poly(A) selection often enriches for shorter isoforms in degraded or clinical samples<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>, further limiting the effectiveness of conventional methods for accurately reconstructing the transcriptome.</p><p id="P6">Here, we present StringTie3, a major update to the widely used StringTie<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> assembler, designed to explicitly model co-transcriptional splicing in order to distinguish nascent transcripts from mature isoforms in rRNA-depleted libraries. Because most splicing (up to 70%) occurs during transcription rather than afterward<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>, nascent RNA often contains partially spliced introns, resulting in characteristic sawtooth intronic coverage patterns (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). These patterns arise because the intron is incrementally transcribed while co-transcriptional splicing progressively removes already transcribed segments, creating overlapping partially spliced intermediates with decreasing read coverage along the intron (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). Building on this insight, StringTie3&#x02019;s new &#x0201c;nascent mode&#x0201d; prevents the erroneous merging of partially spliced introns into exons, improving transcript accuracy and correctly allocating reads to nascent molecules. This logic also benefits poly(A)-selected datasets by detecting and filtering internal priming artifacts<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>, which can otherwise inflate false transcript assemblies. As a result, StringTie3 consistently outperforms existing methods in both short-read and long-read assembly across multiple library types, achieving higher precision and sensitivity.</p><p id="P7">By differentiating partially processed from fully mature transcripts in total RNA-seq data, StringTie3 facilitates more nuanced analyses of co- and post-transcriptional regulation, reduces reliance on specialized nascent assays, and expands the utility of rRNA-depleted libraries, which have historically been used for non-polyadenylated RNA studies (e.g., A-to-I editing, circRNAs). Ultimately, StringTie3 addresses long-standing challenges in rRNA-depleted workflows and provides an effective solution for transcriptome assembly in these datasets.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Overview of StringTie3</title><p id="P8">To improve transcriptome assembly from rRNA-depleted (total) RNA-seq data, we developed a &#x02018;nascent mode&#x02019; within our previously developed transcriptome assembler StringTie2<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> that explicitly accounts for partially spliced nascent transcripts (see <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref rid="S20" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). In rRNA-depleted libraries, abundant intronic coverage often reflects transcripts that have not fully completed elongation or splicing, and failing to account for these intermediates can lead to frequent misassemblies (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><p id="P9"><xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref> shows how introns are progressively transcribed (green lines) and then spliced out (gray lines), generating partially spliced intermediates with decreasing intron coverage and resulting in a &#x02018;sawtooth&#x02019; coverage pattern. Rather than building a separate transcript for each incremental nucleotide addition, StringTie3 consolidates all co-transcriptional intermediates into a single nascent transcript (pink lines), capturing every in-progress version that terminates within the same intron (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref> and <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>).</p><p id="P10">By default, StringTie assumes that most reads originate from mature transcripts (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>). However, in rRNA-depleted data, ignoring intronic reads leads to misassemblies. To address this, nascent mode augments the splicing graph with intronic nodes and edges, allowing transcripts to terminate in unspliced introns. As shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref> (pink nodes and edges), this design more accurately reflects multiple elongation stages and prevents reads spanning introns from being misassembled as exons. Because splicing generally occurs co-transcriptionally, StringTie3 inserts intronic nodes between exonic nodes that are connected by a splice junction, along with edges that allow the transcript to terminate there (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref>, pink nodes and arrows). This approach ensures correct intronic termination for nascent transcripts while also enabling the accurate assembly of isoforms with retained introns, supported by reads spanning the intron and adjacent exonic nodes (see <xref rid="S20" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>).</p><p id="P11">Although the nascent mode is not expected to significantly affect the assembly of poly(A)-selected RNA-seq libraries, we observed consistently improved transcriptome reconstruction, particularly in long-read data. This improvement occurs because the nascent mode systematically removes intronic priming artifacts, which often arise from internal poly(A) tracts within introns and cause inadvertent sequencing of nascent intermediates (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Building on this insight, we updated StringTie3&#x02019;s long-read module to detect and remove these poly(A) priming artifacts (see <xref rid="S20" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>), further improving the accuracy of long-read assemblies.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Benchmarking on rRNA-depleted short-read datasets</title><p id="P12">To benchmark StringTie3 (nascent mode) against StringTie2 and the widely used Scallop2<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> transcriptome assembler, we evaluated three distinct short-read, rRNA-depleted RNA-seq datasets: (1) Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex (DLPFC)<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>, (2) Breast Cancer (tumor vs. normal pairs)<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>, and (3) Neuron Differentiation (time points from Day 0 to Day 5 of induced pluripotent stem cells)<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. From each dataset, we randomly selected ten samples (30 samples total) and measured sensitivity and precision by comparing the assembled transcripts to a reference annotation. Because Scallop2 lacks an annotation-guided assembly mode, all three programs were run in annotation-free mode (see <xref rid="S20" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>).</p><p id="P13">As shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, StringTie3 (nascent mode) outperforms StringTie2 and Scallop2 in both sensitivity and precision. Relative to Scallop2, StringTie3 achieves an average relative improvement of 2.5% and 42.0% in sensitivity and precision, respectively, across all 30 samples, and 2.9% and 13.0%, respectively, when compared to StringTie2. In 7 out of the 30 samples, Scallop2 displayed a minor (1&#x02013;4%) relative gain in sensitivity over StringTie3 but generally lags by more than 40% in precision (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). We attribute the slight sensitivity drop in StringTie3 (vs. Scallop2) to reference transcripts sharing intron chains with assembled nascent transcripts, where coverage dips can be misconstrued as transcript boundaries (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). While Scallop2 and StringTie2 often interpret variable intronic coverage&#x02014;common in rRNA-depleted libraries&#x02014;as transcript boundaries, StringTie3 classifies these regions as nascent RNA based on surrounding intronic coverage and excludes them from the mature transcript assembly (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Notably, when such transcripts are genuinely present at coverage levels exceeding the nascent background, StringTie3 correctly assembles them as mature (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>). Overall, these findings highlight the advantage of nascent-aware modeling for improving rRNA-depleted transcriptome assembly accuracy.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Comparison of matched poly(A)-selected and rRNA-depleted RNA-Seq datasets</title><p id="P14">To evaluate how library preparation affects transcriptome assembly, we analyzed 144 matched dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) RNA-seq samples, generated using either poly(A) selection or rRNA depletion. Each sample was assembled with StringTie3 (nascent mode) and StringTie2 in both annotation-guided and annotation-free modes, and we assessed precision and sensitivity against the CHESS 3.0 reference annotation<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P15">In poly(A)-selected libraries, StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent mode improved precision by an average of 10.7% in annotation-guided mode and 2.9% in annotation-free mode, while maintaining essentially the same sensitivity. As expected, the gains were more pronounced in rRNA-depleted libraries, with an average precision increase of 21.4% in annotation-guided mode and 13.2% in annotation-free mode, respectively, along with an additional 2.1% rise in sensitivity for annotation-free assembly (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>; see <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 1</xref> and <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref> for per-sample statistics). Violin plots of precision and the number of reference transcripts assembled (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">H</xref>) confirm that StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent mode consistently outperforms StringTie2 across individual samples. Additionally, for annotation-guided assemblies, the precision of rRNA(&#x02013;) libraries processed with StringTie3 nearly matches that of poly(A)+ libraries, whereas rRNA(&#x02013;) precision under StringTie2 remained substantially lower than that of the poly(A)+ assembly, highlighting the specific benefit of nascent mode for rRNA depleted data.</p><p id="P16">We observed that poly(A)-selected libraries generally exhibit higher sensitivity, as they primarily capture mature transcripts, whereas rRNA-depleted datasets also include incomplete nascent molecules. However, most reference transcripts detected exclusively in poly(A)+ assemblies but absent from rRNA(&#x02013;) libraries have low TPM values (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3A</xref>). Reference transcripts found only in rRNA-depleted libraries tend to be longer, suggesting that poly(A)+ selection, particularly in lower-quality samples (e.g., biopsies), biases transcript detection toward shorter isoforms due to 5&#x02032; degradation (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3B</xref>). By comparison, rRNA depletion captures transcripts more evenly along their entire length, yielding a broader spectrum of RNA isoforms<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. These length distributions, combined with nascent-mode assembly, indicate that rRNA depletion recovers isoforms that would otherwise be missed by poly(A)+ selection alone (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4I</xref>). Consequently, an rRNA-depleted, nascent-aware approach offers a more comprehensive view of the transcriptome, including longer isoforms that might be missed by poly(A)-selected protocols.</p><p id="P17">Both rRNA-depleted and poly(A)-selected library assemblies showed improved accuracy relative to the reference annotation. Because each sample included paired rRNA(&#x02013;) and poly(A)+ libraries, we assessed whether StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent mode would increase the overlap between these two assemblies compared to StringTie2. In annotation-guided mode, the average number of assembled transcripts unique to rRNA(&#x02013;) decreased by 38%, and those unique to poly(A)+ decreased by 20%, with little change in their shared transcript count (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). In annotation-free mode, the count of transcripts exclusive to rRNA(&#x02013;) decreased by 7%, and those unique to poly(A)+ dropped by 13%, again with minimal impact on the overlap. Per-sample counts illustrating these comparisons are provided in <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 3</xref>. Overall, these results indicate that explicitly modeling co-transcriptional splicing in nascent mode improves assembly accuracy relative to the reference annotation and brings rRNA(&#x02013;) and poly(A)+ assemblies into closer agreement for matched samples.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Long-read and hybrid assembly performance</title><p id="P18">We next evaluated StringTie3 on a hybrid dataset of short- and long-read RNA-seq from induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) differentiating into neurons over five days. The dataset included rRNA-depleted short-read and poly(A)+ long-read sequencing at days 0, 3, and 5.</p><sec id="S7"><title>Long-read assembly</title><p id="P19">We evaluated StringTie3 in long-read mode and compared it to StringTie2 across nine samples from the iPSC-to-neuron differentiation time course. Unlike StringTie2, StringTie3&#x02019;s long-read module discards long reads terminating with a poly(A) tract aligned to the genome&#x02014;likely reflecting incomplete nascent transcripts arising from poly(A) priming artifacts (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>). We ran StringTie3 in both default and nascent modes. In long-read mode, StringTie&#x02019;s default parameters (for both versions) are highly permissive, assembling any transcript supported by a single long read.</p><p id="P20">Using default parameters in annotation-free mode (averaged over the nine samples), StringTie3 nascent mode improved precision by 41.7% relative to StringTie2, with only a minor &#x02212;1.8% drop in sensitivity (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 6C</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6G</xref>). Nascent mode provided only a slight additional improvement in annotation-free conditions, as expected given that the long reads were poly(A)- selected (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>). When sensitivity was matched, StringTie3 consistently outperformed StringTie2 in precision. Under annotation-guided mode, StringTie3 nascent mode increased sensitivity by 40% and precision by 76%, substantially enhancing isoform reconstruction (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>, and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 6A</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6E</xref>). Notably, violin plots (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 6A</xref>) show that StringTie3 produces a tighter precision range, with some samples far exceeding the mean improvement.</p><p id="P21">We next benchmarked StringTie3 against IsoQuant<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>, recently identified as the most accurate long-read assembler in a benchmarking study by Su et al.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. As shown in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, StringTie3 outperforms IsoQuant under both annotation-free (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>) and annotation-guided (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>) modes. In annotation-free mode, at equivalent sensitivity, StringTie3 consistently achieved higher precision in six of the nine samples and was comparable in the remaining three. Under annotation-guided conditions, StringTie3 boosted precision by 15% relative to IsoQuant and identified 64% more reference transcripts.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Hybrid assembly</title><p id="P22">Because StringTie uniquely supports hybrid assembly from short- and long-read data, we compared StringTie3 only to StringTie2 for this dataset. Hybrid data combine the high coverage of short reads with the full-length isoform resolution of long reads, facilitating improved detection of complex splicing events <sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. Given that the short-read sequencing is total RNA-seq, StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent mode is particularly well suited to model co-transcriptional splicing in this dataset.</p><p id="P23">In annotation-free mode, StringTie3 increased precision by 53.5% on average, albeit with a 4.1% decrease in sensitivity (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6D</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6H</xref>). This reduction largely results from more stringent filtering of partial or low-coverage transcripts in hybrid-mode&#x02014;reads that might otherwise be allocated to mature isoforms are recognized as nascent, reducing apparent coverage below the default detection threshold. However, in annotation-guided mode, StringTie3 demonstrates a 53.9% relative gain in precision along with a 28.8% gain in sensitivity, indicating that co-transcriptional modeling and poly(A) artifact filtering work synergistically to enhance transcript reconstruction in hybrid RNA-seq datasets (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6B</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6F</xref>). Moreover, while the average improvement is substantial, examining the violin-plot distributions (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 6B</xref>) shows a tighter precision range for StringTie3, with certain samples far exceeding the mean. In one example, precision nearly doubled from 47.6% (StringTie2) to 83.4% (StringTie3 with nascent mode).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Disentangling nascent and mature RNA to probe transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulation</title><p id="P24">One important application of StringTie3&#x02019;s ability to quantify both nascent and mature RNA species from rRNA-depleted total RNA-seq data is investigating the regulatory dynamics of gene expression. To demonstrate this, we analyzed RNA-seq data from two biologically relevant contexts where both transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulation are at play: (1) Argonaute knockouts in HCT116 cells and (2) tumor&#x02013;normal comparisons in breast cancer samples. These case studies demonstrate how quantifying nascent and mature RNA reveals whether changes in gene expression are primarily driven by transcription or shaped by post-transcriptional mechanisms.</p><p id="P25">In all subsequent experiments, we used StringTie3 in nascent mode to identify and quantify transcripts and performed differential expression analyses for nascent and mature RNA components. To minimize potential noise from incorrectly predicted novel transcripts, we restricted our analysis to transcripts present in the reference annotation and their nascent counterparts (see <xref rid="S20" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>).</p><sec id="S10"><title>Argonaute (AGO1/AGO2) knockouts reveal post-transcriptional buffering</title><p id="P26">To demonstrate StringTie3&#x02019;s ability to distinguish nascent from mature RNA, we analyzed data from Chu et al. (2020) in which AGO1 and AGO2 were knocked out individually or in combination (AGO1/2 and AGO1/2/3) in HCT116 colorectal cancer cells, followed by rRNA-depleted RNA-seq. Argonaute proteins are core components of RNA interference (RNAi) and microRNA pathways and have also been implicated in transcriptional regulation<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>.</p><sec id="S11"><title>Minimal mature-RNA changes in single knockouts</title><p id="P27">To assess how Argonaute proteins influence transcription and mRNA abundance, we compared nascent and mature RNA expression across various knockout conditions. <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6 (A</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">D)</xref> plots nascent (x-axis) vs. mature (y-axis) log&#x02082; fold changes for each knockout relative to wild-type. In single knockouts (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">B</xref>), many genes show large changes in nascent RNA without corresponding changes in mature RNA, suggesting that although Argonaute proteins modulate transcription, other family members buffer the final mRNA levels. Conversely, removing both AGO1 and AGO2 or all three (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6C</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">D</xref>) eliminates this buffering capacity and induces differential expression in both nascent and mature fractions. These findings align with earlier reports of Argonaute-mediated transcriptional regulation<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>HMGA2: a post-transcriptional target of let-7</title><p id="P28">HMGA2 is an oncogene regulated post-transcriptionally by the let-7 microRNA family<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. In single AGO1 or AGO2 knockouts, HMGA2 mRNA levels remain unchanged, whereas double AGO1/2 depletion leads to a two- and four-fold increase (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">H</xref>). Nascent HMGA2 expression remains stable across conditions, suggesting that partial Argonaute loss has little effect on transcription. The lack of change in single knockouts indicates that remaining Argonautes buffer mRNA levels, while combined Argonaute depletion (AGO1/2 and AGO1/2/3) leads to significant accumulation of HMGA2&#x02013;highlighting the role of miRNA-directed decay in maintaining normal HMGA2 expression.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>c-MYC: multiple layers of AGO-mediated regulation</title><p id="P29">c-MYC is an oncogene frequently overexpressed in human cancers and is subject to complex post-transcriptional regulation<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. In single AGO1 or AGO2 knockouts, nascent c-MYC levels double while mature RNA levels remain steady (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6F</xref>), suggesting that each Argonaute represses c-MYC transcription, and the resulting mRNA abundance is buffered post-transcriptionally by the remaining Argonautes. This observation is consistent with prior evidence that AGO1 can repress MYC transcription<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. In AGO1/2 double knockouts, mature c-MYC decreases by ~50% despite stable nascent levels, and triple AGO1/2/3 knockout reduces both fractions. The decrease in mature c-MYC in the double and triple knockouts mirrors results from Chu et al.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>, who found that Argonaute binding in the c-MYC 3&#x02032;UTR does not reliably predict repression. By separately measuring nascent and mature RNA, we show that partial Argonaute loss primarily affects transcription, whereas multi-Argonaute depletion reduces mature c-MYC abundance at both the transcriptional and post-transcriptional levels.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>LDLR: distinguishing transcriptional vs. post-transcriptional effects</title><p id="P30">LDLR is a key regulator of cholesterol homeostasis that is subject to microRNA-mediated transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulation<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. In single AGO1 or AGO2 knockouts, nascent LDLR levels decrease, yet mature LDLR remains unchanged (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6G</xref>), suggesting that Argonaute-mediated transcriptional changes are buffered at the mRNA level by the remaining AGOs. However, in double or triple knockouts, mature LDLR levels increase two- to four-fold despite minimal changes in nascent RNA, revealing a dominant post-transcriptional effect. These observations suggest that LDLR mRNA abundance relies primarily on microRNA-mediated post-transcriptional silencing: losing a single Argonaute reduces transcription but does not alter mature LDLR abundance, while depleting multiple Argonautes disrupts post-transcriptional repression and leads to the observed increase in mature LDLR.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Regulatory insights from StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent and mature RNA analysis</title><p id="P31">Across HMGA2, c-MYC, and LDLR, StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent-mode analysis highlights cases where nascent RNA levels diverge from mature RNA, indicating transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulation. For instance, in c-MYC and LDLR, single Argonaute knockouts alter nascent levels with minimal effect on mature RNA, reflecting redundant buffering by remaining Argonautes. Conversely, removing two or more Argonautes disrupts both nascent and mature RNA abundance, demonstrating the collective role of Argonautes in stabilizing steady-state mRNA levels. This observation is consistent with previous findings that Argonautes act redundantly to buffer gene expression fluctuations, even when one family member is lost<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. See <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">7</xref> for a detailed overview of these differential expression analyses. By analyzing nascent vs. mature fractions, StringTie3 enables researchers to determine whether expression changes stem from altered transcription, post-transcriptional buffering, or both&#x02014;mechanisms that are often obscured in poly(A)-selected or mature-only RNA-seq.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Application of StringTie3 to breast cancer data</title><p id="P32">Building on the Argonaute findings, we next applied StringTie3 to an rRNA-depleted dataset of 21 matched tumor&#x02013;normal breast cancer samples<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. While the Argonaute experiments illustrate how nascent-mode quantification disentangles transcriptional from post-transcriptional effects in a controlled knockout model, the breast cancer dataset shows that the same approach can provide insights into complex regulatory mechanisms in a disease context.</p><sec id="S17"><title>Post-transcriptional regulation of collagens in breast cancer</title><p id="P33">Collagens are increasingly recognized as key factors in tumor dormancy, immune evasion, and treatment response<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. In our nascent vs. mature differential expression analysis (<xref rid="S20" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>), all ten differentially expressed collagen genes lie above the x = y line in a nascent vs. mature log<sub>&#x02082;</sub> fold-change plot (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6I</xref>), indicating stronger upregulation in their mature fractions than in nascent RNA. This trend suggests a shared post-transcriptional mechanism affecting the collagen family. For example, COL5A1 showed negligible changes at the nascent level but was over two-fold higher in its mature fraction, consistent with recent findings linking its overexpression to breast cancer progression and chemoresistance<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. Similarly, COL3A1 undergoes only minor changes in nascent RNA but is substantially elevated in its mature form, aligning with earlier studies that report COL3A1 stabilization in breast cancer<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P34">Several pathways may explain the discrepancy between nascent and mature collagen expression. miR-29, a known tumor suppressor microRNA, negatively regulates collagen<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>, and its downregulation or loss (e.g., miR-29b/c) has been associated with elevated expression of multiple collagen genes<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Additional factors, such as m<sup>6</sup>A modifications<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> or lncRNA &#x0201c;sponges&#x0201d; that sequester collagen-targeting miRNAs<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>, may also contribute to the pronounced differences we observe between nascent and mature collagen RNA. By disentangling these two RNA pools, StringTie3 highlights a post-transcriptional signature underlying collagen overexpression in breast tumors.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Other genes with nascent&#x02013;mature discrepancies</title><p id="P35">Beyond collagens, we identified numerous genes whose nascent and mature expression levels diverge. For instance, FN1 (fibronectin), an extracellular matrix protein that interacts with collagen, increased by over four-fold at the nascent level but more than six-fold in mature RNA, consistent with reports that miR-29 loss can jointly upregulate FN1 and collagens<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. In contrast, the tumor suppressors FHL1 and TNS1 declined by approximately three- and five-fold, respectively, in nascent RNA, yet dropped by more than eight- and twelve-fold in their mature fraction. This pattern suggests additional post-transcriptional regulation beyond the observed transcriptional changes. For instance, FHL1 is repressed by miR-410<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> while TNS1 is targeted by miR-942<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. Other genes, including CRTAP, ALAD, and RGS5, showed elevated nascent RNA but reduced mature levels, indicating that post-transcriptional mechanisms can counterbalance transcriptional upregulation. Refer to <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 8</xref> for the complete differential expression analysis in this breast cancer cohort.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P36">Accurately assembling rRNA-depleted (total) RNA-seq data requires disentangling nascent transcripts from fully processed mature isoforms, a challenge that standard assemblers often overlook. Here, we introduced StringTie3, an updated version of the widely used StringTie algorithm, specifically engineered to address these complexities. By modeling co-transcriptional splicing and filtering internal poly(A)-priming artifacts, StringTie3 substantially improves transcript assembly across a variety of library types&#x02014;short-read, long-read, and hybrid RNA-seq datasets.</p><p id="P37">Our short-read benchmarks show that StringTie3 (nascent mode) consistently outperforms existing tools (StringTie2, Scallop2) in rRNA-depleted datasets from multiple tissue and cell types. Achieving over 20% and 50% higher precision relative to StringTie2 and Scallop2, respectively&#x02014;while maintaining or improving sensitivity&#x02014;highlights how co-transcriptional modeling prevents the high intronic coverage typical of rRNA-depleted libraries from introducing assembly noise. Moreover, analysis of matched rRNA-depleted and poly(A)-selected libraries shows that nascent mode aligns these datasets more closely, underscoring its potential to unify transcript sets across diverse sample-preparation methods.</p><p id="P38">In long-read applications, StringTie3&#x02019;s refined module discards incomplete transcripts arising from intronic poly(A)-priming artifacts, substantially improving assembly. In annotation-guided mode, precision increases by up to 75% and sensitivity by 37% compared to StringTie2. In annotation-free mode, StringTie3 surpasses both StringTie2 and IsoQuant at the same sensitivity level, achieving higher precision and a closer match to the reference annotation. Hybrid assemblies also benefit from nascent mode, especially in datasets that pair rRNA-depleted short-read coverage with the isoform resolution of poly(A)-selected long reads, thereby enabling more accurate reconstruction of complex splicing events.</p><p id="P39">Argonaute knockout experiments illustrate how StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent-mode quantification can distinguish transcriptional changes from post-transcriptional effects. Single Argonaute knockouts elicit large shifts in nascent RNA but little alteration of mature RNA, whereas double or triple knockouts disrupt both fractions. Such findings illustrate the collective role of Argonautes in maintaining steady-state mRNA levels. Similarly, in breast cancer samples, nascent-mode analysis reveals a unifying &#x0201c;collagen signature,&#x0201d; in which differentially expressed collagen genes show greater upregulation in their mature fractions compared to nascent RNA as well as revealing other pathways governed by a combination of transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulation&#x02014;insights typically obscured when only mature RNA is profiled.</p><p id="P40">StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent flag streamlines nascent transcription profiling without requiring specialized protocols such as GRO-seq, PRO-seq, or 4sU-seq. The resulting assemblies capture incomplete nascent RNAs alongside mature transcripts in the same rRNA-depleted sample. In doing so, StringTie3 broadens the applicability of total RNA-seq and opens new avenues to investigate transcriptional and post-transcriptional dynamics. Clinical samples often cannot accommodate nascent RNA assays, which require actively transcribing cells, so StringTie3 offers a practical solution for characterizing both nascent and mature transcripts simultaneously. Moreover, poly(A) selection in degraded or biopsy-derived samples often biases analyses toward shorter isoforms, whereas combining rRNA libraries with StringTie3&#x02019;s improved assembly better captures full-length transcripts, expanding the scope of total RNA-seq in translational research.</p><p id="P41">By explicitly modeling co-transcriptional splicing and filtering spurious poly(A)-priming events, StringTie3 fully leverages total RNA-seq data: reducing assembly errors, boosting precision and sensitivity, and enabling the separation of nascent from mature RNAs in one experiment. This comprehensive approach not only illuminates hidden layers of RNA regulation but also lays the groundwork for a more complete exploration of transcriptomes, particularly in scenarios where poly(A)-selected libraries or specialized nascent-capture methods are impractical.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S21"><title>StringTie3 Algorithm</title><p id="P42">StringTie3 extends the original StringTie algorithm<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> to improve transcriptome assembly, particularly from rRNA-depleted (total) RNA-seq data, through two main innovations: a &#x0201c;nascent mode&#x0201d; for modeling co-transcriptional splicing and a refined long-read module for filtering artifacts.</p><p id="P43">Similar to the original StringTie algorithm, StringTie3 reconstructs transcripts at each gene locus by first building a splice graph from overlapping read alignments in that locus. The nodes in this splice graph represent contiguous genomic regions and edges represent reads&#x02014;either single reads or paired-end fragments (hereafter referred to as <italic toggle="yes">transfrags</italic>)&#x02014;that align across two such nodes in the correct 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; orientation. It is important to note that nodes do not necessarily correspond to complete exons but may represent partial exons, as illustrated by node 3 in <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>. Two additional nodes, a global source (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and a sink (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), are added to the graph so that any path from source to sink represents a potential transcript.</p><p id="P44">To identify transcripts at a locus, StringTie3 iteratively selects a candidate transcript as the heaviest path from source to sink (i.e., the path with the highest overall read coverage) and constructs a generalized flow network restricted to the nodes along that path. Formally, the generalized flow network is defined as a quadruple <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a directed graph with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" display="inline"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> representing the nodes along the candidate transcript path, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" display="inline"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the set of directed edges connecting two nodes if a transfrag starts at one and ends at the other, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the source and sink nodes of the network, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a function assigning to each edge a capacity equal to the number of transfrags supporting it. A function <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a <italic toggle="yes">flow</italic> over the network <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> if the following two conditions are satisfied:
<list list-type="order" id="L1"><list-item><p id="P45"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, for every <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P46"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, for every node <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P47">where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a gain factor associated with each node <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" display="inline"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> that accounts for coverage bias in RNA-seq data. This factor is computed during splice graph construction as:
<disp-formula id="FD1">
<mml:math id="M20" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="" open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable equalrows="true" equalcolumns="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the sets of transfrags entering and exiting node <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" display="inline"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively. The value of the flow is defined as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P48">Once the flow network is built, StringTie3 estimates the abundance of the candidate transcript by solving a <italic toggle="yes">maximum flow problem</italic> that identifies a flow <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" display="inline"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> with maximum value in the network <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. This flow value is then used to compute the transcript&#x02019;s abundance by attributing a corresponding fraction of the coverage from all nodes along the path to the transcript, reflecting the proportion of transfrags explained by this transcript relative to the total coverage. The intuition behind this flow network design is that StringTie3 attempts to stitch together compatible fragments that collectively account for the maximum number of reads supporting the underlying transcript path. In default mode (non-nascent), after the transfrags that contribute to the maximum flow are removed from the splice graph the process repeats until no remaining path meets a minimum coverage threshold.</p><p id="P49">To address the abundance of incomplete, nascent transcripts common in total RNA-seq, StringTie3 incorporates a &#x02018;nascent mode&#x02019; that explicitly models these co-transcriptional splicing intermediates, distinguishing them from fully processed, mature isoforms. This mode is activated using either the <monospace>--nasc</monospace> or <monospace>-N</monospace> flag. The <monospace>--nasc</monospace> flag includes the assembled nascent intermediates (representing partially spliced forms) in the output GTF file, whereas the <monospace>-N</monospace> flag performs the internal modeling and read assignment adjustments but excludes these nascent transcript models from the final output, reporting only mature forms. The key algorithmic modifications enabling this are:</p><sec id="S22"><label>1.</label><title>Intronic Node Representation</title><p id="P50">In nascent mode, StringTie3 systematically introduces &#x02018;intronic nodes&#x02019; into the splice graph at every exon-exon splice junction. An edge is added connecting each intronic node to the terminus (sink node). This structure explicitly represents unspliced introns and allows transcript paths to terminate within them, modeling incomplete nascent RNA molecules.</p><p id="P51">This approach differs from the original StringTie algorithm, which typically incorporates intronic regions only when there is direct read evidence supporting their inclusion&#x02014;such as reads spanning intron&#x02013;exon boundaries. In contrast, StringTie3 includes intronic nodes even in the absence of such spanning reads (e.g., node 1_2 in <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>), as long as the intron shows non-zero coverage. The original method is sensitive to the variable and often low read coverage found in introns, frequently misinterpreting coverage gaps as transcript start or end points. This can result in inappropriate edges from the source or to the sink node, prematurely terminating transcript paths within introns or generating fragmented assemblies based on patchy coverage.</p><p id="P52">To address this issue, StringTie3 creates additional intronic nodes to ensure that the entire intron is represented, even when nodes from the original algorithm cover only portions of the intronic region. Formally, in nascent mode, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are two nodes in the original splice graph that are linked by a splice junction, and the intron between them has non-zero coverage, then StringTie3 ensures there is a path <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the splice graph that spans the entire intronic region. In this path, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and each pair of consecutive nodes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, are adjacent in the genomic coordinate space. New nodes are added as needed to represent regions of the intron not already covered by nodes in the original graph. If no edge exists between any pair <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, StringTie3 adds a virtual transfrag with a minimal abundance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (default: 1). The final intronic node <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mtext>_</mml:mtext><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is also connected to the sink node by another virtual transfrag with abundance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, explicitly modeling nascent transcripts.</p><p id="P53">For example, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref> illustrates a case where the original graph includes nodes 3, 4, and 5 within the intron between nodes 2 and 6. StringTie3 adds a new node, 5_6, to span a previously unrepresented region and connects it to both node 5 and the sink. This approach enables StringTie3 to allocate intronic reads to co-transcriptional intermediates and avoid misassemblies caused by uneven coverage. To achieve this, it uses the maximum flow algorithm described above to estimate the proportion of reads attributable to intronic nodes, distinguishing between alternative isoforms and nascent transcription.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><label>2.</label><title>Heaviest Path &#x00026; Flow Update</title><p id="P54">The core iterative process of identifying the heaviest path (representing the most abundant mature isoform) and assigning coverage using the maximum-flow algorithm remains similar to that of the original StringTie. However, after identifying a candidate transcript as the heaviest path in the splice graph and computing its abundance using the maximum-flow algorithm, StringTie3 removes all transfrags that contributed to that transcript and proceeds to identify all nascent transcripts associated with it. Coverage is then assigned to each nascent path by constructing a separate flow network for each one (see <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref>). Once the abundance of a nascent transcript is computed, the transfrags associated with it are removed. Only after all nascent transcript abundances have been estimated does StringTie3 search for the next heaviest path in the updated graph.</p><p id="P55">StringTie3 refines the long-read module introduced in StringTie2<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> by adding two complementary filters that reduce spurious isoforms caused by intronic poly(A) priming. For single-exon alignment, the algorithm scans the first and last 25 bp that map to the genome. Reads in which at least 80% of the aligned 3&#x02019; bases are adenines (or 5&#x02019; bases are thymines), or that contain a homopolymer run of more than 10 consecutive A/T bases, are flagged as poly(A)-priming artifact and discarded. When the nascent mode is enabled, the remaining long-read assemblies are evaluated locus by locus: a candidate isoform is labelled a nascent intermediate when its exon chain matches the 5&#x02032; portion of a longer transcript yet terminates within one of that transcript&#x02019;s introns, consistent with co-transcriptional splicing in which the final intron has not yet been removed. Whether these intermediates appear in the final GTF is user-controlled: <monospace>-- nasc</monospace> retains them and tags each record as &#x0201c;nascent,&#x0201d; whereas <monospace>-N</monospace> performs the same classification but omits nascent models from the output file.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Reference Genome and Annotation</title><p id="P56">All RNA-seq datasets were aligned to the human reference genome GRCh38 (RefSeq accession GCF_000001405.39), excluding pseudoautosomal regions on chromosome Y and alternative scaffolds. Guided transcript assembly and accuracy assessment were performed using the CHESS version 3.0.1 annotation, filtered to retain only full-length protein-coding and long non-coding RNA (lncRNA) transcripts. The filtered annotation is available at <ext-link xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ccb.jhu.edu/pub/StringTie3" ext-link-type="ftp">ftp://ftp.ccb.jhu.edu/pub/StringTie3</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Alignment</title><sec id="S26"><title>Short-Read Data</title><p id="P57">Short reads were aligned using HISAT2 (v2.2.1)<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. A genome index was built incorporating splice sites and exons from the CHESS 3.0.1 annotation using <monospace>hisat2-build -p 16 -- exon genome.exon --ss genome.ss genome.fa hisat_index</monospace>. Alignments were performed with <monospace>hisat2 -p 8 -x hisat_index &#x02212;1 R1.fastq &#x02212;2 R2.fastq -S aligned.sam</monospace>. For strand-specific libraries (fr-firstrand), the --rna-strandedness RF flag was added.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Long-Read Data</title><p id="P58">Long reads (ONT) from the neuron differentiation dataset were aligned using minimap2 (v2.28-r1209)<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. A genome index was built using <monospace>minimap2 -k14 -d mm2_index.mmi</monospace>. Alignments were performed with <monospace>minimap2 -ax splice --junc-bed short_read_junctions.bed mm2_index.mmi sample.fastq &#x0003e; aligned.sam</monospace>. The <monospace>-k14</monospace> parameter was used as recommended for ONT reads. The <monospace>short_read_junctions.bed</monospace> file contained splice junctions identified from the corresponding short-read samples after alignment and filtering (see below).</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Alignment File Processing</title><p id="P59">Resulting SAM files were converted to sorted, indexed BAM format using samtools (v1.20). To remove spurious alignments potentially arising from library preparation artifacts or mapping errors, particularly short-read junctions, BAM files were processed using EASTR (v1.1.0)<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> with default parameters before transcriptome assembly.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Transcriptome Assembly</title><p id="P60">Transcriptome assembly was performed using several tools and configurations to evaluate performance across different data types (short-read, long-read, hybrid) and conditions. Where applicable (StringTie2, StringTie3, IsoQuant) assemblies were executed in both annotation-free (de novo) mode and annotation-guided mode (using the filtered CHESS 3.0.1 reference annotation). The specific assemblers and key configurations tested included:</p><sec id="S30"><title>StringTie3 (v3.0.0):</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L2"><list-item><p id="P61">Short-read (Default): <monospace>stringtie -o output.gtf aligned.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P62">Short-read (Nascent Mode): <monospace>stringtie --nasc -o output.gtf aligned.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P63">Long-read (Default): <monospace>stringtie -L -o output.gtf aligned.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P64">Long-read (Nascent Mode): <monospace>stringtie -L --nasc -o output_lr_nasc.gtf aligned.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P65">Hybrid (Default): <monospace>stringtie -o output.gtf --mix short_read.bam long_read.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P66">Hybrid (Nascent Mode): <monospace>stringtie &#x02013;nasc -o output.gtf --mix short_read.bam long_read.bam</monospace></p></list-item></list><p id="P67">Flags: <monospace>-G reference_annotation.gtf</monospace> was added for annotation-guided assembly. <monospace>--rf</monospace> was added for stranded short-read libraries.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>StringTie2 (v2.2.3):</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L3"><list-item><p id="P68">Short-read: <monospace>stringtie -o output.gtf aligned.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P69">Long-read: <monospace>stringtie -L -o output.gtf aligned.bam</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P70">Hybrid: <monospace>stringtie -o output.gtf --mix short_read.bam long_read.bam</monospace></p></list-item></list><p id="P71">Flags: <monospace>-G reference_annotation.gtf</monospace> was added for annotation-guided assembly. <monospace>--rf</monospace> was added for stranded short-read libraries.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Scallop2 (v1.1.2):</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L4"><list-item><p id="P72">Short-read: <monospace>scallop2 -i aligned.bam -o output.gtf</monospace></p></list-item></list><p id="P73">Flags: <monospace>--library_type first</monospace> was used for stranded libraries (equivalent to <monospace>--rf</monospace> in StringTie).</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>IsoQuant (v3.6):</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L5"><list-item><p id="P74">Long-read (Annotation-free): <monospace>isoquant.py --reference reference_genome.fasta --bam aligned.bam --data_type nanopore -o output_dir</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P75">Long-read (Annotation-guided): <monospace>isoquant.py --reference reference_genome.fasta --bam aligned.bam --data_type nanopore --complete_genedb reference_annotation.gtf -o output_dir</monospace></p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="S34"><title>Assembly accuracy metrics</title><p id="P76">Assembly accuracy was evaluated against the filtered CHESS 3.0.1 reference annotation using gffcompare (v0.12.6)<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>. An assembled transcript was considered a correct match (True Positive, TP) if it shared the exact same splice junction chain as a reference transcript and its terminal exon boundaries were within 100 bp of the reference transcript&#x02019;s boundaries. Sensitivity was calculated as TP / (TP + FN), where FN (False Negatives) represent reference transcripts not found in the assembly. Precision was calculated as TP / (TP + FP), where FP (False Positives) represent assembled transcripts not matching any reference transcript. It should be noted that some FPs may correspond to genuine but unannotated transcripts.</p><p id="P77">Relative percentage changes in sensitivity (Sr) and precision (Pr) between StringTie3 with the nascent flag (Method 1) and a comparison method (Method 2) were calculated as:
<disp-formula id="FD2">
<mml:math id="M41" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD3">
<mml:math id="M42" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula></p><p id="P78">Where S1 and P1 are the sensitivity and precision of StringTie3 (nascent mode), and S2 and P2 are the sensitivity and precision of the comparison method.</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>Differential Expression Analysis of Mature and Nascent Transcripts</title><p id="P79">Transcriptomes were first assembled using StringTie3 (run with <monospace>--nasc -G reference.gtf</monospace>). This process generates transcript models in GTF format, where mature and nascent transcripts matching the provided reference annotation are flagged (via <monospace>ref_gene_id</monospace> and <monospace>reference_id</monospace> attributes) and include a per-transcript coverage estimate (the <monospace>cov</monospace> attribute). Gene-level read counts for differential expression analysis were subsequently derived using a custom python script based on this StringTie3 output. Specifically, for each assembled transcript identified by StringTie3 and matching the CHESS 3.0.1 reference annotation, an estimated read count was calculated using the formula:
<disp-formula id="FD4">
<mml:math id="M43" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula></p><p id="P80">In this formula, &#x02018;Transcript Coverage&#x02019; corresponds to the value of the <monospace>cov</monospace> attribute from the StringTie3 GTF output, &#x02018;Transcript Length&#x02019; is the total exonic length of the assembled transcript in base pairs, and &#x02018;Library Read Length&#x02019; is the average read length of the sequencing library. For each gene, &#x02018;mature counts&#x02019; were then calculated by summing these estimated read counts over all assembled transcripts matching annotated mature isoforms of that gene. Correspondingly, &#x02018;nascent counts&#x02019; were calculated by summing the estimated read counts of assembled nascent transcripts (identified by StringTie3 with the nascent flag and associated with the same parent gene ID) matching that gene.</p><p id="P81">Differential expression analysis comparing tumor and matched normal samples (breast cancer dataset) or knockout and wild-type conditions (Argonaute dataset) was performed on the derived gene-level counts, separately for mature and nascent transcript populations, using R (v4.3.1) with the edgeR (v4.0.3)<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> and limma (v3.58.1)<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> Bioconductor packages. To account for inherent differences between the two RNA fractions, mature and nascent counts were processed independently. Given that low gene expression can lead to incomplete transcript reconstruction by assembly, potentially affecting mature and nascent quantification differently, a stringent filtering step was applied prior to differential analysis. Genes were retained only if they exhibited counts per million (CPM) exceeding 1 in all samples, ensuring analysis was focused on genes with reliable quantification across all conditions; this filter was applied separately to mature and nascent count matrices. Library sizes and compositional biases were normalized using the Trimmed Mean of M-values (TMM) method (<monospace>edgeR::calcNormFactors</monospace>). Normalized counts were transformed using <monospace>limma::voom</monospace>, which estimates the mean-variance relationship and computes precision weights for linear modeling (<monospace>limma::lmFit</monospace>). For the paired breast cancer data, inter-patient variability was modeled using <monospace>limma::duplicateCorrelation</monospace>, incorporating the resulting correlation into <monospace>lmFit</monospace> via the block argument (patient ID). For non-paired Argonaute data, standard linear models were used. Contrasts were defined for comparisons of interest, and empirical Bayes moderation (<monospace>limma::eBayes</monospace>) was applied to stabilize variances and calculate p-values, which were adjusted for multiple testing using the Benjamini-Hochberg method to control the false discovery rate (FDR).</p><p id="P82">To generate the scatter plots comparing nascent and mature RNA regulation (e.g., <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), the log<sub>2</sub> fold change (log2FC) values for both the nascent and mature component of each gene were retrieved from the differential expression results described above. For improved clarity and to focus on more robustly expressed genes in the visualization, an additional filter was applied: only genes for which both the nascent and mature components had an average expression (calculated across all samples in the comparison) of at least 8 CPM were included in these plots. In the scatter plots, the log2FC of the nascent fraction was plotted against the log2FC of the mature fraction for each qualifying gene. Genes were considered significantly differentially expressed if the FDR was less than 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1</label><media xlink:href="media-1.pdf" id="d67e1930" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 2</label><media xlink:href="media-2.xlsx" id="d67e1933" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S36"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P83">This work was supported in part by NSF grant DBI-2412449 (M.P.) and NIH grants R01-MH123567 and R35-GM156470 (M.P.).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2"><p id="P85">Code Availability</p><p id="P86">StringTie3 is implemented in C++ and is freely available as open-source software under the MIT license at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/gpertea/stringtie" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/gpertea/stringtie</ext-link>. Additional instructions for running nascent mode, including parameters and command-line flags, can be found in the project documentation.</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p id="P87">Competing Interests</p><p id="P88">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S37"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="P84">The RNA-Seq data for DLPFC poly(A) and DLPFC RiboZ libraries are available through the Lieber Institute for Brain Development at <ext-link xlink:href="http://eqtl.brainseq.org/phase2/" ext-link-type="uri">http://eqtl.brainseq.org/phase2/</ext-link> and <ext-link xlink:href="http://eqtl.brainseq.org/phase1/" ext-link-type="uri">http://eqtl.brainseq.org/phase1/</ext-link>, respectively. The neuron differentiation long and short read RNA-seq data are accessible in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) under accession number GSE245325, and the breast cancer RNA-seq dataset is available in GEO under accession number GSE103001.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grzelak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNA sequencing: the teenage years</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews. Genetics</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>656</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>A comparison of experimental assays and analytical methods for genome-wide identification of active enhancers</article-title>. <source>Nature biotechnology</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1056</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1065</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Chromatin run-on and sequencing maps the transcriptional regulatory landscape of glioblastoma multiforme</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1564</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30349114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gaidatzis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Florescu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Analysis of intronic and exonic reads in RNA-seq data characterizes transcriptional and post-transcriptional regulation</article-title>. <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>722</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>729</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ameur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Total RNA sequencing reveals nascent transcription and widespread co-transcriptional splicing in the human brain</article-title>. <source>Nature structural &#x00026; molecular biology</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1440</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gamini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>von Schack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of two main RNA-seq approaches for gene quantification in clinical RNA sequencing: polyA+ selection versus rRNA depletion</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>4781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29556074</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adiconis</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Comparative analysis of RNA sequencing methods for degraded or low-input samples</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>629</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23685885</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>StringTie enables improved reconstruction of a transcriptome from RNA-seq reads</article-title>. <source>Nature biotechnology</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kovaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Transcriptome assembly from long-read RNA-seq alignments with StringTie2</article-title>. <source>Genome Biology</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31842956</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Choquet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Pre-mRNA splicing order is predetermined and maintains splicing fidelity across multi-intronic transcripts</article-title>. <source>Nature structural &#x00026; molecular biology</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1064</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1076</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Internal oligo(dT) priming introduces systematic bias in bulk and single-cell RNA sequencing count data</article-title>. <source>NAR genomics and bioinformatics</source>
<volume>4</volume>, lqac035 (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viscardi</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Arribere</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name> Poly(a) <article-title>selection introduces bias and undue noise in direct RNA-sequencing</article-title>. <source>BMC genomics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>530</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34979896</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>A joint NCBI and EMBL-EBI transcript set for clinical genomics and research</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>604</volume>, <fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>315</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35388217</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shumate</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Improved transcriptome assembly using a hybrid of long and short reads with StringTie</article-title>. <source>PLoS computational biology</source>
<volume>18</volume>, e1009730 (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Accurate assembly of multi-end RNA-seq data with Scallop2</article-title>. <source>Nature Computational Science</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>152</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36713932</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collado-Torres</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Regional Heterogeneity in Gene Expression, Regulation, and Coherence in the Frontal Cortex and Hippocampus across Development and Schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>.e8 (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31174959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Developmental and genetic regulation of the human cortex transcriptome illuminate schizophrenia pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1125</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30050107</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wenric</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Transcriptome-wide analysis of natural antisense transcripts shows their potential role in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Scientific reports</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>17452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29234122</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ulicevic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Uncovering the dynamics and consequences of RNA isoform changes during neuronal differentiation</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>798</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38755290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Varabyou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>CHESS 3: an improved, comprehensive catalog of human genes and transcripts based on large-scale expression data, phylogenetic analysis, and protein structure</article-title>. <source>Genome Biology</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37904256</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nido</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Common gene expression signatures in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease are driven by changes in cell composition</article-title>. <source>Acta neuropathologica communications</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prjibelski</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Accurate isoform discovery with IsoQuant using long reads</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>915</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>918</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36593406</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Comprehensive assessment of mRNA isoform detection methods for long-read sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>3972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38730241</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cernilogar</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Chromatin-associated RNAi components contribute to transcriptional regulation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature (London)</source>
<volume>480</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>395</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22056986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zaytseva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Transcriptional repression of Myc underlies the tumour suppressor function of AGO1 in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Development (Cambridge)</source>
<volume>147</volume> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Ago1 Interacts with RNA Polymerase II and Binds to the Promoters of Actively Transcribed Genes in Human Cancer Cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hemann</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Disrupting the Pairing Between let-7 and Hmga2 Enhances Oncogenic Transformation</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>315</volume>, <fpage>1576</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1579</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322030</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>MYC on the Path to Cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>149</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Argonaute binding within 3&#x02032;-untranslated regions poorly predicts gene repression</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>7439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7453</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501500</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Activation of LDL Receptor Expression by Small RNAs Complementary to a Noncoding Transcript that Overlaps the LDLR Promoter</article-title>. <source>Chemistry &#x00026; biology</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1355</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21168770</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wagschal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification of microRNAs regulating cholesterol and triglyceride homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1297</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26501192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trombly</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>Essential and overlapping functions for mammalian Argonautes in microRNA silencing</article-title>. <source>Genes &#x00026; Development</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19174539</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Martino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Bravo-Cordero</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Collagens in Cancer: Structural Regulators and Guardians of Cancer Progression</article-title>. <source>Cancer research (Chicago, Ill.)</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>1386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1392</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>COL5A1 promotes triple-negative breast cancer progression by activating tumor cell-macrophage crosstalk</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1742</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1756</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38609499</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Reduced Expression of METTL3 Promotes Metastasis of Triple-Negative Breast Cancer by m6A Methylation-Mediated COL3A1 Up-Regulation</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in oncology</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1126</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32766145</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Factora</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Kota</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Systematic Review of miR-29 in Cancer</article-title>. <source>Molecular therapy. Oncolytics</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30788428</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>Chaperone Hsp47 Drives Malignant Growth and Invasion by Modulating an ECM Gene Network</article-title>. <source>Cancer Research</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>1580</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1591</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25744716</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>. <article-title>LncRNA LINC00511 promotes COL1A1-mediated proliferation and metastasis by sponging miR-126&#x02013;5p/miR-218&#x02013;5p in lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>BMC pulmonary medicine</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34980061</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>MiR-410 Is Overexpressed in Liver and Colorectal Tumors and Enhances Tumor Cell Growth by Silencing FHL1 via a Direct/Indirect Mechanism</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>9</volume>, e108708 (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <etal/>
<article-title>lncRNA ZNRD1-AS1 promotes malignant lung cell proliferation, migration, and angiogenesis via the miR-942/TNS1 axis and is positively regulated by the m6A reader YTHDC2</article-title>. <source>Molecular cancer</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36581942</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paggi</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Graph-based genome alignment and genotyping with HISAT2 and HISAT-genotype</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>915</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31375807</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Minimap2: pairwise alignment for nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>3094</fpage>&#x02013; <lpage>3100</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29750242</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shinder</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>EASTR: Identifying and eliminating systematic alignment errors in multi-exon genes</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>7223</fpage> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37940654</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>GFF Utilities: GffRead and GffCompare</article-title>. <source>F1000 research</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Limma Powers Differential Expression Analyses for RNA-Sequencing and Microarray Studies</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>e47</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25605792</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Comparison of poly(A)+ selection and rRNA-depletion reveals misassemblies arising from nascent transcripts.</title><p id="P89"><bold>(A)</bold> Schematic comparing poly(A)+ selection, which enriches for mature polyadenylated RNAs (blue) but may also capture poly(A)-priming artifacts (green transcripts with internal poly(A) sequences), and rRNA depletion (rRNA(&#x02212;)), which removes ribosomal RNAs (gray) while retaining mature polyadenylated RNAs (blue), non-polyadenylated RNAs (e.g., circRNAs in orange, histone and other RNAs in yellow), and incomplete nascent transcripts (green).</p><p id="P90"><bold>(B)</bold> Read coverage and transcript assemblies at the <italic toggle="yes">AUTS2</italic> locus in rRNA-depleted (blue) and poly(A)+ (green) RNA-seq data, each assembled with StringTie2. The reference MANE annotation<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> (black) depicts exons (rectangles) and introns (connecting lines). In rRNA-depleted data, intronic reads are misassembled as exons, obscuring an annotated exon (orange arrow) that is accurately reconstructed in poly(A)+ data. The sawtooth pattern (gray highlight) in rRNA-depleted coverage reflects co-transcriptional intron removal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Modeling partially spliced nascent transcripts and mature isoforms within StringTie3&#x02019;s splicing graph.</title><p id="P91"><bold>(A)</bold> A hypothetical gene model illustrates how introns are progressively transcribed (green lines) and eventually spliced out (gray lines). As the RNA polymerase advances, co-transcriptional splicing removes fully transcribed introns, creating partially spliced intermediates with decreasing intron coverage. Rather than producing a separate transcript for every incremental intron extension, StringTie3 consolidates each set of co-transcriptional intermediates into a single nascent transcript (pink lines). This captures multiple maturation states for every intron. <bold>(B)</bold> A gene with three isoforms (all containing three exons) is transcribed into both fully spliced (mature) RNAs and partially spliced (nascent) RNAs. Although all three isoforms share the first exon, the second isoform (green) skips exon 2, and the third isoform (dark blue) skips exon 3. Each isoform produces one or more nascent intermediates; arrows indicate the longest nascent RNA for each intron. <bold>(C)</bold> Splicing graph constructed under the assumption that only mature isoforms are present. The two yellow nodes (s and t) mark the source and sink of the transcripts. <bold>(D)</bold> In nascent mode, StringTie3 adds intronic nodes and edges (shown in pink) to represent transcripts that terminate within unspliced introns. By allowing intronic nodes to connect to the sink node (t), the graph accurately models incompletely processed RNAs co-existing with mature isoforms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Comparison of StringTie3 (nascent mode), StringTie2, and Scallop2 in rRNA-depleted RNA-seq</title><p id="P92"><bold>(A)</bold> Relative changes in sensitivity (top panel) and precision (bottom panel) of StringTie3 (nascent mode) versus StringTie2 (dark blue bars) and Scallop2 (light blue bars) across 30 rRNA-depleted RNA-seq samples from three distinct datasets: Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex (DLPFC), Breast Cancer (tumor&#x02013;normal pairs), and Neuron Differentiation (Day 0&#x02013;Day 5). Positive values indicate improved sensitivity or precision for StringTie3 relative to the other assemblers, while negative values indicate a decrease. Although Scallop2 occasionally shows a 1&#x02013;4% relative sensitivity increase over StringTie3, it generally lags by more than 40% in precision. <bold>(B)</bold> A gene locus with multiple introns and variable intronic coverage, where Scallop2 and StringTie2 interpret coverage dips as transcript boundaries (orange marker, 5 kb region), producing partial transcripts that lower precision. In contrast, StringTie3 classifies these coverage dips as nascent RNA. When the coverage drop exceeds the variability of the intronic region, StringTie3 properly assembles a transcript end that matches the reference annotation (pink marker, 10 kb region). <bold>(C)</bold> Zoomed view of the orange region in (B) highlighting an intronic coverage dip interpreted as a transcript end by Scallop2 and StringTie2 but not by StringTie3. <bold>(D)</bold> Zoomed view of the pink region in (B) (10 kb marker) showing a significant coverage drop that StringTie3 correctly treats as a transcript boundary.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Precision, sensitivity, and coverage differences for StringTie2 vs. StringTie3 (nascent mode) in poly(A)+ and rRNA-depleted libraries.</title><p id="P93"><bold>(A-D)</bold> Violin plots of precision and <bold>(E-H)</bold> sensitivity in poly(A)+ (green) and rRNA-depleted (blue) libraries, each evaluated in annotation-guided and annotation-free modes. Each distribution represents 144 matched DLPFC RNA-seq samples, with medians and quartiles shown by dashed lines. Across all conditions, StringTie3 (nascent mode) consistently achieves higher precision than StringTie2 while maintaining or improving sensitivity. <bold>(I)</bold> Coverage and StringTie3 assemblies in rRNA-depleted (blue) versus poly(A)+ (green) libraries. The rRNA-depleted data shows relatively uniform coverage across exons, enabling full-length transcript assembly, whereas coverage in the poly(A)+ library sharply declines toward the 5&#x02032; end and prevents complete assembly of the transcript. In this example, StringTie3 assembles two reference transcripts from the rRNA(&#x02212;) library, while in the poly(A)+ library, low 5&#x02032; coverage yields a single truncated transcript.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Long-Read Assembly Performance of StringTie3, StringTie2, and IsoQuant</title><p id="P94"><bold>(A)</bold> Annotation-free mode. Each panel plots precision (x-axis) vs. number of matched reference transcripts (y-axis) for a single sample at days 0, 3, and 5 (three replicates each). StringTie2 is shown in blue, StringTie3 in green, StringTie3 nascent mode in orange, and IsoQuant in yellow. Curves are generated by varying the minimum coverage threshold used to filter low-coverage transcripts before calculating sensitivity and precision. On average, StringTie3 achieves higher precision than StringTie2, and nascent mode adds only a minor improvement in annotation-free conditions. <bold>(B)</bold> Annotation-guided mode. Scatter plots of precision vs. matched reference transcript counts for the same nine samples. StringTie3 shows substantial gains in both precision and sensitivity over StringTie2 and IsoQuant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Argonaute Knockouts Reveal Transcriptional vs. Post-Transcriptional Regulation</title><p id="P95"><bold>(A&#x02013;D)</bold> Scatter plots of nascent (x-axis) vs. mature (y-axis) log<sub>2</sub> fold changes for AGO1 <italic toggle="yes">(A)</italic>, AGO2 <italic toggle="yes">(B)</italic>, AGO1/2 <italic toggle="yes">(C)</italic>, and AGO1/2/3 <italic toggle="yes">(D)</italic> knockouts relative to wild type. Dots are colored yellow if FDR-adjusted p &#x0003c; 0.05 in both analyses, blue if significant only in mature, and reddish purple if significant only in nascent<bold>. (E&#x02013;G)</bold> Fold-change bar plots for HMGA2, c-MYC, and LDLR, each comparing nascent vs. mature fold changes for single (AGO1, AGO2) and double/triple (AGO1/2, AGO1/2/3) knockouts. <bold>(H)</bold> Coverage tracks of HMGA2 in WT, AGO1 KO, AGO2 KO, AGO1/2 KO, and AGO1/2/3 KO cells, illustrating how multi-Argonaute depletion shifts the mature-to-nascent RNA ratio, consistent with panel E. <bold>(I)</bold> A scatter plot of nascent (x-axis) vs. mature (y-axis) log<sub>2</sub> fold changes&#x02014;mirroring panels (A&#x02013;D) but applied to 21 matched tumor&#x02013;normal rRNA-depleted breast cancer samples. Notably, collagens appear above the diagonal (y = x), indicating stronger post-transcriptional upregulation than co-transcriptional changes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>StringTie3&#x02019;s nascent mode algorithm.</title><p id="P96"><bold>A</bold>. Candidate transcript selection and quantification in a gene locus. Read coverage is shown at the top, with regions corresponding to the candidate transcript highlighted in orange. Arcs below the coverage plot represent splice junctions supported by spliced reads; thicker arcs indicate stronger read support. The splice graph, with the candidate transcript (i.e., the heaviest path) highlighted in orange, is shown below. Arrows beneath the coverage plot indicate the genomic regions corresponding to the nodes in the splice graph. Dashed nodes and edges (e.g., nodes 1_2 and 5_6) represent intronic nodes that, due to sparse coverage, are not included in the splice graph when using the non-nascent mode. A flow network (highlighted in green) is then constructed using all nodes from the heaviest path, with edges connecting two nodes if a transfrag starts at one and ends at the other. <bold>B</bold>. Nascent transcript quantification. Splice graphs and flow networks corresponding to the two nascent transcripts derived from the transcript in panel A are shown. The paths of the nascent transcripts are highlighted in orange in the splice graphs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.05.21.655404v1-f0007" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>