<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40475633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12139728</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.01.05.574406</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">2</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The control of overt and covert attention across two nodes of the attention-control network</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0820-4601</contrib-id><name><surname>Polosecki</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steenrod</surname><given-names>Sara C.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stemmann</surname><given-names>Heiko</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Freiwald</surname><given-names>Winrich A.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>The Rockefeller University, 1230 York Ave, New York, NY 10065, U.S.A.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Computational Biology Center, T.J. Watson IBM Research Laboratory, 1101 Kitchawan Rd, Yorktown Heights, NY 10598, U.S.A.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Michigan State University, 426 Auditorium Road, East Lansing, MI 48824, U.S.A.</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Institute for Brain Research &#x00026; Center for Advanced Imaging, University of Bremen, P.O.B. 330440, D-28334 Bremen, FR Germany</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</p><p id="P2">P.P., S.C.S., and W.A.F. conceived experiments. H.S. provided experimental resources. P.P. and S.C.S. performed experiments. P.P. analyzed experiments. P.P. and W.A.F. wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>pipolose@us.ibm.com</email> (P.P.); <email>wfreiwald@rockefeller.edu</email> (W.A.F.)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2024.01.05.574406</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to copy and distribute the material in any medium or format in unadapted form only, for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2024.01.05.574406.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P3">Attention is a central cognitive capability whose focus is thought to be directed by a spatial map coding behavioral priority. Here we tested the three defining properties of priority map theory with electrophysiological recordings from two attentional control areas. Both areas, lateral intraparietal area LIP and dorsal posterior inferotemporal cortex PITd, selected behaviorally relevant locations even in the absence of visual stimuli (cognitive sustainment principle). Second, priority signals are thought to arise from the summation of multiple spatial signals (superposition principle). LIP approximated linear summation for visual stimuli, spatial attention, and eye movements, while PITd did not. Third, the same priority signal should guide different behaviors (agnosticity principle). LIP, instead, used separable processing channels for representing attentional focus and eye position, while PITd coded attentional focus only. Thus primate attentional control circuits implement multiple priority maps, whose functional diversity and dimensionality increase the computational capacity of attentional selection.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="P4">Areas of attention control in parietal and prefrontal cortex (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) contain spatial maps of the visual world (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). These maps are thought to encode a priority signal that can direct attention to a region of interest in space or a saccadic eye movement (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The theory of priority maps includes a set of prescriptions for how priority is assembled from different visual and cognitive sources, and for the informational contents of the resulting signal in neural populations.</p><p id="P5">First, one basic property of attention control areas is their ability to highlight task-relevant spatial locations even in the absence of a visual stimulus (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), a feature we will refer to here as cognitive sustainment. This has frequently been shown as spatial tuning of neurons during the memory epoch in memory-guided saccade (MGS) tasks, where animals are required to make a saccade to remembered locations not signaled by a persistent visual stimulus. Cognitive sustainment has thus been proposed as characteristic of cognitive control, in contrast to earlier visual areas in which the attention gating is usually described as a function of the attention signal on the visual signal (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Cognitive sustainment has been reported across the set of brain regions thought to be part of the attention control network; in fact it has even been historically important for neurons to even be included in studies of cognitive control (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Cognitive sustainment has not been tested, to the best of our knowledge, for inferotemporal areas, where recently a new attentional control area has been found (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p><p id="P6">Second, priority maps result from the integration of information from multiple channels (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). How are these input signals combined? Summation of overlapping spatial signals from visual regions and top-down signals related to goals and expectations has been proposed as a specific integration mechanism to generate priority signals (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). We refer to this as the superposition principle. It has originally been proposed for a region long thought to contain a priority map, the lateral intraparietal area (LIP) in the context of free-viewing visual search experiments (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The superposition principle can also explain the interaction between spatial and feature-based attention (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). However, the decisive test of the superposition principle where cognitive spatial signals thought to be the core representation of priority maps (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) are independently controlled, has been lacking.</p><p id="P7">Third, the purpose of the construction of a priority map is that it would serve to support all kinds of goal-oriented behaviors. Priority signals are thus thought to be multi-purpose. They are also thought to be one-dimensional (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), lacking predetermined behavioral meaning (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). We refer to these properties as agnosticity (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>). Priority signals should be agnostic in the sense that they do not provide information about how they are used (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Thus the same population activity generating a priority signal should be used to guide covert attention or overt attention (eye movements), whatever is appropriate at a given moment. The presumed lack of intrinsic information in population signals as to their eventual use has not been tested.</p><p id="P8">These basic hypotheses, the cognitive sustenance hypothesis, the superposition and the agnosticity hypothesis, are central to the understanding of attention control. Yet they have not been directly tested together in a controlled experiment, nor directly compared across the different brain areas that are thought to implement them. Here we do this, taking advantage of the recent discovery of a new attention control area.</p><p id="P9">Recently, functional MRI (fMRI) has been used to map brain areas in the macaque brain modulated by attention (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Beyond known attention control areas in parietal regions (LIP) and prefrontal regions (the frontal eye fields, FEF), the dorsal portion of posterior inferotemporal cortex (PITd) was strongly modulated by spatial attention, irrespective of visual features of relevant stimuli. Electrophysiological recordings confirmed this, and causal manipulations demonstrate that PITd activity controls the focus of spatial attention (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). This finding raises a fundamental question: Is this area in inferotemporal cortex really a priority map? The finding also offers a unique opportunity to determine the functional properties of priority maps and test the three core hypotheses about them. This is because PITd, unlike classical attention control areas like LIP (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and FEF (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), has not been linked to eye movement control and might thus exhibit different functional properties from these classical attentional control areas.</p><p id="P10">How do the main principles of priority map theory compare in different locations of the attention control network? We tested the three principles of priority maps on areas PITd and LIP (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) using fMRI-guided extra-cellular recordings while monkeys performed a MGS task (for cognitive sustainment) and a novel behavioral paradigm that dissociates covert attention and eye movements (for superposition and agnosticity).</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="S3"><title>fMRI-guided electrophysiology</title><p id="P11">We performed extracellular recordings in areas PITd and LIP from two male rhesus monkeys (<italic toggle="yes">macaca mulatta</italic>, M1 and M2). Recording locations were chosen based on fMRI maps of spatial attention effects (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) in the same animals (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S1</xref>). We recorded from 85 PITd and from 66 LIP units, respectively. The only selection requirement for cells was that their receptive fields (RFs) had to be non-foveal (see <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Cognitive sustainment</title><p id="P12">We first measured the ability of each area to highlight task-relevant spatial locations in the absence of visual stimuli during a standard MGS task (See <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). We computed spike density functions (SDFs) in single units and found units with spatially tuned activity throughout the duration of the trial (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). Large fractions of LIP and PITd cells, 73% and 40%, respectively, were significantly tuned during the memory epoch of the trial (600 to 400ms before saccade onset, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2C</xref>). Selectivity was significant in a larger fraction of the recorded LIP units than of PITd units, and the range of effects strengths was larger in LIP than PITd. Yet both areas reflected pure spatial selection. The similarity of responses in both areas is surprising given their very different locations within the visual system (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), one part of the dorsal, the other of the ventral stream. Results from PITd suggest strictly cognitive signals, reflecting covert attention to a location with no stimulus, exist in an inferotemporal cortical area. This property, up to now a hallmark of higher cognitive and oculomotor areas, is expected from a priority map.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Behavior during a covert motion discrimination task</title><p id="P13">For the study of superposition and agnosticity, we used a second task. The defining feature of this covert motion discrimination (CMD) task (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">B</xref>) was that the loci of covert and overt spatial attention were independently manipulated. In brief, subjects were required to attend one of two moving-dot surfaces (MDSs), while keeping fixation on the central fixation point (FP), in order to be able to report the motion direction of the cued MDS (the target stimulus) with a saccade to a saccade target dot (ST). Trials started with a central fixation period after which a small central cue indicated the location of the task-relevant MDS appearing 2s later (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). In each MDS, only a fraction of dots moved coherently in the same direction, and the direction of motion changed every 60ms (independently for each MDS) for a variable period of time (60 to 3600ms, also independent for each MDS) until the occurrence of the task-relevant event. These features required subjects to pay sustained covert attention over long periods of time, without any information about the direction of the saccade they would eventually need to generate. The task-relevant event was a prolonged motion event (PME) with constant motion direction, which lasted up to 2.7 seconds. (PME timing and direction were independent for each MDS.) PME motion directions were in one of two opposite directions, and monkeys had to indicate the motion direction in the target MDS, as soon as they made a decision, with a saccade to a ST. Monkeys successfully performed this task and, specifically, responded to the PME in the cued MDS, while ignoring that in the distractor (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3C</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Information</xref> &#x0201c;<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Behavior Results</xref>&#x0201d;).</p><p id="P14">Crucially for the purposes of this study, the spatial position of task-relevant elements (MDSs and STs) relative to the RF of the recorded neuron, was changed across trials into four unique physical stimulus arrangements (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>): an MDS as the only stimulus inside the RF, a ST as the only stimulus inside the RF, both an MDS and a ST overlapping inside the RF, and neither an MDS nor a ST positioned inside the RF. For each spatial arrangement, there were four unique behavioral situations (two possible cued MDSs and two possible saccade directions), making a total of 16 unique conditions overall, where all spatial combinations of covert and overt cognitive spatial signals were exhaustively sampled.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Combination of spatial signals</title><p id="P15">Neurons obeying the superposition principle summate incoming signals. This property can be tested by determining the responses of a neuron to conditions with a single spatial signal inside their RF (response r<sub>A</sub> when covert attention is paid into its RF, response r<sub>S</sub> when a saccade is generated into its RF) and the response to conditions when both signals overlap in the RF. For a neuron to obey the superposition principle, this response should be the sum of r<sub>A</sub> and r<sub>S</sub>. An example for how such a neuron should behave in the CMD task is shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref> (top row). Neurons in both areas exhibited a large response repertoire including modulation by covert attention, pre-saccadic tuning, and their combination (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4A</xref>, second row, and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref> for examples). Population-average SDFs (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>, third and bottom row for PITd and LIP, respectively) demonstrate widespread attention and saccadic modulations in both areas. Thus PITd, like LIP, is modulated by overt attention.</p><p id="P16">For the superposition principle to hold, saccade and attention signals should be independent of each other. Surprisingly though, they were not. In particular, saccade signals depended strongly on the attention condition. This deviation was not just a quantitative deviation from exact summation, but qualitative: in particular, no saccadic signals existed in PITd when the attended MDS was inside the RF. In contrast, they still existed in LIP, although reduced (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>, third and bottom row).</p><p id="P17">To characterize the contributions of physical (presence of stimuli in the RF) and cognitive factors (attention and pre-saccadic tuning), we computed a time-resolved generalized linear model (GLM) of neural activity temporally aligned to saccade onset. Interaction terms in the GLM directly quantified the size of nonlinearities or deviations from superposition (which predicts no interactions between spatial signals, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>, top). We calculated time courses of these effects in individual units and their normalized population average (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4A</xref>). Both areas exhibited strong effects of covert attention (PITd, mean&#x000b1;SEM in z-score units: 0.85&#x000b1;0.06, LIP: 0.88&#x000b1;0.09; see <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>) and saccade tuning (PITd: 0.40&#x000b1;0.06, LIP: 1.0&#x000b1;0.1) as well as a nonlinear interaction between them (PITd: &#x02212;0.39&#x000b1;0.06, LIP: &#x02212;0.37&#x000b1;0.06). The interaction was negative, indicating signals on average combined sub-additively. Its size in PITd was so big, it was of the order of main saccade tuning effect. In LIP, interaction effects were small compared to saccade tuning and covert attention. We next determined strength and significance of these effects for each neuron separately, and then computed the distribution of all effects across the population in each area (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4B</xref>). Large fractions of neurons were significantly affected by each task variable. Interactions between covert attention and saccade direction were common in PITd (significant in 21% of neurons) and less common and significant in LIP (0% of neurons). These results provide strong evidence for a systematic interaction between two kinds of spatial cognitive signals in PITd and thus against the superposition principle operating in this attention control area. The results also provide strong evidence that spatial cognitive signals are superposed, although attenuated, in area LIP.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Spatial information represented by neural populations</title><p id="P18">According to the agnosticity principle, priority maps should provide no intrinsic information about the behavioral use of the combined spatial signals in the RF. The independent control of spatial orienting behaviors in the CMD task enabled us to test this prediction by measuring the simultaneous information about them in neural populations in PITd and LIP. We quantified the presence of information by the decoding accuracy of support vector machines using single trial activity of pseudopopulations (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) aligned to saccade onset (see <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). We attempted to decode the covertly attended location when an MDS was alone in the RF, and the saccade direction when a ST was alone inside the RF. Crucially, we repeated the analyses when the MDS and ST overlapped in the RF. If agnostic, the resulting spatial signals should simply indicate the behaviorally relevant location at each time: the covertly attended location initially, then the upcoming saccade (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>, left).</p><p id="P19">In PITd, when single stimuli where in the RF, attention could be decoded significantly better than chance at all times (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>, <bold>center</bold>, light green), and saccadic information at the end of the trial (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>, <bold>center</bold>, pink). In the overlapping condition, decoding of covert attention remained practically unchanged (dark green), and decoding accuracy of saccade direction was weaker (purple). Thus, the observed interactions in PITd (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4A</xref>) come at the expense of information loss about saccades. The resulting signal in PITd is not agnostic, but robustly signals the locus of covert attention. In LIP, covert attention location could be decoded at all times for both stimulus arrangements (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>, <bold>right</bold>, light and dark green). Notably though, decoding of covert attention was degraded by the presence of a saccade target inside the RF, and it was degraded at all times (dark versus light green lines), even before any information about the saccade target could be decoded. This information about saccade direction increased until saccade onset reaching similar and significant levels for both stimulus arrangements (pink and purple lines). Thus LIP accommodates information about attention and saccades simultaneously, sacrificing attentional signal-to-noise. Crucially, these results rule out the agnosticity principle in both areas.</p><p id="P20">LIP representations have been suggested to be one-dimensional (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). How then is spatial information about covert and overt attention (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>) accommodated in the population? To answer this question, we used targeted dimensionality reduction (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) to visualize dynamics in population space (see <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). For each population (PITd and LIP), GLM regression coefficients from trials with MDSs <italic toggle="yes">alone</italic> inside the neurons&#x02019; RF were used to compute a population direction associated with covert attention. Analogously, regression coefficients from trials with saccade targets <italic toggle="yes">alone</italic> in the RF were used to isolate a direction associated with saccade direction. Into the plane these two axes span, we then projected the mean time course in trials when <italic toggle="yes">both</italic> MDSs and STs were present inside the RF (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figs. 5B</xref>). An agnostic representation resulting from superposition would be one dimensional (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>, <bold>left</bold>). Motor representations would also be one-dimensional, but show different dynamics (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S5</xref>). PITd population activity deviated from this scenario in multiple ways (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>, <bold>center</bold>). First, PITd population activity showed no saccadic contribution when attention was inside the RF. Second, activity during the two covert attention conditions was separable at all times. In LIP attention and saccadic spatial signals evolved along each population axis independently (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>, <bold>right</bold>). Thus LIP population activity was not one-dimensional, but exhibited separable dynamics for overt and covert attention.</p><p id="P21">These results clarify the nature of cognitive signal representations in two attentional control areas. In PITd, covert attention signals dominate. Saccade directions, in contrast to attention signals, are not reliably represented. In fact, the PITd population lacks a representation of saccade-direction when attention is already directed to the RF. A purely attentional representation (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S5</xref>), comes closest to PITd population dynamics. In LIP, the meaning of axes computed from single-stimulus conditions remained valid when spatial signals overlapped in space (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>, <bold>right</bold>). This shows how the superposition principle can apply to a population code, while the resulting priority signal is entirely &#x0201c;gnostic&#x0201d;, allowing to tell overt and covert attention apart. Thus, we find empirically that the superposition principle preserves rather than dilutes the behavioral meaning of each signal, close to what is expected in a full dissociation scenario (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S5</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="P22">We have tested three fundamental principles of priority maps in two fMRI-identified attention control areas: one, PITd, whose role in attention control was recently discovered (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and another, LIP, for which many of the priority map ideas had been originally proposed but not systematically tested. The demonstration of cognitive sustainment in PITd puts it in a comparable position with established attention control nodes such as LIP. Yet, differences in superposition and information content suggest diverse functional roles of the contributions of both areas to the control of spatial attention. Strong nonlinearities in PITd invalidated the superposition principle and instead provide a robust readout of covert attention. In LIP, the superposition principle holds, and rather than providing an agnostic one-dimensional signal it allows simultaneous representations of cognitive spatial information to coexist.</p><sec id="S9"><title>Cognitive Sustainment</title><p id="P23">Cognitive sustainment of neural activity is a defining characteristic of parietal (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), prefrontal (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and subcortical attention (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) control nodes. These areas are all part of the oculomotor system, where cognitive sustainment has been used as a criterion for identifying cells not involved in exclusively in motor planning (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The finding of the same signals outside of this system, in inferotemporal cortical area PITd, shows that cognitive sustainment can exist outside of the oculomotor system and is thus not tied to saccade planning. The finding, furthermore, differentiates area PITd from the standard view on early and ventral stream areas as recipients of attentional gating signals modulating visual activity (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Instead the results support the new hypothesis (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) that PITd is a possible source of cognitive spatial signals in the temporal lobe, yet one not involved in saccade planning.</p><p id="P24">The finding of cognitive sustainment in PITd shows how, in many ways, this temporal lobe area is functionally similar to parietal area LIP. Below we are discussing functional differences between the areas, but the results demonstrate how both are coding for visual stimuli, for covert, and for overt attention. The finding of an area located right next to two face-selective areas (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), to share properties with other attention control areas is surprising. It suggests that LIP and PITd might be directly connected to each other to negotiate a joint focus of attention and how PITd might serve to relay priority signals it has computed into other attentional control areas that are part of the oculomotor system. Our results thus force a re-conceptualization of attention control networks. And they force a network-oriented thinking where the major functions of an area can be highly different from those of neighboring areas, yet similar to more distant areas in the brain.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Superposition of spatial cognitive signals</title><p id="P25">Linear superposition has been proposed as a mechanism for the formation of a spatial priority signal (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). To our knowledge, this is the first time this hypothesis has been tested for spatial cognitive signals, arguably the core computation of priority maps (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), in a experiment that manipulated them independently, in any node of the attention network. In LIP, we find spatial signals can be attenuated when overlapping, yet their presence is preserved, largely validating the superposition principle. This offers a general prescription for how activity observed in simple experiments (as trials with a single stimulus in the RF can be considered) can predict that in more elaborate scenarios, perhaps indicating an effective limit to the complexity they could reveal (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In PITd however, superposition fails. This indicates that there is not one mechanism for the formation of attentional control areas, and suggests how each area might read out signals originating elsewhere in the network while preserving its functional identity.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Agnosticity of population representations</title><p id="P26">The idea of an agnostic general signal has been suggested as a key property of priority maps (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). It has also been proposed to result directly from superposition (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>): if multiple sources are combined in neuron responses, there might not be a predefined behavioral meaning to them. Results in both PITd and LIP rule out a general agnostic signal. In PITd only information about the attended location was robust. This confirms expectations for an area outside of the oculomotor system, and instead suggests a role as a true spotlight of attention (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, <bold>left</bold>) for adjacent-feature coding areas, consistent with causal interventions (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The lack of agnosticity in LIP is surprising, since we observed the expected superposition of spatial signals there. Key for understanding this is that even if superposition were to take place perfectly, there is heterogeneity in neural responses (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). This differential selectivity can preserve information in ways that are simple but not obvious in responses of individual neurons. Superposition, then, a straightforward encoding scheme for neuron responses, preserves the nature of contributing signals. Because of it, multiple parallel channels of spatial information coexist (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, <bold>right</bold>), perhaps allowing LIP to function as a versatile look-up table for the variety of brain regions to which it is connected and the behaviors they support.</p><p id="P27">The present findings also bear on the recently growing interest in understanding the dimensionality of neural representations (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The study of attention and decision-making in separate experiments has led to the proposal that responses in LIP evolve along a one-dimensional manifold (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) but it has been recently argued that additional dimensions can only be revealed in more complex tasks (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In that sense, the superposition principle provides a linear embedding of task parameters in neural space, in contrast with higher cortical areas where interactions account for the richness of the representation (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) needed for learning arbitrary associations.</p><p id="P28">Taken together, the results highlight the role of PITd as an attention control area in the temporal lobe with a relatively specialized representation for attention robust to perturbations from other cognitive sources, and that of LIP as holding as a multidimensional map able to guide perception and action at once.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12"><title>METHODS</title><p id="P29">Two adult male rhesus monkeys (10 and 8 kg) were trained on a memory-guided saccade (MGS) and a covert-discrimination tasks. All animal procedures complied with the US National Institutes of Health <italic toggle="yes">Guide for Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic> and were approved by The Rockefeller University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC). While the monkeys were engaged in the behavioral tasks, we recorded single- and multiunit responses in temporal area PITd and parietal area LIP, targeting attention-sensitive hotspots measured with functional MRI in a previous study on the same animals (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The great majority of neurons were not recorded simultaneously, but rather in separate behavioral sessions. For the MGS task, we quantified the existence of spatial tuning during the memory period. For the covert-discrimination task, we first analyzed the behavioral responses to verify monkeys were reliably using the cue for covertly guiding their responses and ignoring the distractor stimulus, and we then analyzed neural responses. First, we quantified the effect in each unit of the spatial signals manipulated during the task as well as their interaction. We then pooled data from single- and multiunit recordings to construct population responses, and used support vector machines to decode different covert attention and direction of impending saccades. We applied a dimensionality reduction technique (&#x02018;targeted dimensionality reduction&#x02019;) to identify a low-dimensional subspace capturing variance due to the task variables of interest within population responses. Full methods are provided in the <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Information</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1</label><media xlink:href="NIHPP2024.01.05.574406v2-supplement-1.pdf" id="d67e544" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S13"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p id="P30">We thank P. Levy and M. Borisov for help with data analysis; R. Huq for help with experimental planning; L. Diaz, A. Gonzalez, S. Rasmussen, and animal husbandry staff of The Rockefeller University for veterinary and technical care. This work was supported by the National Institute Of Mental Health of the National Institutes of Health under Award Number R01MH120288 and the National Science Foundation under Award Number BCS-1057006. W.A.F. is a NYSCF-Robertson Investigator. P.P. received financial support from the David Rockefeller Graduate Program. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health and the National Science Foundation.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p id="P31">DECLARATION OF INTERESTS</p><p id="P32">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kastner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ungerleider</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The neural basis of biased competition in human visual cortex</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>39</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11566310</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Space and attention in parietal cortex</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202542</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fallah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Control of eye movements and spatial attention</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>98</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fallah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Visuomotor Origins of Covert Spatial Attention</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>683</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14622573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bisley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Attention, intention, and priority in the parietal lobe</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192813</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gnadt</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Memory related motor planning activity in posterior parietal cortex of macaque</article-title>. <source>Exp Brain Res</source>
<volume>70</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3402565</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Primate frontal eye fields. I. Single neurons discharging before saccades</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>635</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3981231</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Funahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldman-Rakic</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Mnemonic coding of visual space in the monkey&#x02019;s dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<volume>61</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2918358</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Glimcher</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Movement selection in advance of action in the superior colliculus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>355</volume>(<issue>6360</issue>):<fpage>542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>545</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1741032</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ekstrom</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roelfsema</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonmassar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vanduffel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bottom-up dependent gating of frontal signals in early visual cortex</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>321</volume>(<issue>5887</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>417</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635806</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Selective gating of visual signals by microstimulation of frontal cortex</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>421</volume>(<issue>6921</issue>):<fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12540901</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Premereur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vanduffel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional heterogeneity of macaque lateral intraparietal neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>31</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>12307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21865473</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stemmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freiwald</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>) <source>An Attentional Priority Map in Inferotemporal Cortex</source>. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Itti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Computational modelling of visual attention</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11256080</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ipata</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neurons in the lateral intraparietal area create a priority map by the combination of disparate signals</article-title>. <source>Exp Brain Res</source>
<volume>192</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>488</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18762926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ibos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Interaction between Spatial and Feature Attention in Posterior Parietal Cortex</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>91</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>943</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27499082</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Spatial and non-spatial functions of the parietal cortex</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>740</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21050743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ganguli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>One-dimensional dynamics of attention and decision making in LIP</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18400159</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikkai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Common neural mechanisms supporting spatial working memory, attention and motor intention</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21182852</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stemmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freiwald</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Attentive Motion Discrimination Recruits an Area in Inferotemporal Cortex</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>36</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>11918</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11928</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27881778</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buneo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Intentional maps in posterior parietal cortex</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052908</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Felleman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Essen</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Distributed hierarchical processing in the primate cerebral cortex</article-title>. <source>Cereb Cortex</source>
<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1822724</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The importance of mixed selectivity in complex cognitive tasks</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>497</volume>(<issue>7451</issue>):<fpage>585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>590</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23685452</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mante</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sussillo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newsome</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Context-dependent computation by recurrent dynamics in prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>503</volume>(<issue>7474</issue>):<fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24201281</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gregoriou</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotts</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Desimone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cell-Type-Specific Synchronization of Neural Activity in FEF with V4 during Attention</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>594</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22325208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ekstrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roelfsema</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonmassar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vanduffel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bottom-up dependent gating of frontal signals in early visual cortex (Supporting Online Material)</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>321</volume>(<issue>5887</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635806</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ganguli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>On simplicity and complexity in the brave new world of large-scale neuroscience</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25932978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zelinsky</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The what, where, and why of priority maps and their interactions with visual working memory</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<volume>1339</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581477</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schall</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Effects of stimulus-response compatibility on neural selection in frontal eye field</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12765614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ohayon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MR-guided stereotactic navigation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience Methods</source>
<volume>204</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22192950</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yekutieli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Adaptive linear step-up procedures that control the false discovery rate</article-title>. <source>Biometrika</source>
<volume>93</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>507</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vapnik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Support-vector networks</article-title>. <source>Machine learning</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The neural decoding toolbox</article-title>. <source>Front Neuroinform</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23734125</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian journal of statistics</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4615733</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p id="P33">Conceptual framework and brain areas. (<bold>A</bold>) The priority map idea. A single spatial priority signal, agnostic as to its eventual use, is computed by summation of signals from feature-coding areas that represent visual-scene properties and internal signals related to goals and expectations. (<bold>B</bold>) Diagram of the macaque brain showing relevant sulci open and attention-control nodes localized by fMRI in areas PITd and LIP where recordings were performed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2024.01.05.574406v2-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p id="P34">Cognitive sustainment: memory-guided saccade (MGS) task and neural responses. (<bold>A</bold>) Timing of events in the MGS task. See main text and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Methods</xref> for task description. (<bold>B</bold>) Spike density function (SDF) of an example PITd unit, aligned to stimulus or saccade onset. Color indicates stimulus position relative to the receptive field (RF). Shading denotes standard error of the mean (SEM). Horizontal bar indicates stimulus duration. (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of strength of spatial tuning during the memory epoch (600 to 400ms before saccade onset) in PITd (left) and LIP (right). Filled bars indicate units with statistically significant tuning (t-test) at a false discovery rate q&#x0003c;0.05 in each area. Units from both monkeys were pooled together.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2024.01.05.574406v2-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p id="P35">Covert discrimination task and behavioral performance. (<bold>A</bold>) Timing of events in the covert-discrimination task. (<bold>B</bold>) The four physical configurations of the stimuli relative to the RF of the unit being recorded: a lone moving-dot surface (MDS), a lone saccade target, both overlapping, or none. See main text and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Methods</xref> for task description. (<bold>C</bold>) Consistency of behavioral responses in monkeys M1 and M2 to timing and direction of the PME in the cued MDS only, both MDSs, distractor MDS only, and none of them. The first two cases correspond to correct trials. Lines indicate average chance levels and 95% confidence intervals (randomization test) across experimental sessions. (<bold>D</bold>) Joint distribution of response times (RTs) of monkey M1 relative to the prolonged motion event (PME) onset time (t<sub>PME_OT</sub>) in the cued and distractor MDS. See also <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2024.01.05.574406v2-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p id="P36">Testing superposition of spatial signals in PITd and LIP. (<bold>A</bold>) Top row: Idealized schematics of the superposition principle of neural responses on the covert discrimination task, showing a SDF, with activity aligned to saccade onset. Signals from covertly attending a lone cued MDS in the RF (left) and planning a saccade to a lone target (center) combine additively when these overlap in space (right), with both attention and saccadic responses observed. Second row: SDF of an example PITd unit with non-additive responses. Shadows indicate standard error of the mean (SEM). Third row: Population average of normalized (z-score units) PITd SDFs. Bottom row: Population average for LIP. (<bold>B</bold>) Main effect of covert attention, of eye movement conditions, and their interaction, in a generalized linear model (GLM). Top row: Idealized superposition showing no interaction between spatial signals. Second row: same PITd unit as in (<bold>A</bold>). Third row: PITd population average. Bottom row: LIP population average.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2024.01.05.574406v2-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p id="P37">Testing agnosticity of population activity in PITd and LIP by decoding cognitive variables in the covert discrimination task. (<bold>A</bold>) Left: Accuracy, aligned on saccade onset, expected on an idealized population with an agnostic priority signal for decoding covert attention location (green) and saccade direction (pink) when single stimuli are inside the RF (light trace) or both are (dark trace). Center: Decoding accuracy for PITd, in 100ms time bins. Right: Decoding accuracy for LIP. Circles indicate the end of a time bin. Filled circles denote performance significantly different from chance levels (p&#x0003c;0.05, permutation test, Holm-Bonferroni controlled for comparisons on multiple time points). (<bold>B</bold>) Population activity when both stimuli are inside the RF of cells, projected on axes associated with covert attention conditions (vertical) and saccade direction (horizontal). Color denotes covert attention condition; and line style, saccade direction. Left: Idealized one-dimensional priority signal. See <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S5</xref> for other alternative scenarios. Center: PITd population. Units (z-scores, not shown) are the same for vertical and horizontal axes. Right: LIP population.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2024.01.05.574406v2-f0005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p id="P38">Schematics of functional specialization of attention-control nodes. Left: Coding of attention in PITd, where nonlinear interactions dominate. Right: Simultaneous representation of multiple spatial variables in LIP at the population level through sum of disparate signals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2024.01.05.574406v2-f0006" position="float"/></fig><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float"><caption><title>SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT</title></caption><p id="P39">A central theory of attention poses that the brain computes a priority map to highlight spatial locations of relevance for behavior. Here we tested the hypothesis and its key predictions about how priority signals are assembled and used, through electrophysiological single-unit recordings from two nodes of the attention control network, localized by functional magnetic resonance imaging. We found both areas to highlight locations even in the absence of a stimulus, and that each assembled spatial signals differently and provided spatial information in different forms. These findings force a revision of how and where spatial attention is controlled in the brain.</p></boxed-text></floats-group></article>