<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40501861</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12157620</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.08.658490</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Interlinked roles for HEB and Id3 in fetal gamma-delta T cell commitment and functional programming</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3713-6302</contrib-id><name><surname>Selvaratnam</surname><given-names>Johanna S.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da Rocha</surname><given-names>Juliana Dutra Barbosa</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3323-181X</contrib-id><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>Vinothkumar</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>Emily C.</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gams</surname><given-names>Miki S.</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2437-507X</contrib-id><name><surname>Murre</surname><given-names>Cornelis</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7674-2612</contrib-id><name><surname>Guidos</surname><given-names>Cynthia J.</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2538-3178</contrib-id><name><surname>Z&#x000fa;&#x000f1;iga-Pfl&#x000fc;cker</surname><given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8820-5910</contrib-id><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Michele K.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Biological Sciences, Sunnybrook Research Hospital, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Immunology, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Molecular Biology, University of California at San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1"><bold>Author contributions.</bold> J.S.S. and M.K.A. conceptualized the study. E.S.R., M.S.G, and C.J.G. developed high parameter flow cytometry panels. J.S.S., E.S.R., and J.D.R. collected the flow cytometry data, and J.S.S. sorted cells for the scRNA-seq experiments. M.K.A. analyzed the scRNA-seq data, assisted by H.W. and V.R., and generated the figures. V.R. and H.W. performed the <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> scRNA-seq experiment. Funding was acquired by M.K.A. and J.C.Z.P. M.K.A., J.C.Z.P., and C.M. interpreted the data and formed the model. M.K.A. wrote the first draft of the manuscript, and all authors contributed to the final manuscript. </p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: <email>manderso@sri.utoronto.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2025.06.08.658490</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to copy and distribute the material in any medium or format in unadapted form only, for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2025.06.08.658490.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P2">&#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells that produce IL-17 (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17) play essential roles in barrier immunity, but the gene networks that install their functions are not well understood. We previously linked T cell receptor (TCR) signal strength to the proportional upregulation of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> during T cell development, which antagonizes the activity of HEB (encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Tcf12</italic>), and showed that HEB is required for &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 development. To understand how HEB and Id3 regulate &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell development, we conducted single cell RNA-sequencing on fetal thymic &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells from <italic toggle="yes">Tcf12</italic>-deficient mice. &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells lacking HEB exhibited profound alterations in the expression of the genes encoding the TCR&#x003b3; and TCR&#x003b4; chains, accompanied by a decrease in expression of genes in the early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell specification network. Surprisingly, <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> was among the most severely decreased genes in HEB-deficient &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors, suggesting a requirement for HEB in <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression. Analysis of fetal thymic &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic>-deficient mice revealed that the TCR&#x003b3; and TCR&#x003b4; repertoires were unaffected, and expression of early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell genes was unperturbed. However, later stage regulators of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell differentiation were decreased, and <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic>-deficient &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells were defective in IL-17 production. Therefore, our findings reveal an interlinked network in which HEB is initially required to upregulate <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression, which in turn enables the later stages of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell development and functional programming.</p></abstract><abstract id="ABS2" abstract-type="summary"><title>One Sentence Summary:</title><p id="P3">During &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development, the transcription factor HEB upregulates its antagonist Id3, which is required in turn for the maturation of pro-inflammatory &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="P4">IL-17 producing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17) are critical mediators of immunity to bacterial and fungal pathogens, and also participate in maintaining barrier integrity, particularly in mucosal tissues including the skin, gut, lungs, and female reproductive tract (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) . However, dysregulation of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells also can induce or foster serious adverse outcomes, including autoimmune diseases such as psoriasis, multiple sclerosis, and diabetes (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells also reside in the meninges and play an important role in stress-induced depression (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), as well as exacerbating tumor growth and metastasis (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells also play critical roles in adipose tissue homeostasis and temperature regulation (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), underscoring their broad clinical importance. Thus, understanding how &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells acquire their functional properties during development will enable manipulation of these functions, providing new approaches for diagnosis and treatment of multiple health conditions and diseases.</p><p id="P5">As T cells develop in the thymus from hematopoietic stem cells, a series of differentiation intermediates arise that set the stage for subsequent branchpoints and T-lineage fate choices. One of the earliest branchpoints during T cell development is the bifurcation of progenitor T (pro-T) cells into the &#x003b1;&#x003b2; or the &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell lineage (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Following T cell receptor (TCR) rearrangements, committed &#x003b3;&#x003b4;-T cell precursors differentiate into distinct functional subsets. T cell development progresses through different stages described by the &#x0201c;cocktail party&#x0201d; paradigm, wherein groups of partygoers interact and then move on to form different conversational clusters, with new participants arriving and departing as the evening progresses (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The participants and their interactions have been well characterized in the &#x003b1;&#x003b2;-T lineage fate choices, with a clear role for TCR signaling in directing dispersal and re-grouping of transcriptional regulators (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). By contrast, much less is known about the transcriptional hand-offs that occur during &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development.</p><p id="P6">&#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells play key roles in mediating barrier integrity and immunity by rapid production of pro-inflammatory cytokines and/or growth factors that promote tissue homeostasis (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In mice, different subsets of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells are specialized by distinct developmental pathways and effector functions that are tightly linked with the expression of specific V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; chains. In the adult thymus, the majority of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells express V&#x003b3;4 or V&#x003b3;1, paired with heterogeneous V&#x003b4; chains. After intrathymic development, &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells exit the thymus as interferon-&#x003b3; (IFN&#x003b3;) producers (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1) or as na&#x000ef;ve &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells that can be polarized in the periphery (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Specialized IL-4 producing V&#x003b3;1 V&#x003b4;6.3 &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells also develop in the early postnatal thymus (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). V&#x003b3;7 cells develop neonatally in a thymic independent manner and reside in the intestinal epithelium (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Very few V&#x003b3;7 cells are detectable in the fetal thymus (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p><p id="P7">&#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells that arise within the fetal thymus appear in transient waves of development that are reflective of the order of V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; rearrangement during ontogeny (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). There are two nomenclature systems for V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; elements, here we use the Tonegawa nomenclature (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). At E15-E17, V&#x003b3;5 V&#x003b4;1 bearing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells develop in the thymus and then migrate to the skin where they reside for life (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). This is followed by the appearance of V&#x003b3;6 V&#x003b4;1 T cells at E16&#x02013;18, and then V&#x003b3;4 V&#x003b4;5 T cells at E18&#x02013;20. These cells can give rise to IL-17 producing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17) that are most prominent and protective in barrier tissues, such as the dermis, intestinal lamina propria, lung, reproductive tract, meninges, and gingiva (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Since the underlying gene networks that control &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell functional programming are highly conserved between mice and humans (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), insights gained from mouse models are highly relevant to human T cell biology.</p><p id="P8">The linkage between &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR chains and functional programming stems from two main factors. Upstream of the TCR signal, there is coordinated programming of rearrangement of specific V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; chains (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Subsequently, TCR ligand engagement and downstream signaling pathways provide instructive input into &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell fate and function (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In T cell precursors, weak pre-TCR (pT&#x003b1;/TCR&#x003b2;) signaling specifies the &#x003b1;&#x003b2;-fate (&#x003b2;-selection), whereas stronger &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling drives cells into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell lineage (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;-selection) (<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Immature, committed fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells then go through a second differentiation step that subdivides them into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 or &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 lineages (<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Strong signaling through the V&#x003b3;5 V&#x003b4;1 TCR, marked by upregulation of CD73, leads to the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 fate during the first wave, whereas intermediate signaling through the V&#x003b3;4 V&#x003b4;5 TCR promotes differentiation into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 fate in the third wave just prior to birth (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Maturation of both lineages is accompanied by downregulation of CD24 expression. There is conflicting evidence on the strength of signal needed to select and program V&#x003b3;6 V&#x003b4;1 T cells into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 lineage during the second wave (<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Additionally, the molecular connections between TCR signal strength and expression of the genes needed for functionality are not well understood.</p><p id="P9">The E protein transcription factors HEB (<italic toggle="yes">Tcf12</italic>) and E2A (<italic toggle="yes">Tcf3</italic>) are important regulators of T-lineage gene expression throughout development, with shifting target genes in different developmental subsets (<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). E protein activity is controlled by Id proteins, which sequester them into inactive dimers incapable of binding DNA (<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> is upregulated by TCR signaling through the ERK-Egr pathway (<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> is upregulated proportionally to TCR signal strength, suggesting that titration of E protein activity is a key determinant of fate choice downstream of TCR signaling (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). We have shown that HEB is required for &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell development and that forced <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors reduced expression of several key &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell regulators (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). HEB is also important for the later stages of &#x003b1;&#x003b2; T cell development in the adult thymus, particularly at the immature CD8 single positive (ISP) to double positive (CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup>; DP) transition and for maturation of CD4 single positive thymocytes (<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Thus, the E/Id protein axis connects TCR signal strength and fate-determining gene expression networks during T cell development.</p><p id="P10">To elucidate how HEB and Id3 regulate &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development, we compared &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells from the fetal thymuses of HEB<sup>fl/fl:Vav-iCre</sup> (HEB conditionally deficient, HEB cKO) mice, <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic>-deficient (Id3-KO) mice, and wildtype (WT) mice. Our results revealed several layers of dysregulation in the absence of HEB, including major changes in V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; gene expression and a dramatic decrease in the expression of early developmental regulators. We also found that HEB is required for the upregulation of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> in early &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell precursors, and that Id3 is needed for effective &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell maturation. Taken together, our results indicate that HEB induces first stage &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell regulators and simultaneously launches &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 differentiation through an Id3-mediated negative feedback loop that switches programs from HEB-dependent gene expression to the expression of genes that require Id3 mediated suppression of E protein activity.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="S3"><title>Alterations in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development in the HEB cKO fetal thymus</title><p id="P11">To understand the impacts of HEB deficiency on fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development, we performed timed matings of HEB<sup>fl/fl</sup> mice (WT) with HEB<sup>fl/fl</sup> Vav-iCre transgenic (HEB cKO) mice to yield WT (Vav-iCre<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) and HEB cKO (Vav-iCre<sup>+</sup>) littermates. Fetal thymuses were harvested at embryonic day 18 (E18), and thymocytes were analyzed by flow cytometry. We observed a decrease in total thymic cellularity (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>), and a severe arrest in development at the immature CD8 to double positive (DP; CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup>) transition (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1</xref>), consistent with the previously reported phenotype in adult and neonatal HEB-deficient mice (<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Although the proportion of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells among all thymocytes was higher in HEB cKO fetal thymus than in WT mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">C</xref>), the absolute numbers of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells were similar (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). Within the &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell population, there was a severe decrease in both the percentages and the absolute cell numbers of V&#x003b3;4 cells in HEB cKO mice and a corresponding increase in the percentages and absolute cell numbers in all other V&#x003b3; subsets (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.1E</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">G</xref>). Nearly all V&#x003b3;4 cells were immature, as assessed by high CD24 expression, in both WT and HEB cKO mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1H</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">I</xref>). However, V&#x003b3;5, V&#x003b3;1, and V&#x003b3;4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>5<sup>&#x02212;</sup>1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> T cell subsets had higher percentages of CD24<sup>+</sup> immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in the HEB cKO mice relative to WT mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1H</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">K</xref>), suggesting a partial block or delay in maturation. As V&#x003b3;6 cells CD3<sup>high</sup> relative to other V&#x003b3; subsets (<xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), the high levels of CD3 on V&#x003b3;4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>5<sup>&#x02212;</sup>1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells indicated that these were primarily V&#x003b3;6 cells (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1J</xref>). Furthermore, V&#x003b3;7 cells are scarce in the fetal thymus (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Therefore, for simplicity, we will refer to V&#x003b3;4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>5<sup>&#x02212;</sup>1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells as V&#x003b3;6 cells in our flow cytometry data. These findings indicate a lack of HEB results in the depletion of V&#x003b3;4 cells and an impairment in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell maturation in the fetal thymus.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Shifts in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell subset populations in E18 HEB cKO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells</title><p id="P12">To understand the molecular basis of these differences, we conducted single cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) on &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> T cells sorted from E18 WT and HEB cKO fetal thymuses. After quality control, the datasets were merged, myeloid cells were excluded, and cell cycle genes were regressed (see Methods and R-markdown files for details). The resulting merged dataset was subjected to principal component analysis (PCA) to generate uniform manifold alignment plots (UMAPs) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Eight clusters (numbered 0&#x02013;7) were identified (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>), some of which had different proportions of WT versus HEB cKO cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Of note, a split UMAP (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>) showed that HEB cKO cells were entirely missing in cluster 4 (green), and poorly represented in cluster 2 (red). By contrast, the cells in cluster 3 (pink) were nearly all HEB cKO cells, and clusters 1 (light gray) and 0 (dark gray) were highly enriched in HEB cKO cells. Clusters 5 (blue), 6 (orange) and 7 (maroon) had strong representation of both WT and HEB cKO cells. To assign identities to these clusters, we generated a heatmap of the 10 most differentially expressed genes in each cluster relative to all other clusters (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref>) and assessed the relative expression of curated &#x003b3;&#x003b4; and &#x003b1;&#x003b2; T cell genes between different clusters with a clustered dot plot (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2E</xref>). This analysis showed the degree of similarity between clusters, using scores derived from individual genes. We also generated gene lists diagnostic for DN3 cells, DP cells, early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T, immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 imm), and mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 mat), based on previous studies (<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>), and used them to create module scores for each cluster (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F</xref>). Only cells co-expressing all genes within a module gene list (&#x0201c;AND&#x0201d; gated in Boolean logic) were included in each module. Applying these criteria allowed us to assign identities to each cluster (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2G</xref>).</p><p id="P13">Interestingly, both Cluster 1 (gray) and Cluster 4 (green) fell into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17-imm bin (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2F</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">G</xref>) and were more closely related to each other than to any of the other clusters (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2E</xref>). Since Clusters 4 and 1 were largely confined to WT or HEB cKO, respectively, we set out to identify genes differentially expressed between them in an unbiased manner by generating an enhanced volcano plot (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2H</xref>). Remarkably, many of the most differentially expressed genes were immediately recognizable as signature genes of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors, including <italic toggle="yes">Ccr9</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Rorc</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Ifngr1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Etv5</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Il21r</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Blk</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">St6gal1</italic> (<xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). These genes were highly expressed in WT cells (Cluster 4) but not in HEB cKO cells (Cluster 1), suggesting that HEB is required for the establishment of the early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell gene network. We also noted decreased levels of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> in Cluster 1(red circle). Since <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> upregulation can be a consequence of TCR signaling, this finding suggested a disruption of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling, a role for HEB in <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression, or both.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Diversion to &#x003b1;&#x003b2; fate and paucity of early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors among HEB cKO cells</title><p id="P14">We next examined the relative module scores of WT cells versus HEB cKO cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The developmental subset modules shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> were supplemented with three additional modules that identified cells co-expressing the genes encoding obligate fetal TCR&#x003b3;-TCR&#x003b4; receptor pairs: 1) V&#x003b3;5 and V&#x003b4;1 (<italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V5, Trdv4</italic>), 2) V&#x003b3;6 and V&#x003b4;1 (<italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V6, Trdv4</italic>), and 3) V&#x003b3;4 and V&#x003b4;5 (<italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V4, Trdv5</italic>). We did not detect genes encoding V&#x003b3;7 (<italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V7</italic>) or V&#x003b4;6.3 (<italic toggle="yes">Trav15d-1-dv6d-1)</italic>, consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) and supporting our designation of V&#x003b3;4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>5<sup>&#x02212;</sup>1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells as V&#x003b3;6 cells. Comparisons of module score distributions in WT versus HEB cKO cells by split UMAPs revealed striking differences. Relative to WT, HEB cKO cells in the &#x003b1;&#x003b2; population (cluster 3) had a mildly elevated DN3 signature (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>), and a greatly increased DP signature (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>). Most WT cells in clusters identified as &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te (clusters 2, 6) and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 imm (cluster 4) co-expressed V&#x003b3;4 and V&#x003b4;5 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>) and displayed strong &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>) and immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3E</xref>) scores. By contrast, very few HEB cKO cells exhibited V&#x003b3;4 V&#x003b4;5 co-expression. Furthermore, the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te score was weak and the immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 signature was nearly absent in HEB cKO cells. We also examined differential expression of specific genes between WT and HEB cKO cells within each cluster using split violin plots (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3F</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">I</xref>) and split feature plots (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>) of single genes. Expression of the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te regulators <italic toggle="yes">Sox13</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Etv5</italic> was lower in HEB cKO cells than in WT cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3F</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>). Moreover, HEB cKO cells displayed severely diminished expression of <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trdv5</italic> was undetectable (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3G</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>). By contrast, the second stage regulators <italic toggle="yes">Rorc</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Maf</italic> did not exhibit major differences in expression between HEB cKO and WT cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3H</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>). Since <italic toggle="yes">Rorc</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Maf</italic> are expressed throughout &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 development, albeit at different levels, we also examined expression of <italic toggle="yes">Il23r</italic>, which is restricted to the mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T subset within the &#x003b3;&#x003b4; cell lineage but observed no differences between WT and HEB cKO cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3I</xref>).Together, these results suggest that HEB cKO cells that survive the immature stages of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 development do not require HEB to upregulate key regulators of the mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 gene program.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Increased proportions of immature V&#x003b3;6 V&#x003b4;1 and V&#x003b3;5 V&#x003b4;1 cells in HEB cKO mice</title><p id="P15">We also compared the distribution of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 module scoring in WT versus HEB cKO cells using split feature plots (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3J</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">L</xref>). In both WT and HEB cKO cells, the mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 module was concentrated in clusters 1, 4, and 5 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3J</xref>), the immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 score was limited to clusters 0 and 7 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3K</xref>), and the mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 score was restricted to cluster 7 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3L</xref>), suggesting little to no perturbation in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 development. In WT cells, the V&#x003b3;6 V&#x003b4;1 co-expression score was primarily found in clusters scoring high for the mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 module (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3M</xref>), and V&#x003b3;5 V&#x003b4;1 co-expressing cells were mainly associated with cluster 7 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3N</xref>). By contrast, V&#x003b3;6 V&#x003b4;1 co-expressing cells from HEB cKO mice were abundant in many different clusters, including those that scored highly for &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te module (clusters 2 and 6). HEB cKO V&#x003b3;5 V&#x003b4;1 cells were likewise more widely distributed, with strong representation in cluster 0, consistent with an immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cell identity. These observations are consistent with an increase in immature V&#x003b3;6 and V&#x003b3;5 cells in the HEB cKO fetal thymus, as suggested by flow cytometry (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p id="P16">The underlying basis of these differences were further probed with split violin plots of the expression of individual genes in WT versus HEBcKO cells within each cluster (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3O</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Q</xref>). WT cells expressing <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V6</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V5</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">Trdv4</italic> were restricted to the clusters that also co-expressed V&#x003b3;6-V&#x003b4;1 (clusters 4, 5) or V&#x003b3;5-V&#x003b4;1 (cluster 7), whereas expression of each of these genes in HEB cKO cells occurred both within and outside those clusters (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3O</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V1</italic>, which does not have a canonical pairing partner during fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development, was expressed across all clusters at the transcriptional level in both WT and HEB cKO cells. We verified that the mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 program was restricted to cluster 7 in both WT and HEB cKO cells by examining expression of <italic toggle="yes">Xcl1</italic> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3P</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Failure of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> upregulation in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te and immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells but not &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells</title><p id="P17">Given the difference in <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression in Clusters 1 and 4, we assessed <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression in WT versus HEB cKO cells in split violin plots (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3Q</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>). In WT cells, <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> was upregulated in &#x003b1;&#x003b2; (DN3/DP; cluster 3) and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te (clusters 2, 6) cells, consistent with the timing of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling at the &#x003b1;&#x003b2;/&#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell checkpoint, and to a lesser extent in immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells (cluster 4). <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> was also high in immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 (cluster 0) and mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (cluster 7). In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression was undetectable in HEB cKO cells in &#x003b1;&#x003b2; (cluster 3) and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 imm (cluster 1), and decreased in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te cells (clusters 2, 6) relative to WT. These results indicate that HEB deficiency severely blunts <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> upregulation in cells expressing the V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; chains associated with the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 fate. However, <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression levels were equivalent between WT and HEB cKO cells in immature and mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (clusters 0 and 7). Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">Nr4a1</italic> was upregulated in immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (cluster 0) in both WT and HEB cKO cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3Q</xref>), consistent with intact cellular perception of strong TCR signaling (<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). Therefore, HEB is required for <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> upregulation during &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 development but not during &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 development.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Unperturbed &#x003b1;&#x003b2; T cell development in the E18 fetal thymus of Id3-KO mice</title><p id="P18">To assess whether the decrease in <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression has an impact on &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development, we examined E18 thymocytes from Id3-KO mice. Previous studies of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development in adult Id3-KO mice were hampered by a major expansion of mature V&#x003b3;1.1<sup>+</sup>V&#x003b4;6.3<sup>+</sup> cells and IL-4 dependent induction of innate CD8 T cell development (<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). This expansion does not occur until after birth (<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>), allowing us to examine the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic>-deficiency on fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development without this confounding factor. Since the phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> deficiency in the thymus can be muted in certain strains of mice (<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>), we first examined the phenotype of thymocytes in adult Id3-KO mice. Id3-KO mice had a marked decrease in thymic cellularity relative to WT (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S3A</xref>). Id3-KO thymocytes also exhibited an increase in DN and CD8 SP thymocytes, and a decrease in DP cells, while the percentages of CD4 T cells were similar (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S3B</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">C</xref>), and these patterns were recapitulated for the most part by absolute cell numbers (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S3D</xref>). Furthermore, we observed a large increase in thymic &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in the Id3-KO thymus (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S3E</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">F</xref>), nearly all of which were V&#x003b3;1.1<sup>+</sup>V&#x003b4;6.3<sup>+</sup>CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD73<sup>+</sup> &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S3H</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">I</xref>). By contrast, E18 fetal thymocytes from Id3-KO mice had equivalent percentages of DN and DP cells (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4</xref>) and normal cellularity (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). The proportions of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells were slightly decreased relative to WT mice (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Therefore, E18 fetal thymocytes from Id3-KO mice did not exhibit any of the characteristics related to V&#x003b3;1 V&#x003b4;6.3 cell expansion seen in the adult, permitting an analysis of the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> deficiency on &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1/&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 lineage choice.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Defects in CD73 upregulation and IL-17 production in fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells from Id3-KO mice</title><p id="P19">We next examined &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell subsets in E18 Id3-KO fetal thymus. V&#x003b3; chain usage in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in fetal Id3-KO thymus was very similar to WT, with a small increase in the proportion of V&#x003b3;6 cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">F</xref>). However, there was a striking loss of CD73<sup>+</sup> cells among Id3-KO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells, accompanied by a corresponding increase in the percentages of CD73<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4G</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">H</xref>). V&#x003b3; subset specific analysis confirmed that CD73 expression was lost in both V&#x003b3;5 and V&#x003b3;1 cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4I</xref>), suggesting that these cells might perceive a weaker &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signal and be diverted into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 lineage. To assess this possibility, we stimulated <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> E18 fetal thymocytes from WT and Id3-KO mice with PMA/ionomycin and examined IL-17 production by intracellular flow cytometry. WT &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells produced IL-17, but Id3-KO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells did not (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">B</xref>).</p><p id="P20">Given this observation, we considered the possibility that the absence of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> could derail the TCR signaling outcomes needed for IL-17 programming. Since CD73 can be upregulated in response to strong &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling (<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), we measured CD73 surface expression on WT and Id3-KO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells with and without 4 hrs of PMA/ionomycin (P/I) treatment. Prior to stimulation, CD27<sup>+</sup>CD73<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and CD27<sup>+</sup>CD73<sup>+</sup> cells were present in the WT population, whereas CD27<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and CD27<sup>+</sup> cells from Id3-KO mice were both CD73 negative. Stimulation resulted in an increase in the proportion of WT CD27<sup>+</sup>CD73<sup>+</sup> &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells, whereas Id3-KO cells remained CD73 negative (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5C</xref>, <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). These results indicate that the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> loss occurs downstream of the PI3K and NFAT signaling pathways mimicked by P/I treatment. Of note, PI3K is an important mediator of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 development (<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Impaired maturation of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells in Id3-KO fetal thymocytes</title><p id="P21">We next examined expression of the second stage &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 regulators MAF, PLZF, and ROR&#x003b3;t in WT and Id3-KO E18 &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells by intracellular low cytometry. In WT V&#x003b3;4 cells, which are primarily immature, about 25% of the cells co-expressed MAF and PLZF at intermediate levels, consistent with priming towards the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 lineage (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). However, this population was significantly dampened in Id3-KO mice. V&#x003b3;6 cells from Id3-KO mice also exhibited a decrease in the proportion of mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells relative to WT (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6C</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). To further assess the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> deficiency on mature V&#x003b3;6 transcription factor expression, we gated on CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells within the V&#x003b3;6 populations (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">F</xref>). The majority of cells from WT mice co-expressed ROR&#x003b3;t and MAF, consistent with programming into the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 lineage. However, the ROR&#x003b3;t<sup>+</sup>MAF<sup>+</sup> population was decreased in mature Id3-KO V&#x003b3;6 cells indicating impaired &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 differentiation in the absence of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic>. Our results thus indicate that <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> is an important driver of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell maturation.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Intact early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell regulatory program in the Id3-KO fetal thymus</title><p id="P22">To more globally assess changes in Id3-KO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell populations, we performed scRNA-seq on DN cells magnetically enriched from E18 WT and Id3-KO fetal thymuses. After quality control, the datasets were merged, and the resulting merged dataset was subjected to PCA to generate UMAP plots. Eleven clusters were defined (0-10) (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A</xref>), with representation from both WT and Id3-KO cells in most clusters (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7B</xref>). Many of the clusters were identified as DN3 or DN4 subsets, based on expression of <italic toggle="yes">Il2ra</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ptcra</italic> (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7C</xref>, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). However, two small clusters were identified as &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T lineage cells based on co-expression of <italic toggle="yes">Sox13</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Etv5</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Maf</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Zbtb16</italic> (cluster 6) or co-expression of <italic toggle="yes">Xcl1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Zbtb16</italic> (cluster 9). Clusters 6 and 9 were subsetted and re-clustered, resulting in four new clusters which were classified using violin plots of diagnostic genes into &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te (gray), &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 imm (purple), &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 mat (red), and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 (orange) subsets (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig.7E</xref>). Notably, a split UMAP plot showed that the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 mat population was less robust among Id3-KO cells than in WT cells (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7F</xref>). This cluster was excluded from further analysis. Next, we generated split violin plots to examine the expression of individual genes in WT versus Id3-KO cells (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7G</xref>). Levels of <italic toggle="yes">Etv5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Sox13</italic> were not diminished in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 imm cells from Id3-KO mice, indicating that &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell commitment was relatively unaffected by the absence of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic>. However, <italic toggle="yes">Rora</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Maf</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Zbtb16</italic> mRNA levels were lower in Id3-KO cells, most markedly in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells, whereas &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 gene expression (<italic toggle="yes">Xcl1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Il2rb</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Id2</italic>) was unperturbed. These finding suggested that in spite of their failure to express CD73, &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells can develop independently of Id3. Notably, <italic toggle="yes">Id2</italic> was ectopically induced at low levels in Id3-KO cells in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells and was elevated in &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7G</xref>), suggesting it may have provided partial compensation for the loss of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> in the fetal thymus, as it is believed to do in the adult thymus (<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="P23">&#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development occurs via a two-step process, in which &#x003b3;&#x003b4;-lineage commitment is followed by functional maturation (<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>), but how these two events are orchestrated is not well understood. Here we show that HEB and Id3 participate in a negative feedback loop that allows HEB-dependent &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell specification to be followed by Id3-dependent &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell maturation. These findings are consistent with the TCR signal strength model but reveal additional levels of complexity. First, HEB is instrumental in shaping the TCR&#x003b3; and TCR&#x003b4; repertoire at the level of V element gene expression. Secondly, HEB is required for <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression downstream of TCR signaling in V&#x003b3;6 V&#x003b4;1 &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells but not V&#x003b3;5 V&#x003b4;1 &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells, which develop independently of HEB. In addition, HEB and Id3 regulate distinct stages of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cell development, with a requirement for HEB for expression of first stage regulators, and Id3 important in the elaboration of second stage regulators. Thus, absence of either HEB or Id3 resulted in a failure of functional programming to the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 fate. Together, these studies have uncovered an HEB-dependent switch that enables the transition from committed &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors to mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 effector cells.</p><p id="P24">Our work reveals that HEB shapes the fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR repertoire to a much greater degree than previously appreciated. Most studies on E protein regulation of <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trdv</italic> elements have been focused on E2A (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). E2A can bind directly to the <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V4</italic> promoter, and is needed for V&#x003b3;4 expression in the adult thymus (<xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>). By contrast, we found that V&#x003b3;4<sup>+</sup> cells are present in the adult thymus (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), but scarce in the fetal thymus, where expression of <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trdv5</italic> are compromised at the transcriptional level. Loss of E2A lifts repression of <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trdv4</italic>, resulting in an aberrant population of V&#x003b3;5<sup>+</sup> &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in the thymus (<xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). We did not observe V&#x003b3;5<sup>+</sup> cells in the adult thymus of HEB cKO mice. However, we found a strong de-repression of <italic toggle="yes">Trdv4</italic> in fetal &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell populations, consistent with E protein-dependent silencing elements in the <italic toggle="yes">Trdv4</italic> locus that restrict <italic toggle="yes">Trdv4</italic> expression in the adult thymus. Together, these findings suggest that HEB and E2A collaborate to restrict temporal <italic toggle="yes">Trdv4</italic> expression. Intriguingly, E proteins directly control the expression of <italic toggle="yes">Trav15d-1-dv6d-1</italic> (which encodes V&#x003b4;6.3) as well, which dictates the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 fate choice by strong induction of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> in V&#x003b3;1.1 V&#x003b4;6.3 cells (<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Thus, the E protein/Id3 axis is instructive upstream of TCR signaling in multiple &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell subsets.</p><p id="P25">Our studies also support important roles for HEB and Id3 in coupling &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signal strength to &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell fate choices. T cell precursors lacking HEB were impaired in their ability to coordinately express genes involved in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell commitment and install the early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell gene network. In addition, HEB or Id3 deficiency each appeared to alter the cellular perception of TCR signal strength, in opposite ways, as measured by an increase or decrease, respectively, in CD73 expression (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). However, mature V&#x003b3;5<sup>+</sup> cells emerged with intact signature genes in both cases, and Id3 was upregulated in V&#x003b3;5<sup>+</sup> cells independently of HEB. Therefore, it is possible that HEB collaborates with Egr factors to induce <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> under conditions of intermediate TCR signal strength, whereas high levels of Egr may be sufficient for <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> upregulation under conditions of strong &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling.</p><p id="P26">Maturation of most &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors into &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells requires TCR signaling, but other signaling pathways, such as SLAM family members, cytokine receptors, Notch receptors, and co-stimulatory molecules are also essential for &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell functional lineage choice (<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). We have previously shown that cytokine receptor signaling can decrease <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> mRNA levels during strong &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR signaling (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), suggesting that an intersection between signaling pathways may keep Id3 levels high enough to suppress &#x003b1;&#x003b2; T cell gene expression but low enough to allow &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 gene expression. This may help to explain the ability of V&#x003b3;6 cells to develop into &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells in the presence of strong TCR signaling (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). HEB has also been linked to several signaling pathways that can regulate activity or gene target specificity. A short form of HEB, HEBAlt can be activated by a JAK-dependent pathway, suggesting a possible connection to cytokine receptors such as IL-7, IL-21 and IL-23 (<xref rid="R79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). The N-terminus of the long form of HEB, HEBCan, can complex with members of the ETO co-repressor family to directly inhibit gene expression. HEB factors can also collaborate directly with SMAD transcription factors, which are activated downstream of TGF&#x003b2;, in embryonic stem cells (<xref rid="R80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>). The context-dependence of these interactions suggest that HEB and/or E2A may regulate distinct sets of genes as progenitor cells migrate through the thymus.</p><p id="P27">There are several caveats to this study. Our <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> examination of E18 &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells by flow cytometry and scRNA-seq provided a snapshot of developing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells with high relevance to &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells but leaves open the possibility HEB could play roles in &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development at different time points that were not captured in our analysis. In addition, it is currently unclear whether the diminished expression of second stage regulators such as PLZF and MAF is a cause or a consequence of impaired maturation of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors. It also remains to be determined whether the first stage regulators are direct targets of HEB factors, and what the relative roles of HEBAlt and HEBCan might be in these processes. We have also not addressed the relationship between E18 &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells with a subset of &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells that arise from fetal precursors independently of TCR signaling (<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), although <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> could be induced by a combination of HEB and non-TCR signaling pathway(s), which might result in similar dynamics. Additional studies will be needed to address these questions.</p><p id="P28">Our studies have revealed multiple negative feedback loops between E proteins and Id factors that occur during T cell development. In developing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells, HEB upregulates <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression. Id3 in turn suppresses E protein activity. When <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> fails to be upregulated in Id3-KO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors, HEB activity is uninterrupted, leading to the activation of Id2 expression. As waning E protein activity leads to the cessation of <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> transcription, the HEB-Id3 interactions comprise a self-limiting feedback loop. Our results also show that Id2 and Id3 are not equivalent, since Id2 can at least partially compensate for Id3 in &#x003b2;-selection and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;-selection in the fetal thymus but is insufficient for &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 maturation. Together, our studies have identified a role for HEB in inducing the early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell gene regulator network while also launching the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 maturation network by activating <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> expression. Further studies identifying direct targets and partners of HEB in early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors and mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells will be necessary to fully understand the impact of shifting ratios of HEB, Id3, and Id2 on &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="S14"><title>Experimental Design and Statistical Analysis</title><p id="P29">The overall goal of this study was to better understand how HEB transcription factors regulate the transcriptional networks required for the development of IL-17 producing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. The subjects of these studies were genetically modified mice. The experimental variable was the genotype of the mice, chosen based on availability of experimental animals and littermate controls. For the scRNA-seq experiments, fetal thymocytes of like genotype from 3 or more mice were pooled prior to enrichment. Each flow cytometry analysis was performed using 3 or more mice of like genotype per experiment, repeated 2&#x02013;3 times. Mice of both sexes were used, and since no sex differences were apparent, data were pooled. Each datapoint depicted in graphs represents an individual mouse, providing biological replicates. The investigators were not blinded to allocation during experiments and outcome assessment, except when fetal thymocytes were individually analyzed by flow cytometry prior to genotyping. Significance of pairwise data was computed by unpaired two-tailed Student&#x02019;s t-test, with p &#x0003c; 0.05 considered statistically significance. The error bars represent standard error of the mean (SEM) values.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Mice</title><p id="P30">HEB<sup>fl/fl</sup> mice have loxP sites flanking exons that encode the bHLH DNA binding and dimerization domain (<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). These mice were bred to Vav-iCre transgenic mice (JAX stock #008610) (<xref rid="R81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>), which deletes in all hematopoietic cells (<xref rid="R82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>), to generate HEB<sup>fl/fl;Vav-iCre</sup> (HEB cKO) mice, as previously described (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="R83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). All experimental mice were obtained from timed matings of HEB<sup>fl/fl</sup> x HEB<sup>fl/fl</sup> Vav-iCre, which gave rise WT and HEB-deleted littermates, differing only in the presence of Cre. Id3 deficient mice (Id3-KO) lacked Id3 in all cells due to a knock-in of RFP into the <italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic> locus resulting in a knock-in/knock-out allele (JAX strain # 010983, B6;129S-<italic toggle="yes">Id3</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">tm1Pzg</italic></sup>/J). RFP was quenched by intracellular staining. Id3-KO mice were bred onto the C57Bl/6 background for 8 generations. Id3<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice were mated together to produce WT and Id3-KO littermates. Adult mice were analyzed at 6&#x02013;8 weeks of age. Mice were bred and maintained in the Comparative Research Facility of the Sunnybrook Research Institute (Toronto, Ontario, Canada) under specific pathogen-free conditions. All animal procedures were approved by the Sunnybrook Research Institute Animal Care Committee.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Timed Matings and Embryo Harvest</title><p id="P31">Timed matings were performed by setting up mating pairs (day 0) and separating them ~16 hrs later. Embryos were harvested 18 days later. Fetal thymuses were dissected out of embryos and single cell suspensions were generated by mechanical disruption and filtered through 40-micron mesh. Cells were resuspended in PBS for sorting or flow cytometry. Embryos were processed and analyzed separately, and tail tissue was collected for genotyping and sample identification.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p id="P32">Antibodies were purchased from eBiosciences (San Diego, California, USA), Biolegend (San Diego, California, USA) and BD Biosciences (Mississauga, Ontario, Canada). The 5&#x000b4; libraries using to generate the HEB cKO scRNA-seq data directly detected <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V6</italic> mRNA, whereas the 3&#x000b4; libraries did not permit detection of <italic toggle="yes">Tcrg-V</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Trdv</italic> transcripts. For flow cytometry, cells were washed and incubated with Fc blocking antibody (BD Biosciences), followed by extracellular staining for surface CD4 (clone GK1.5), CD8&#x003b1; (clone 53&#x02013;6.7), CD3 (clone 145&#x02013;2C11), TCR&#x003b3;&#x003b4; (clone GL3), TCR&#x003b2; (clone H57&#x02013;597), V&#x003b3;4 (V&#x003b3;2; clone UC3&#x02013;10A6), V&#x003b3;5 (V&#x003b3;3; clone 536), V&#x003b3;1 (V&#x003b3;1.1; clone 2.11), CD27 (clone LG3&#x02013;1A10), V&#x003b4;6.3 (clone 8F4H7B7, CD24 (clone M1/ 69), CD73 (clone TY11.8), CD44 (clone IM7), CD25 (clone PC615). To assess functional capacities, cells were stimulated by incubation for five h with PMA (50 ng/ml) and Ionomycin (500 ng/ml) in the presence of Brefeldin A (5mg/ml; eBioscience), washed with 1XHBSS/BSA, and incubated with Fc block before staining for surface epitopes. Cells were then fixed and permeabilized (Fix and Perm Cell Permeabilization Kit; eBioscience) and stained with antibodies against IL-17A (clone eBio17B7). For intracellular transcription factor staining, the cells were fixed, permeabilized (FoxP3 Staining Kit, eBioscience) and stained for ROR&#x003b3;t (clone B2D), MAF (clone sym0F1), and PLZF (clone R17&#x02013;809). All flow cytometric analyses were performed using Becton-Dickenson (BD) LSRII, Fortessa, or SymphonyA5-SE. FACSDiva and FlowJo software were used for analysis. Sorting was performed on BD ARIA and BD Fusion sorters.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Single-cell RNA sequencing</title><p id="P33">E18 fetal thymuses from HEB cKO mice were dissected from embryos and individually pushed through a 40-micron mesh with a syringe plunger. Cells were incubated with Fc block for 30 min on ice. Small aliquots from each sample were stained with CD4, CD8, and CD3 to assess the genotypes, with a lack of DP indicating HEB deletion. Genotypes were verified by PCR. The remainder of the cells (3 WT and 3 HEB cKO) were stained and sorted for TCR&#x003b3;&#x003b4;<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> cells. Single cells were isolated using the 10X Chromium controller and barcoded libraries were generated using the Chromium Next GEM Single Cell 5&#x02019; Kit v2 (Dual Index) (10X Genomics) at the Princess Margaret Genomics Facility (Toronto, ON, Canada). Next generation Illumina sequencing was performed to a depth of ~20,000 reads.</p><p id="P34">E18 fetal thymuses from Id3-KO mice were dissected from embryos, pushed through mesh as above, and incubated with Fc block. Embryos were genotyped by PCR, and thymocytes were pooled according to genotype. DN (CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) cells were enriched by magnetic sorting using anti-CD4 and anti-CD8 microbeads according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (Miltenyi Biotech). Flow through cells were processed in-house as above but using the Chromium Next GEM Single Cell 3&#x02019; Kit v2 (Dual Index) (10X Genomics).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>scRNA-seq data analysis</title><p id="P35">FASTQ raw data files were aligned to the mm10 genome using Cell Ranger version 1.1.7 (10X Genomics) (<xref rid="R84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). Matrix files were analyzed using programs in R Seurat version 4.4 (<xref rid="R85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>), as detailed in the R-Markdown file (supplementary material). WT and HEBcKO datasets were processed for quality control by excluding cells with more than 7% mitochondrial genes and less than 1000 genes or 4000 RNA sequences, resulting in 1272 WT cells and 1951 HEB cKO cells for further analysis. Filtered WT and HEB cKO datasets were merged, and SCTransform was applied to the merged dataset to limit the variation due to sequencing depth. Cell cycle regression was performed to mitigate the influence of cell cycle heterogeneity on clustering. Cells expressing high levels of <italic toggle="yes">Lyz2</italic> were excluded to remove most myeloid cells. PCA analysis was performed (RunPCA) and used to compute a nearest neighbor graph (FindNeighbors) and identify clusters (FindClusters). UMAP plots were generated using RunUMAP, and displayed using DimPlot_scCustom. FindMarkers was used to generate heatmaps (DoHeatmap) of the top ten genes most differentially expressed (DEGs) between the clusters. Since the DEGs in cluster 8 indicated a myeloid identity, this cluster was removed, and the remaining cells were re-clustered. UMAP plots were generated showing 1) clusters in the merged dataset and 2) distribution of WT versus HEBcKO cells within each cluster, 3) WT cells only, and 4) HEBcKO cells only. The re-clustered merged dataset was used to generate a heatmap using DoHeatmap, which aided in assigning cluster identities. To further evaluate cluster identity, we generated curated gene sets based on the literature (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="R86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, <xref rid="R87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>) and used them to create module scores corresponding to &#x003b1;&#x003b2; and &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell developmental subsets. Importantly, module scores were based on the inclusion of all genes in the gene set used to specify the module. Module scores were compared among merged clusters using Stacked_VlnPlot, and split feature plots were used to display the localization and intensity of module scoring in the UMAP clusters. Comparisons of the expression of single genes between WT and HEBcKO clusters was shown using split feature plots and split violin plots. A clustered dot plot of genes diagnostic for &#x003b1;&#x003b2; and &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell subsets was generated for the merged dataset to further assist in cluster identification. To compare cluster 1, composed mostly of HEBcKO cells, and cluster 4, composed mostly of WT cells, in the merged dataset, we performed FindMarkers using the Wilcox test, minimum three cells per feature and three cells per group. The Enhanced Volcano Plot was calculated with a pCutoff = 10e-26, and an FCcutoff = 0.5.</p><p id="P36">For the Id3-KO dataset, the following analysis was conducted. FASTQ raw data files were aligned to the mm39 genome using Cell Ranger. R-Seurat programs were used to filter the cells as described above in the HEB cKO dataset, resulting in 2324 WT cells and 2895 cells for further analysis. Datasets were merged and subjected to SCTransform as above. PCA plots were generated and used to construct UMAP plots depicting clusters in merged datasets and distribution of WT versus Id3-KO cells across the UMAP. Feature plots and violin plots were used to identify clusters with &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell characteristics. Clusters 6 and 9 were subsetted, and new clusters were obtained using FindClusters. A myeloid cluster was omitted, and a split UMAP were generated to show localization of WT versus HEB cKO cells. Violin plots were generated to classify the four remaining clusters, and split violin plots were generated to show relative expression of early and late &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell genes in WT versus HEB cKO cells within each cluster.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Gene module curation</title><p id="P37">Genes included in each module were chosen as described above. The genes chosen for each module are as follows: DN3 (<italic toggle="yes">Il2ra</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Ptcra</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Rag1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cd24a</italic>), DP (<italic toggle="yes">Rag1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cd8a</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cd8b1</italic>), early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;Te: <italic toggle="yes">Il17re, Cd24a, Blk, Maf, Sox13, Etv5, Ccr9, Sox4, Igfbp4, Rora, Rorc, Cpa3, Il17a, Gzma, Sell, Sox5</italic>), immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 imm: <italic toggle="yes">Il17re, Blk, Maf, Ccr9, Rorc, Nr4a1, Il21r, Sox13, Id3</italic>), mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 mat: <italic toggle="yes">Il17re, Blk, Maf, Rorc, Il23r, Cxcr6, Il1r1, Zbtb16</italic>), immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 imm: <italic toggle="yes">Il2rb, Cd24a, Nr4a1, Xcl1, Il21r, Id3</italic>) and mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (&#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 mat: <italic toggle="yes">Il2rb, Fcer1g, Klrd1, Klra5, Tyrobp, Ifitm1, Xcl1, Cxcr3, Zbtb16, Id3</italic>) subsets. Co-expression of all genes included in the module was required for cells to be assigned a positive module score.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1</label><media xlink:href="NIHPP2025.06.08.658490v1-supplement-1.pdf" id="d67e1413" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S21"><title>Acknowledgments.</title><p id="P38">We would like to thank Lisa Wells, Madeline Harvey, Vivien Musiime, and the SRI Animal Facility for excellent mouse care. We thank Yuan Zhuang for provision of the HEB cKO and Id3-KO mice. We are thankful to David Wiest for thoughtful discussions and providing valuable insights. We are indebted to the SickKids Flow Cytometry Core (supported by the Canadian Foundation for Innovation (CFI) and the SickKids&#x02019; Foundation) for antibody panel design and high parameter flow cytometry analysis, and the SRI Flow Cytometry and Microscopy Core for flow cytometry and sorting. We also thank the UHN Princess Margaret Genomics Facility for construction of the WT and HEBcKO scRNA-seq libraries. The Digital Research Alliance of Canada (RRG #5070) provided cloud computing capacity for scRNA-seq data analysis.</p><sec id="S22"><title>Funding.</title><p id="P39">This work was supported by the Canadian Institutes for Health Research (CIHR; PJT 153058 to MKA, FDN154332 and PJT192050 to JCZP, and PJT165973 to CJG), National Institutes of Health (NIH: 1P01AI102853-06) to MKA and JCZP, and a CFI John Evans Fund Leaders&#x02019; Infrastructure Grant to CJG (#37562). JS was supported by an American Association for Immunologists Careers in Immunology Award and a CIHR Postdoctoral Fellowship. VR was supported by a CIHR Postdoctoral Fellowship, and HW was the recipient of an Ontario Graduate Scholarship.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p id="P49">Conflict of Interest</p><p id="P50">The authors declare there are no conflicts of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S23"><title>Data and materials availability.</title><p id="P40">Matrix files and R-markdown code have been deposited to the Dryad repository and can be accessed private for review at:</p><p id="P41">HEB-WT scRNA-seq matrix files and R-markdown code</p><p id="P42">
<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.08kprr5cq" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.08kprr5cq</ext-link>
</p><p id="P43">HEB cKO scRNA-seq matrix files and R-markdown code</p><p id="P44">
<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.qv9s4mwqh" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.qv9s4mwqh</ext-link>
</p><p id="P45">Id3-WT scRNA-seq matrix files and R-markdown code</p><p id="P46">
<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.j6q573nqd" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.j6q573nqd</ext-link>
</p><p id="P47">Id3-KO scRNA-seq matrix files and R-markdown code</p><p id="P48">
<ext-link xlink:href="10.5061/dryad.x0k6djhvj" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.x0k6djhvj</ext-link>
</p></sec><glossary><title>Definitions of Acyronyms:</title><def-list><def-item><term>TCR</term><def><p id="P51">T cell receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Id</term><def><p id="P52">Inhibitor of DNA binding</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HEB</term><def><p id="P53">HeLa binding box transcription factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p id="P54">interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>E</term><def><p id="P55">embryonic day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>V</term><def><p id="P56">variable region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Egr</term><def><p id="P57">early growth response</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DP</term><def><p id="P58">CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> double positive thymocytes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DN</term><def><p id="P59">CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> double negative thymocytes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UMAP</term><def><p id="P60">uniform manifold approximation and projection for dimensional reduction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCA</term><def><p id="P61">principle component analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>sc</term><def><p id="P62">single cell</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Itohara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Homing of a gamma delta thymocyte subset with homogeneous T-cell receptors to mucosal epithelia</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>343</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>757</lpage> (<year>1990</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2154700</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hovav</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilharm</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Development and Function of gammadeltaT Cells in the Oral Mucosa</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>505</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32091949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Monin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>gammadelta T cells compose a developmentally regulated intrauterine population and protect against vaginal candidiasis</article-title>. <source>Mucosal Immunol</source>, (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akitsu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwakura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Interleukin-17-producing gammadelta T (gammadelta17) cells in inflammatory diseases</article-title>. <source>Immunology</source>
<volume>155</volume>, <fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30133701</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kadekar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>The neonatal microenvironment programs innate gammadelta T cells through the transcription factor STAT5</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>130</volume>, <fpage>2496</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2508</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32281944</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alves de Lima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Meningeal gammadelta T cells regulate anxiety-like behavior via IL-17a signaling in neurons</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1429</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32929273</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wakita</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Tumor-infiltrating IL-17-producing gammadelta T cells support the progression of tumor by promoting angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1937</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20397212</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coffelt</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>IL-17-producing gammadelta T cells and neutrophils conspire to promote breast cancer metastasis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>522</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25822788</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kohlgruber</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>gammadelta T cells producing interleukin-17A regulate adipose regulatory T cell homeostasis and thermogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>474</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29670241</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Fahl</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kappes</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiest</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, in <source>Signaling Mechanisms Regulating T Cell Diversity and Function</source><italic toggle="yes">,</italic>
<name><surname>Soboloff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kappes</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, Eds. (<publisher-loc>Boca Raton (FL)</publisher-loc>, <year>2018</year>), pp. <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sieweke</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <article-title>A transcription factor party during blood cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>551</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9794826</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>The order and logic of CD4 versus CD8 lineage choice and differentiation in mouse thymus</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397934</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gimferrer</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Regulation of GATA-3 expression during CD4 lineage differentiation</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>186</volume>, <fpage>3892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3898</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21357543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Views on helper/cytotoxic lineage choice from a bottom-up approach</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source>
<volume>271</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27088909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Komori</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Cutting edge: dendritic epidermal gammadelta T cell ligands are rapidly and locally expressed by keratinocytes following cutaneous wounding</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>188</volume>, <fpage>2972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2976</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22393149</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Girardi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Regulation of cutaneous malignancy by gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>294</volume>, <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>609</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11567106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>IL-17-producing gammadelta T cells protect against Clostridium difficile infection</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>130</volume>, <fpage>2377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2390</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31990686</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witherden</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Havran</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>, <article-title>The Role of Tissue-resident T Cells in Stress Surveillance and Tissue Maintenance</article-title>. <source>Cells</source>
<volume>9</volume>, (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmolka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Epigenetic and transcriptional signatures of stable versus plastic differentiation of proinflammatory gammadelta T cell subsets</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1093</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1100</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995235</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <article-title>The natural and the inducible: interleukin (IL)-17-producing gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23266231</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Joannou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>&#x003b3;&#x003b4; Thymocyte Maturation and Emigration in Adult Mice</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>208</volume>, <fpage>2131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2140</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35396221</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>IL-4-producing gamma delta T cells that express a very restricted TCR repertoire are preferentially localized in liver and spleen</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>163</volume>, <fpage>3076</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3082</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477572</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Azuara</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levraud</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lembezat</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <article-title>A novel subset of adult gamma delta thymocytes that secretes a distinct pattern of cytokines and expresses a very restricted T cell receptor repertoire</article-title>. <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>553</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9045929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>du Halgouet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Multimodal profiling reveals site-specific adaptation and tissue residency hallmarks of gammadelta T cells across organs in mice</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>356</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38177282</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witherden</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Havran</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>, <article-title>gammadelta T cells in homeostasis and host defence of epithelial barrier tissues</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>745</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28920588</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lambolez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Characterization of T cell differentiation in the murine gut</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>195</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>449</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11854357</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>In</surname><given-names>T. S. H.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>HEB is required for the specification of fetal IL-17-producing gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>2004</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29222418</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kashani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>A clonotypic Vgamma4Jgamma1/Vdelta5Ddelta2Jdelta1 innate gammadelta T-cell population restricted to the CCR6(+)CD27(&#x02212;) subset</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>6477</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25765849</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sandrock</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Genetic models reveal origin, persistence and non-redundant functions of IL-17-producing gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>215</volume>, <fpage>3006</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3018</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30455268</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Havran</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Developmentally ordered appearance of thymocytes expressing different T-cell antigen receptors</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>335</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>445</lpage> (<year>1988</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2458531</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carding</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Gammadelta T cells: functional plasticity and heterogeneity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12033739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raulet</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Gene placement and competition control T cell receptor gamma variable region gene rearrangement</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>205</volume>, <fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>938</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378791</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heilig</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tonegawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Diversity of murine gamma genes and expression in fetal and adult T lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>322</volume>, <fpage>836</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>840</lpage> (<year>1986</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2943999</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edelblum</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>gammadelta Intraepithelial Lymphocyte Migration Limits Transepithelial Pathogen Invasion and Systemic Disease in Mice</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>1417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1426</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25747597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Disruption of alpha beta but not of gamma delta T cell development by overexpression of the helix-loop-helix protein Id3 in committed T cell progenitors</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>2793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2802</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10329625</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>A fetal wave of human type 3 effector gammadelta cells with restricted TCR diversity persists into adulthood</article-title>. <source>Sci Immunol</source>
<volume>6</volume>, (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sanchez Sanchez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tafesse</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vermijlen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Surfing on the waves of the human &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell ontogenic sea</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source>
<volume>315</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36625367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Rocha</surname><given-names>J. D. B.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Direct regulation of TCR rearrangement and expression by E proteins during early T cell development</article-title>. <source>WIREs Mech Dis</source>, <fpage>e1578</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35848146</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Selvaratnam</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Interaction between gammadeltaTCR signaling and the E protein-Id axis in gammadelta T cell development</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source>
<volume>298</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33058287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Munoz-Ruiz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>TCR signal strength controls thymic differentiation of discrete proinflammatory gammadelta T cell subsets</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>727</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043412</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>E. L. Y.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Ontogenic timing, T cell receptor signal strength, and Notch signaling direct &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell functional differentiation in vivo</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>109227</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34107257</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scaramuzzino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Single-cell transcriptomics uncovers an instructive T-cell receptor role in adult gammadelta T-cell lineage commitment</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>e110023</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35128689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haks</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Attenuation of gammadeltaTCR signaling efficiently diverts thymocytes to the alphabeta lineage</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15894277</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>, <article-title>TCR signal strength influences alphabeta/gammadelta lineage fate</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>593</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15894276</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stadanlick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kappes</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiest</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Towards a molecular understanding of the differential signals regulating alphabeta/gammadelta T lineage choice</article-title>. <source>Semin Immunol</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20471282</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sumaria</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Constrained TCRgammadelta-associated Syk activity engages PI3K to facilitate thymic development of IL-17A-secreting gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>Sci Signal</source>
<volume>14</volume>, (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Turchinovich</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayday</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Skint-1 identifies a common molecular mechanism for the development of interferon-gamma-secreting versus interleukin-17-secreting gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21737317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Integration of T-cell receptor, Notch and cytokine signals programs mouse gammadelta T-cell effector differentiation</article-title>. <source>Immunol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>96</volume>, <fpage>994</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1007</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29754419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>The TCR ligand-inducible expression of CD73 marks gammadelta lineage commitment and a metastable intermediate in effector specification</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>211</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>343</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24493796</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Munoz-Ruiz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sumaria</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva-Santos</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Thymic Determinants of gammadelta T Cell Differentiation</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28285814</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Spidale</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Interleukin-17-Producing gammadelta T Cells Originate from SOX13(+) Progenitors that Are Independent of gammadeltaTCR Signaling</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>872 e855</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30413363</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fahl</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>The E protein-TCF1 axis controls gammadelta T cell development and effector fate</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>108716</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33535043</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldrath</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>E proteins and Notch signaling cooperate to promote T cell lineage specification and commitment</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>203</volume>, <fpage>1329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1342</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16682500</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kersh</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Interplay between RORgammat, Egr3, and E proteins controls proliferation in response to pre-TCR signals</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>813</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>826</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782036</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones-Mason</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>E protein transcription factors are required for the development of CD4(+) lineage T cells</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22425249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Helix-loop-helix proteins and the advent of cellular diversity: 30 years of discovery</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602438</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Regulation of the helix-loop-helix proteins, E2A and Id3, by the Ras-ERK MAPK cascade</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175815</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Early thymocyte development is regulated by modulation of E2A protein activity</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>194</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>745</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11560990</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lauritsen</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Marked induction of the helix-loop-helix protein Id3 promotes the gammadelta T cell fate and renders their functional maturation Notch independent</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833086</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alonzo</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Development of promyelocytic zinc finger and ThPOK-expressing innate gamma delta T cells is controlled by strength of TCR signaling and Id3</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>184</volume>, <fpage>1268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1279</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038637</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>E-protein regulatory network links TCR signaling to effector Treg cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>, (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barndt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>A novel role for HEB downstream or parallel to the pre-TCR signaling pathway during alpha beta thymopoiesis</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>163</volume>, <fpage>3331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3343</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477603</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wojciechowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>E2A and HEB are required to block thymocyte proliferation prior to pre-TCR expression</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>178</volume>, <fpage>5717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5726</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442955</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paget</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>CD3bright signals on gammadelta T cells identify IL-17A-producing Vgamma6Vdelta1+ T cells</article-title>. <source>Immunol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25385067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sagar <etal/>, <article-title>Deciphering the regulatory landscape of fetal and adult &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T-cell development at single-cell resolution</article-title>. <source>Embo j</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>e104159</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32627520</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Intrathymic programming of effector fates in three molecularly distinct gammadelta T cell subtypes</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>518</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22473038</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>T cell receptor signal strength in Treg and iNKT cell development demonstrated by a novel fluorescent reporter mouse</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>208</volume>, <fpage>1279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1289</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21606508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiest</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Id3 Restricts gammadelta NKT Cell Expansion by Controlling Egr2 and c-Myc Activity</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>201</volume>, <fpage>1452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1459</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30012846</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Verykokakis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Inhibitor of DNA binding 3 limits development of murine slam-associated adaptor protein-dependent &#x0201c;innate&#x0201d; gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e9303</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20174563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ueda-Hayakawa</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahlios</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Id3 restricts the developmental potential of gamma delta lineage during thymopoiesis</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>182</volume>, <fpage>5306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5316</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19380777</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Id3 and Id2 act as a dual safety mechanism in regulating the development and population size of innate-like gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>192</volume>, <fpage>1055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1063</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379125</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sumaria</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grandjean</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva-Santos</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Strong TCRgammadelta Signaling Prohibits Thymic Development of IL-17A-Secreting gammadelta T Cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>2469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2476</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28636936</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romanow</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Havran</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Positive and negative regulation of V(D)J recombination by the E2A proteins</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>189</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9892611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Regulation of TCR Vgamma2 gene rearrangement by the helix-loop-helix protein, E2A</article-title>. <source>Int Immunol</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21421735</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mihai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>E proteins control the development of NKgammadeltaT cells through their invariant T cell receptor</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>5078</fpage> (<year>2024</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38871720</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dienz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Critical Role for SLAM/SAP Signaling in the Thymic Developmental Programming of IL-17- and IFN-gamma-Producing gammadelta T Cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>204</volume>, <fpage>1521</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1534</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32024701</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Interleukin 7 (IL-7) selectively promotes mouse and human IL-17-producing gammadelta cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>17549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17554</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23047700</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ribot</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>CD27 is a thymic determinant of the balance between interferon-gamma- and interleukin 17-producing gammadelta T cell subsets</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>436</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19270712</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoganathan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Regulation of the Signal-Dependent E Protein HEBAlt Through a YYY Motif Is Required for Progression Through T Cell Development</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>848577</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35990644</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>HEB associates with PRC2 and SMAD2/3 to regulate developmental fates</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>6546</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25775035</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Transgenic mice with hematopoietic and lymphoid specific expression of Cre</article-title>. <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12548562</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Siegemund</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <article-title>hCD2-iCre and Vav-iCre mediated gene recombination patterns in murine hematopoietic cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0124661</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25884630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Welinder</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>The transcription factors E2A and HEB act in concert to induce the expression of FOXO1 in the common lymphoid progenitor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>17402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17407</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21972416</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>G. X.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Massively parallel digital transcriptional profiling of single cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>14049</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28091601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>Integrated analysis of multimodal single-cell data</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>184</volume>, <fpage>3573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3587 e3529</lpage> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34062119</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zuberbuehler</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>, <article-title>The transcription factor c-Maf is essential for the commitment of IL-17-producing gammadelta T cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30538336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Painter</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Immunological Genome Project</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <article-title>The Immunological Genome Project: networks of gene expression in immune cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1091</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1094</lpage> (<year>2008</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18800157</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Decreased V&#x003b3;4<sup>+</sup> &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells and increased immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in E18 fetal thymocytes from HEB cKO mice compared to WT.</title><p id="P63">WT and HEB cKO mice were set up for timed matings to produce WT and HEB cKO littermates. E18 thymocytes analyzed by flow cytometry. <bold>A</bold>. Numbers of cells per thymus. <bold>B, C</bold>. Representative flow plots (<bold>B</bold>) and percentages (<bold>C</bold>) of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. <bold>D</bold>. Absolute numbers of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells per thymus. <bold>E, F</bold>. Representative contour plots (<bold>E</bold>) and percentages (<bold>F</bold>) of V&#x003b3;4 and V&#x003b3;1 cells out of all &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. <bold>G</bold>. Absolute numbers of V&#x003b3; subset cells per thymus. <bold>H, I</bold>. Representative contour plots (H) and percentages (I) of CD24<sup>+</sup> cells within V&#x003b3;4 and V&#x003b3;1 subsets. <bold>J.</bold> Representative contour plot of V&#x003b3;5 and V&#x003b3;6 CD24 expression in the V&#x003b3;4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>V&#x003b3;1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> population. <bold>K</bold>. Percentages of CD24<sup>+</sup> cells in V&#x003b3;5 and V&#x003b3;6 subsets out of all &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. Blue = WT, orange = HEB cKO. Data is presented as mean +/&#x02212; SEM. Statistical significance was assessed using unpaired student&#x02019;s T tests. ****p &#x0003c;0.0001, ***p &#x0003c; 0.005, **p &#x0003c; 0.001, *p &#x0003c; 0.05, n=non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Single cell RNA-sequencing of E18 &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR<sup>+</sup> fetal thymocytes reveals perturbations in V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; expression and early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell regulators in HEB cKO fetal thymus.</title><p id="P64">E18 &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> thymocytes were sorted from WT and HEB cKO littermates, subjected to scRNA-seq, and analyzed using R-Seurat. <bold>A</bold>. UMAP plot of merged data from WT and HEB cKO cells revealing 8 clusters (0&#x02013;7). <bold>B</bold>. UMAP plot grouped by WT (blue) and HEB cKO (orange) cells. <bold>C</bold>. Split UMAP plot showing location and proportions of WT cells (left) and HEB cKO cells (right) within the UMAP. <bold>D.</bold> Single cell heatmap depicting the 10 most differentially expressed genes between all clusters. <bold>E</bold>. Clustered dot plot showing the proportions and levels of curated genes in each cluster. <bold>F</bold>. Violin plots of the relative magnitude of gene set modules in each cluster. <bold>G</bold>. Identities assigned to each cluster based on the analysis in (A-F). <bold>H</bold>. Enhanced volcano plot depicting differentially expressed genes between cluster 4 and cluster 1. Pink dots = statistically significant Log<sub>2</sub>Fc and Log<sub>10</sub>P. Red circle highlights that Id3 is severely decreased in Cluster 1 relative to Cluster 4.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Disruptions of V&#x003b3; and V&#x003b4; element expression and early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursor gene expression in fetal HEB cKO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells.</title><p id="P65">Gene sets diagnostic for cells belonging to specific developmental subsets and cells with V&#x003b3;-V&#x003b4; paired expression were assembled and used to generate module scores. Module scores were applied to split UMAP plots, allowing a detailed comparison between WT and HEB cKO cells (A-E, J-N). Split violin plots (blue=WT, orange=HEB cKO) were generated for specific genes belonging to these modules (F-G, O-Q), revealing differences in expression within each cluster. The cluster numbers and names depicted below the violin plots correspond to the numbers on the UMAPs and the identities assigned to those clusters in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2G</xref>. Clusters composed mostly of WT cells (*4) or HEBcKO cells (**1) are designated by asterisks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Fetal thymus of Id3-deficient mice fail to upregulate CD73 during &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell development.</title><p id="P66">E18 thymocytes were obtained from WT and Id3-KO mice and analyzed by flow cytometry. <bold>A.</bold> Absolute numbers of cells per thymus. <bold>B, C</bold>. Percentages (B) and representative flow cytometry plots (C) of &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in E18 fetal thymus. <bold>D, E</bold>. Representative flow plots (D) and percentages (E) of V&#x003b3;1<sup>+</sup> and V&#x003b3;4<sup>+</sup> &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells out of all &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. <bold>F</bold>. Percentages of V&#x003b3;5 and V&#x003b3;6 cells out of all &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. <bold>G</bold>. Representative flow plots showing CD24/CD73 subsets within the &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell population. <bold>H.</bold> Percentages of mature (CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) CD73<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and CD73<sup>+</sup> cells out of all &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells. <bold>I</bold>. Representative flow plots depicting CD24/CD73 subsets within each V&#x003b3; subset. Plots are gated on V&#x003b3; chains as indicated. Blue = WT, pink = Id3-KO. Data is presented as mean +/&#x02212; SEM. Statistical significance was assessed using unpaired student&#x02019;s T tests. ****p &#x0003c;0.0001, *p &#x0003c; 0.05, n=non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Id3-KO &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells fail to produce IL-17 in response to stimulation.</title><p id="P67">Fetal thymocytes were harvested at E18 and cultured with or without PMA/ionomycin (P/I) for four hours in the presence of brefeldin A, followed by flow cytometry. <bold>A</bold>. Representative flow cytometry plots showing IL-17 expression in the &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>V&#x003b3;5<sup>&#x02212;</sup>V&#x003b3;1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD27<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD73<sup>&#x02212;</sup> population (primarily mature V&#x003b3;6 cells) at baseline (top) or after stimulation (bottom), as assessed by intracellular staining. <bold>B</bold>. Percentages of stimulated cells expressing IL-17; note that IL-17 was not expressed outside this population. <bold>C</bold>. Representative flow plots showing CD73 expression at baseline (top) and after stimulation by P/I (bottom) within the &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell population. <bold>D.</bold> Quantification of percentages of CD27<sup>+</sup>CD73<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells and CD27<sup>+</sup>CD73<sup>+</sup> cells at baseline (top) or after stimulation (bottom) within the WT (left) or Id3-KO (right) populations. Blue bars =WT, Pink bars = Id3-KO. Statistical significance was determined using Student&#x02019;s t-tests, ****p &#x0003c;0.0001, ***p &#x0003c; 0.005, **p &#x0003c; 0.001, n=non-significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells in Id3-KO E18 thymus exhibit decreased expression of MAF and PLZF.</title><p id="P68">E18.5 fetal thymocytes were harvested from WT and Id3-KO mice and subjected to intracellular flow cytometry. Cells were gated on &#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> V&#x003b3;1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>V&#x003b3;5<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x003b3;&#x003b4;TCR<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> cells to enrich for &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells with &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 potential. <bold>A, B.</bold> Representative flow plots of MAF and PLZF expression in V&#x003b3;4<sup>+</sup>TCR&#x003b3;&#x003b4;<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> cells from WT versus Id3-KO mice. <bold>B</bold>. Percentages of V&#x003b3;4<sup>+</sup> cells co-expressing MAF and PLZF. <bold>C.</bold> Representative flow plots showing MAF and PLZF expression in V&#x003b3;6 cells. <bold>D</bold>. Percentages of V&#x003b3;6 cells co-expressing MAF and PLZF. <bold>E</bold>. Representative flow plots showing ROR&#x003b3;t and MAF expression in mature CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> V&#x003b3;6 cells. <bold>F</bold>. Percentages of mature CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup> V&#x003b3;6<sup>+</sup> &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells co-expressing ROR&#x003b3;t and MAF. Blue bars =WT, pink bars = Id3-KO. Statistical significance was determined using Student&#x02019;s t-tests, ****p &#x0003c;0.0001, ***p &#x0003c; 0.005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><title>Diminished expression of second stage but not first stage regulators in Id3-KO E18 &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells as assessed by scRNA-seq.</title><p id="P69">E18 thymocytes from WT and Id3-KO mice were harvested and enriched for DN (double negative; CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) cells by magnetic sorting. Sorted cells were subjected to scRNA-seq. <bold>A</bold>. UMAP plot of the merged dataset showing clustering. <bold>B</bold>. Grouped UMAP plot of merged dataset showing WT versus Id3-KO cells. <bold>C</bold>. Violin plots showing relative expression of specific genes within each cluster. <bold>D</bold>. Feature maps showing expression of different genes in merged dataset. Clusters (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) containing &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cells were re-clustered for analysis, generating four new clusters that were classified into early &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell precursors (gdTe, gray), immature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells (gdT17_imm, purple), mature &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T17 cells (gdT17_mat, red), and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T1 cells (gdT1, orange). <bold>E</bold>. Violin plots of gene expression used to assign lineages and developmental stages to the clusters. <bold>F.</bold> Split UMAP plots depicting WT cells (top) and Id3-KO cells (bottom) in the merged &#x003b3;&#x003b4; T cell dataset. <bold>G</bold>. Split violin plots showing relative expression of these genes in WT (blue) versus Id3-KO (pink) knockout cells within the gdTe, gdT17_imm, and gdT1 clusters. The gdT17_mat cluster was excluded from this analysis due to the paucity of Id3-KO data points.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.08.658490v1-f0007" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>