<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40502136</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12157423</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.04.657687</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Live-cell analyses with unsegmented images to study cancer cell response to modified T cell therapy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0009-0607-854X</contrib-id><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>Leo</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">+</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5968-3606</contrib-id><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>Adam C</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">+</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2318-1011</contrib-id><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Archit</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saedi</surname><given-names>Mozhgan</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9410-7148</contrib-id><name><surname>Carnevale</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2734-5776</contrib-id><name><surname>Marson</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6139-7334</contrib-id><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>Barbara E</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Gladstone Institutes, Institute of Data Science and Biotechnology, San Francisco, CA, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Humboldt Universitat zu Berlin, Informatik, Unter den Linden 6, 10117 Berlin, Germany</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>University of California San Francisco, School of Medicine, San Francisco, CA, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Gladstone Institutes, Institute of Genomic Immunology, San Francisco, CA, USA</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Stanford University, Biomedical Data Science, Stanford, CA, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="equal" id="FN1"><label>+</label><p id="P1">these authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="FN2"><p id="P2">Author contributions statement</p><p id="P3">L.E., B.E.E., A.M., J.C., and A.V. conceived the study. J.C. and A.M. generated, preserved, and shared the imaging data. L.E., A.C.W., and M.S. conducted the computational experiments. L.E., A.C.W., B.E.E., J.C., and A.M. analyzed the results. L.E., A.C.W., and B.E.E. wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>corresponding author(s): Barbara E Engelhardt (<email>barbara.engelhardt@gladstone.ucsf.edu</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2025.06.04.657687</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to copy and distribute the material in any medium or format in unadapted form only, for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2025.06.04.657687.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P4">Live-cell imaging (LCI) of modified T cells co-cultured with cancer cells is commonly used to quantify T cell anti-cancer function. Videos captured by LCI show complex multi-cell behavioral phenotypes that go beyond simple cancer cell fluorescence measurements. Here, we develop an unsupervised analysis workflow to characterize LCI data generated using the Incucyte imaging platform. Unlike most LCI analyses, we avoid cell segmentation due to the low spatiotemporal resolution of the LCI videos and high levels of cell-cell contact. Instead, we develop methods that identify global aggregation patterns and local cellular keypoints to characterize the multicellular interactions that determine cancer cell sensitivity to, or escape from, T cell surveillance. We demonstrate our segmentation-free live-cell behavioral analysis (SF-LCBA) methods on TCR T cells from four donors with varying proportions of cells with a beneficial RASA2 knockout and effector-to-target initial concentrations in a co-culture with A375 melanoma cells. We find that different T cell modifications affect the spatiotemporal dynamics of multicellular aggregate formation. In particular, we show that fewer and smaller cancer cell aggregates form at high ratios of effector T cells to target cancer cells and high titrations of T cells with RASA2 knockouts. Our SF-LCBA method identifies, characterizes, and tracks cellular aggregate formation in datasets that are unsuitable for cell segmentation and tracking, opening the door to more therapeutically-relevant measurements of modified T cell therapy cell behavioral phenotypes from LCI data.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P5">T cell cancer immunotherapies have in the past decade gained recognition for their therapeutic potential. The 2017 success of anti-CD19 chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cell therapy and subsequent FDA approval was a bell weather for this class of therapies for liquid cancers<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Since then, research to improve T cell therapies and adapt them for use in solid tumors has accelerated<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. T cell receptor (TCR) based immunotherapies have been particularly promising; an anti-MAGE-A4 TCR T cell therapy for metastatic synovial sarcoma became the first FDA-approved T cell therapy for solid tumors in 2024<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. TCR T cells differ from CAR T cells in that they bind to cancer-specific proteins presented on the cell surface by human leukocyte antigens (HLAs) instead of cancer cell surface proteins such as CD19. This advantage of TCR T cells increases the number of potential cancer-specific antigens that can be targeted with a T cell therapy.</p><p id="P6">Another active area of T cell cancer immunotherapy research is to improve anti-cancer activity of the modified T cell. Endogenous regulatory pathways and immunosuppressive tumor microenvironments can both trigger T cell dysfunction, which is characterized by reduced T cell proliferation and cytotoxic signaling. Fortunately, targeted gene editing with CRISPR-Cas9 has the potential to overcome these limitations and enhance therapeutic efficacy<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Several recent studies have performed genome-wide CRISPR knockout screens under <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic><sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic><sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> immunosuppressive conditions to identify genetic perturbations that reduce T cell therapeutic functions. These modified CAR and TCR T cells hold immense promise to improve anti-cancer cellular immunotherapy.</p><p id="P7">While genome-wide CRISPR screens successfully nominate promising T cell perturbations in a high-throughput fashion, these candidates are validated using lower throughput experiments. In particular, fluorescence-based killing assays are a common <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> functional assay for quantifying anti-cancer activity<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. In this assay, modified T cells are co-cultured with cancer cells that express a fluorescent reporter. The co-cultures are then subject to multi-channel live-cell imaging (LCI) to quantify the amount of fluorescent signal coming from cancer cells. Experimental conditions associated with the largest reduction in fluorescent intensity across the well plate, as a proxy for a reduction in viable cancer cells, are determined to have the greatest anticancer potential and then often followed-up with <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies. However, there is often a discrepancy between <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> cancer cell killing efficacy<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P8">To address the discrepancy between <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> efficacy and to better understand the mechanisms for increased anticancer potential, computational researchers have been trying to extract additional features from co-culture live-cell imaging (LCI) data beyond cancer cell killing efficacy<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Research in this area has been made possible through critical advancements from the deep learning computer vision field to develop models that segment individual cells from phase channel images<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. The resulting cell segmentation masks enable measurements of cell morphology, such as quantifying cell size and circularity, which are known to vary between cell types and phenotypic states<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. In LCI datasets with high temporal resolution, cell tracking models are often run downstream of segmentation, which allows for estimation of cell motility, cell division events, and changes in cell morphology over time<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. Recent work from our group has demonstrated that cell segmentation and tracking outputs can be used to compare T cell interaction times, changes in morphology, and proliferation dynamics between different genetically modified TCR T cells<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P9">Despite the promise of cell segmentation and tracking to provide informative features, these pre-trained deep learning models are often incompatible with existing cancer and T cell co-culture LCI data. Co-culture experiments test cancer cells and T cell products across many different experimental conditions and technical replicates. Given that automated LCI microscopes only have one camera per 96-well plate, there is a tradeoff between number of wells imaged and the spatiotemporal resolution of the images. The spatiotemporal resolution of co-culture experiment LCI data is commonly 5<italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>m/pixel and 2 hours between frames<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. This is too low to perform cell segmentation and tracking for T cells, which requires &#x02264; 1<italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>m/pixel (&#x02265; 10x magnification) and &#x02264; 15 minutes between frames, respectively<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. Additionally, even when the spatiotemporal resolution criteria are satisfied, these models struggle to segment and track cells belonging to cancer cell aggregates&#x02014; commonly found in co-culture LCI experiments&#x02014;since cell aggregates are not present in any training data for these models. Therefore, there is a critical need to measure biologically-relevant features of co-culture LCI data, such as T cell activation and cancer cell aggregation, without the use of pre-trained cell segmentation and tracking methods.</p><p id="P10">In this paper, we analyzed LCI data of RASA2 knockout (RASA2KO) TCR T cells co-cultured with the A375 melanoma cell line<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> to characterize cancer cell aggregation across experimental conditions. Deletion of RASA2 was chosen as the genetic pertubation for these experiments as its ablation was found to enhance MAPK signaling and T cell cytolitic activity in a genome-wide CRISPR screen. Each LCI co-culture varied in the titration of RASA2KO mutant to wildtype T cells, the effector to target (E:T) ratio, and the primary T cell donor. Since the cancer cells expressed red fluorescent protein (RFP), each well had phase and red channel images taken once every 2 hours for a total of 144 hours.</p><p id="P11">In order to circumvent low spatiotemporal imaging resolution that prevented cell segmentation and tracking of this data, we formulated a segmentation-free live-cell behavioral analysis (SF-LCBA) framework to understand the multicellular interactions associated with the observed cancer cell aggregation processes. This works builds on a segmentation-free deep learning model for classification that was naive to any observed behaviors of the cells<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. The two main components of SF-LCBA are the calculation of cancer cell spatial entropy across each well<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>, and using scale-invariant feature transform (SIFT) to identify and characterize local keypoints in the phase channel images as one of five single or aggregate cell types<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. SIFT extracted hundreds to thousands of keypoints per image&#x02014;where each keypoint represents a single- or multi-cellular instance and is captured using a length-128 descriptor vector. We clustered SIFT descriptor vectors and interpreted the meaning of each SIFT cluster through visual inspection and comparison of RFP intensities. Statistical testing was applied to both the SIFT clusters and the spatial entropy scores to show their relationships with experimental conditions and temporal dynamics. Overall, our analysis demonstrated that cancer cell growth and, importantly, aggregation is most effectively inhibited in co-cultures with high starting doses of RASA2KO TCR T cells (high E:T ratio, high RASA2KO titration). We believe the SF-LCBA framework has broad potential to improve analyses of co-culture LCI data beyond total cancer cell counts, stratifying distinct conditions where total RFP expression would otherwise be equal in a wide variety of imaging scenarios, ultimately leading to better cellular cancer immunotherapies.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Methods</title><p id="P12">The proof-of-concept data for our segmentation-free live-cell behavioral analyses (SF-LCBA) methods come from LCI taken with the Incucyte platform from a study of TCR T cells in four donor backgrounds. These TCR T cells with the RASA2 knockout are co-cultured with cells from the A375 malignant melanoma cell line<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. These LCI data allow us to showcase the association of our metrics with donor, E:T ratio, and RASA2KO mutant-to-wildtype TCR T cell titration. The SF-LCBA workflow that we develop may also be applied to LCI experiments from different experimental systems as long as there are phase contrast and fluorescence channels available.</p><sec id="S3"><title>Live-cell imaging experiments</title><p id="P13">NY-ESO1-reactive 1G4 TCR T cells were co-cultured with pre-plated red fluorescent protein positive (RFP+) A375 tumor cells in 96 well flat-bottom plates. The plates were imaged every 2 hours for 144 hours using the IncuCyte Zoom live-cell imaging platform (Essen Bioscience). Across two channels images were acquired. These channels consisted of a phase (brightfield) channel and an RFP (red) channel. The plates were laid out in a matrix as follows: Across 12 columns, T cell titration was serially diluted from 100% RASA2KO T cells to 3.1% RASA2KO T cells and 96.9% wild type T cells. These titrations were duplicated across four technical replicates. Across 14 rows, Effector T cell to cancer (A375 cancer cells) cell ratio (E:T ratio) is progressively diluted from 2.8284 by a factor of 1.14142 to 0.2. These dilutions are duplicated (across four technical replicates) for all E:T ratios except for the lowest one. Each combination of E:T ratio and RASA2KO percentage is replicated four times, except for the lowest E:T ratio, which only has two technical replicates. There are four plates, the T cells of each plate across mutational status are derived from different donors. Each experiment has approximately sixty five images; there is variation in time series length of &#x000b1;3 frames between donor replicates. The spatial resolution per image frame is 4.975 <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>m/pixel. To ensure time frames exactly matched across conditions, we restricted our analysis of this dataset to the first 64 time frames from 5 RASA2KO titrations (100%, 50%, 25%, 12.5%, 6.25%), 5 effector to target (E:T) ratios (2.83, 2.00, 1.41, 1.00, 0.71), 4 donors, and 2 technical replicates; however, these filters are performed for simplicity of presentation and are not essential to the analyses.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Thresholding on RFP intensity to obtain cancer cell masks</title><p id="P14">Red fluorescent protein (RFP) was primarily localized to the nucleus and cytoplasm of A375 cancer cells; however, RFP was also detected at low levels throughout the well due to background auto-fluorescence. We therefore created a binary cancer cell mask <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by thresholding the red channel&#x02019;s intensity values at &#x02265; 3.5. We quantified the binary cancer cell mask as follows:
<disp-formula id="FD1">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math id="M21" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="" open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>otherwise</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the red channel&#x02019;s intensity value at pixel coordinates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the resulting binary mask where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> indicates RFP+ pixels, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> indicates RFP&#x02212; pixels.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Cancer cell mask summary statistics</title><p id="P15">The two summary statistics we computed from cancer cell masks were the cancer cell area and spatial entropy. We approximated cancer cell area for a region of interest (ROI) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> using the ROI&#x02019;s fraction of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RFP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>pixels</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RFP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as follows:
<disp-formula id="FD2">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math id="M29" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RFP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L1"><list-item><p id="P16"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the binary cancer cell mask,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P17"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the set of pixel coordinates within the ROI, and</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P18"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of pixels in the ROI.</p></list-item></list><p id="P19">To compute spatial entropy, we partitioned the binary mask <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of ROI <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> into a set of 100 &#x000d7; 100 pixel subregions <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We computed the Shannon entropy measure based on the fraction of RFP+ pixels within each region. We used the following equation to compute entropy:
<disp-formula id="FD3">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math id="M36" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L2"><list-item><p id="P20"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the spatial entropy of the cancer cell mask <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in ROI <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P21"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the set of 100 &#x000d7; 100 pixel subregions in ROI <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P22"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the proportion of RFP+ pixels in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" display="inline"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>th subregion, given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of RFP+ pixels in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" display="inline"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>th subregion, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of RFP+ pixels in the entire ROI <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list><p id="P23">For both summary statistics, the ROI <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" display="inline"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> can either be the entire image or a window within an image.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Applying SIFT to LCI phase images</title><p id="P24">The scale-invariant feature transform (SIFT)<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> was applied to all phase (brightfield) image frames in the LCI dataset using the scikit-image implementation with default settings of 8 octaves and 3 scales<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. The SIFT algorithm consists of two steps: 1) identifying keypoints and 2) computing descriptors. Each SIFT keypoint is a set of image coordinates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that represents a local maximum or minimum of a Gaussian pyramid transform of the image. SIFT identifies keypoints across three discrete scales <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and 8 octaves <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" display="inline"><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, whereby the radius <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" display="inline"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of each keypoint is defined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. SIFT also captures the orientation angle of the gradient around every keypoint. Keypoint angle is used to standardize the orientation of the calculated descriptor histograms, insuring rotational invariance. After identifying all keypoints in an image, SIFT computes a length-128 descriptor vector for each keypoint. This vector is a flattened histogram of gradients calculated around the keypoint coordinates on the untransformed image.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Subsampling SIFT descriptor matrix</title><p id="P25">Since SIFT key-points correspond to local maxima and minima in the feature space of a Gaussian pyramid transform of the image, we obtained <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> keypoints (and descriptors) for each phase image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" display="inline"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> instead of a constant number of keypoints per image. To limit memory usage, we randomly subsampled 10% of each image&#x02019;s keypoints when constructing the original descriptor matrix of shape <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>389</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>740</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We further randomly subsampled the descriptor matrix down to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> keypoints when performing statistical tests and visualization to avoid overpowered p-values and improve interpretation, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>K-means clustering of SIFT descriptors</title><p id="P26">We used K-means to cluster the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptor matrix. We used the scikit-learn implementation of K-means clustering<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> with default parameters, and we performed a parameter sweep for the number of clusters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, ranging from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We computed the silhouette score and sum of squared distances (SSD) to cluster center for each set of clustering results <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The silhouette score measures the quality of clustering by evaluating how similar a (key)point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is to its own cluster compared to other clusters. It first computes the the mean intra-cluster distance for each keypoint <inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula id="FD4">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math id="M67" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L3"><list-item><p id="P27"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the cluster to which keypoint <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> belongs,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P28"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of keypoints in cluster <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P29"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the length-128 descriptor vectors for the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>th and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" display="inline"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>th keypoints, respectively,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P30"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the Euclidean distance between descriptor vectors <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list><p id="P31">The second step of computing the silhouette score is to find the nearest cluster distance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which represents the average distance of keypoint <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> to all keypoints in the nearest neighboring cluster:
<disp-formula id="FD5">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math id="M81" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L4"><list-item><p id="P32"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" display="inline"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is any cluster other than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P33"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of keypoints in cluster <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" display="inline"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list><p id="P34">Using both <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for all keypoints, we compute the mean silhouette coefficient over all keypoints in the SIFT matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" display="inline"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula id="FD6">
<label>(6)</label>
<mml:math id="M89" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula></p><p id="P35">Note that we only computed silhouette score on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> keypoints since computing silhouette scores has runtime complexity of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Silhouette scores range from &#x02212;1 to 1, where 1 represents perfectly clustered data.</p><p id="P36">The other metric we computed was the sum of squared distances (SSD) from each keypoint to the cluster center, also known as the within-cluster sum of squares (WCCS) metric:
<disp-formula id="FD7">
<label>(7)</label>
<mml:math id="M92" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>WCSS</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L5"><list-item><p id="P37"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" display="inline"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of keypoints,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P38"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the length-128 descriptor vector for the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>th keypoint,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P39"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the cluster to which keypoint <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> belongs,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P40"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the length-128 centroid of cluster <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P41"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the Euclidean distance between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and cluster center <inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list><p id="P42">We selected the optimal number of clusters by applying the elbow heuristic to WCCS scores and jointly examining the silhouette scores.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Principal components analysis</title><p id="P43">We used principal component analysis (PCA) to visualize the 128-length SIFT descriptors in a lower dimensional space. To do so, we ran PCA on the full <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> descriptor matrix with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>389</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>740</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with 30 principal components (PCs). Only the first two 2 PCs (PC1 and PC2) were used in the SIFT PCA embedding plots, although we studied latter PCs for additional correlations with relevant covariates without success.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Mixed effects linear models</title><p id="P44">We related several image-level summary statistics (cancer cell area, cancer cell spatial heterogeneity) to experimental conditions of the image (RASA2KO titration, E:T ratio, donor, technical replicate, time) using mixed effects linear models implemented in statsmodels<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Each model performed linear regression where one summary statistic was the response variable. Across models, <italic toggle="yes">RASA2KO titration</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E:T ratio</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">technical replicate</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">time</italic> were the fixed effect covariates, while <italic toggle="yes">donor</italic> was the random effect variable. Coefficients were estimated for each fixed effect variable, a <inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" display="inline"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-intercept term, and all possible combinations of 2-, 3-, and 4-variable interaction terms. <italic toggle="yes">Donor</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">technical replicates</italic> were treated as categorical variables while all other variables were continuous. Categorical variables were one-hot encoded. Since we only have two technical replicates, we showed the term for replicate ID of 1 in tables and figures while replicate ID of 0 was absorbed into the intercept term. We reported the coefficients and p-values for fixed effect estimates in these models, where the p-values represent the Wald test probability of accepting the null hypothesis that a true coefficient is equal to 0. All p-values from these tests were corrected with Benjamini-Hochberg false discovery rate (FDR) correction.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>SIFT cluster enrichment testing</title><p id="P45">When testing whether certain SIFT clusters were enriched or depleted for certain experimental conditions, we had to treat categorical experimental covariates differently from continuous ones.</p><p id="P46">The categorical covariates were <italic toggle="yes">donor</italic> ID and technical replicate ID. We iterated through each cluster ID (0, 1, &#x02026; , 6) and variable value (donor 0, donor 1, &#x02026; , replicate 1). For each unique combination of cluster ID and variable value, we created a 2 &#x000d7; 2 contingency table comparing that value&#x02019;s presence inside the cluster versus outside of it. The contingency tables were then used to perform <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c7;</italic>-squared tests and compute the log<sub>2</sub> odds ratios, yielding p-values and effect sizes, respectively.</p><p id="P47">The continuous covariates were <italic toggle="yes">time</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">RASA2KO titration</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E:T ratio</italic>. We iterated through each cluster ID and covariate type, performing a Kruskal-Wallis test to obtain a p-value and computing the Cohen&#x02019;s d (standardized mean difference) effect size. Cohen&#x02019;s d measures how much the mean covariate value differs between the points in a cluster and the points not in a cluster. Therefore, positive Cohen&#x02019;s d means that the cluster had more points at large values for that covariate (e.g., enriched in later time frames) or fewer points at low values for that covariate (e.g., depleted in earlier time frames).</p><p id="P48">We used the subsampled set of SIFT keypoints <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> when performing these statistical tests to limit the number of p-values that were smaller than the machine float precision of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;308</sup>. All p-values from these tests were corrected with Benjamini-Hochberg FDR correction.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Results</title><p id="P49">In this paper, we examine how segmentation-free analysis of live-cell imaging (LCI) data can be used to characterize cellular behavior in cancer and T cell co-culture assays. We focused on a dataset of co-cultured RASA2KO TCR T cells and A375 cancer cells<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. This dataset contains Incucyte images collected every two hours from wells that varied in their RASA2KO titration, effector to target (E:T) ratio, T cell donor, and technical replicate number (see <xref rid="S2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). We constructed a fully-observed image tensor (with no missing images) from this dataset of the following shape:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L6"><list-item><p id="P50">5 RASA2KO titrations (100%, 50%, 25%, 12.5%, 6.25%),</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P51">5 E:T ratios (2.83, 2.00, 1.41, 1.00, 0.71),</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P52">4 donors,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P53">2 technical replicates,</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P54">and 64 time frames.</p></list-item></list><p id="P55">Two channels&#x02014;phase and red&#x02014;were collected for each image as the A375 cancer cells expressed red fluorescent protein (RFP; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1a</xref>). The red channel was thresholded to create a binary cancer cell mask where individual pixels were labeled RFP positive (RFP+) or RFP negative (RFP-). Qualitative assessment of cancer cell masks across E:T ratio, RASA2KO titration, and time suggested that cancer cells divided more and survived longer at low E:T ratios and low RASA2KO titrations (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1b</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S1</xref>-<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>).</p><sec id="S13"><title>Spatial entropy distinguishes cancer cell aggregation patterns across experiments</title><p id="P56">The most commonly reported metric for T cell killing assays is total cancer cell area over time<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Indeed, we were able to distinguish the different experimental conditions when examining the number of RFP+ pixels in each image over time (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S4a</xref>,<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">b</xref>); however, solely looking at total cancer cell area did not provide insights into the spatial distribution of cancer cells, failing to suggest which cancer cells get killed by T cells or continue to proliferate. Moreover, images with identical RFP+ pixels may have wildly different spatial organizations of the cells.</p><p id="P57">We were interested in developing a metric to quantify different aggregation dynamics in live-cell imaging experiments. To do this, we first decided to calculate spatial entropy<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>, which measures how evenly cancer cells are dispersed across the well. High entropy represents uniform cellular distributions and low entropy represents uneven distributions in 2D space. We found that the spatial entropy across RASA2KO titration (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1c</xref>) and E:T ratio (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1d</xref>) showed distinctive time-indexed curves in which entropy decreased over time, indicating that cancer cells become more less uniformly distributed across the well as they evade T cell surveillance or become crippled through T cell interactions. These curves also revealed that wells with high E:T ratio or high RASA2KO titration underwent the largest decrease in spatial entropy over time. This result suggests that, while high E:T ratio and high RASA2KO titration led to the largest reduction in cancer cell area, certain areas of each well had more dramatic reduction of cancer cells than others.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Linear mixed model relates experimental conditions to spatial metrics</title><p id="P58">We next wanted to quantify the relative contribution of each experimental condition to the spatial metrics of cancer cell area and entropy. We fit two mixed-effects linear models, one that predicts <italic toggle="yes">area</italic> and one that predicts <italic toggle="yes">entropy</italic>, using covariates of <italic toggle="yes">RASA2KO titration</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E:T ratio</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">time</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">technical replicate ID</italic> (see <xref rid="S2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). When modeling cancer cell area, we observed area increased over time across all conditions (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>308</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S4c</xref>; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). While the terms for E:T ratio and RASA2KO were not significant on their own, the interaction terms with time revealed that cancer cell area increased faster at low RASA2KO titrations <inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>48</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and low E:T ratios <inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>255</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P59">When modeling spatial entropy, the linear mixed-effects model revealed that cancer cell entropy was lower at high RASA2KO titrations <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, high E:T ratios <inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>32</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and later time frames (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>8.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1c</xref>-<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">e</xref>; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The fact that the RASA2KO and E:T solo terms showed greater significance than their interaction terms with time (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively) suggests that these experimental T cell parameters influence spatial entropy across all frames &#x02013; not only in a time-dependent manner. Another significant term in the spatial entropy model was the three-way interaction term between RASA2KO, E:T, and time <inline-formula><mml:math id="M115" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>36</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, finding that cellular entropy was lowest when all three terms were high together. Together, these cancer cell mask statistics show that higher doses of RASA2KO T cells lead to less cancer cell growth and less uniform spatial configurations of cancer cells.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>SIFT feature detection and descriptor vectors from phase images</title><p id="P60">While computing spatial statistics on the RFP cell masks showed that high concentrations of RASA2KO T cells led to reduction in both cancer cell area and spatial entropy, these statistics failed to quantify the number of cancer cells that appear as singlets or in multi-cellular aggregates between different RASA2KO T cell concentrations. If cancer aggregates were larger and more frequent at high RASA2KO T cell concentrations, this would indicate that aggregates mostly consist of debris clumps or damaged cancer cells that migrate towards one another after sublethal cytotoxicity<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. Conversely, if cancer aggregates were smaller and less frequent at high RASA2KO T cell concentrations, it would indicate that they mostly consist of proliferating cancer cells that evade T cell surveillance.</p><p id="P61">Additionally, computing spatial statistics on cell masks can only be applied to cells that express a fluorescent reporter. In the context of the RASA2KO LCI dataset<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>, we cannot examine how T cells grow, move, and change shape over time since they are not fluorescently labeled. Being limited to analysis of fluorescent channels would be particularly problematic for next-generation co-culture experiments where the number of immune cell subtypes (e.g., monocytes, B cells, dendritic cells) exceeds the number of available fluorescent channels<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> or patient-derived cancer cells lack a fluorescent reporter<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. For analysis of the raw phase images, one could pass all images through an autoencoder<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> to create a low-dimensional embedding; however, each point in the resulting embedding would represent an entire image, and not each of the hundreds of cells within that image, preventing more granular, localized downstream analysis of cellular behavior (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S5</xref>). We therefore wished to explore analyses that could extract single- and multi-cell instances such as cancer cell singlets, cancer cell aggregates, and cancer-T cell interactions within individual phase images without using segmentation methods. Such analyses would allow us to tease apart the nuanced cellular interactions and aggregation dynamics that are unobservable from image-level statistics.</p><p id="P62">We chose to use the scale-invariant feature transform (SIFT) algorithm<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> to analyze the phase images. For each image in our dataset <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, SIFT extracts <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> keypoints per image and computes a length-128 descriptor vector that encodes image properties surrounding each keypoint (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a</xref>, left). We then subsample the number of keypoints and concatenate across all images, producing a SIFT descriptor matrix with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" display="inline"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (total number of descriptors) rows and 128 columns (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a</xref>, right; see <xref rid="S2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref> for full details). In our dataset, there were 2590 +/&#x02212; 1528 (mean +/&#x02212; stdev) keypoints per image (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2b</xref>). When cross-referencing the number of keypoints per image to the total cancer cell area obtained from the corresponding RFP mask, we found a positive correlation (Pearson <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.93</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>308</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), suggesting that the number of keypoints per image roughly approximates the cell count (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2c</xref>). The original SIFT descriptor matrix had <inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>35</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> million descriptors across <inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>13</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>446</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> images; however, for computational expediency, we only included 10% of each image&#x02019;s descriptors in the final SIFT descriptor matrix. The analyses proceeds identically when all of the keypoints are included.</p><p id="P63">We next wanted to cluster the SIFT descriptor matrix to group keypoints by their similarity to one another. We performed K-means clustering of the SIFT descriptor matrix, performing a parameter sweep over the number of clusters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> to find the optimal cluster size. For each clustering <inline-formula><mml:math id="M124" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, we examined the silhouette score, the sum of squared distances to cluster centers, and the cluster IDs annotated onto an embedding of the first two principal components (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2d</xref>,<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">e</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S6a</xref>-<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">h</xref>). Evaluating these three components led us to select <inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for downstream analysis (see <xref rid="S2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). The first two principal components cumulatively explained only 21% of the total variance in the SIFT descriptor matrix (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S6i</xref>-<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">n</xref>), indicating that the clusters capture additional complexity beyond what is shown in the PC1 versus PC2 SIFT embeddings.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>SIFT cluster characterization</title><p id="P64">We next define and give a label to the image properties that united keypoints within a SIFT cluster. We started by visually inspecting SIFT keypoint 30 &#x000d7; 30 pixel regions of interest (ROIs), both with and without RFP masks, and investigated 400 &#x000d7; 400 pixel ROIs containing dozens of keypoints per ROI (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2f</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S7</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S8</xref>). We made the following observations about each cluster from visual inspection:</p><list list-type="bullet" id="L7"><list-item><p id="P65">Clusters 2 and 3 were &#x0201c;edge&#x0201d; clusters as they were located near the polystyrene edges of each well;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P66">Clusters 5 and 6 were &#x0201c;aggregate&#x0201d; clusters with high cell density;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P67">Clusters 1 and 4 were &#x0201c;singlet&#x0201d; clusters as the ROIs were commonly centered around a single, often polar, cell rather than a group of cells;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P68">Cluster 0 was a mixture of &#x0201c;aggregates&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;singlets&#x0201d; with a subset of this cluster representing well-wide polystyrene reflections.</p></list-item></list><p id="P69">We next performed a series of analyses to quantitatively support these cluster definitions.</p><p id="P70">We first wished to quantitatively support our observation that keypoints in clusters 2, 3, and a subset of 0 captured properties of the polystyrene well rather than the cells inside. To support the observation that clusters 2 and 3 were truly at well edges, we computed the distance of each keypoint to the center of the well. We found that distance to the center of the well was substantially larger in edge effect clusters compared to all other clusters (independent t-test <inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>308</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M127" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>227.3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) with the standard deviation in distance being 3.8-fold smaller in edge clusters (stdev of 37 in edge clusters, 142 in other clusters; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3a</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S9a</xref>). To determine which keypoints represented well-wide polystyrene reflections, we examined the radius <inline-formula><mml:math id="M128" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of each keypoint. We found that 3.4% of all keypoints belonging to cluster 0 had an ROI radius &#x0003e; 250 pixels (72 / 2109) while the largest ROI radius outside of cluster 0 was 24 pixels, indicating that the well-wide polystyrene reflections were exclusive to a subset of cluster 0.</p><p id="P71">We next wished to more clearly define the singlet and aggregate clusters from one another. We hypothesized that aggregate clusters should have higher cancer cell density than singlet clusters. We therefore computed the fraction of RFP+ pixels within each keypoint&#x02019;s ROI and compared these values between clusters. We found that aggregate clusters 5 and 6 had a substantially higher fraction of RFP+ pixels than singlet clusters 1 and 4 (independent t-test <inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>308</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>38.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), confirming our qualitative observation that there is higher cancer cell density in aggregate keypoints compared to singlet keypoints (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3b</xref>; <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S9b</xref>).</p><p id="P72">We also compared the RFP+ fraction of ROIs within cluster types. Between the two singlet clusters, cluster 4 had a higher fraction of RFP+ pixels than cluster 1 (independent t-test <inline-formula><mml:math id="M131" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>105</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M132" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3b</xref>). Upon further exploration of keypoint ROIs, we believe this relationship reflects that cluster 1 has more T cell singlets than cluster 4 and that cluster 4 singlets contain neighboring cancer cells more often than cluster 1. Between the two aggregate clusters, cluster 6 had a substantially higher fraction of RFP+ pixels than cluster 5 (independent t-test <inline-formula><mml:math id="M133" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>69</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>17.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3b</xref>). This relationship suggests that cluster 6 aggregates have a higher cancer cell density than cluster 5. A summary of all cluster labels is shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Enrichment of SIFT clusters between experimental conditions</title><p id="P73">We identified clusters that were enriched for certain experimental conditions over others. Such statistical testing is critical for quantifying how experimental perturbations alter the abundance of different cellular states captured by our phase images. In this dataset, we tested for cluster enrichment against the experiment variables of technical replicate ID, donor ID, time, RASA2KO titration, and E:T ratio (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4a</xref>-<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">f</xref>). We treated time, RASA2KO titration, and E:T ratio as continuous variables while donor ID and technical replicate ID were treated as categorical for statistical testing (see <xref rid="S2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). After false-discovery correction, no cluster was enriched or depleted beyond <inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for a specific donor or technical replicate, indicating that phase images were largely similar across donors and technical replicates. However, there were nine cluster &#x000d7; covariate interactions across time, E:T ratio, and RASA2KO titration covariates showing substantial cluster enrichment (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4g</xref>,<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">h</xref>). A table of all p-values and effect sizes can be found in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File 1</xref>.</p><p id="P74">Looking into these enrichments more carefully, we found that edge effect clusters (2 and 3) were enriched at high E:T ratios and high RASA2KO titrations (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>216</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = 0.45 for cluster 2 &#x000d7; E:T; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M138" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>81</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = 0.28 for cluster 2 &#x000d7; RASA2KO; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>56</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = 0.29 for cluster 3 &#x000d7; E:T; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = 0.18 for cluster 3 &#x000d7; E:T), likely because there are few cells in the center of the well when T cells successfully limit cancer cell growth. Interestingly, both singlet clusters (1 and 4) were enriched at early time frames (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M141" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>230</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = &#x02212;0.49 for cluster 1 &#x000d7; time; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>57</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = &#x02212;0.19 for cluster 4 &#x000d7; time) but were not enriched for any RASA2KO titrations and E:T ratios. These results suggest that singlets disappear over time regardless of whether their absence is caused by 1) increased T cell killing of cancer cell singlets at high RASA2KO T cell concentrations, or 2) unconstrained cancer cell proliferation that turns singlets into aggregates at low RASA2KO T cell concentrations. Finally, we found that both aggregate cell clusters (5 and 6) were enriched at late time frames (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>223</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = 0.36 for cluster 5 &#x000d7; time; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M144" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>80</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = 0.21 for cluster 6 &#x000d7; time), depleted at high E:T ratios (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>19</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = &#x02212;0.09 for cluster 5 &#x000d7; E:T; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>135</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = &#x02212;0.25 for cluster 6 &#x000d7; E:T), and depleted at high RASA2KO titrations (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = &#x02212;0.09 for cluster 5 &#x000d7; RASA2KO; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>45</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d = &#x02212;0.16 for cluster 6 &#x000d7; RASA2KO). The depletion of aggregates in wells with high RASA2KO T cell concentrations shows that the presence of these modified T cells limits the absolute number of cancer cells in aggregates. Moreover, these findings suggest that the lower entropy at high RASA2KO T cell concentrations (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) were a consequence of anticancer T cell activity creating more empty space between cancer aggregates in the RFP masks rather than more cancer cells belonging to aggregates. A graphical summary of these findings and their relationship to underlying cellular dynamics is illustrated in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P75">Our segmentation-free live-cell behavioral analysis (SF-LCBA) framework enabled the characterization of cancer cell aggregation dynamics at varying RASA2KO TCR T cell concentrations in low-resolution LCI co-culture experiments. By applying spatial entropy to the RFP fluorescence channel, we captured spatial patterns of cancer cell proliferation and death that extend beyond total cancer cell burden. Additionally, by clustering scale-invariant feature transform (SIFT) keypoints derived from phase images, we identified recurring local cellular topologies such as well edges, cell singlets, and multi-cellular aggregates, and we associated their abundances with distinct experimental conditions. Together, these analyses revealed that cancer cell aggregation was most effectively disrupted in co-cultures with high RASA2KO TCR T cell titrations and high effector-to-target (E:T) ratios, corroborating the findings of earlier work<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and validating aggregation inhibition as a potentially valuable phenotypic marker of T cell therapeutic efficacy.</p><p id="P76">While the high E:T ratio and RASA2KO titration experimental conditions were faithfully stratified by RFP area alone in our dataset, the potential of SF-LCBA lies in the orthogonal information it offers. Whereas RFP area measures total cancer cell burden, spatial entropy and unsupervised enrichment testing of SIFT keypoints reflect the spatial organization of cancer cells and their morphological state&#x02013;particularly the degree of aggregation versus dispersion. In solid tumor contexts, where immune evasion is often mediated by the formation of dense tumor cell aggregates<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>, assessing the ability of T cell therapies to infiltrate and dismantle these evasive cancer cell aggregate structures is highly relevant. Our results suggest that SF-LCBA metrics may become a critical readout in future studies designed to differentiate T cell products that enhance elimination of cancer cell aggregates from those that merely clear cancer cell singlets more effectively.</p><p id="P77">This study has several important limitations. Chief among them is the relatively low spatial resolution of our LCI data (4.975 <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>m/pixel), which is near the lower limit for detecting individual T cells (typically 5&#x02013;10 <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>m in diameter<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>). As a result, most SIFT keypoints detected in singlet-rich images were centered on cancer cells (typically 10&#x02013;20 <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic>m in diameter<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>), with very few SIFT cluster singlet keypoints being centered on T cells. Additionally, low image resolution likely hindered our ability to identify mitotic cells as distinct keypoint clusters. We believe that applying SF-LCBA to images of &#x02265; 10x magnification would allow for more detailed description cancer and T cell morphologies, their patterns of co-localization, and, consequently, their phenotypic cell states. Other limitations stem from the SIFT algorithm itself. SIFT was originally designed for robust image registration by placing keypoints at high-contrast regions of the image. Consequently, many SIFT keypoints are located at the highest contrast regions of cells, most notably their edges, and therefore fails to capture multi-cellular interactions involving more than two cells. Future work where descriptor vectors, or analogous image embeddings, represent image patches spanning tens of microns could enable the detection of more complex spatial structures, such as immune infiltration gradients within aggregates. SIFT is also limited by only allowing for single-channel image inputs. While we passed phase images into SIFT in this study, future models could ingest multi-channel image data directly, enabling embeddings that better reflect local cell type composition and activity.</p><p id="P78">Despite these limitations, SF-LCBA opens up new opportunities for analyzing complex co-culture datasets in which traditional cell segmentation and tracking are infeasible. Our approach could be especially powerful in future experiments involving more complex microenvironments, including three or more interacting cell types. For example, adding dendritic cells or macrophages to T cell&#x02013;cancer cell co-cultures would better recapitulate the tumor microenvironment<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> and allow for perturbation studies across multiple immune cell types, but segmentation in these complex cell cultures is infeasible due to their high cell density and prevalence of multi-cellular interactions. Similarly, the segmentation-free nature of SF-LCBA means it could also be extended from adherent cell lines shown in this manuscript to cancer cell suspensions and patient-derived organoids, further broadening the translational potential<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Furthermore, incorporating additional fluorescent markers, such as cell viability stains, cell cycle reporters, or CD4/CD8 labels, would greatly enhance interpretability of keypoint clusters and support more nuanced phenotypic classifications<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. Notably, even sparse use of additional fluorescent channels would suffice, as SIFT embeddings are computed from the phase channel and require fluorescence data only for cluster annotation. Collectively, the methodological improvements presented in this paper move the field closer to an ideal unsupervised framework for behavioral phenotyping in complex, multicellular systems.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHPP2025.06.04.657687v1-supplement-1.pdf" id="d67e2923" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S20"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P80">The Marson laboratory has received research support from the Parker Institute for Cancer Immunotherapy, the Emerson Collective, Arc Institute, Sanofi, GlaxoSmithKline, and Gilead and reagents from Genscript and Illumina. L.E., A.W., and B.E.E. were funded in part by grants from the Parker Institute for Cancer Immunology (PICI), the Chan-Zuckerberg Institute (CZI), NIH NHGRI R01 HG012967, and NIH NHGRI R01 HG013736. B.E.E. is a CIFAR Fellow in the Multiscale Human Program.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN3"><p id="P81">Code availability</p><p id="P82">The SF-LCBA software package, along with accompanying code to reproduce the figures shown in this manuscript, is publicly available at <ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/bee-hive/sflcba" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/bee-hive/sflcba</ext-link>. Instructions for installation and usage can be found in the repository&#x02019;s README.md file.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN4"><p id="P83">Competing interests</p><p id="P84">A.M. is a cofounder of Site Tx, Arsenal Biosciences, and Survey Genomics, serves on the boards of directors at Site Tx, and Survey Genomics, is a member of the scientific advisory boards of Site Tx, Arsenal Biosciences, Cellanome, Spotlight Therapeutics, Survey Genomics, NewLimit, Amgen, and Tenaya, owns stock in Arsenal Biosciences, Site Tx, Cellanome, Spotlight Therapeutics, NewLimit, Survey Genomics, Tenaya and Lightcast and has received fees from Site Tx, Arsenal Biosciences, Cellanome, Spotlight Therapeutics, NewLimit, Abbvie, Gilead, 23andMe, PACT Pharma, Tenaya, Lightcast, Vertex, Merck, Amgen, GLG, ClearView Healthcare, and AlphaSights. A.M. is an investor in and informal advisor to Offline Ventures and a client of EPIQ. J.C. was supported by NIH/NCI K08, 11271K08CA252605&#x02013;01, a Burroughs Wellcome Fund Career Award for Medical Scientists, the Lydia Preisler Shorenstein Donor Advised Fund, and the Parker Institute for Cancer Immunotherapy, and the Pascarella Scholars Fund. B.E.E. is on the Scientific Advisory Board for Arrepath and Freenome.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S19"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P79">All processed data is contained in one AnnData object that has the SIFT descriptor matrix and all the associated keypoint-, image-, and well-level metadata (including spatial entropy statistics). This data object can be freely downloaded from Zenodo at the following DOI: <ext-link xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.15277488" ext-link-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15277488</ext-link>. Raw images will be uploaded to Bioimage Archive upon peer-reviewed publication.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neelapu</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Axicabtagene ciloleucel car t-cell therapy in refractory large b-cell lymphoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>377</volume>, <fpage>2531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2544</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1707447</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29226797</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Chimeric antigen receptor t cells in refractory b-cell lymphomas</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>377</volume>, <fpage>2545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2554</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1708566</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29226764</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sterner</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Sterner</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Car-t cell therapy: current limitations and potential strategies</article-title>. <source>Blood cancer journal</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33824268</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uslu</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>June</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Beyond the blood: expanding car t cell therapy to solid tumors</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-024-02446-2</pub-id> (<year>2025</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39533105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>D&#x02019;Angelo</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Afamitresgene autoleucel for advanced synovial sarcoma and myxoid round cell liposarcoma (spearhead-1): an international, open-label, phase 2 trial</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>
<volume>403</volume>, <fpage>1460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1471</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00319-2</pub-id> (<year>2024</year>). Doi: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00319-2" ext-link-type="uri">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00319-2</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barrangou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Doudna</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Applications of crispr technologies in research and beyond</article-title>. <source>Nat. biotechnology</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>933</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>941</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Crispr/cas9-mediated pd-1 disruption enhances anti-tumor efficacy of human chimeric antigen receptor t cells</article-title>. <source>Sci. Reports</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>737</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-00462-8</pub-id> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Targeting regnase-1 programs long-lived effector t cells for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>576</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>476</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1821-z</pub-id> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31827283</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stadtmauer</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Crispr-engineered t cells in patients with refractory cancer</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>367</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aba7365</pub-id> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>c-jun overexpression in car t cells induces exhaustion resistance</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>576</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1805-z</pub-id> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31802004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shifrut</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Genome-wide crispr screens in primary human t cells reveal key regulators of immune function</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>175</volume>, <fpage>1958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1971</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30449619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Genome-wide crispr screen identifies fam49b as a key regulator of actin dynamics and t cell activation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>E4051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e4060</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1801340115</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29632189</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Carnevale</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<part-title>RASA2 ablation in T cells boosts antigen sensitivity and long-term function</part-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>609</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-05126-w</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>). Number: 7925 Publisher: <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36002574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Belk</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Genome-wide crispr screens of t cell exhaustion identify chromatin remodeling factors that limit t cell persistence</article-title>. <source>Cancer cell</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35750052</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Systematic immunotherapy target discovery using genome-scale in vivo crispr screens in cd8 t cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>178</volume>, <fpage>1189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1204.e23</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.07.044</pub-id> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31442407</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>In vivo cd8(+) t cell crispr screening reveals control by fli1 in infection and cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>184</volume>, <fpage>1262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1280.e22</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.019</pub-id> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33636129</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Korell</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>In vivo crispr screens identify key modifiers of car t cell function in myeloma</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv 2024.11.19.624352</source>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.11.19.624352</pub-id> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Gradeci</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charras</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<part-title>Single-cell approaches to cell competition: high-throughput imaging, machine learning and simulations</part-title>. In <source>Seminars in cancer biology</source>, vol. <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage> (<publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31108201</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alieva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wezenaar</surname><given-names>A. K. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wehrens</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Bridging live-cell imaging and next-generation cancer treatment</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>745</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41568-023-00610-5</pub-id> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37704740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alieva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Behav3d: a 3d live imaging platform for comprehensive analysis of engineered t cell behavior and tumor response</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dekkers</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Uncovering the mode of action of engineered t cells in patient cancer organoids</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35879361</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Valen</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Deep learning automates the quantitative analysis of individual cells in live-cell imaging experiments</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1005177</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005177</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27814364</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Stardist image segmentation improves circulating tumor cell detection</article-title>. <source>Cancers</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>2916</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35740582</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michaelos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Pachitariu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cellpose: a generalist algorithm for cellular segmentation</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-020-01018-x</pub-id> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33318659</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pachitariu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cellpose 2.0: how to train your own model</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1634</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1641</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-022-01663-4</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36344832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weigert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broaddus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<source>Cell detection with star-convex polygons</source>. <conf-name>In Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention - MICCAI 2018 &#x02013; 21st International Conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Granada, Spain</conf-loc>, <conf-date>September 16&#x02013;20, 2018</conf-date>, Proceedings, Part II, <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>273</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-00934-2_30</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edlund</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Livecell&#x02014;a large-scale dataset for label-free live cell segmentation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1038</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1045</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-021-01249-6</pub-id> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34462594</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Freckmann</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Traject3d allows label-free identification of distinct co-occurring phenotypes within 3d culture by live imaging</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>5317</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32958-x</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36085324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Linking the genotypes and phenotypes of cancer cells in heterogenous populations via real-time optical tagging and image analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biomed. Eng.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>675</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41551-022-00853-x</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35301448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crainiciuc</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Behavioural immune landscapes of inflammation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>601</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-04263-y</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34987220</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Cellular behavior analysis from live-cell imaging of TCR T cell-cancer cell interactions</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv 2024-11</source> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><name><surname>Hayashida</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bise</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<source>Cell tracking with deep learning for cell detection and motion estimation in low-frame-rate</source>. In <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<etal/> (eds.) <conf-name>Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention &#x02013; MICCAI 2019 &#x02013; 22nd International Conference, Proceedings, Lecture Notes in Computer Science (including subseries Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics)</conf-name>, <fpage>397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>405</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-32239-7_44</pub-id> (<conf-loc>Springer Science and Business Media Deutschland GmbH, Germany</conf-loc>, <year>2019</year>). Publisher Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019, Springer Nature Switzerland AG.; 22nd International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention, MICCAI 2019 ; Conference date: 13-10-2019 Through 17-10-2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cuny</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ponti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>K&#x000fc;ndig</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rudolf</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Stelling</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cell region fingerprints enable highly precise single-cell tracking and lineage reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1285</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-022-01603-2</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36138173</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Guignard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<part-title>Mathematical and bioinformatic tools for cell tracking</part-title>. In <source>Cell Movement in Health and Disease</source>, <fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage> (<publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Caliban: Accurate cell tracking and lineage construction in live-cell imaging experiments with deep learning</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv</source>
<fpage>803205</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/803205</pub-id> (<year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gallusser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Weigert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<source>Trackastra: Transformer-based cell tracking for live-cell microscopy</source> (<year>2024</year>). 2405.15700.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Blennemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bachl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carnevale</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<part-title>Understanding TCR T cell knockout behavior using interpretable machine learning</part-title>. <source>In Biocomputing 2025: Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium</source>, <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage> (<publisher-name>World Scientific</publisher-name>, <year>2024</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bernascone</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Entropy measures of cellular aggregation</article-title>. <source>Phys. A: Stat. Mech. its Appl.</source>
<volume>388</volume>, <fpage>2762</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2770</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
<part-title>Object recognition from local scale-invariant features</part-title>. In <source>Proceedings of the Seventh IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision</source>, vol. <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1157</lpage> (<publisher-name>Ieee</publisher-name>, <year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van der Walt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>scikit-image: image processing in python</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>e453</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25024921</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Otero</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Anatomy of the SIFT Method</article-title>. <source>Ph.D. thesis, &#x000c9;cole normale sup&#x000e9;rieure de Cachan-ENS Cachan</source> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seabold</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Perktold</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>statsmodels: Econometric and statistical modeling with python</article-title>. <source>In 9th Python in Science Conference</source> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weigelin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Cytotoxic t cells are able to efficiently eliminate cancer cells by additive cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>5217</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25282-3</pub-id> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34471116</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Severin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Multiplexed high-throughput immune cell imaging reveals molecular health-associated phenotypes</article-title>. <source>Sci Adv</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>eabn5631</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abn5631</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36322666</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Cancercelltracker: a brightfield time-lapse microscopy framework for cancer drug sensitivity estimation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>4002</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4010</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btac417</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35751591</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Salakhutdinov</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Reducing the dimensionality of data with neural networks</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>313</volume>, <fpage>504</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>507</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1127647</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>). <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.science.org/doi/pdf/10.1126/science.1127647" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.science.org/doi/pdf/10.1126/science.1127647</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16873662</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Masci</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cire&#x0015f;an</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Schmidhuber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<part-title>Stacked convolutional auto-encoders for hierarchical feature extraction</part-title>. In <name><surname>Honkela</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girolami</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kaski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (eds.) <source>Artificial Neural Networks and Machine Learning &#x02013; ICANN</source>
<volume>2011</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage> (<publisher-name>Springer Berlin</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mellman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Turley</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The cancer-immunity cycle: Indication, genotype, and immunotype</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>2188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2205</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2023.09.011</pub-id> (<year>2023</year>). Doi: <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2023.09.011" ext-link-type="uri">10.1016/j.immuni.2023.09.011</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37820582</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zygourakis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Analysis of lymphocyte activation and proliferation by video microscopy and digital imaging</article-title>. <source>Cytometry</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cyto.990140710</pub-id> (<year>1993</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8243206</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shashni</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Size-based differentiation of cancer and normal cells by a particle size analyzer assisted by a cell-recognition pc software</article-title>. <source>Biol Pharm Bull</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.b17-00776</pub-id> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29332929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Analysis and modeling of cancer drug responses using cell cycle phase-specific rate effects</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>3450</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-39122-z</pub-id> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37301933</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Multiplexed and reproducible high content screening of live and fixed cells using dye drop</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>6918</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-34536-7</pub-id> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36376301</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Cancer cell area and spatial entropy are computed via RFP masks.</title><p id="P85"><bold>a)</bold> Overview of the Carnevale <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> imaging dataset that was analyzed in this paper. 5D tensor represents the experimental metadata associated with each image. Red and brightfiend (phase) channels were captured in each image. <bold>b)</bold> RFP+ masks over time at varying RASA2KO titrations and E:T ratios. Time increases from left to right columns. RASA2KO titrations and E:T ratios vary between rows. <bold>c-d)</bold> Spatial entropy of the cancer cell (RFP+) mask over time, stratified by <bold>c)</bold> RASA2KO titration and <bold>d)</bold> E:T ratios. Shaded areas represent 95% confidence intervals. <bold>e)</bold> Mixed linear model results for predicting RFP spatial entropy using the covariate values for RASA2KO titration, E:T ratio, time, and technical replicate. Technical replicate ID is modeled as a categorical variable while the other covariates are modeled as continuous variables. The model is conditioned on donor ID. The intercept term is excluded here but shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Boxes represent mean values of each coefficient and whiskers represent +/&#x02212; standard error. Interaction terms between multiple covariates are noted using colons in the x-tick labels. Adjusted P-values (Benjamini-Hochberg correction) are annotated above each term if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where the null hypothesis is that the term has no effect on entropy (coefficient=0).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.04.657687v1-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>SIFT extracts relevant keypoints and computes their corresponding descriptor vectors from phase images.</title><p id="P86"><bold>a)</bold> Schematic diagram for extracting matrix of SIFT descriptors from all phase images. Each image is passed through SIFT independently to obtain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptors for each image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" display="inline"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. We then concatenate the SIFT descriptor matrices across all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> images to obtain a final SIFT descriptor matrix of shape <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We commonly only use a subset of all rows in this SIFT descriptor matrix to speed up computational analysis. <bold>b)</bold> Histogram of the total number of SIFT keypoints extracted per image <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> prior to any subsampling. Distribution is shown for all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>13446</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> images analyzed. <bold>c)</bold> Relationship between total number of SIFT keypoints and the cancer cell RFP+ area of each image. Relationship is shown for all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>13446</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> images analyzed. The linear regression line of best fit is annotated with a dashed gray line alongside the Pearson correlation <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" display="inline"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> value. <bold>d)</bold> K-means clustering silhouette scores for different numbers of clusters K. K-means clustering was performed on all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>389</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>740</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptors but the Silhouette scores were computed on a <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> subset. <bold>e)</bold> Sum of squared distances from each point to its K-means cluster center for different number of clusters K. K-means clustering and the sum of squared distance calculation were both performed on all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>389</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>740</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptors. <bold>f)</bold> PCA embedding of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptors colored by their K-means cluster ID. PCA was run on all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>389</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>740</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptors prior to subsetting to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Two representative ROI phase images are shown for each cluster. The circle in each ROI represents the radius of each SIFT keypoint and the line represents its relative orientation. ROIs are annotated with the SIFT keypoint&#x02019;s xy-coordinate along with the associated image metadata.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.04.657687v1-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Image properties of the SIFT clusters.</title><p id="P87"><bold>a)</bold> Distance of SIFT keypoints from the center of the well and <bold>b)</bold> fraction of RFP+ pixels in keypoint ROIs, grouped by cluster ID and cluster group. Edges consist of cluster IDs 2 &#x00026; 3, singlets of cluster IDs 1 &#x00026; 4, and aggregates of cluster IDs 5 &#x00026; 6. All p-values represent independent t-tests. P-values within each cluster group compare its two cluster IDs against one another. Other p-values compare the edges group vs non-edges group in panel <bold>a</bold> and compare adjacent cluster groups to one another in panel <bold>b</bold>. Boxes represent the quartiles of the dataset while the whiskers extend up to 1.5x the interquartile range. Outlier points beyond the whiskers are drawn with small circles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.04.657687v1-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Enrichment of SIFT clusters between experimental conditions.</title><p id="P88"><bold>a-f)</bold> PCA embedding of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SIFT descriptors colored by <bold>a)</bold> K-means cluster ID, <bold>b)</bold> technical replicate ID, <bold>c)</bold> donor ID, <bold>d)</bold> time frame, <bold>e)</bold> RASA2KO titrations, and <bold>f)</bold> E:T ratios. <bold>g-h)</bold> Volcano plots testing for enrichment and depletion of covariate values within clusters. The y-axis is &#x02212;log<sub>10</sub> adjusted p-values and x-axis is effect size. Cluster &#x000d7; covariate value combinations are annotated with the color of the covariate and those with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are also annotated with the cluster ID and covariate value. Benjamini-Hochberg correction is applied to all p-values. <bold>g)</bold> A chi-squared test and log<sub>2</sub> odds ratio effect size are used for the covariates treated as categorical variables (donor ID and technical replicate ID). <bold>h)</bold> A Kruskal-Wallis test and Cohen&#x02019;s d effect size are used for continuous variables (E:T ratio, RASA2KO, and time). Positive Cohen&#x02019;s d for time means the cluster is enriched at late time points, high E:T ratios, or high RASA2KO titrations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.04.657687v1-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Graphical abstract of results.</title><p id="P89">Schematic diagram of cancer cell aggregation dynamics from early (left column) to late time frames (right column) at low RASA2KO T cell concentrations (top row) and high RASA2KO T cell concentrations (top row). Arrow annotations along the x-axis represent SIFT singlets decreasing over time and SIFT aggregates increasing over time at both RASA2KO T cell concentrations. Arrow annotations along the y-axis represent features comparisons between the two experimental conditions at late time frames.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.04.657687v1-f0005" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p id="P90">General linear model regression results for cancer cell mask total area. RASA2KO titration, E:T ratio, technical replicate, and time were the fixed effect variables while donor was the random effect variable. Donor and technical replicate are modeled as categorical variables and all others are continuous. Interaction terms are denoted with colons between each variable name. Adjusted p-values represent the Wald test probability of accepting the null hypothesis that a true coefficient is 0 after Benjamini-Hochberg FDR correction. All decimals are rounded to 3 digits.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MixedLM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent Variable:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFP area</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. Observations:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13446</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ML</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. Groups:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scale:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2609194480.4813</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min. group size:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3304</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log-Likelihood:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-164861.9334</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max. group size:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3400</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Converged:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean group size:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3361.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Term</th><th align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coef.</th><th align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std.Err.</th><th align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">z</th><th align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M18" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.025</th><th align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.975]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intercept</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22577.944</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11473.154</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.968</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.977</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45064.912</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9857.058</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6141.586</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.605</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21894.345</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2180.229</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.682</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.119</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.103</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;173.552</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.187</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.997</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.962</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.774</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22.163</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444.158</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;513.736</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2466.333</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.208</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5347.659</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4320.188</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4867.097</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3487.920</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.395</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1969.100</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11703.294</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.040</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.777</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.712</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;59.601</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.681</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;73.653</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.567</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.090</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;206.082</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.775</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7500.794</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.125</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.305</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264; 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;308</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7279.072</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7722.516</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;17.801</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159.983</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.111</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;331.361</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295.760</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32.328</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.190</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14.760</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;48</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36.621</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18.511</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.098</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.976</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24.582</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12.440</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET:time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2195.995</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.236</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34.186</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;255</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2321.896</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2070.095</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET:time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;253.394</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.843</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.789</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;431.444</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;75.344</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET:time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.791</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.244</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.459</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.353</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.229</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET:time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.223</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.759</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.674</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.775</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.671</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p id="P91">General linear model regression results for cancer cell mask spatial entropy. RASA2KO titration, E:T ratio, technical replicate, and time were the fixed effect variables while donor was the random effect variable. Donor and technical replicate are modeled as categorical variables and all others are continuous. Interaction terms are denoted with colons between each variable name. Adjusted p-values represent the Wald test probability of accepting the null hypothesis that a true coefficient is 0 after Benjamini-Hochberg FDR correction. All decimals are rounded to 3 digits.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MixedLM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent Variable:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFP entropy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. Observations:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13446</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ML</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. Groups:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scale:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0204</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min. group size:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3304</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log-Likelihood:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7062.6310</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max. group size:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3400</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Converged:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean group size:</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3361.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Term</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coef.</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std.Err.</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">z</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M19" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.025</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.975]</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intercept</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.564</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.553</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264; 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;308</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.502</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.626</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.007</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.415</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.041</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.256</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.082</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.948</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;32</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.096</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.069</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.005</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.508</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.024</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2:ET:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.497</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.002</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.457</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.978</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.838</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET:time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.170</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET:time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.810</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.002</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET:time</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12.846</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;36</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA2KO:ET:time:replicate</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.829</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="right" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Summary of SIFT clusters.</title><p id="P92">Cellular clusters can consist of either singlets (single cells) or aggregates (multiple cells). Edge effect clusters were located at the edges of each well and therefore were not centered on particular cells. Cancer cell abundace was determined based on fraction of RFP+ pixels in ROIs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIFT cluster ID</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group type</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer cell abundance</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">well reflections</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mixed</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mixed</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low-medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cancer-poor singlets</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">singlet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">edge 1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">edge effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">well</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">edge 2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">edge effect</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">well</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cancer-rich singlets</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">singlet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medium-high</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cancer-poor aggregates</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aggregate</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medium-high</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cancer-rich aggregates</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aggregate</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">high</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>