<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40316929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12048943</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-025-10916-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Data-driven machine learning algorithm model for pneumonia prediction and determinant factor stratification among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>Addisalem Workie</given-names></name><address><email>addisalemworkie599@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>Rediet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gezimu</surname><given-names>Wubishet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kitil</surname><given-names>Gemeda Wakgari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tizazu</surname><given-names>Michael Amera</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lambebo</surname><given-names>Abera</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bekele</surname><given-names>Firomsa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>Solomon Seyife</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jarso</surname><given-names>Mohammedamin Hajure</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>Geleta Nenko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wedajo</surname><given-names>Lema Fikadu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>Sanju</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalayou</surname><given-names>Mulugeta Hayelom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04e72vw61</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.464565.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0455 7818</institution-id><institution>Debre Berhan University, Asrat Woldeyes Health Science Campus, </institution><institution>Public Health Department, </institution></institution-wrap>Debre Berihan, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01gcmye25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 8496 1254</institution-id><institution>Mattu University, Health Science College, </institution></institution-wrap>Mettu, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Wallaga University, Health Science College, Nekemte, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04zte5g15</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466885.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 457X</institution-id><institution>Madda Walabu University, </institution><institution>Health Science College, Shashemene Campus, </institution></institution-wrap>Shashemene, Ethiopia </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Environmental/Ecological Studies and Sustainability, Akamai University, Kamuela, USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/000y2g343</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442884.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0451 6135</institution-id><institution>Women Researchers Council, Azerbaijan State University of Economics, </institution></institution-wrap>Baku, Azerbaijan </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01ktt8y73</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.467130.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0515 5212</institution-id><institution>Health Science Campus, Health Informatics Department, </institution><institution>Wollo University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wollo, Ethiopia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><elocation-id>647</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025, corrected publication 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">Pneumonia is the leading cause of child morbidity and mortality and accounts for 5.6 million under-five child deaths. Pneumonia has a significant impact on the quality of life, the country's economy, and the survival of children. Therefore, this study aimed to develop data-driven predictive model using machine learning algorithms to predict pneumonia and stratify the determinant factors among children aged 6&#x02013;23&#x000a0;months in Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">A total of 2035 samples of children were used from the 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey dataset. Jupyter Notebook from Anaconda Navigators was used for data management and analysis. Important libraries such as Pandas, Seaborn, and Numpy were imported from Python. The data was pre-processed into a training and testing dataset with a 4:1 ratio, and tenfold cross-validation was used to reduce bias and enhance the models&#x02019; performance. Six machine learning algorithms were used for model building and comparison, and confusion matrix elements were used to evaluate the performance of each algorithm. Principal component analysis and heatmap function were used for correlation detection between features. Feature importance score was used to identify and stratify the most important predictors of pneumonia.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">From 2035 total samples, 16.6%, 20.1%, and 24.2% of children had short rapid breath, fever, and cough respectively. The overall magnitude of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23&#x000a0;months was 31.3% based on the 2016 EDHS report. A random forest algorithm is the relatively best performance model to predict pneumonia and stratify its determinates with 91.3% accuracy. The health facility visits, child sex, initiation of breastfeeding, birth interval, birth weight, husbands&#x02019; education, women&#x02019;s age, and region, are the top eight important predictors of pneumonia among children with important scores of more than 5% to 20% respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Random forest is the best model to predict pneumonia and stratify its determinant factors. The implications of this study are profound for advanced research methodology, tailored to promote effective health interventions such as lifestyle modification and behavioral intervention, based on individuals&#x02019; unique features, specifically for stakeholders to take proactive childcare interventions. The study would serve as pioneering evidence for future research, and researchers are recommended to use deep learning algorithms to enhance prediction accuracy.
</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Data-driven</kwd><kwd>Prediction Model</kwd><kwd>Pneumonia</kwd><kwd>Children</kwd><kwd>Machine learning</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par15">Pneumonia is an infectious disease caused by viruses and bacteria that commonly affect the respiratory organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Though pneumonia can cause mild to severe illness in people of all ages, it is the most significant infectious disease and cause of death in children worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Globally, pneumonia is the leading cause of child death and accounts for 5.6 million under-five child deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The annual incidence of clinical pneumonia in under-five children is approximately 152 million globally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Approximately 156 million cases of pneumonia occurred among children, of which 151 million episodes of pneumonia are found in developing countries, and 1.2 million pneumonia cases last in death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Pneumonia combined with malaria, diarrhea, and HIV/ADIS cases accounted for 1 million child deaths around the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">In most developing countries, the mortality rates of children range from 60 to 100 per 1000 live births, and 20% of child deaths are caused by pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Nearly 172 under-five child deaths from a total of 1,000 live births occur in sub-Saharan African countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Pneumonia and its complications are very common in LMICs. For instance, a systematic review and meta-analysis of pneumonia among under-five children in East Africa is 34% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. A study from Nigeria states that 54.3% of children have pneumonia case and heart failure complication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Based on the national surveillance report of Uganda, the incidence of severe pneumonia is 108 per 100,000 children under five years in 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In Burkina Faso, 21% of children aged 12 months, and 15% of children aged 1&#x02013;4 years were confirmed for severe pneumonia from a total of 17% of pneumonia cases identified from a total of 2843 patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">In Ethiopia, pneumonia is a major risk factor for child morbidity and mortality. An estimated 3,370 children encounter pneumonia annually, and over 40,000 children's deaths are affected by pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. More than pneumonia infections and associated deaths, pneumonia has a significant clinical and economic burden, on the access and utilization of healthcare resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Pneumonia infection affects the life expectancy of the populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], and significantly lowers the quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Studies from different regions of Ethiopia show that the prevalence of pneumonia is 30% in the Gamo zone of the southern region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], 18.5% in Northwest Amhara region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], 18.1% of caprine pleuropneumonia case in Gambela region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and 285 children are admitted for severe pneumonia in the Tigray region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">Among the factors that affect pneumonia infectious and prevalence, nonexclusive breastfeeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], age of children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], vaccine inaccessibility and incompleteness, environmental conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], air pollution, food insecurity, undernutrition, and micronutrient deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] are significant risk factors for pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Parents&#x02019; educational status, wealth status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], place of residency, place of delivery, birth interval, birth order, age of children, and vaccination during and after pregnancy are also predictors for pneumonia infection among children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Following the World Health Organization's Integrated Management of Childhood Illness recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], Ethiopia introduced community-based pneumonia screening and treatment to control and minimize the risk of pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Moreover, child vaccinations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], nutritional supplementations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], environmental hygiene, and sanitation services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] are provided to reduce the risk of pneumonia.</p><p id="Par19">Regardless of the efforts made to reduce pneumonia infections, the problem and risks of pneumonia and its complications among children are increasing. For instance, a study shows that children less than 24 months have a higher frequency of complications associated with pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. This shows that pneumonia is a serious public health problem among young children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Even if many studies have been done about pneumonia and its associated factors, little is known and investigated about pneumonia case prediction, pneumonia development after respiratory tract infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], risk factors stratification, and pneumonia prediction using a large dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Additionally, the previous studies are affected by recall bias, have temporal relationships as data is not managed using advanced data management techniques such as machine learning techniques, and lack representativeness as data have been acquired from selected institutions or communities. Thus, the methods often fail to provide specific insights, which can lead to ineffective decision-making in healthcare settings, unable to capture hidden patterns and complex relationships between features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Moreover, the traditional analysis methods rely on assumptions, have a static nature in model building, and are not able to integrate diverse data sources, which potentially provides misleading results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Thus, employing machine learning algorithms to develop a predictive model for pneumonia and determinant factors stratification among children is crucial for understanding the prediction magnitude, and determinant factors of pneumonia.</p><p id="Par21">Recently, machine learning algorithms have been increasingly growing research methods to investigate large amounts of health data generated from various health institutions. The algorithms are important for generating and discovering insights from a large amount of dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The need for a data-driven machine learning algorithm model for pneumonia prediction and risk factor stratification among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months is critical due to the high prevalence of pneumonia in this vulnerable age group, which significantly contributes to child morbidity and mortality. The development of tailored algorithms that account for unique demographic, environmental, and healthcare factors is essential to effectively address the lack of specific insights in traditional analysis reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Leveraging machine learning can enhance accuracy for problem detection and provide intervention strategies, ultimately reducing the burden of pneumonia through timely and targeted healthcare resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">Moreover, this research can inform public health policies and improve health outcomes by identifying risk factors through guiding preventive measures and optimizing resource allocation in healthcare systems. The findings would provide evidence for policymakers and stakeholders to take interventions, and work on the predictive factors. Moreover, this research would serve as input and state-of-the-art evidence for further similar research initiatives. Therefore, this study aimed to develop a data-driven predictive model of pneumonia and determinant factors stratification among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Data source</title><p id="Par23">The dataset was accessed from the 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey (EDHS) survey report, available from the DHS program website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dhsprogram.com">https://dhsprogram.com</ext-link>). The Ethiopian Public Health Institute collected the survey data in collaboration with the Central Statistical Agency cross-sectionally.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study design and setting</title><p id="Par24">A cross-sectional study design is used for this study as long as the data is collected cross-sectionally by the Ethiopian Public Health Institute. The data was collected across nine regions and two city administrations of Ethiopia. Thus, this study used nationally representative data to study pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia. Ethiopia is located in the Horn of Africa, bordered by Eritrea in the north, Kenya in the south, Sudan in the west, and Djibouti in the east.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sampling techniques and procedures</title><p id="Par25">The sampling frame used for the 2016 EDHS is a frame of all Census Enumeration Areas (EAs) created for the 2016 Ethiopia Population and Housing Census and conducted by the Central Statistical Agency. A two-stage stratified cluster sampling technique was used. First, the regions were stratified into urban and rural areas. In the second stage, a household listing operation was used as a sampling frame for household selection. Finally, a fixed number of households were selected in each cluster, and samples of EAs were selected independently in each stratum.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Study populations</title><p id="Par26">All living children were the source population, and all sampled living children aged 6&#x02013;23 months were the study population. Children aged 6&#x02013;23 months are more likely vulnerable to pneumonia incidence and severity, and many vaccines are administered in this period to prevent pneumonia infection. Thus, children aged 6&#x02013;23 months are included in this study. Based on the set of measurement items of pneumonia and the data management process, the children aged 6&#x02013;23 months have more sufficient data as compared with children aged below 6 and above 23 months, to provide valid and generalizable reports. Thus, children under 6&#x000a0;months and above 23 months were excluded to maximize the validity and generalizability of the findings. Details about the methodology of the data source, sampling procedure, and source population were presented in the 2016 EDHS report from the Measure DHS website [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Study variables</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Dependent variable</title><p id="Par27">Pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Independent variables</title><p id="Par28">Socio-demographic characteristics such as region, residency, wealth status, educational status of mothers, husbands&#x02019; education, mothers&#x02019; age, sex, and age of children were used as sociodemographic characteristics of the study participants. Place of delivery, health facility visits, breastfeeding initiation, birth interval, birth order, ANC visit, working status, and media exposure was also an independent predictor used to develop a data-driven predictive model for pneumonia infection among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Operationalizations</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Pneumonia among children</title><p id="Par29">Pneumonia is a dependent variable in this study. The cough, fever, and short or rapid breaths among children are used as symptoms of pneumonia. Thus, children had pneumonia if the children had either one of the symptoms based on the verbal report of mothers two weeks before the survey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Birth interval</title><p id="Par30">The period between two successive live births is a birth interval. For this study, a birth interval of &#x0003c;&#x02009;33 months between two consecutive live births is a <italic>short birth interval</italic>, whereas a birth interval of 33 and above is an <italic>optimum birth interval</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>ANC visits</title><p id="Par31">These pregnant women who had visited health facilities for ANC services at most three times are considered inadequate. Otherwise, the women had adequate ANC visits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Media exposure</title><p id="Par32">If the mothers had access to either radio or television or both, then the mothers had media exposure; and if mothers did not have any means of media access, then the mothers had no media exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Breastfeeding initiation</title><p id="Par33">The baby has early breastfeeding initiation If the child was provided the mother's breast milk within 1&#x000a0;h after birth. Otherwise, late initiation of breastfeeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Data management and analysis</title><p id="Par34">The dataset was downloaded in STATA format, and the data cleaning and labeling were done. Jupyter Notebook in Anaconda Navigator was used for data management and model building. Important libraries such as Pandas, NumPy, and Seaborn were imported from Python software. Python packages such as matplotlib and sklearn were used to import important supervised machine-learning algorithms for data analysis and visualization. The missing values, outliers, noise, and duplication are very common in the dataset and were checked in the preprocessing stage of the machine learning concept [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The data types of each feature are converted to numeric data types for ease of outlier detection. Missing values, outliers&#x02019; detection, and duplication were detected using isnull(), the threshold Z score, and duplicated() function respectively. Accordingly, missing values were not detected in the original data set. The threshold Z score values were computed using the mean and variance of each feature. Thus, the Z score value for each feature ranges from 3 and &#x02212; 3, which indicates the absence of outliers in the dataset. Then all the features which have not any missing values, outliers, and duplications are retained for further correlation analysis and final feature selections.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Correlation detection and feature selection</title><p id="Par35">For data-driven predictive model development for pneumonia, the variable was checked for their dependency and correlation before the feature selection process to keep the loss of important variables twice. Managing and removing the correlated features in the dataset is important for the reduction of high dependency between features, and improve the model performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], and crucial to focus on the most informative features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In this study, a heatmap() function was built for correlation analysis by importing the seaborn library from Python. A variable that correlated with other variables was dropped from the dataset. The variables that insignificantly correlated were kept for the final important feature selection and prediction of pneumonia and to stratify the risk factors among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months using a more accurate algorithm. In the heatmap function, features with a correlation level between 0 and 0.5 are considered insignificantly correlated, while features with a correlation greater than 0.5 are deemed significantly correlated. Additionally, a principal component analysis (PCA) was used for the dimensionality reduction technique that can reveal relationships among variables by transforming them into a set of uncorrelated variables [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The PCA divides the dataset into different components and each component shows how many variations exist in the original dataset. The higher variance of a component indicates that the variables in a component are more likely represented and show the absence of significant redundancy or correlation in the dataset.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Methods for Feature Importance Score Measurement</title><p id="Par36">The feature importance score (FIS) is a technique used to evaluate and order the contribution of each feature in a model to determine their prediction power for pneumonia among children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. It helps to understand which features are most influential in making predictions, enabling better model interpretation, feature selection, and insights into the data. A Gini impurity is used to calculate FIS considering how much a feature impurity is reduced, and it explains the contribution of each feature to the prediction for individual instances. In the FIS measurement, variables that have relatively higher Gini Impurity scores are considered as the most important or first important feature, and the next important features are stratified based on their order of FIS values.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Data split and model selection</title><p id="Par37">The datasets were divided into training and testing datasets considering the K-fold cross-validation technique for bias reduction and model performance enhancement. K-fold cross-validation divides the dataset into nearly K-equal subsets or folds. The process partitions the dataset into K folds for the validation set, and the remaining K- 1 folds for training. The process iterated repeated K times until the validation set is ensured by either one of each fold. However, the choice of K is crucial, as smaller values can lead to high bias and larger values can increase computational cost. To control such problems, a maximum of tenfold cross-validation technique was considered. A total of 2035 records were included for model development and prediction of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months. To ensure the normalization of the data, sklearn.preprocessing packages were imported from Python, and the training and testing dataset was fitted using the MinMaxScaler() function.</p><p id="Par38">From the previous research reports, various machine learning algorithms such as Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes, logistic regression, multilayer perceptron, random forest, decision tree classifier, support vector machine, and K-nearest neighbor random forest are used for predictive model development for different health parameters among various study populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In this study, six machine-learning algorithms are considered, and details about each algorithm are stated as follows.</p><sec id="Sec20"><title>Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes</title><p id="Par39">Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes is a probabilistic classifier based on Bayes'theorem, which assumes independence among predictors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. It is widely used in data classification due to its simplicity and speed, making it suitable for large datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. However, its main limitation lies in the assumption of feature independence, which is often unrealistic in practice. Additionally, it can struggle with small datasets and issues related to zero probabilities.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Logistic Regression</title><p id="Par40">Logistic regression is a statistical method used to predict binary outcomes by modeling the probability that a given input belongs to a particular category [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. It is easy to implement and interpret, providing probabilities for class membership, which adds significant insight into the model's predictions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. However, logistic regression assumes a linear relationship between the features. This makes it less suitable for complex relationships, limiting its applicability in certain aspects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Random Forest</title><p id="Par41">Random Forest is an ensemble learning method that constructs multiple decision trees and merges them to enhance predictive accuracy. By reducing the risk of overfitting associated with individual trees, Random Forest is robust and can handle various data types effectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. It also accommodates missing values and provides insights into feature importance. However, it can be computationally intensive and slower than other models, especially with large datasets, and its complexity may make it less interpretable compared to single decision trees.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Decision Tree Classifier</title><p id="Par42">The Decision Tree Classifier is a model that makes decisions based on feature values by creating a tree-like structure of branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. This approach is straightforward to understand and interpret, requiring minimal data preprocessing, as it can handle both numerical and categorical data. However, decision trees are prone to overfitting, particularly when they become too complex. They are also sensitive to small variations in the training data, which can lead to significant changes in the resulting model structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Support Vector Machine</title><p id="Par43">Support Vector Machine is a powerful supervised learning model that finds the hyperplane that best separates classes in a high-dimensional space. It is particularly effective when there is a clear margin of separation between classes and is robust against overfitting in high-dimensional scenarios [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Despite its strengths, support vector machines can be less effective on very large datasets and require careful tuning of parameters, such as kernel choice, to achieve optimal performance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>K-Nearest Neighbor</title><p id="Par44">K-Nearest Neighbor is a non-parametric classification method that assigns a class to an instance based on the majority class among its k-nearest neighbors in the feature space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Its simplicity and intuitive nature make it easy to implement, and it does not require a training phase, as it merely stores the dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. However, the K-Nearest Neighbor is computationally expensive during prediction, as it calculates distances to all training samples. It is also sensitive to the choice of distance metric and the value of k, and its performance can degrade with high-dimensional data due to the curse of dimensionality.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Model building and evaluation</title><sec id="Sec27"><title>Model evaluation</title><p id="Par45">The confusion matrix model was used to determine the algorithm's performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The confusion matrix elements such as true positive, false positive, true negative, and false negative, and receiver operators&#x02019; curve (ROC) were also used for model evaluation based on sensitivity, and specificity relationships. The ROC is based on probability, the area under the ROC curve (AUC) is crucial to representing the degree or measure of separability, and it&#x02019;s important to differentiate the model&#x02019;s ability to predict the classes. Hence, the algorithm with higher AUC values shows the most accurate algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Moreover, the accuracy, precision, recall, and f1-measure were used to determine the machine learning algorithms'performance. Accuracy measures the overall correctness of the model to predict pneumonia cases by calculating the ratio of true results to the total instances of pneumonia. Precision is vital in pneumonia prediction because high precision means that the model is reliable in identifying actual pneumonia cases, and vital when false positives can lead to unnecessary treatments and healthcare costs. The model's ability to identify all pneumonia cases, reflects how well it captures true positives measured by the recall and is vital to detect missing pneumonia cases (false negative), specifically in medical diagnosis, and decline child morbidity due to pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. F1 Measure provides a balance between precision and recall, making it particularly useful in pneumonia prediction where both false positives and false negatives carry significant risks. It helps in understanding the balance between false positives and false negatives, ensuring a comprehensive evaluation of model performance for pneumonia prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. The mathematical relationship of the performance measurement indicators is described as follows:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par46">
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e719">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text{Accuracy}=\frac{TP+TN}{\text{FP}+\text{FN}+\text{TP}+\text{TN}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e725" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Accuracy</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>FN</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TN</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par47">
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e748">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text{Precision}=\frac{TP}{\text{TP}+\text{FP}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e754" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Precision</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>FP</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par48">
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e770">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text{Recall}=\frac{TP}{\text{TP}+\text{FN}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e776" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Recall</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>FN</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par49">
<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e792">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\text{F}1-\text{score}= 2* \frac{Precision*Recall}{\text{Precision}+\text{Recall}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="d33e798" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>score</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Precision</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Recall</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par50">The machine learning workflow for pneumonia prediction begins with data aquation and preprocessing, which includes cleaning the dataset, removing null values, and resampling. A random dataset is taken to create a training and testing dataset. The process involves cross-validation and hyperparameter tuning to optimize model performance. Various machine learning models are then employed, followed by performance evaluation. The final step produces predictions regarding pneumonia among children, confirming the presence or absence of pneumonia in each class. The overall methodology flow of the study is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The workflow of the entire machine methodology in this study</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Result</title><sec id="Sec29"><title>Descriptive result</title><sec id="Sec30"><title>Sociodemographic characteristics of the study participants</title><p id="Par51">A total of 2035 study participants were included for analysis. Nearly, three-tenth (31.0%) of children&#x02019;s mothers were under 25&#x02013;29 years. Nine hundred seventy-seven (48.0%), and seven out of ten (69.0%) of children&#x02019;s fathers and mothers had no formal education respectively. The majority (43.5) of the respondents were from the Oromia region, and 40.5% were Muslim religious followers. Nearly three-fourths (67.9%) and 44.6% of children&#x02019;s parents had no media exposure and were under poor wealth status respectively. The majority (90.2%) of household heads were male, and 73.5% of the respondents did not work during the survey (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics of the study participants, 2016 EDHS data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Category</th><th align="left">Frequency (n)</th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7">Age of mothers (year)</td><td align="left">15&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">20&#x02013;24</td><td align="left">323</td><td align="left">15.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">25&#x02013;29</td><td align="left">630</td><td align="left">31.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30&#x02013;34</td><td align="left">577</td><td align="left">28.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">35&#x02013;39</td><td align="left">334</td><td align="left">16.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">40&#x02013;44</td><td align="left">126</td><td align="left">6.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">45&#x02013;49</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Husbands&#x02019; educational status</td><td align="left">No education</td><td align="left">977</td><td align="left">48.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Primary</td><td align="left">858</td><td align="left">42.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Secondary</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">6.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Higher</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Mothers&#x02019; educational status</td><td align="left">No education</td><td align="left">1404</td><td align="left">69.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Primary</td><td align="left">551</td><td align="left">27.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Secondary</td><td align="left">53</td><td align="left">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Higher</td><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="11">Region</td><td align="left">Tigray</td><td align="left">149</td><td align="left">7.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Afar</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Amhara</td><td align="left">383</td><td align="left">18.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Oromia</td><td align="left">885</td><td align="left">43.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Somali</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Benishangul</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SNNPR</td><td align="left">449</td><td align="left">22.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gambela</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Harari</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Addis Adaba</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dire Dawa</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Media access and exposure</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1382</td><td align="left">67.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">654</td><td align="left">32.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Respondents currently working</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1496</td><td align="left">73.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">540</td><td align="left">26.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Wealth status</td><td align="left">Poor</td><td align="left">907</td><td align="left">44.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Middle</td><td align="left">464</td><td align="left">22.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rich</td><td align="left">664</td><td align="left">32.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Religion</td><td align="left">Orthodox</td><td align="left">681</td><td align="left">33.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Catholic</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Protestant</td><td align="left">460</td><td align="left">22.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Muslin</td><td align="left">824</td><td align="left">40.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Traditional and others</td><td align="left">44</td><td align="left">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Sex of household head</td><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">1835</td><td align="left">90.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">200</td><td align="left">9.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>The characteristics of children and mothers</title><p id="Par52">Most (90.4%) of children were found feeding breast during the interview period, and 77.7% initiated their breastfeeding within one hour after birth. 17.9% and 52.6% of children had short birth intervals and less than five birth orders. The majority (52.6%) of children were female, and 56.1% of the children had received tetanus injections more than once before birth. The majority of mothers gave birth at home (67.5%), had inadequate ANC visits (67.4%), had no health facility visits in the last 12 months (51.3%) before the survey, and never attended school in their life (69.0%) till the interview period (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the children and mothers, 2016 EDHS data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Category</th><th align="left">Frequency (n)</th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Currently breastfeeding</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">195</td><td align="left">9.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">1840</td><td align="left">90.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Initiation of breastfeeding</td><td align="left">Early</td><td align="left">1581</td><td align="left">77.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Late</td><td align="left">454</td><td align="left">22.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Preceding birth interval</td><td align="left">Short</td><td align="left">364</td><td align="left">17.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Optimal</td><td align="left">622</td><td align="left">30.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Larger</td><td align="left">1050</td><td align="left">51.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Birth order</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003c; 5</td><td align="left">1070</td><td align="left">52.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003e; =&#x02009;5</td><td align="left">965</td><td align="left">47.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Sex of children</td><td align="left">Male</td><td align="left">954</td><td align="left">46.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female</td><td align="left">1081</td><td align="left">53.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Number of tetanus injections before birth</td><td align="left">No injection</td><td align="left">894</td><td align="left">43.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">One and more injection</td><td align="left">1141</td><td align="left">56.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Place of delivery</td><td align="left">Home</td><td align="left">1374</td><td align="left">67.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Health facility</td><td align="left">662</td><td align="left">32.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Health facility visits in the last 12 months</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1044</td><td align="left">51.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">991</td><td align="left">48.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Respondents ever attended school</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">1404</td><td align="left">69.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">632</td><td align="left">31.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">ANC visits</td><td align="left">Inadequate</td><td align="left">1373</td><td align="left">67.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Adequate</td><td align="left">663</td><td align="left">32.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Magnitude of pneumonia, fever, cough, and short/rapid breath among children</title><p id="Par53">As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, 16.6%, 20.1%, and 24.2% of children aged 6&#x02013;23 months had short or rapid breath, fever, and cough respectively. The overall magnitude of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months is 31.3% (95% CI: 29.29%&#x02212; 33.32%) based on the 2016 EDHS data report.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Magnitude of pneumonia, fever, cough, and short/rapid breath among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia using the 2016 EDHS dataset</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Correlation matrix and dimensionality reduction</title><p id="Par54">The correlation function analysis indicates the presence of a significant correlation (90%) between birth order and women&#x02019;s age, and 80% between wealth index and media exposure in the given dataset. The yellow color indicates the correlation of each predictor with itself with the value of 100%. The dark and light blue colors show the relationship between each predictor with values ranging from 0 to 0.4 which indicates the absence of a significant correlation between the predictors (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Correlation detection within the dataset; Where BF =&#x02009;breast feeding, BI =&#x02009;Birth Interval, ANC =&#x02009;Antenatal care, BW =&#x02009;Birth weight</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par55">Moreover, the principal component analysis before the dimensionality reduction shows a 54% and 17% variance for Component 1 and Component 2 respectively. This means that principal component 1 is approximately 3.2 times more significant to explain the total variance in the original dataset than principal component 2. Additionally, 54% shows the need for dimensionality reduction in the dataset. After the dimensionality reduction, principal component 1 counted 64% power to explain the total variance, and underly the structure of the original dataset is 9 times well repressed by principal component 1 as compared with principal component 2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The principal component analysis before and after dimensionality reduction</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Data imbalance detection and management</title><p id="Par56">Data imbalance usually occurs in the dataset, showing unequal class representation. The data imbalance leads biased model that performs poorly on underrepresented classes. The data imbalance is detected through class distribution analysis using bar plot visualization. After the data imbalance is detected, a synthetic minority over-sampling technique (SMOTE) is used to generate synthetic samples for the minority class to ensure that the data is balanced between classes. Accordingly, a 21.9% synthetic sample was generated for the minority class (class 0), and a similar number of samples was reduced from the overfitted class (class 1) using SMOTE (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The data imbalance detection and management using SMOTE</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Data-driven model performance comparison</title><p id="Par57">The data-driven model developments were done considering six machine learning algorithms such as support vector machine, K-nearest neighbors, random forest, decision tree classifier, Gaussian Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes, and logistic regression algorithms. Based on predictive model development, a random forest algorithm had relatively high performance to predict pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;24 months compared to other data-driven machine learning algorithms, with an AUC value of 91.8%. Furthermore, the same line in the curve shows, that logistic regression and support vector machines demonstrate 70.3% of AUC to predict pneumonia in children 6 to 24 months of age. Whereas, the Gaussian Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes shows the lowest AUC value of 68%, a relatively low-performance algorithm to predict pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;24 months (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Data-driven model comparison of included machine learning algorithms</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec36"><title>Confusion matrix</title><p id="Par58">To evaluate the performance of the included machine learning algorithm; accuracy, precision, recall, F1-score, and the confusion matrix elements were used for the data-driven predictive models. Accordingly, the random forest algorithm stands out with relatively high accuracy (83.3%), high precision (87.3%), high recall (77.2%), and high F1 score (93.7%). Based on all performance measure metrics, the decision tree algorithm shows the second-best algorithm next to the random forest with 81.4% of accuracy, 84.3% of precision, 76.8% of recall, and 91.1% of F1 score. With an accuracy of 61.1%, precision of 64.3%, recall of 49.7%, and F1-score of 69.3%, the decision Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes algorithm demonstrates relatively the least performance algorithm. Its low recall indicates that the algorithm struggles to identify positive instances effectively, leading to more false negatives (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Machine learning algorithms&#x02019; model performance and comparisons with confusion matrix</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Algorithms</th><th align="left">Accuracy</th><th align="left">Precision</th><th align="left">Recall</th><th align="left">F1-score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Support vector machine</td><td char="." align="char">65.9%</td><td char="." align="char">68.2%</td><td align="left">58.3%</td><td char="." align="char">73.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gaussian Na&#x000ef;ve Bayes</td><td char="." align="char">61.1%</td><td char="." align="char">64.3%</td><td align="left">49.7%</td><td char="." align="char">69.3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Random forest</td><td char="." align="char">83.3%</td><td char="." align="char">87.3%</td><td align="left">77.2%</td><td char="." align="char">93.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">K-nearest neighbors</td><td char="." align="char">76.6%</td><td char="." align="char">85.2%</td><td align="left">62%</td><td char="." align="char">88.2%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Logistic regression</td><td char="." align="char">65.7%</td><td char="." align="char">67.9%</td><td align="left">58.3</td><td char="." align="char">73.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Decision tree classifier</td><td char="." align="char">81.4%</td><td char="." align="char">84.3%</td><td align="left">76.8%</td><td char="." align="char">91.1%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec37"><title>Determinant factor stratification for pneumonia among children</title><p id="Par59">A random forest algorithm was used to stratify determinants of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;12 months. Based on the algorithm&#x02019;s report, all the included predictors have their impact on pneumonia infection with FIS value range from 1.25% to 20%. Importantly, region, women&#x02019;s age, husbands&#x02019; education, birth weight, birth interval, initiation of breastfeeding, child six, and health facility visits were stratified as the top seven important predictors of pneumonia with an important score value of 5% to 20% (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Important feature stratification based on random forest algorithms</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec38"><title>Prediction of pneumonia</title><p id="Par60">The final step of the machine learning model is prediction of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months. Accordingly, the predicted value of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months is presented along with its actual value in the confusion matrix model. In the confusion matrix, the actual values for children with pneumonia and without pneumonia are represented by 1 (No) and 0 (Yes) compared to against predicted values. Of the total of 1007 children with pneumonia cases, 81.6% of children were correctly predicted as positive (True Positives), while 18.6% of children were incorrectly predicted as negative or not confirmed for pneumonia (False Negatives). Additionally, from a total of 1028 children without pneumonia cases, 70.1% of children were accurately predicted as negatives (True Negatives), and 29.9% of children without actual pneumonia cases were misclassified as positive or confirmed for pneumonia (False Positives). The classification report shows 81.4% and 70.1% precision for children with pneumonia and without pneumonia cases, indicating that the model is relatively reliable in predicting pneumonia cases. Recall values show that about 73% of actual children with pneumonia cases and, 79.3% of children without pneumonia cases were correctly identified. The F1 scores for both classes highlighted the presence of a good balance between precision and recall with nearly three-fourths (75%). Overall, the model shows 75.6% accuracy in the prediction of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months, suggesting a reasonably acceptable predictive model for pneumonia case prediction among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>The actual and predictive values of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia, using the 2019 EDHS dataset</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2025_10916_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec39"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par61">In this study, six machine learning algorithms were built and compared using various performance measurement indicators using a dataset accessed from the 2016 EDHS report. The various predictors such as sociodemographic, maternal, and child health characteristics were included for pneumonia prediction among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months. A total of 2035 observations were considered for predictive model development. The algorithms were built and compared using these input variables once the dataset was split into training and testing data sets. A K-fold cross-validation technique was applied to enhance the model performance and reduce predicting bias. The k-fold cross-validation method worked with computed average values for enhancing model performance and is vital to providing an optimized model specifically when there is a limited dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par62">Based on the dataset used for this study, a random forest has a relative high-performance score as compared with other algorithms with an AUC value of 91.8%. Additionally, the performance measurement metrics of the random forest algorithm have relatively higher scores than others&#x02019; algorithm performance metrics. The 83.3% of accuracy, 87.3% of precision, 77.2% of recall, and 93.7% of F1 measures of the random forest algorithm show a relatively good model to predict pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months. Thus, based on overall performance metrics the random forest algorithm is marked as a top-scoring algorithm for pneumonia prediction and risk factors stratification. The performance of the random forest in this study is consistent with previous machine learning studies such as the prediction of acute respiratory infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], prediction of childhood vaccination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], mental health prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], and prediction of under-five child death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Moreover, the accuracy and ROC value of the random forest algorithm in the current study are consistent with the accuracy and ROC values of a study done about the early detection of cardiovascular disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Moreover, the performance of the random forest algorithm in this study shows the relative performance as compared with the included algorithms rather than the general context of machine learning algorithms. This is because the performance of the algorithm might be affected by the data nature, sample size, and the characteristics of the predictive model.</p><p id="Par63">In this study, 31.3% of children aged 6&#x02013;23 months had pneumonia based on fever, cough, and rapid breath symptoms assessment reports. After data normalization and standardization have been done, a 3.2% discrepancy is observed from 31.3% to 28.15%. Additionally, after data imbalance between the classes is detected, a total of 50% of children aged 6&#x02013;23 months have been confirmed for pneumonia cases. This finding is consistent with studies conducted in various geographical areas such as Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The finding is higher than studies done in India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], and Nigeria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. This discrepancy might be due to the study subjects&#x02019; variation. The nationwide data might create significant variation in the magnitude of pneumonia as compared with single location data. Moreover, the measurement items including the case definition of pneumonia among children might be a reason for the discrepancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">In the optimized predictive model, from a total of 1007 children with pneumonia cases, which is approximately 49.48% of total children, 81.6% of children were correctly predicted as positive for pneumonia with a predictive accuracy of 75.6%. The figure of 81.6% represents the true magnitude of pneumonia among children and highlights a significant public health concern, particularly in LMICs, which underscores the urgent need for effective diagnostic strategies and timely interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. The pneumonia cases become increasing in magnitude which necessarily indicate the preparedness to tackle the problem effectively. The fact that nearly one-fifth of children may not be identified as having pneumonia emphasizes the importance of training healthcare providers to recognize symptoms accurately, investing in improved diagnostic tools, and raising community awareness about pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Addressing these issues is crucial to ensure that vulnerable populations receive the necessary care for ultimate child health outcome improvements in the region.</p><p id="Par65">Approximately 18.6% and 29.9% of children aged 6-23 months were incorrectly predicted as negative and positive for pneumonia. This shows that there is still room that needs improvement, particularly in reducing false negative and false positive pneumonia cases among children aged 6-23 months. The false negative prediction report may compromise the chance of children to get an effective treatment and medication. Whereas, the false positive also brings resource wastage in pneumonia case diagnosis and treatment, specifically in LMICs where medical resources and budgets are significantly inefficient. Minimizing this false negative and false positive prediction is crucial in pneumonia prediction among children aged 6-23 months using more robust and deep learning algorithms.</p><p id="Par66">From the determinant factors of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months, the region is identified and stratified as the most important or the first determinant factor for pneumonia cases with a 20% feature important score report. The geographical variation in health service access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], socioeconomic differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], seasonal variations, and population density in regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>] might be reasons that make region is the most determinant factor for pneumonia among children. Maternal age is a second important determinant factor for pneumonia among children with approximate important score values of 13%. This finding is congruent with primary studies conducted in Indonesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>], and Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. This might be due to the mothers&#x02019; different experiences in child health care, understanding and knowledge they have towards pneumonia and determinant factors, and socioeconomic challenges that can affect the child's immune system development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. Maternal age might also influence birth outcomes such as prematurity, and premature infants are at higher risk for respiratory infections and health complications, including pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Moreover, maternal age influences child health as mothers may face challenges like inadequate nutrition and lower health literacy, leading to increased vulnerability to pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Husbands&#x02019; education is a third important predictor for pneumonia among children with an important score value of 10%. The education level of fathers can significantly impact children's health outcomes, including the risk of pneumonia. Educated fathers can foster better health practices, improve the economy, and encourage proactive healthcare in reducing the risk of respiratory infections including pneumonia in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. The educative husbands reduce the likelihood of exclusive decision-making power in maternal and child health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">Childbirth weight is an important predictor of pneumonia among children with an approximated important score value of 9%. Similar to the previous findings, this study identified that birth weight is an important predictor of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Circuitously, it could be due to prematurity, a cause of low birth weight, which can predispose the child to respiratory problems due to lung immaturity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Likewise, it could be linked with malnutrition, which causes low birth weight and might lead to pneumonia due to compromised immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>].</p><p id="Par68">Birth interval is an important predictor for pneumonia among children with an approximated important score value of 7.7%. This is because birth intervals, specifically short birth and long birth intervals have negative effects on mothers&#x02019; and children&#x02019;s health in LMICs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. The biological, social, or environmental components might have effects on why birth interval could be a predictor for pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. For instance, high birth interval may lead children to a greater risk of pneumonia due to increased exposure to infections, reduced parental resources, and potential delays in healthcare access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. Breastfeeding initiation is an important predictor for pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months with an important score value of 7.5%. Evidence shows that lack of breastfeeding in the first six months of life is leading exposure to pneumonia in under-five children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. This finding is also consistent with the previous studies conducted in Bangladesh [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>], and Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. Timely breastfeeding is a critical determinant in reducing the risk of pneumonia in infants, provides essential nutrients, supports immune function, and minimizes exposure to harmful pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. Nonetheless, a study based on 2019 EDHS data reveals that many women experience delayed breastfeeding at the national level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>], and a systematic review report in Ethiopia reveals that breastfeeding initiation is below the World Health Organization's recommendation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>].</p><p id="Par69">The disparity in pneumonia infection by sex of children can be attributed to a combination of biological and social factors, including variations in immune response and differences in exposure to risk factors, which necessitate a comprehensive understanding of how gender influences health outcomes in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Moreover, research indicates that boys are generally more susceptible to pneumonia than girls, possibly due to inherent immunological differences that affect their vulnerability to infections; this pattern suggests the need for gender-sensitive approaches in health interventions targeted at preventing and managing pneumonia in pediatric populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>].</p><p id="Par70">Health facility visit within 12 months before the survey is an important predictor for pneumonia among children with an important score value of 7.53%. Within 24 h of birth, the maternal and child health complication is common in LMICs such as Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. Even though, health facilities are crucial to preventing, early diagnosis and treatment, and management of pneumonia through sharing information and receiving postnatal maternal and child health services receiving, many women might be challenged by finance and distance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>].</p><p id="Par71">The TT vaccine is administered during pregnancy to protect both the mother and the newborn from tetanus, a severe bacterial infection. While the TT vaccine does not directly prevent pneumonia, it plays a role in reducing the risk factors associated with the disease by improving neonatal health, enhancing maternal health, and promoting health-seeking behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">The relationship between media exposure and pneumonia infection among children is multifaceted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. Media serves as a powerful tool for disseminating information about pneumonia, its causes, symptoms, prevention, and treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. Public health campaigns that utilize mass media platforms; such as television, radio, social media, and print media; can effectively raise awareness about pneumonia and promote preventive measures like vaccination, breastfeeding, and proper hygiene practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. By strategically using media to educate the public, counter misinformation, and reach underserved populations, we can reduce the incidence and impact of pneumonia, ultimately improving health outcomes for all.</p><p id="Par73">Antenatal care serves as a vital opportunity to educate mothers, identify risk factors, and establish a foundation for ongoing care that can significantly reduce the risk of pneumonia in newborns and young children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. However, to maximize the benefits of antenatal visits in preventing pneumonia, it is essential to address barriers to access and ensure the quality of care provided [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>].</p><p id="Par74">The relationship between media exposure and pneumonia infection among children is multifaceted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. Media serves as a powerful tool for disseminating information about pneumonia, its causes, symptoms, prevention, and treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. Public health campaigns that utilize mass media platforms; such as television, radio, social media, and print media; can effectively raise awareness about pneumonia and promote preventive measures like vaccination, breastfeeding, and proper hygiene practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. By strategically using media to educate the public, counter misinformation, and reach underserved populations, we can reduce the incidence and impact of pneumonia, ultimately improving health outcomes for all.</p><p id="Par75">The place of delivery is a critical determinant of neonatal and infant health outcomes, including the risk of pneumonia. Deliveries in healthcare facilities are generally associated with better health outcomes due to higher quality care, better infection control, and access to essential newborn care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>]. In contrast, home deliveries, particularly in low-resource settings, can increase the risk of pneumonia due to factors such as poor sanitation, lack of skilled care, and increased exposure to indoor air pollution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Moreover, long-term hospitalization due to birth may also explore pneumonia infection and facilitate its severity among children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>]. Place of residency and child twin are also stratified as important predictors of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months with important score values of 2.5%, and 1% respectively.</p><p id="Par76">The place of residency is identified as a determinant factor of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months. Mothers&#x02019; and caregivers&#x02019; place of residency often challenges maternal and child health, which is a critical factor in limiting access to healthcare and providing inadequate living conditions, which increases children&#x02019;s vulnerability to respiratory infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. A study in Brazil shows that urban areas, characterized by high levels of air pollution, can exacerbate respiratory issues in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. Conversely, rural areas may lack adequate healthcare facilities, which can delay treatment and worsen health outcomes. Furthermore, overcrowded living conditions can facilitate the spread of infections, making children more susceptible to respiratory illnesses. Generally, residency is key determinant for healthcare service access and delivery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. study show that timely access to healthcare is essential for reducing pneumonia-related morbidity and mortality in young children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>].</p><p id="Par77">Being a twin is also a determinant factor of pneumonia in children. Twins often share a close living environment, which increases their exposure to etiologies, and pathogens, which can lead to a higher incidence of infections, including pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>]. Research has demonstrated that twins are at a greater risk of respiratory illnesses due to shared exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. Additionally, twins are more likely to experience nutritional deficiencies, particularly if born preterm or with low birth weight. These factors can compromise their immune systems, making them more susceptible to infections like pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>]. Moreover, the demands of caring for twins can lead to divided parental attention, which may result in less vigilant monitoring of a child's health. This lack of attention can delay the recognition and treatment of pneumonia symptoms and increase the risk of severe illness, like pneumonia among children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec40"><title>Conclusions and recommendations</title><p id="Par78">In this study, six machine learning algorithms were developed and compared for pneumonia prediction, determinant factors identification and stratification. Accordingly, the random forest algorithm was the most accurate algorithm for pneumonia prediction with an 91.8% of AUC value. The magnitude of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months was 31.3% and 28.1% before and after data normalization. According to the prediction model, pneumonia cases among children is become increasing, which indicate pneumonia is significant public health problem for young children. Based on an important feature selection for pneumonia among children, region, women&#x02019;s age,, husbands&#x02019; education, birth weight, birth interval, initiation of breastfeeding, child sex, and health facility visits were stratified as the top importance predictors of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months.</p><sec id="Sec41"><title>Strengths and limitation</title><p id="Par79">This study is important for generating insights for stakeholders to take clinical and public health problems specifically in pneumonia prevention and interventions. The data-driven predictive model prioritized key determinant factors of pneumonia among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months, which can support the timely lifestyle modification, and behavioral intervention, facilitate health service delivery and access for pneumonia case prevention. Moreover, the study is crucial for the advancement of research methodology, and add theoretical knowledge through learning in machine learning algorithms for healthcare practices and health data science. As a limitation, important variables of pneumonia might not be included in this study, and the strength of the relationship between variables might be limited based on the cross-sectional nature of the data. Moreover, the verbal reports of mothers of fever, cough, and rapid breaths among children might not confirm the presence of pneumonia. Methodologically, there is also high false negative of pneumonia case among children in the predictive model. Therefore, researchers are strongly recommended to advance the limitation the current study using more advanced deep learning algorithms to enhance the prediction accuracy and minimize false negative prediction probability of the algorithm.</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ANC</term><def><p id="Par5">Antenatal care</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AUC</term><def><p id="Par6">Area under ROC Curve</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DHS</term><def><p id="Par7">Demographic and Health Survey</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDHS</term><def><p id="Par8">Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDHS</term><def><p id="Par9">Ethiopia Demography and Health Survey</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LMICs</term><def><p id="Par10">Low- and middle-income countries</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNNPR</term><def><p id="Par11">South Nations and Nationality and Peoples of the region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TT</term><def><p id="Par12">Tetanus Toxoid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROC</term><def><p id="Par13">Receiver operative curve</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STATA</term><def><p id="Par14">Statistical software for data science</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p>The original online version of this article was revised: Following publication of the original article, we were notified of an error in Figure 8: the outcome variable was labelled as (where 1= yes, and 0=no), however the reverse was true.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>6/26/2025</p><p>A Correction to this paper has been published: 10.1186/s12879-025-11137-5</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to express our deepest appreciation to the Measure DHS program for permitting data access and use for this study.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Clinical trial number</title><p id="Par80">Not applicable.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors' contributions
</title><p>AWD was involved in study design, data management, data analysis, interpretation, and discussion of the findings. RA, WG, GWK, MAT, AL and MHK had significant role in drafting and editing the manuscript. FB, SSA, MHJ, GND, LFW, and SP had significantly contribution in the revision of the manuscript. All authors approved the final submission of the revised manuscript for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was received for this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability
</title><p>The dataset used for analysis is available on the Measure DHS program (http://dhsprogram.com) website. All the data generated, and analyzed are included in this article.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par81">Ethical approval and consent from study participants were not necessary for this study. This is because this study was based on a secondary data source that is publicly available from the Measure DHS program website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dhsprogram.com/Date/terms-of-use.cfm">https://dhsprogram.com/Date/terms-of-use.cfm</ext-link><underline>)</underline>.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par82">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests
</title><p id="Par83">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manohar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Secondary bacterial infections in patients with viral pneumonia</article-title><source>Front Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2020.00420</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Manohar P, et al. Secondary bacterial infections in patients with viral pneumonia. Front Med. 2020;7: 420.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pneumonia, symptom, and treatment: Accessed from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/pneumonia/#tab=tab_1">https://www.who.int/health-topics/pneumonia/#tab=tab_1</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lema</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and associated factors of pneumonia among under-five children at public hospitals in Jimma zone, South West of Ethiopia, 2018</article-title><source>J Pulmonol Clin Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Lema K, et al. Prevalence and associated factors of pneumonia among under-five children at public hospitals in Jimma zone, South West of Ethiopia, 2018. J Pulmonol Clin Res. 2018;2(1):25&#x02013;31.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasrin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with community acquired severe pneumonia among under five children in Dhaka, Bangladesh: A case control analysis</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e0265871</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0265871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35320317</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Nasrin S, et al. Factors associated with community acquired severe pneumonia among under five children in Dhaka, Bangladesh: A case control analysis. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(3): e0265871.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35320317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beletew</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of pneumonia and its associated factors among under-five children in East Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Pediatr</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900152</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Beletew B, et al. Prevalence of pneumonia and its associated factors among under-five children in East Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Pediatr. 2020;20:1&#x02013;13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31900152</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>CLF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global burden of childhood pneumonia and diarrhoea</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2013</year><volume>381</volume><issue>9875</issue><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60222-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23582727</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Walker CLF, et al. Global burden of childhood pneumonia and diarrhoea. Lancet. 2013;381(9875):1405&#x02013;16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23582727</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of pneumonia and its determinant factors among under-five children in Gamo Zone, southern Ethiopia, 2021</article-title><source>Front Pediatr</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1017386</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fped.2022.1017386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36619517</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Solomon Y, et al. Prevalence of pneumonia and its determinant factors among under-five children in Gamo Zone, southern Ethiopia, 2021. Front Pediatr. 2022;10: 1017386.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36619517</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odeyemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complications of pneumonia and its associated factors in a pediatric population in Osogbo, Nigeria</article-title><source>Nigerian J Paediatr</source><year>2020</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/njp.v47i4.4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Odeyemi A, et al. Complications of pneumonia and its associated factors in a pediatric population in Osogbo, Nigeria. Nigerian J Paediatr. 2020;47(4):318&#x02013;23.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wanyana</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with severe pneumonia among children&#x0003c; 5 years, Kasese District, Uganda: a case-control study, January&#x02013;April 2023</article-title><source>Pneumonia</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41479-024-00134-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39049136</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Wanyana MW, et al. Factors associated with severe pneumonia among children&#x0003c; 5 years, Kasese District, Uganda: a case-control study, January&#x02013;April 2023. Pneumonia. 2024;16(1):13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39049136</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence, seasonality, age distribution, and mortality of pneumococcal meningitis in Burkina Faso and Togo</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>48</volume><issue>Supplement_2</issue><fpage>S181</fpage><lpage>S189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/596498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19191614</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Traore Y, et al. Incidence, seasonality, age distribution, and mortality of pneumococcal meningitis in Burkina Faso and Togo. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;48(Supplement_2):S181&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19191614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deribew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessema</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Girma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of under-five mortality in Gilgel gibe field research center, Southwest Ethiopia</article-title><source>Ethiopian J Health Dev</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ejhd.v21i2.10038</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Deribew A, Tessema F, Girma B. Determinants of under-five mortality in Gilgel gibe field research center, Southwest Ethiopia. Ethiopian J Health Dev. 2007;21(2):117&#x02013;24.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isturiz</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and economic burden of pneumonia among adults in Latin America</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e852</fpage><lpage>e856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2010.02.2262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615741</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Isturiz RE, Luna CM, Ramirez J. Clinical and economic burden of pneumonia among adults in Latin America. Int J Infect Dis. 2010;14(10):e852&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615741</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acemoglu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disease and development: the effect of life expectancy on economic growth</article-title><source>J Polit Econ</source><year>2007</year><volume>115</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/529000</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Acemoglu D, Johnson S. Disease and development: the effect of life expectancy on economic growth. J Polit Econ. 2007;115(6):925&#x02013;85.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welte</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathwani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and economic burden of community-acquired pneumonia among adults in Europe</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2012</year><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2009.129502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20729232</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Welte T, Torres A, Nathwani D. Clinical and economic burden of community-acquired pneumonia among adults in Europe. Thorax. 2012;67(1):71&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20729232</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chekole</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and associated risk factors of pneumonia in under five years children using the data of the University of Gondar Referral Hospital</article-title><source>Cogent Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2029245</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/2331205X.2022.2029245</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Chekole DM, et al. Prevalence and associated risk factors of pneumonia in under five years children using the data of the University of Gondar Referral Hospital. Cogent Public Health. 2022;9(1): 2029245.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fasil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological study of contagious caprine pleuropneumonia (CCPP) in selected districts of Gambella Region, Western Ethiopia</article-title><source>Afr J Agric Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>2470</fpage><lpage>2479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJAR2014.9264</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Fasil A, et al. Epidemiological study of contagious caprine pleuropneumonia (CCPP) in selected districts of Gambella Region, Western Ethiopia. Afr J Agric Res. 2015;10(24):2470&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amare</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of recovery from severe pneumonia and its predictors among children 2&#x02013;59 months admitted to pediatric ward of Ayder Comprehensive Specialized Hospital, Tigray, Ethiopia: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>J Family Med Primary Care</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>5285</fpage><lpage>5292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_2006_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36505606</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Amare RA, et al. Incidence of recovery from severe pneumonia and its predictors among children 2&#x02013;59 months admitted to pediatric ward of Ayder Comprehensive Specialized Hospital, Tigray, Ethiopia: a retrospective cohort study. J Family Med Primary Care. 2022;11(9):5285&#x02013;92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36505606</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of pneumonia and factors associated among children 2&#x02013;59 months old in Wondo Genet district, Sidama zone, SNNPR, Ethiopia</article-title><source>Curr Pediatr Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Abuka T. Prevalence of pneumonia and factors associated among children 2&#x02013;59 months old in Wondo Genet district, Sidama zone, SNNPR, Ethiopia. Curr Pediatr Res. 2017;21(1):19&#x02013;25.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial and multilevel analysis of sanitation service access and related factors among households in Ethiopia: using 2019 Ethiopian national dataset</article-title><source>PLOS Global Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0001752</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0001752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37014843</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, et al. Spatial and multilevel analysis of sanitation service access and related factors among households in Ethiopia: using 2019 Ethiopian national dataset. PLOS Global Public Health. 2023;3(4): e0001752.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37014843</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanu</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Walle</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring spatial patterns, and identifying factors associated with insufficient cash or food received from a productive safety net program among eligible households in Ethiopia: a spatial and multilevel analysis as an input for international food aid programmers</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-16001-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37312083</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, Emanu MD, Walle AD. Exploring spatial patterns, and identifying factors associated with insufficient cash or food received from a productive safety net program among eligible households in Ethiopia: a spatial and multilevel analysis as an input for international food aid programmers. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):1141.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37312083</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roomaney</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of lower respiratory infection and pneumonia in South Africa (1997&#x02013;2015): a systematic review protocol</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e012154</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27633638</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Roomaney RA, et al. Epidemiology of lower respiratory infection and pneumonia in South Africa (1997&#x02013;2015): a systematic review protocol. BMJ Open. 2016;6(9): e012154.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27633638</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramezani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aemmi</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Emami Moghadam</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting the rate of pediatric pneumonia in developing countries: a review and literature study</article-title><source>Int J Pediatr</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><issue>6.2</issue><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1181</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Ramezani M, Aemmi SZ, Emami Moghadam Z. Factors affecting the rate of pediatric pneumonia in developing countries: a review and literature study. Int J Pediatr. 2015;3(6.2):1173&#x02013;81.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Budge S, Ambelu A, Bartram J, Brown J, Hutchings P. Environmental sanitation and the evolution of water, sanitation and hygiene. Bull World Health Organ. 2022;100(4):286&#x02013;8. 10.2471/BLT.21.287137. Epub 2022 Mar 3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prenatal and postnatal risk factors for infantile pneumonia in a representative birth cohort</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>2012</year><volume>140</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>1285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268811001890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21920066</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Chen C, et al. Prenatal and postnatal risk factors for infantile pneumonia in a representative birth cohort. Epidemiol Infect. 2012;140(7):1277&#x02013;85.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21920066</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aslam A, et al. The state of the world's children 2014 in numbers: every child counts. revealing disparities, advancing children's rights. ERIC; 2014. Accessed from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.unicef.org/media/89221/file/SOWC%202014.pdf">https://www.unicef.org/media/89221/file/SOWC%202014.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health system considerations for community-based implementation of automated respiratory counters to identify childhood pneumonia in 5 regions of Ethiopia: a qualitative study</article-title><source>Int J Health Policy Manag</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>7385</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38618793</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Rawat A, et al. Health system considerations for community-based implementation of automated respiratory counters to identify childhood pneumonia in 5 regions of Ethiopia: a qualitative study. Int J Health Policy Manag. 2023;12:7385.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38618793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vaccines to prevent pneumonia and improve child survival</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ</source><year>2008</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.07.044503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18545739</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Madhi SA, et al. Vaccines to prevent pneumonia and improve child survival. Bull World Health Organ. 2008;86:365&#x02013;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18545739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiguli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nutritional supplementation in children with severe pneumonia in Uganda and Kenya (COAST-Nutrition): a phase 2 randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Eclinicalmedicine</source><year>2024</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>102640</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2024.102640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38774673</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Kiguli S, et al. Nutritional supplementation in children with severe pneumonia in Uganda and Kenya (COAST-Nutrition): a phase 2 randomised controlled trial. Eclinicalmedicine. 2024;72:102640.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38774673</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enebeli</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Amadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iro</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Association between water, sanitation and hygiene practices and the occurrence of childhood pneumonia in Abia State, Nigeria</article-title><source>Int J Res Sci Innov</source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Enebeli U, Amadi A, Iro O. The Association between water, sanitation and hygiene practices and the occurrence of childhood pneumonia in Abia State, Nigeria. Int J Res Sci Innov. 2019;6:55&#x02013;60.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JAG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The definition of pneumonia, the assessment of severity, and clinical standardization in the Pneumonia Etiology Research for Child Health study</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>54</volume><issue>suppl_2</issue><fpage>S109</fpage><lpage>S116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cir1065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403224</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Scott JAG, et al. The definition of pneumonia, the assessment of severity, and clinical standardization in the Pneumonia Etiology Research for Child Health study. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;54(suppl_2):S109&#x02013;16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403224</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Douiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulliford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applying machine learning algorithms to electronic health records to predict pneumonia after respiratory tract infection</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2022.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35045315</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Sun X, Douiri A, Gulliford M. Applying machine learning algorithms to electronic health records to predict pneumonia after respiratory tract infection. J Clin Epidemiol. 2022;145:154&#x02013;63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35045315</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Swetha K, et al. Prediction of pneumonia using big data, deep learning and machine learning techniques. In: 2021 6th International Conference on Communication and Electronics Systems (ICCES). IEEE; 2021. 10.1109/ICCES51350.2021.9489188.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alowais</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Revolutionizing healthcare: the role of artificial intelligence in clinical practice</article-title><source>BMC Med Educ</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>689</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12909-023-04698-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37740191</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Alowais SA, et al. Revolutionizing healthcare: the role of artificial intelligence in clinical practice. BMC Med Educ. 2023;23(1):689.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37740191</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Demsash AW. Using best performance machine learning algorithm to predict child death before celebrating their fifth birthday. Inform Med Unlocked. 2023;40:101298.&#x000a0;10.1016/j.imu.2023.101298.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning algorithms&#x02019; application to predict childhood vaccination among children aged 12&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: Evidence 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey dataset</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e0288867</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0288867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37851705</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, et al. Machine learning algorithms&#x02019; application to predict childhood vaccination among children aged 12&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: Evidence 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey dataset. PLoS ONE. 2023;18(10): e0288867.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37851705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Challenges to implementing artificial intelligence in healthcare: a qualitative interview study with healthcare leaders in Sweden</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>850</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-022-08215-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35778736</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Petersson L, et al. Challenges to implementing artificial intelligence in healthcare: a qualitative interview study with healthcare leaders in Sweden. BMC Health Serv Res. 2022;22(1):850.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35778736</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baghdadi</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advanced machine learning techniques for cardiovascular disease early detection and diagnosis</article-title><source>J Big Data</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40537-023-00817-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Baghdadi NA, et al. Advanced machine learning techniques for cardiovascular disease early detection and diagnosis. J Big Data. 2023;10(1):144.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The 2016 Ethiopian demography and health survey. 2016. Accessed from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/FR328/FR328.pdf">https://www.dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/FR328/FR328.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Atoloye K, et al. A spatio-temporal mapping and bayesian modelling of risk factors of pneumonia symptoms in under-five children in Nigeria<italic>.</italic> medRxiv, 2022: p. 2022.12. 19.22283675.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakeyo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Short birth interval and its associated factors among multiparous women in Mieso agro-pastoralist district, Eastern Ethiopia: A community-based cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Front Glob Womens Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>801394</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgwh.2022.801394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36159883</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Wakeyo MM, et al. Short birth interval and its associated factors among multiparous women in Mieso agro-pastoralist district, Eastern Ethiopia: A community-based cross-sectional study. Front Glob Womens Health. 2022;3: 801394.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36159883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kassie</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution of short birth interval and associated factors among reproductive age women in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-023-05610-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36593447</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Kassie SY, et al. Spatial distribution of short birth interval and associated factors among reproductive age women in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2023;23(1):1&#x02013;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36593447</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution of vitamin A rich foods intake and associated factors among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey</article-title><source>BMC Nutr</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40795-022-00573-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34980278</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, et al. Spatial distribution of vitamin A rich foods intake and associated factors among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey. BMC Nutr. 2022;8(1):1&#x02013;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34980278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muhwava</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morojele</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>London</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychosocial factors associated with early initiation and frequency of antenatal care (ANC) visits in a rural and urban setting in South Africa: a cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-016-0807-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26728010</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Muhwava LS, Morojele N, London L. Psychosocial factors associated with early initiation and frequency of antenatal care (ANC) visits in a rural and urban setting in South Africa: a cross-sectional survey. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2016;16(1):1&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26728010</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution of vitamin A rich foods intake and associated factors among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey</article-title><source>BMC nutrition</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40795-022-00573-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35953835</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, et al. Spatial distribution of vitamin A rich foods intake and associated factors among children aged 6&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey. BMC nutrition. 2022;8(1):77.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35953835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kolluri J, et al. Reducing overfitting problem in machine learning using novel L1/4 regularization method. In: 2020 4th international conference on trends in electronics and informatics (ICOEI)(48184). IEEE; 2020. 10.1109/ICOEI48184.2020.9142992.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Khan NM, et al. Analysis on improving the performance of machine learning models using feature selection technique. In: Intelligent systems design and applications: 18th International Conference on Intelligent Systems Design and Applications (ISDA 2018) held in Vellore, India, December 6&#x02013;8, 2018, vol. 2. Springer; 2020. 10.1007/978-3-030-16660-1_7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feature selection based on mutual information with correlation coefficient</article-title><source>Appl Intell</source><year>2022</year><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>5457</fpage><lpage>5474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10489-021-02524-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Zhou H, Wang X, Zhu R. Feature selection based on mutual information with correlation coefficient. Appl Intell. 2022;52(5):5457&#x02013;74.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chumachenko T, Bazilevych K. Dimensionality reduction of chronic kidney disease data using principal component analysis. 2023.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Demsash AW. Using best performance machine learning algorithm to predict child death before celebrating their fifth birthday. Inform Med Unlocked. 2023:101298. 10.1016/j.imu.2023.101298.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning algorithms' application to predict childhood vaccination among children aged 12&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: Evidence 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey dataset</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e0288867</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0288867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37851705</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, et al. Machine learning algorithms&#x02019; application to predict childhood vaccination among children aged 12&#x02013;23 months in Ethiopia: Evidence 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey dataset. PLoS ONE. 2023;18(10): e0288867.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37851705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalayou</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassaw</surname><given-names>AAK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiferaw</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Empowering child health: Harnessing machine learning to predict acute respiratory infections in Ethiopian under-fives using demographic and health survey insights</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>338</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-09195-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38515014</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Kalayou MH, Kassaw AAK, Shiferaw KB. Empowering child health: Harnessing machine learning to predict acute respiratory infections in Ethiopian under-fives using demographic and health survey insights. BMC Infect Dis. 2024;24(1):338.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38515014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">G&#x000e9;ron A. Hands-on machine learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow. O'Reilly Media, Inc.; 2022. Accessed from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com.et/books?id=HHetDwAAQBAJ&#x00026;printsec=frontcover&#x00026;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&#x00026;cad=0#v=onepage&#x00026;q&#x00026;f=false">https://books.google.com.et/books?id=HHetDwAAQBAJ&#x00026;printsec=frontcover&#x00026;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&#x00026;cad=0#v=onepage&#x00026;q&#x00026;f=false</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual coordinate descent methods for logistic regression and maximum entropy models</article-title><source>Mach Learn</source><year>2011</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10994-010-5221-8</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Yu H-F, Huang F-L, Lin C-J. Dual coordinate descent methods for logistic regression and maximum entropy models. Mach Learn. 2011;85:41&#x02013;75.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">James G. An introduction to statistical learning. Springer; 2013. 10.1007/978-1-0716-1418-1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenta</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors of acute respiratory infection among under-five children across sub-Saharan African countries using machine learning approaches</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15801</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-65620-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38982206</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Fenta HM, et al. Factors of acute respiratory infection among under-five children across sub-Saharan African countries using machine learning approaches. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):15801.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38982206</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction to machine learning: k-nearest neighbors</article-title><source>Ann transl Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>218</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm.2016.03.37</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27386492</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Zhang Z. Introduction to machine learning: k-nearest neighbors. Ann transl Med. 2016;4(11):218.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27386492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narkhede</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding auc-roc curve</article-title><source>Towards Data Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>227</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Narkhede S. Understanding auc-roc curve. Towards Data Sci. 2018;26(1):220&#x02013;7.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Khouli</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship of temporal resolution to diagnostic performance for dynamic contrast enhanced MRI of the breast</article-title><source>J Magnetic Resonance Imaging</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmri.21947</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">El Khouli RH, et al. Relationship of temporal resolution to diagnostic performance for dynamic contrast enhanced MRI of the breast. J Magnetic Resonance Imaging. 2009;30(5):999&#x02013;1004.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Team A. Accuracy vs. precision vs. recall in machine learning: what's the difference? 2024. Accessed from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.evidentlyai.com/classification-metrics/accuracy-precision-recall">https://www.evidentlyai.com/classification-metrics/accuracy-precision-recall</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vakili M, Ghamsari M, Rezaei M. Performance analysis and comparison of machine and deep learning algorithms for IoT data classification. arXiv preprint arXiv:2001.09636, 2020. 10.48550/arXiv.2001.09636.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental health analysis of international students using machine learning techniques</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e0304132</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0304132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38843140</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Rahman MA, Kohli T. Mental health analysis of international students using machine learning techniques. PLoS ONE. 2024;19(6):e0304132.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38843140</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bitew</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning approach for predicting under-five mortality determinants in Ethiopia: evidence from the 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey</article-title><source>Genus</source><year>2020</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41118-020-00106-2</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Bitew FH, et al. Machine learning approach for predicting under-five mortality determinants in Ethiopia: evidence from the 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey. Genus. 2020;76:1&#x02013;16.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nirmolia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of pneumonia in under five children living in slums of Dibrugarh town</article-title><source>Clin Epidemiol Global Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cegh.2017.07.004</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Nirmolia N, et al. Prevalence and risk factors of pneumonia in under five children living in slums of Dibrugarh town. Clin Epidemiol Global Health. 2018;6(1):1&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mengstie</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of pneumonia and associated factors among children aged 6&#x02013;59 months in Angolela Tera district, North Shoa, Ethiopia, 2021, community-based cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Bull National Res Centre</source><year>2022</year><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>231</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42269-022-00921-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Mengstie LA. Prevalence of pneumonia and associated factors among children aged 6&#x02013;59 months in Angolela Tera district, North Shoa, Ethiopia, 2021, community-based cross-sectional study. Bull National Res Centre. 2022;46(1):231.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igweonu-Nwakile</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of Pneumonia and Its Determinants among Under-five Children attending a Primary Health Care Clinic in Amuwo Odofin Local Government Area, Lagos, Nigeria</article-title><source>J Community Med Primary Health Care</source><year>2023</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/jcmphc.v35i1.4</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Igweonu-Nwakile C, et al. Prevalence of Pneumonia and Its Determinants among Under-five Children attending a Primary Health Care Clinic in Amuwo Odofin Local Government Area, Lagos, Nigeria. J Community Med Primary Health Care. 2023;35(1):40&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chanie</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of community acquired childhood pneumonia among 2&#x02013;59 months old children in the Amhara Region, Ethiopia</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>179</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-021-01548-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34034726</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Chanie MG, et al. Predictors of community acquired childhood pneumonia among 2&#x02013;59 months old children in the Amhara Region, Ethiopia. BMC Pulm Med. 2021;21(1):179.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34034726</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low rates of treatment failure in children aged 2&#x02013;59 months treated for severe pneumonia: a multisite pooled analysis</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>56</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>978</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cis1201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23264361</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Fox MP, et al. Low rates of treatment failure in children aged 2&#x02013;59 months treated for severe pneumonia: a multisite pooled analysis. Clin Infect Dis. 2013;56(7):978&#x02013;87.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23264361</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Walle</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Women&#x02019;s health service access and associated factors in Ethiopia: application of geographical information system and multilevel analysis</article-title><source>BMJ Health Care Inform</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e100720</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjhci-2022-100720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37116949</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, Walle AD. Women&#x02019;s health service access and associated factors in Ethiopia: application of geographical information system and multilevel analysis. BMJ Health Care Inform. 2023;30(1):e100720.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37116949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Weather Variability, Socioeconomic Factors, and Pneumonia in Children Under Five-Years Old&#x02014;Bangladesh, 2012&#x02013;2016</article-title><source>China CDC Weekly</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>620</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46234/ccdcw2021.161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34594948</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Hossain MZ, et al. Weather Variability, Socioeconomic Factors, and Pneumonia in Children Under Five-Years Old&#x02014;Bangladesh, 2012&#x02013;2016. China CDC Weekly. 2021;3(29):620.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34594948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Annual and seasonal patterns in etiologies of pediatric community-acquired pneumonia due to respiratory viruses and Mycoplasma pneumoniae requiring hospitalization in South Korea</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-4810-9</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Lee E, et al. Annual and seasonal patterns in etiologies of pediatric community-acquired pneumonia due to respiratory viruses and Mycoplasma pneumoniae requiring hospitalization in South Korea. BMC Infect Dis. 2020;20:1&#x02013;10.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umar</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk Factor of Paediatric Community-Acquired Pneumonia in Wajo Regency, Indonesia</article-title><source>National J Commun Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55489/njcm.150220243601</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Umar KF, et al. Risk Factor of Paediatric Community-Acquired Pneumonia in Wajo Regency, Indonesia. National J Commun Med. 2024;15(02):98&#x02013;104.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazie</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Seid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Admassu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of community acquired pneumonia among 2 to 59 months of age children in Northeast Ethiopia: a case-control study</article-title><source>Pneumonia</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41479-020-00077-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31998604</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Bazie GW, Seid N, Admassu B. Determinants of community acquired pneumonia among 2 to 59 months of age children in Northeast Ethiopia: a case-control study. Pneumonia. 2020;12:1&#x02013;10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31998604</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Endale A, et al. Determinants of community-acquired pneumonia among 2-59 months old children attending health facility in Hossaena Town, Ethiopia. 2022.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aftab</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring health care seeking knowledge, perceptions and practices for childhood diarrhea and pneumonia and their context in a rural Pakistani community</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-018-2845-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29291745</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Aftab W, et al. Exploring health care seeking knowledge, perceptions and practices for childhood diarrhea and pneumonia and their context in a rural Pakistani community. BMC Health Serv Res. 2018;18:1&#x02013;10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29291745</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complications in infants hospitalized for bronchiolitis or respiratory syncytial virus pneumonia</article-title><source>J Pediatr</source><year>2003</year><volume>143</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/S0022-3476(03)00514-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="journal">Willson DF, et al. Complications in infants hospitalized for bronchiolitis or respiratory syncytial virus pneumonia. J Pediatr. 2003;143(5):142&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR76" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apisarnthanarak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ventilator-associated pneumonia in extremely preterm neonates in a neonatal intensive care unit: characteristics, risk factors, and outcomes</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2003</year><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>1289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.112.6.1283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654598</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76" publication-type="journal">Apisarnthanarak A, et al. Ventilator-associated pneumonia in extremely preterm neonates in a neonatal intensive care unit: characteristics, risk factors, and outcomes. Pediatrics. 2003;112(6):1283&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654598</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Buhr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parental health literacy and health knowledge, behaviours and outcomes in children: a cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31898494</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">de Buhr E, Tannen A. Parental health literacy and health knowledge, behaviours and outcomes in children: a cross-sectional survey. BMC Public Health. 2020;20:1&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31898494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajungu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with caretakers&#x02019; knowledge, attitude, and practices in the management of pneumonia for children aged five years and below in rural Uganda</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>700</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-023-09713-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37370154</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Kajungu D, et al. Factors associated with caretakers&#x02019; knowledge, attitude, and practices in the management of pneumonia for children aged five years and below in rural Uganda. BMC Health Serv Res. 2023;23(1):700.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37370154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR79" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakare</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Community and caregivers&#x02019; perceptions of pneumonia and care-seeking experiences in Nigeria: A qualitative study</article-title><source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source><year>2020</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>S104</fpage><lpage>S112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.24620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31985894</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79" publication-type="journal">Bakare AA, et al. Community and caregivers&#x02019; perceptions of pneumonia and care-seeking experiences in Nigeria: A qualitative study. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2020;55:S104&#x02013;12.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31985894</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR80" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadisuwarno</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Setyoningrum</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Umiastuti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host factors related to pneumonia in children under 5 years of age</article-title><source>Paediatr Indones</source><year>2015</year><volume>55</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14238/pi55.5.2015.248-51</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80" publication-type="journal">Hadisuwarno W, Setyoningrum RA, Umiastuti P. Host factors related to pneumonia in children under 5 years of age. Paediatr Indones. 2015;55(5):248&#x02013;51.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR81" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karmany</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahardjo</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Low Birth Weight on the Risk of Pneumonia in Children Under Five: Meta-Analysis</article-title><source>Int Confer Public Health Proceed</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>106</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81" publication-type="journal">Karmany PA, Rahardjo SS, Murti B. Effect of Low Birth Weight on the Risk of Pneumonia in Children Under Five: Meta-Analysis. Int Confer Public Health Proceed. 2020;5(1):106.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR82" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutriana</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitaresmi</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for childhood pneumonia: a case-control study in a high prevalence area in Indonesia</article-title><source>Clinical and experimental pediatrics</source><year>2021</year><volume>64</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>588</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3345/cep.2020.00339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33721928</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82" publication-type="journal">Sutriana VN, Sitaresmi MN, Wahab A. Risk factors for childhood pneumonia: a case-control study in a high prevalence area in Indonesia. Clinical and experimental pediatrics. 2021;64(11):588.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33721928</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR83" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fadl</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousry Muhammad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pneumonia among under-five children in Alexandria, Egypt: a case-control study</article-title><source>J Egypt Public Health Assoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42506-020-00043-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32813100</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83" publication-type="journal">Fadl N, Ashour A, Yousry Muhammad Y. Pneumonia among under-five children in Alexandria, Egypt: a case-control study. J Egypt Public Health Assoc. 2020;95:1&#x02013;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32813100</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR84" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiconco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and associated factors of pneumonia among under-fives with acute respiratory symptoms: a cross sectional study at a Teaching Hospital in Bushenyi District, Western Uganda</article-title><source>African Health Sciences</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1701</fpage><lpage>1710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ahs.v21i4.25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35283986</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84" publication-type="journal">Kiconco G, et al. Prevalence and associated factors of pneumonia among under-fives with acute respiratory symptoms: a cross sectional study at a Teaching Hospital in Bushenyi District, Western Uganda. African Health Sciences. 2021;21(4):1701&#x02013;10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35283986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR85" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kassie</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution of short birth interval and associated factors among reproductive age women in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>275</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-023-05610-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37087447</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85" publication-type="journal">Kassie SY, et al. Spatial distribution of short birth interval and associated factors among reproductive age women in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of 2019 Ethiopian mini demographic and health survey. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2023;23(1):275.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37087447</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR86" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkegren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Svaleryd</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Birth order and health disparities throughout the life course</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>115605</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.115605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36630815</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86" publication-type="journal">Bj&#x000f6;rkegren E, Svaleryd H. Birth order and health disparities throughout the life course. Soc Sci Med. 2023;318:115605.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36630815</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR87" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debere</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjiwanou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of reproductive variables on child mortality in Ethiopia: evidence from demographic and health surveys from 2000 to 2016</article-title><source>Reproductive Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12978-023-01734-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38200569</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR87" publication-type="journal">Debere HR, Adjiwanou V. The effects of reproductive variables on child mortality in Ethiopia: evidence from demographic and health surveys from 2000 to 2016. Reproductive Health. 2024;21(1):4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38200569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR88" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nurmala</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurniawan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between gravidity and low birth weight in Kendari City hospital</article-title><source>Indonesian J Contemp Multidiscip Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55927/modern.v2i3.4372</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR88" publication-type="journal">Nurmala I, Kurniawan F. Relationship between gravidity and low birth weight in Kendari City hospital. Indonesian J Contemp Multidiscip Res. 2023;2(3):445&#x02013;64.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR89" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geleta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessema</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewnetu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of community acquired pneumonia among children in Kersa District, Southwest Ethiopia: facility based case control study</article-title><source>J Pediatr Neonatal Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>00179</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR89" publication-type="journal">Geleta D, Tessema F, Ewnetu H. Determinants of community acquired pneumonia among children in Kersa District, Southwest Ethiopia: facility based case control study. J Pediatr Neonatal Care. 2016;5(2):00179.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR90" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dina</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Djuwita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of exclusive breastfeeding in reducing pneumonia prevalence in children under five</article-title><source>J Gizi Pangan</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR90" publication-type="journal">Dina RA, Djuwita R. The role of exclusive breastfeeding in reducing pneumonia prevalence in children under five. J Gizi Pangan. 2021;16(28):89&#x02013;98.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR91" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karmany</surname><given-names>PAW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahardjo</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of non-exclusive breastfeeding on the risk of pneumonia in children under five: Meta-analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Epidemiology and Public Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26911/jepublichealth.2020.05.04.01</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR91" publication-type="journal">Karmany PAW, Rahardjo SS, Murti B. The effects of non-exclusive breastfeeding on the risk of pneumonia in children under five: Meta-analysis. Journal of Epidemiology and Public Health. 2020;5(4):393&#x02013;401.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR92" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakib</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripon Rouf</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanny</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of early initiation of breastfeeding practices of newborns in bangladesh: evidence from bangladesh demographic and health survey</article-title><source>Nutrition and Metabolic Insights</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>11786388211054677</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/11786388211054677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34720590</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR92" publication-type="journal">Sakib MS, Ripon Rouf ASM, Tanny TF. Determinants of early initiation of breastfeeding practices of newborns in bangladesh: evidence from bangladesh demographic and health survey. Nutrition and Metabolic Insights. 2021;14:11786388211054676.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34720590</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR93" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gedefaw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berhe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinates of childhood pneumonia and diarrhea with special emphasis to exclusive breastfeeding in north Achefer district, northwest Ethiopia: a case control study</article-title><source>Open Journal of Epidemiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/ojepi.2015.52014</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR93" publication-type="journal">Gedefaw M, Berhe R. Determinates of childhood pneumonia and diarrhea with special emphasis to exclusive breastfeeding in north Achefer district, northwest Ethiopia: a case control study. Open Journal of Epidemiology. 2015;5(02):107&#x02013;12.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR94" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadate</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determinants of pneumonia among under-five children in Oromia region, Ethiopia: unmatched case-control study</article-title><source>Archives of Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>81</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>87</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13690-023-01103-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37165410</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR94" publication-type="journal">Yadate O, et al. Determinants of pneumonia among under-five children in Oromia region, Ethiopia: unmatched case-control study. Archives of Public Health. 2023;81(1):87.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37165410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR95" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitaw</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial variation and determinants of delayed breastfeeding initiation in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of recent evidence from EDHS 2019</article-title><source>Int Breastfeed J</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13006-024-00616-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38326812</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR95" publication-type="journal">Haile RN, Abate BB, Kitaw TA. Spatial variation and determinants of delayed breastfeeding initiation in Ethiopia: spatial and multilevel analysis of recent evidence from EDHS 2019. Int Breastfeed J. 2024;19(1):10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38326812</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR96" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Timely initiation of breastfeeding and its association with birth place in Ethiopia: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int Breastfeed J</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13006-017-0133-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070207</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR96" publication-type="journal">Alebel A, et al. Timely initiation of breastfeeding and its association with birth place in Ethiopia: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int Breastfeed J. 2017;12:1&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070207</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lembang ND, P.R. The Relationship between nutritional status and shortness of breath in children with pneumonia at Mappi General Hospital, Indonesia. Open Access Indonesian J Med Rev. 2023;3(4):437&#x02013;40. 10.1080/24694193.2019.1578435.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR98" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajaraman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Antani</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A deep modality-specific ensemble for improving pneumonia detection in chest x-rays</article-title><source>Diagnostics</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics12061442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35741252</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR98" publication-type="journal">Rajaraman S, Guo P, Xue Z, Antani SK. A deep modality-specific ensemble for improving pneumonia detection in chest x-rays. Diagnostics. 2022;12(6):1442.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35741252</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR99" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyu</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vongpradith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirota</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Novotney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Troeger</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Doxey</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledesma</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Biehl</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Frostad</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age&#x02013;sex differences in the global burden of lower respiratory infections and risk factors, 1990&#x02013;2019: results from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1626</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(22)00510-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35964613</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR99" publication-type="journal">Kyu HH, Vongpradith A, Sirota SB, Novotney A, Troeger CE, Doxey MC, Bender RG, Ledesma JR, Biehl MH, Albertson SB, Frostad JJ. Age&#x02013;sex differences in the global burden of lower respiratory infections and risk factors, 1990&#x02013;2019: results from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22(11):1626&#x02013;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35964613</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR100" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asmamaw</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early Postnatal Home Visit Coverage by Health Extension Workers and Associated Factors Among Postpartum Women in Gidan District, Northeast Ethiopia</article-title><source>Int J Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1605203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/ijph.2023.1605203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077510</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR100" publication-type="journal">Asmamaw DB, et al. Early Postnatal Home Visit Coverage by Health Extension Workers and Associated Factors Among Postpartum Women in Gidan District, Northeast Ethiopia. Int J Public Health. 2023;68: 1605203.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077510</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR101" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demsash</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Birth preparedness and pregnancy complication readiness and associated factors among pregnant women in Ethiopia: A multilevel analysis</article-title><source>PLOS Global Public Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e0003127</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38748714</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR101" publication-type="journal">Demsash AW, et al. Birth preparedness and pregnancy complication readiness and associated factors among pregnant women in Ethiopia: A multilevel analysis. PLOS Global Public Health. 2024;4(5): e0003127.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38748714</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR102" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for child pneumonia-focus on the Western Pacific Region</article-title><source>Paediatric respiratory reviews</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prrv.2016.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27515732</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR102" publication-type="journal">Nguyen TK, Tran TH, Roberts CL, Fox GJ, Graham SM, Marais BJ. Risk factors for child pneumonia-focus on the Western Pacific Region. Paediatric respiratory reviews. 2017;21:95&#x02013;101.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27515732</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ooko SA. Media framing of infectious diseases in Kenya: a case study of pneumonia (Doctoral dissertation, University of Nairobi). 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR104" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhingra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimizing care-seeking for childhood pneumonia: a public health perspective</article-title><source>Indian Pediatrics</source><year>2021</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13312-021-2368-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34837362</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR104" publication-type="journal">Kumar S, Mohanraj R, Dhingra B, Agarwal M, Suresh S. Optimizing care-seeking for childhood pneumonia: a public health perspective. Indian Pediatrics. 2021;58:1030&#x02013;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34837362</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR105" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziade</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jatuworapruk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Caballero-Uribe</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Khursheed</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Impact of Social Media on Vaccination: A Narrative Review</article-title><source>Journal of Korean Medical Science</source><year>2023</year><volume>38</volume><issue>40</issue><fpage>e326</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2023.38.e326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37846789</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR105" publication-type="journal">Rodrigues F, Ziade N, Jatuworapruk K, Caballero-Uribe CV, Khursheed T, Gupta L. The Impact of Social Media on Vaccination: A Narrative Review. Journal of Korean Medical Science. 2023;38(40):e326.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37846789</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR106" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naugle</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornik</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review of the effectiveness of mass media interventions for child survival in low-and middle-income countries</article-title><source>J Health Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><issue>sup1</issue><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10810730.2014.918217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25207453</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR106" publication-type="journal">Naugle DA, Hornik RC. Systematic review of the effectiveness of mass media interventions for child survival in low-and middle-income countries. J Health Commun. 2014;19(sup1):190&#x02013;215.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25207453</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR107" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiferaw</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengiste</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobena</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dheresa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of antenatal care on perinatal outcomes in Ethiopia: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0245003</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0245003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33444374</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR107" publication-type="journal">Shiferaw K, Mengiste B, Gobena T, Dheresa M. The effect of antenatal care on perinatal outcomes in Ethiopia: A systematic review and meta-analysis. PloS one. 2021;16(1):e0245003.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33444374</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR108" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassi</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Padhani</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabbani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rind</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhutta</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of dietary interventions during pregnancy on maternal, neonatal, and child outcomes in low-and middle-income countries</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>531</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu12020531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32092933</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR108" publication-type="journal">Lassi ZS, Padhani ZA, Rabbani A, Rind F, Salam RA, Das JK, Bhutta ZA. Impact of dietary interventions during pregnancy on maternal, neonatal, and child outcomes in low-and middle-income countries. Nutrients. 2020;12(2):531.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32092933</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR109" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennell</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrese</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keelan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies to prevent preterm birth</article-title><source>Frontiers in immunology</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>584</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2014.00584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25477878</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR109" publication-type="journal">Newnham JP, Dickinson JE, Hart RJ, Pennell CE, Arrese CA, Keelan JA. Strategies to prevent preterm birth. Frontiers in immunology. 2014;5:584.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25477878</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR110" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Workineh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gultie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of pneumonia among under two children in southern Ethiopia: A case control study 2016</article-title><source>Curr Pediatr Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR110" publication-type="journal">Workineh Y, Hailu D, Gultie T. Determinants of pneumonia among under two children in southern Ethiopia: A case control study 2016. Curr Pediatr Res. 2017;21(4):604&#x02013;12.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR111"><label>111.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR111" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Roux</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with serious outcomes of pneumonia among children in a birth cohort in South Africa</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e0255790</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0255790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34388194</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR111" publication-type="journal">Le Roux DM, et al. Factors associated with serious outcomes of pneumonia among children in a birth cohort in South Africa. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(8):e0255790.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34388194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR112"><label>112.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR112" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baseer</surname><given-names>KAA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd-Elmawgood</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors of respiratory diseases among neonates in neonatal intensive care unit of Qena University Hospital, Egypt</article-title><source>Annals of global health</source><year>2020</year><volume>86</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/aogh.2739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32140431</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR112" publication-type="journal">Baseer KAA, Mohamed M, Abd-Elmawgood EA. Risk factors of respiratory diseases among neonates in neonatal intensive care unit of Qena University Hospital, Egypt. Annals of global health. 2020;86(1):22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32140431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR113"><label>113.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR113" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Urban air pollutants are significant risk factors for asthma and pneumonia in children: the influence of location on the measurement of pollutants</article-title><source>Archivos de Bronconeumologia (English Edition)</source><year>2012</year><volume>48</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arbr.2012.08.002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR113" publication-type="journal">Vieira SE, et al. Urban air pollutants are significant risk factors for asthma and pneumonia in children: the influence of location on the measurement of pollutants. Archivos de Bronconeumologia (English Edition). 2012;48(11):389&#x02013;95.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR114"><label>114.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR114" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000e4;llander</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal access to pneumonia prevention and care: a call for action</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70248-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466341</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR114" publication-type="journal">K&#x000e4;llander K, Young M, Qazi S. Universal access to pneumonia prevention and care: a call for action. Lancet Respir Med. 2014;2(12):950&#x02013;2.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466341</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR115"><label>115.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR115" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wonodi</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of risk factors for severe pneumonia in children: the Pneumonia Etiology Research for Child Health study</article-title><source>Clinical infectious diseases</source><year>2012</year><volume>54</volume><issue>suppl_2</issue><fpage>S124</fpage><lpage>S131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cir1067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403226</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR115" publication-type="journal">Wonodi CB, et al. Evaluation of risk factors for severe pneumonia in children: the Pneumonia Etiology Research for Child Health study. Clinical infectious diseases. 2012;54(suppl_2):S124&#x02013;31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR116"><label>116.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Demsash AW, Asefa EY, Bekana T. Mothers&#x02019; experience of losing infants by death and its predictors in Ethiopia. PLoS ONE. 2024;19(6):e0303358. 10.1371/journal.pone.0303358.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR117"><label>117.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR117" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Derom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Follow-up of twins: health, behaviour, speech, language outcomes and implications for parents</article-title><source>Early Human Dev</source><year>2006</year><volume>82</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2006.03.007</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR117" publication-type="journal">Sutcliffe AG, Derom C. Follow-up of twins: health, behaviour, speech, language outcomes and implications for parents. Early Human Dev. 2006;82(6):379&#x02013;86.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>