<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40501997</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12157556</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.02.657541</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>aNy-way ICA and its application to estimate cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional links in schizophrenia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>KuaiKuai</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>Rogers F.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rahaman</surname><given-names>Md Abdur</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Zening</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jingyu</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kochunov</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Erp</surname><given-names>Theo G.M.</given-names></name><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="A7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shultz</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>Vince D.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Tri-Institutional Center for Translational Research in Neuroimaging and Data Science (TReNDS), Georgia State University, Georgia Institute of Technology, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Marcus Autism Center, Children&#x02019;s Healthcare of Atlanta, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Pediatrics, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, Georgia, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, The University of Texas Health Science Center Houston, TX, 77054, USA</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Clinical Translational Neuroscience Laboratory, Department of Psychiatry and Human Behavior, University of California Irvine, Irvine, California</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Center for the Neurobiology of Learning and Memory, University of California Irvine, 309 Qureshey Research Lab, Irvine, CA, 92697, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2025.06.02.657541</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to copy and distribute the material in any medium or format in unadapted form only, for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2025.06.02.657541.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P1">Multimodal data collected by international and national biobanking efforts have distinct scales and model orders and provide unique and complementary insights into disease mechanisms. We propose a novel, flexible and efficient data fusion approach&#x02014;aNy-way independent component analysis (aNy-way ICA). aNy-way ICA fuses N-way multimodal or multidomain data by optimizing the entire loading correlation structure of linked components via Gaussian independent vector analysis (IVA-G) and simultaneously optimizing independence via separate ICAs. This allows for distinct model orders for different modalities/domains and multiple linked sources detection across any number of modalities or domains without requiring orthogonality constraints on sources. Simulation results demonstrate that aNy-way ICA identifies the designed sources and loadings, as well as the true covariance patterns, with improved accuracy compared to other approaches, especially under noisy conditions. Applying aNy-way ICA to fuse 4D multi-domain fMRI data in schizophrenia, we identified a cortico-thalamo-cerebellar circuit, highlighting the functional linkages among higher order thalamic nuclei, the visual cortex, default mode network, and the posterior lobe of cerebellum. Their function links were replicated in two independent datasets. The connection among higher order thalamic nuclei, the visual cortex, and default mode network discriminates schizophrenia from controls and this aberrant connection is related to multiple cognitive deficits in both discovery and replication datasets, indicating the identified cortico-thalamo-cerebellar circuit may underlie "cognitive dysmetria" in schizophrenia.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Multimodal fusion</kwd><kwd>multidomain fusion</kwd><kwd>aNy-way ICA</kwd><kwd>schizophrenia</kwd><kwd>cortico-thalamo-cerebellar circuit</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Data fusion is an important analytical approach to perform integration of multiple data types collected from the same individuals&#x02014;such as imaging, genetics, and behavioral measures. The goal is to extract coherent and unique patterns or brain networks that may be missed when analyzing each data type or each brain network separately. By capturing shared and distinct patterns across modalities or brain networks, data fusion can enhance the sensitivity and specificity of biomarker discovery for complex brain disorders. Over the past decades, several data fusion approaches have been proposed to uncover latent components/sources that explain variation across datasets. These methods aim to identify either shared structures across modalities or both shared and modality-specific features. For instance, joint independent component analysis (jICA) (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Calhoun et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">Moosmann, Eichele, Nordby, Hugdahl, &#x00026; Calhoun, 2008</xref>), parallel multilink jICA (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">Khalilullah et al., 2023</xref>), and linked ICA (<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">Groves, Beckmann, Smith, &#x00026; Woolrich, 2011</xref>) have focused on identifying shared loadings across modalities. Multiset canonical correlation analysis (mCCA) maximizes correlation linkage across modalities directly but is limited to orthogonal features. Meanwhile, mCCA+jICA (<xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">Sui et al., 2011</xref>) proposed a mCCA preprocessing in order to improve the correspondence across modalities and more closely satisfy the assumption of shared identical loadings prior to jICA, enabling N-way multimodal fusion. While there is no theoretical limit to the number of modalities analyzed together by jICA, mCCA, or the two-step approach mCCA+jICA, these approaches are generally limited to extracting only shared features and require the same number of components from each modality.</p><p id="P3">Disjoint subspace analysis using ICA (DS-ICA) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Adali, Akhonda, &#x00026; Calhoun, 2019</xref>) and parallel ICA(pICA) (<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2009</xref>) were developed to capture both common and distinct structures from two modalities. DS-ICA applies jICA on the common subspace extracted with principal component analysis (PCA) and CCA (<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">Levin-Schwartz, Song, Schreier, Calhoun, &#x00026; Adali, 2016</xref>), and utilizes separate ICAs on the remaining (distinct) subspace. pICA proposes to integrate separate (parallel) ICAs, one per modality, with simultaneous maximization of correlation between specific multimodal loading pairs. Thus, both independence and linkage are optimized together rather than in two steps. However, pICA (and 3-way pICA) (<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">Vergara et al., 2014</xref>) is limited in the number of modalities and linked components it can robustly detect since it optimizes individual correlation pairs rather than the entire underlying linkage structure.</p><p id="P4">We proposed a new model called aNy-way ICA that overcomes these limitations (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Duan, Calhoun, Liu, &#x00026; Silva, 2020</xref>). aNy-way ICA optimizes the entire loadings correlation structure of linked components via Gaussian independent vector analysis (IVA-G) (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Adali, &#x00026; Li, 2012</xref>) and simultaneously optimizes independence via separate (parallel) ICAs. Therefore, aNy-way ICA can detect multiple linked sources over any number of modalities or domains without requiring orthogonality constraints on sources and permitting a different number of sources for different modalities/domains. Here, we expand it with comprehensive theoretical developments, detailed implementation and simulation procedures, and additional real human brain data analyses.</p><p id="P5">Parallel to the burgeoning interest in multimodal fusion, there is a growing focus on fusing multi brain network domain data, including regions such as the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortical areas (P. H. <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Chen, Ye, Jin, Zhu, &#x00026; Wang, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Collin et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Ferri et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). Traditional data-driven functional connectivity approaches, e.g., group independent component analysis (GICA) (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Calhoun, Adali, Pearlson, &#x00026; Pekar, 2001</xref>), often decompose whole-brain fMRI data into a single model order (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Calhoun &#x00026; Adali, 2012</xref>). However, this may not be optimal as different brain domains have different spatial organizations (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Bijsterbosch et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Diedrichsen, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr">Tzourio-Mazoyer et al., 2002</xref>) and subdivisions of specific domains (e.g., thalamus) have distinct connectivity with other domains (e.g., cortex and cerebellum) (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Giraldo-Chica &#x00026; Woodward, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Gong et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Ha et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>; M. Q. <xref rid="R77" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2021</xref>). Recent studies employing domain-wise brain decomposition have revealed crucial insights on brain functionalities and enhanced sensitivity in detecting subdomain networks potentially overlooked in whole-brain connectivity studies (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Dobromyslin et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Hwang, Bertolero, Liu, &#x00026; D'Esposito, 2017</xref>). Meanwhile, functional parcellations of specific regions or domains, such as the thalamus (<xref rid="R78" ref-type="bibr">S. Zhang &#x00026; Li, 2017</xref>) and cerebellum (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Dobromyslin et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Ren, Guo, &#x00026; Guo, 2019</xref>), have revealed informative details at higher spatial scales and revealed distinct connectivity with other domains/networks (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Giraldo-Chica &#x00026; Woodward, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Gong et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Ha et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="P6">Andreasen and colleagues suggests disrupted prefrontal-thalamic-cerebellar circuitry in schizophrenia (SZ) patients, leading to "cognitive dysmetria" characterized by difficulties in prioritizing, processing, coordinating, and responding to information (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Andreasen, Paradiso, &#x00026; O&#x02032;Leary, 1998</xref>). The thalamus serves as a passive relay station for integrating sensory information and is crucial for information processing between cortical regions (<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et al., 2017</xref>). Impairments in thalamus structure (<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">Pergola, Selvaggi, Trizio, Bertolino, &#x00026; Blasi, 2015</xref>) and thalamocortical connectivity (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Anticevic et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Avram, Brandl, Bauml, &#x00026; Sorg, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">P. H. Chen et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Gong et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">Sheffield et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr">Yao, Neggers, Kahn, &#x00026; Thakkar, 2020</xref>) have been extensively documented in SZ patients. The cerebellum, renowned for its diverse roles in motor learning, working memory, emotion, and language (<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2019</xref>), exhibits both anatomical and functional alterations in SZ (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Andreasen &#x00026; Pierson, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Ding et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">X. Li, Liu, Yang, Zhang, &#x00026; Lui, 2022</xref>). Aberrant thalamus-cerebellum connectivity (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Ha et al., 2023</xref>) and altered cerebro-cerebellar connections (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Collin et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">Kang, Chung, Lee, &#x00026; Bang, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>) have also been reported in SZ.</p><p id="P7">Studies to date have employed region of interest (ROI)-based approaches to explore finer-grained thalamocortical connectivity (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">P. H. Chen et al., 2019</xref>), cerebro-cerebellar connectivity (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Collin et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>), or cortico-thalamo-cerebellar connectivity in SZ (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Ha et al., 2023</xref>). These approaches primarily rely on anatomical definitions of ROIs without leveraging functional and connectivity information, and may miss relevant subregions crucial for the disease. To our knowledge, no study has investigated the links within the cortico-thalamo-cerebellar circuit using data-driven fusion approaches with variable model orders for each domain in SZ.</p><p id="P8">We used aNy-way ICA (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2020</xref>) to conduct domain-specific granular parcellation and optimize connections between subdivisions of different domains. By utilizing aNy-way ICA, we can perform targeted cortico-thalamo-cerebellar connectivity analysis while simultaneously optimizing inter-domain connections and separating sources within each domain. Unlike the traditional approaches mentioned above, which assume an identical number of components across all domains, aNy-way ICA allows for distinct model orders for each domain. This added flexibility makes it better suited to capture the complex and heterogeneous neurobiology of SZ. To evaluate its effectiveness, we first validate aNy-way ICA using simulated sMRI, fMRI, and EEG data under a range of scenarios, and compare its performance to widely used multimodal fusion approaches such as MCCA and MCCA +jICA. To examine its performance on multidomain fusion of 4-D human fMRI data, we apply aNy-way ICA to integrate data from the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortical regions extracted from resting-state fMRI data collected from 311 subjects (151 with SZ) within the Function Biomedical Informatics Research Network (FBIRN) cohort (<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Keator et al., 2016</xref>). In this application, we employ distinct model orders for each domain to identify cortico-thalamo-cerebellar subdomain linkages and evaluate their clinical relevance. We further validate these identified linkages in two independent replication datasets: one comprising 364 subjects from the Maryland Psychiatric Research Center (MPRC) cohort (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al., 2019</xref>) ), and the other comprising 148 individuals from the Center for Biomedical Research Excellence (COBRE) cohort (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Aine et al., 2017</xref>). Our results demonstrate that the identified cortico-thalamo-cerebellar subdomain linkages are consistently and largely replicated across both the COBRE and MPRC datasets. Moreover, we observe that the identified thalamus-cortex connection distinguishes SZ patients from controls and is associated with various cognitive scores in both the discovery and replication datasets.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Method and Materials</title><p id="P9">In this section, we first introduce the aNy-way ICA algorithm and its simulation design. We then describe the application of aNy-way to 4-D human brain multidomain (i.e., cortico-thalamo-cerebellar) fusion in SZ and the subsequent statistical analyses.</p><sec id="S3"><title>aNy-way ICA</title><p id="P10">aNy-way ICA (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2020</xref>) aims to simultaneously maximize the independence of sources while minimizing the mutual information between subspace component vectors (SCV). SCV represents correspondence across modalities in subsets of sources. As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig.1</xref>, without loss of generality, we consider three modalities: sMRI, fMRI, and EEG, each with 5, 4, and 6 sources, respectively. While the total number of sources <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is different per modality, at most <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> SCVs (maximum number of one-to-one correspondences across all modalities) can be extracted. For each modality, ICA decomposes the data <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (dimension: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> modality indices; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of subjects; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the feature dimensionality) into a source matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (dimension: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) with corresponding loading matrices <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (dimension: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P11">The source matrix is estimated by the product of a weight matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and data as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The loading matrix is then reconstructed as the product of data and pseudo-inverse of the source matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, a key strategy of this work. SCVs are then formed by the concatenation of linked loadings across the three modalities, where the total number of SCVs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the minimum component number among the three modalities. Assuming each SCV follows a multivariate Gaussian distribution, mutual information among SCVs is minimized utilizing IVA-G since that has been shown to correspond to mCCA&#x02019;s generalized variance (GENVAR) approach without orthogonality constraints (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Anderson et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p id="P12">The cost function of aNy-way ICA is thus defined as:
<disp-formula id="FD1">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math id="M21" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:msub><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of modalities, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the entropy of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (the same as infomax ICA cost (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Bell &#x00026; Sejnowski, 1995</xref>)), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a nonlinear transformation of the bias-adjusted source <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a bias), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the mutual information among SCVs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is a regularizer to balance between independence (ICA) and mutual information (IVA-G) optimization. The entropy of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Bell &#x00026; Sejnowski, 1995</xref>) and mutual information among SCVs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Anderson et al., 2012</xref>) are defined in <xref rid="FD2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equations 2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>, respectively:
<disp-formula id="FD2">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math id="M35" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD3">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math id="M36" display="block"><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the probability density function of the vector <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" display="inline"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-th SCV <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be formed as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is akin to a permutation matrix that selects the loadings from the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" display="inline"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-th component of each modality, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a concatenation of loadings from all modalities. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the joint entropy of all SCVs, which simplifies to a determinant function on the sources after noting the entropy of the data is constant. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the sum of the marginal entropy of all SCVs, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the marginal entropy of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" display="inline"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-th SCV (i.e., the concatenation of loading vectors of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" display="inline"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-th component across <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" display="inline"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> modalities). We assume each SCV forms a zero-mean (with covariance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) multivariate Gaussian distribution (IVA-G model) to leverage the second-order statistical information across modalities. Then <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be defined as:
<disp-formula id="FD4">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math id="M53" display="block"><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mo mathsize="big">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math>
</disp-formula></p><p id="P13">Plugging <xref rid="FD4" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 4</xref> into <xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 3</xref>, and combining it with <xref rid="FD2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 2</xref>, we can get the final form for aNy-way ICA cost. We then solve aNy-way ICA by SGD, utilizing the relative/natural gradients (<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">Pierre Comon, 2010</xref>) of <xref rid="FD2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equations 2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="FD3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref> with respect to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" display="inline"><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>, which are given, respectively, as:
<disp-formula id="FD5">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math id="M55" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02207;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD6">
<label>(6)</label>
<mml:math id="M56" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02207;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" display="inline"><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is an identity matrix, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" display="inline"><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula> is a column vector of ones, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" display="inline"><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is the matrix transpose, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mtext>=diag</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>std</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a diagonal matrix, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>std</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a vector with the standard deviations from each row of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is based on eigenvalue decomposition (EVD) of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>EVD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>&#x0039b;</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> being the sample covariance matrices from each modality <inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> has zero mean rows and columns). <inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is an intermediate gradient for the pseudo-inverse of the source matrix of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" display="inline"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-th modality, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Note that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> selects the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" display="inline"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-th column from the matrix to its left, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> expands the concatenation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> vectors from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (effectively inserting zero columns as needed). Finally, approximating the determinants in the SCV joint entropy term as the product of singular values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SVD</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (via SVD) and collecting constant terms into <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022a4;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, yields the final form in <xref rid="FD6" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 6</xref>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P14">Since the source/loading ordering from separate ICAs per modality would be arbitrary (not linked), it is important not to over-emphasize independence early during the optimization. We also observed improved loading linkage (SCV) and source alignment by initially optimizing only IVA-G for a few steps/epochs before optimizing aNy-way ICA. To provide an initial effective (moderately linked) starting point for aNy-way ICA optimization, we propose to initially optimize only IVA-G until IVA-G cost is stabilized (usually around 50 steps) and then use the weight matrix obtained from IVA-G to project/align the data, which is then employed as the input for aNy-way ICA. Moreover, the regularizer parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is initialized with 1 and adaptively adjusted by annealing it according to the entropy trend during the optimization: whenever entropy decreases with a slope larger than a threshold (here, 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>), this triggers <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" display="inline"><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> to be reduced by a factor (here, 0.8).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Simulation</title><p id="P15">Simulated sMRI, fMRI, and EEG data were employed to validate the proposed aNy-way ICA, where sMRI and fMRI sources were simulated with the SimTB toolbox (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">Erhardt, Allen, Wei, Eichele, &#x00026; Calhoun, 2012</xref>). For EEG sources, we used a subset of simulated independent Laplacian time series in (<xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">Silva, Plis, Adali, Pattichis, &#x00026; Calhoun, 2021</xref>), which had an autocorrelation around 0.85 between timepoint <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" display="inline"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and 0.2 between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" display="inline"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Each SCV was sampled from a zero mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" display="inline"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-dimensional multivariate Gaussian distribution with unique covariance structures, where the correlations granularly varied from 0.2 to 0.8 to mimic correlations observed in real human brain data. SCVs were then organized into loading matrices <inline-formula><mml:math id="M89" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. If applicable, extra loadings for non-linked sources were sampled from a standard Normal distribution and padded to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Finally, the data was generated as the product of the loading and source matrices as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The following scenarios were then examined:</p><sec id="S5"><title>Scenario 1:</title><p id="P16">All 3 modalities had the same number of sources <inline-formula><mml:math id="M92" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The number of subjects was fixed at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>500</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Feature dimensions <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for sMRI, fMRI and EEG data were 31064 (voxels), 17420 (voxels), 4444 (time points), respectively (same <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was used for scenario 2). Comparisons were performed against both mCCA and mCCA+jICA.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Scenario 2:</title><p id="P17">sMRI, fMRI, and EEG data had a different number of sources. In part (a), we assessed the effect of varying the number of linked SCVs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>9</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> while keeping <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>500</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> fixed. The number of sources <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for sMRI, fMRI and EEG data were set as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively, except for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In part (b), the number of sources <inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for sMRI, fMRI and EEG data were fixed at 8, 7, 9, respectively, while the subject number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> varied from 100 to 1000. For each subject number, 10 sets of SCV/loadings were generated and run for each modality. Finally, in part (c), we assessed the effect of additive Gaussian white noise with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> fixed at 8, 7, 9 for sMRI, fMRI, and EEG, respectively, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> fixed at 500. SNR varied from 0db to 30dB with a step size of 5dB. For each SNR level, the noise samples <inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were generated 5 times, yielding noisy data <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for modality <inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" display="inline"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Note: scenarios 1, 2(a), and 2(b) were noise-free.</p><p id="P18">The following component-wise performance measures were computed per modality for aNy-way ICA, mCCA, and mCCA+jICA: correlations between recovered <italic toggle="yes">sources</italic> and ground-truth, as well as correlations between recovered <italic toggle="yes">loadings</italic> and ground-truth. To examine SCV recovery, we also calculated the mean square error (MSE) value between the recovered and ground-truth SCV cross-correlations (linkages), considering the diagonal blocks and off-diagonal portions separately, as well as together (whole matrix). For mCCA and mCCA+jICA, we estimated components under both settings when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:munder><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:munder><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for all modalities (two separate runs). For scenario 2(a), correlations were averaged across matched components per modality, while for scenarios 2(b) and 2(c), correlations were averaged across runs and matched components. MSE values were averaged across runs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Human Brain Data</title><sec id="S8"><title>Samples</title><p id="P19">Resting state fMRI datasets from three independent multicenter studies, i.e., FBIRN (<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Keator et al., 2016</xref>), COBRE (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Aine et al., 2017</xref>), and MPRC(<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al., 2019</xref>), were used to test the feasibility and robustness of aNy-way ICA in identifying cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional links and whole-brain functional network connectivity (FNC) in individuals with SZ and healthy controls (HCs). Each study was approved by the institutional review board and all participants provided written informed consent.</p><p id="P20">The discovery sample was composed of 311 individuals (age: 37.88&#x000b1;11.26 years) recruited from the FBIRN project that also passed quality control (QC, see details later) (<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Keator et al., 2016</xref>), including 151 individuals with SZ (36 female) and 160 HCs (45 female). All participants are adults (18&#x02013;62 years old), and their cognitive performance was measured by the Computerized Multiphasic Interactive Neurocognitive System (CMINDS) (<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">van Erp et al., 2015</xref>). Diagnosis of SZ was determined using DSM-IV (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">American Psychiatric, 1994</xref>). <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table I</xref> summarizes the demographic and cognitive scores of included FBIRN subjects. Age and sex were matched between individuals with SZ and HCs (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P21">Two replication datasets were used to validate the results. The first replication dataset was collected from 148 participants passed QC (65 SZ patients and 83 HCs; 33 females; age: 37.87&#x000b1;12.77 years) in the COBRE cohort (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Aine et al., 2017</xref>). Their cognition was evaluated using the MATRICS Consensus Cognitive Battery (MCCB) (<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">Nuechterlein et al., 2008</xref>). Diagnosis of SZ was confirmed by two research psychiatrists using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I Disorders (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">First &#x00026; Gibbon, 2004</xref>). Demographics and cognitive scores of COBRE participants are listed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Age and sex were matched between SZ patients and HCs (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Another replication dataset included 364 participants recruited from the MPRC cohort (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al., 2019</xref>) that passed QC (135 SZ patients and 229 HCs; 192 females; age: 39.88&#x000b1;14.72 years). Diagnoses were confirmed using the Structured Clinical Interview for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV (DSM-IV)(<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Association, 1996</xref>). <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref> lists the demographics of MPRC participants. Age was matched between SZ patients and HCs (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>fMRI data acquisition and preprocessing</title><p id="P23">The acquisition information of each fMRI dataset can be found in the <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary information</xref>. All fMRI data were preprocessed using statistical parametric mapping (SPM12, <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/</ext-link>) following the NeuroMark fully automated spatially constrained ICA pipeline (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al., 2021</xref>) implemented in the GIFT software (<ext-link xlink:href="http://trendscenter.org/software/gift" ext-link-type="uri">http://trendscenter.org/software/gift</ext-link>). Specifically, subject head motion was corrected using rigid body motion correction, followed by slice-timing correction to adjust timing difference in slice acquisition. The slice-timing corrected fMRI data were further normalized to the standard Montreal Neurological Institute (MNI) space using an echo planar imaging (EPI) template (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Calhoun et al., 2017</xref>). Normalized fMRI data were resampled to 3 &#x000d7; 3 &#x000d7; 3 mm<sup>3</sup> (for extraction of thalamus and cerebellum) and 6 &#x000d7; 6 &#x000d7; 6 mm<sup>3</sup> (for extraction of regions excluding thalamus and cerebellum, see details later) isotropic voxels separately and further spatially smoothed using a Gaussian kernel with a full width at half maximum (FWHM) of 6 mm.</p><p id="P24">NeuroMark QC (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">J. Chen et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al., 2021</xref>) was applied to all preprocessed scans. We excluded (1) subjects with head motions of any frames greater than 3 mm translation or exceeding 3&#x000b0; rotation (compared to the first frame after discarding the first five frames to account for signal equilibrium and participants&#x02019; adaptation to the scanner&#x02019;s noise); (2) subjects with number of time points less than 120; (3) subjects with poor normalization quality.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>fMRI feature extraction in the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortex</title><p id="P25">Thalamus, cerebellum and cortex regions (i.e., all other regions excluding thalamus and cerebellum, we referred it as cortex since they are primarily cortical regions) were defined and extracted from preprocessed fMRI data using the automated anatomical labeling (AAL) atlas (<xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr">Tzourio-Mazoyer et al., 2002</xref>). To make feature dimensions of subdomains (thalamus, cerebellum, cortex) compatible and speed up the convergence of domain-wise fMRI data fusion, thalamus and cerebellum were extracted from fMRI data with 3 &#x000d7; 3 &#x000d7; 3 mm<sup>3</sup> resolution, yielding 609 voxels for thalamus and 7217 voxels for cerebellum. Cortical regions were extracted from fMRI data with 6 &#x000d7; 6 &#x000d7; 6 mm<sup>3</sup> resolution, yielding 5916 voxels.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>4-D multidomain fusion using aNy-way ICA</title><p id="P26">For each subdomain (thalamus, cerebellum, cortex) fMRI data, time courses were concatenated along subject direction to form a two-dimensional feature matrix with dimensions <inline-formula><mml:math id="M115" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>total</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>number</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>subjects</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>number</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>points</mml:mtext><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>number</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>voxels</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Subject-wise mean removal was then applied, and the resulting data were input into aNy-way for domain-wise data fusion. aNy-way ICA simultaneously maximizes the independence of components within each subdomain while maximizing the connectivity between these subdomains. The component number was estimated separately for each subdomain based on the order selection method proposed in (<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Y. O. Li, Adali, &#x00026; Calhoun, 2007</xref>). Assuming the minimum component number across the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortex is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, aNy-way ICA can effectively optimize <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional linkages (i.e., triplets or SCVs).</p><p id="P27">After aNy-way ICA converged, the sources (representing spatial maps of intrinsic connectivity networks (ICNs)) and their corresponding loadings (representing time courses (TC)) were obtained for the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortex, separately. A series of postprocessing steps were conducted on the TCs to eliminate noise sources, including (1) removal of linear, quadratic, and cubic trends; (2) adjusting motion effect using a multiple regression model with six realignment parameters and their temporal derivatives as independent variables; (3) de-spiking to detect and exclude outliers; and (4) band-pass filtering with [0.01&#x02013;0.15] Hz.</p><p id="P28">Beyond identifying linked subdomain SCVs, aNy-way ICA decompositions enable the computation of whole-brain FNC to further investigate group differences (SZ vs. HC). Both <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional linkages and whole-brain FNC were derived from the postprocessed TCs. Specifically, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> cortico-thalamo-cerebellar triplets (i.e., SCVs) were formed by concatenating the postprocessed TCs of the first <inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> components from the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortex subdomains. Cross-correlation of these <inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" display="inline"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> triplets was computed using Pearson correlation and then Fisher-transformed to quantify cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional linkages. Whole-brain FNC was computed in a similar manner, with cross-correlation estimated using all components from the thalamus, cerebellum, and cortex subdomains.</p><p id="P29">Multiple comparison was corrected over whole-brain FNCs using a false discovery rate (FDR) of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (&#x02018;mafdr&#x02019; command in Matlab 2023a) (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Duan, Premi, et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">Storey &#x00026; Tibshirani, 2003</xref>) to take dependencies of connections within SCVs into account. SCVs were considered significantly interlinked when all their pair-wise connection were whole-brain wide significant (i.e., passed FDR at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> correction over whole-brain FNCs).</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Statistical inference</title><p id="P30">For each significantly interlinked SCV, we computed pair-wise subdomain connection for each participant and examined their ability for discriminating SZ from controls using a N-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) model:
<disp-formula id="FD7">
<mml:math id="M124" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>pair-wise</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>subdomain</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>connection</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>diagnosis</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>age</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>gender</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>frame-wise</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>displacement</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>site</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x003b5;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where each pair-wise subdomain connection is treated as the response variable and diagnosis is the predictor. Age, sex, mean frame-wise displacement (FD) and site are covariates of no interest. FDR at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was applied to correct for comparisons from all pair-wise subdomain connections tested. SZ vs. HC difference of the whole-brain FNC was also examined using the abovementioned N-way ANOVA model, and multiple comparison was corrected over all whole-brain FNCs at FDR <inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We further tested the associations between pair-wise subdomain connections and cognitive variables listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Tables I</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">II</xref> using a N-way ANOVA model:
<disp-formula id="FD8">
<mml:math id="M127" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>pair-wise</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>subdomain</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>connection</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>cognition</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>variable</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>age</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>gender</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mtext>FD</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>site</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x003b5;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula></p><p id="P31">Similarly, each pair-wise subdomain connection is treated as the response variable and age, sex, mean FD and site are covariates of no interest. Cognitive variables are the predictors. FDR at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M128" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was applied to correct for comparisons from all pair-wise subdomain connections tested.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Replicability of subdomain connections</title><p id="P32">We assessed the replicability of the identified subdomain linkages, their group differences (SZ vs. HC) and associations with cognition, as well as whole-brain FNC group differences in COBRE and MPRC datasets. For each replication dataset, we applied the same preprocessing steps as in the discovery (FBIRN) dataset and projected the decomposed subdomain ICNs from FBIRN onto COBRE and MPRC data to extract the corresponding TCs (<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Duan, Jiang, et al., 2021</xref>). The resulting TCs underwent the same post-processing steps, including detrending, motion correction, de-spiking, and band-pass filtering. Since cognitive performance data included in FBIRN were not available in the MPRC dataset but were available in comparable formats for the COBRE dataset, we specifically examined the replicability of associations between subdomain connections and cognition in the COBRE dataset.</p><p id="P33">Consistent with the FBIRN dataset, we used Pearson correlation tests to evaluate subdomain linkages and applied N-way ANOVA models to assess group difference (SZ vs. HC) and associations with cognition for each pair-wise subdomain connection in the COBRE and MPRC datasets. A pair-wise subdomain linkage was considered replicated if its p-value was less than 0.05 and it exhibited the same directionality as in the FBIRN dataset. The group difference (SZ vs. HC) for a pairwise subdomain connection was considered replicated if (1) the connection was replicated; (2) the p-value for SZ vs. HC difference was below 0.05; and (3) the directionality aligned with the FBIRN findings. A similar criterion was applied to assess the replicability of associations between pair-wise subdomain connections and cognition in the COBRE dataset.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Results</title><sec id="S15"><title>Results of Simulation</title><p id="P34">The recovery accuracies of SCVs under scenario 1 (i.e., seven nonoverlapping sources for sMRI, fMRI, and EEG data (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2020</xref>)) are plotted in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 (a)</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">(d)</xref>, where aNy-way ICA recovered all designed SCV structures very well (the MSE value was 2.8&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>). Both mCCA and mCCA+jICA failed to recover, as indicated by the large values on off-diagonal positions, likely due to overfitting of correlations and inability to estimate non-orthogonal sources in mCCA, plus potential residual source misalignments from mCCA leaking into jICA for mCCA+jICA and overly strong assumption on shared loadings in mCCA+jICA. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 (e)</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">(f)</xref> demonstrates that aNy-way ICA accurately recovered both sources and loading coefficients for all three modalities, while the source and loading accuracies were low for most independent components (ICs) recovered by mCCA and mCCA+jICA.</p><p id="P35">Performance measures for scenario 2(a) are shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. aNy-way ICA accurately recovered components and loadings for sMRI and fMRI data, with slightly reduced recovery accuracy for EEG data (especially for 9 and 11 SCVs). Lower accuracies for EEG data are likely due to its relatively small feature dimensionality <inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4444</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and weaker correlation linkages with other modalities within each SCV (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 (a)</xref>). Overall, aNy-way ICA outperformed mCCA+jICA and mCCA in terms of source and loading recovery. mCCA+jICA and mCCA decompositions with the minimum component number of the three modalities had higher accuracies compared to those obtained with the maximum component number. As the SCV number increased (e.g., 9 or 11 SCVs), source and loading accuracies from both mCCA and mCCA+jICA dropped. The log10-transformed MSE values of the covariance structure of SCVs recovered by aNy-way ICA for scenario 2(a) are plotted in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">a</xref>). aNy-way ICA fully recovered the designed covariance structure when SCV number was 3, 5, and 7, and largely recovered it when SCV number was 9 and 11 (sMRI and fMRI were aligned well but not sMRI-EEG and fMRI-EEG when SCV number was 9 and 11).</p><p id="P36"><xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> demonstrates performance measures for scenario 2(b). As the number of subjects increased, the recovery accuracies of sources and loadings for fMRI and EEG, as well as the covariance structure of SCVs, increased, although there were some variations when the subject number was less than 400. Variation of accuracies of EEG data from aNy-way ICA was probably due to weak covariance structures generated from few samples. Log10-transformed MSE values for the whole matrix, diagonal blocks, and off-diagonal blocks of the recovered SCV cross-correlation are plotted in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">b</xref>). As the number of subjects increased, the MSE values decreased (except for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>400</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M131" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p><p id="P37">Performance measures for scenario 2(c) are plotted in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. Increasing the strength of noise superimposed on data, recovery accuracies of sources, and loadings dropped. aNy-way ICA outperformed mCCA and mCCA+jICA when SNR &#x02265; 5dB (when SNR = 5dB, the accuracy of EEG component and loading matrices recovered from aNy-way ICA was similar to that from MCCA and MCCA+jICA). When SNR = 0db, aNy-way ICA, mCCA, and mCCA+jICA failed to recover the sources and loadings. Overall, in contrast to using MCCA and MCCA+jICA to decompose all three modalities into the maximum component number of the three modalities, using MCCA and MCCA+jICA to decomposing data into the minimum component number achieved slightly higher component and loading accuracy. The log10-transformed MSE values of the whole matrix, diagonal blocks, and off-diagonal blocks of the recovered SCV cross-correlation under scenario 2(c) are plotted <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">c</xref>), where increased noise (smaller SNR) produces larger MSE values.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Results of Human Brain Data</title><p id="P38">We estimated 7 components for the thalamus, 11 components for the cerebellum, and 29 components for the cortex using the method in (<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Y. O. Li et al., 2007</xref>). Thus, the total number of SCV is seven (i.e., the minimum component number among the three subdomains). Among the identified seven subdomain SCVs, one SCV (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, SCV 6) was significantly interlinked after FDR at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M132" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> correction. The thalamus component (blue color in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 (a)</xref>) was positively and significantly connected with the cerebellum component (green color in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 (a)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M133" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.19</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 (b)</xref>). The cortex component (hot color in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 (a)</xref>) was significantly anti-correlated with the thalamus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.15</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.01</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 (c)</xref>) and the cerebellum component (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M138" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.41</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 (d)</xref>). <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref> plots the identified thalamus, cerebellum, and cortex components overlaid to their corresponding masks. The thalamus component highlighted medial and posterior thalamus (e.g., the mediodorsal and the pulvinar nuclei). The cerebellum component highlighted Crus I and declive, and the cortex component highlighted cuneus, precuneus, lingual, and posterior cingulate cortex.</p><p id="P39">The connection between thalamus and cortex in SCV 6 showed significant difference between SZ and HC (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(a)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.77</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Cohen&#x02019;s d (referred as d hereafter) = 0.62), where SZ patients had weaker anti-correlation (i.e., hyperconnectivity) compared to HCs. Stronger thalamus-cortex connection in SCV 6 was significantly corrected with lower CMINDS composite score (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(b)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M141" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.87</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), slower processing speed (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(c)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and poorer reasoning/problem solving skills (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(d)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M144" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>8.09</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), poorer verbal learning ability (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(e)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.48</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), poorer attention/vigilance (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(f)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M149" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.15</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and poorer working memory performance (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7(g)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M150" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M151" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.73</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Stronger thalamus-cortex connection in SCV 6 was marginally related to poorer visual learning abilities (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>(<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">a</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M152" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p><p id="P40">In the whole-brain FNC analysis, 254 out of 1081 total connection pairs were significantly linked after FDR at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M154" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> correction (see their connectogram in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). Moreover, 47 out of the 254 significantly linked pairs showed significant SZ vs. HC difference after FDR at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M155" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> correction. <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8(a)</xref> plots the connectogram of 47 FNCs showing significant SZ vs. HC difference and the connectogram of corresponding SZ vs. HC difference (Cohen&#x02019;s d value) is plotted in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8 (b)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Replication in the COBRE dataset</title><p id="P41">The interconnections of the identified SCV 6 were replicated in the COBRE dataset (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (a)</xref>). The thalamus component had a significant and positive association with the cerebellum component (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.19</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M157" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.95</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the left panel in <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (a)</xref>). The cortex component showed significant anticorrelations with the thalamus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M159" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.03</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the middle panel in <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (a)</xref>) and the cerebellum components (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.03</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the right panel in <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (a)</xref>).</p><p id="P42">In the COBRE dataset, the thalamus-cortex connection in SCV 6 was significantly and negatively associated with MATRICS composite score (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (b)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), processing speed (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (b)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M164" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.32</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M165" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.13</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), reasoning/problem solving skills (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9 (b)</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M166" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M167" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.19</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and visual learning abilities (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>(<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">b</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M168" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M169" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The thalamus-cortex connection in SCV 6 did not show significant difference between SZ and HCs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.09</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In the whole-brain FNC analysis, 6 out of 47 FNCs showing significant SZ vs HC difference in the FBIRN (discovery) dataset were replicated in the COBRE dataset, and the connectogram of their Cohen&#x02019;s d values for SZ vs. HC differences is plotted in <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Replication in the MPRC dataset</title><p id="P43">Two out of the three interconnections of the identified SCV 6 were replicated in the MPRC dataset. The cortex component was significantly anti-correlated with the thalamus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M171" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M172" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.03</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10 (a)</xref>) and the cerebellum components (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M173" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.71</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10 (b)</xref>). SZ patients also had significantly weaker anti-correlation between thalamus and cortex TCs in SCV 6 compared to HCs (d = 0.29, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M175" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>9.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10 (c)</xref>). In the whole-brain FNC analysis, 11 out of 47 FNCs showing significant SZ vs HC difference in the FBIRN (discovery) dataset were replicated in the MPRC dataset, and the connectogram of their Cohen&#x02019;s d values for SZ vs. HC differences is plotted in <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10 (d)</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P44">In this paper, we used a novel approach called aNy-way ICA to enable flexible fusion of N-way multimodal or N-way 4-D multidomain fMRI data that allows for a different number of sources per modality/domain. The proposed aNy-way ICA simultaneously optimizes the independence of sources within modalities/domains and the correlations among their expression levels across modalities/domains without imposing orthogonality constraints. When applied to the fusion of thalamus, cerebellum and cortical regions extracted from 4-D fMRI data, aNy-way ICA allows to simultaneously identify multiple cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional linkages and enables granular source separation within each domain by allowing distinct spatial scales and overlapping sources (rather than nonoverlapping subregions in ROI-based approaches) per domain (i.e., thalamus/cerebellum/cortex in this case). Furthermore, aNy-way facilitates the computation of more refined whole-brain FNC from the fusion results of 4-D multidomain data, thereby enabling a detailed examination of functional connectivity perturbations in individuals affected by specific brain disorders.</p><p id="P45">Simulation results demonstrated that aNy-way ICA reliably recovered sources and loadings, as well as the true covariance patterns, with improved accuracy compared to mCCA and mCCA+jICA under various scenarios, including (1) all three modalities have the same number of sources (e.g., 7 sources, an ideal case for mCCA and mCCA+jICA models); (2) different modalities have different sources and with varying number of SCVs, sample size, or level of noise superimposed on the data. The improved accuracy is particularly appreciated under noisy conditions.</p><p id="P46">Applying aNy-way ICA to fuse thalamus, cerebellum and cortical regions extracted from 4-D fMRI data collected from HCs and individuals with SZ, we identified one cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional linkage (SCV 6) in the discovery dataset (FBIRN) and largely replicated this cortico-thalamo-cerebellar circuit in two independent replication datasets (COBRE and MPRC). This cortico-thalamo-cerebellar circuit highlights the functional connections among medial and posterior thalamus, Crus I, declive and cortical regions in the visual network (e.g., cuneus and lingual) and default mode network (DMN, e.g., precuneus and posterior cingulate cortex). The identified anti-correlation between medial and posterior thalamus and cortex (mostly in the visual network and DMN) in SCV 6 was significantly weaker in SZ compared to HCs in both FBIRN and MPRC datasets. More importantly, stronger connectivity between medial/posterior thalamus and DMN/visual network was reliably related to more severe cognitive deficits in both FBIRN and COBRE datasets, including lower CMINDs/MATRICS composite score, slower processing speed, impaired visual learning abilities and reduced reasoning/problem-solving skills.</p><p id="P47">Our identified thalamus component highlights higher order thalamic nuclei (e.g., the mediodorsal and the pulvinar nuclei), displaying similar spatial patterns as those reported involving in visual process (<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Steiner et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">Tu et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">D. Y. Zhang et al., 2008</xref>). The mediodorsal and pulvinar have shown to be largely connected to DMN (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Ha et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Steiner et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>), and their connectivity was related to processing speed, selective attention and cognitive flexibility (<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Steiner et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, the connections between the visual cortex and the pulvinar nucleus have been well documented in humans (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Cortes, Ladret, Abbas-Farishta, &#x00026; Casanova, 2024</xref>; <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">C. Li, Chen, Han, Chui, &#x00026; Wu, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">Sabatinelli et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Steiner et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr">D. Y. Zhang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="R79" ref-type="bibr">Zuo et al., 2010</xref>), monkeys (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Adams, Hof, Gattass, Webster, &#x00026; Ungerleider, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Baldwin, Kaskan, Zhang, Chino, &#x00026; Kaas, 2012</xref>), prosimian primates (<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">Purushothaman, Marion, Li, &#x00026; Casagrande, 2012</xref>), as well as mice (<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">Scholl, Foik, &#x00026; Lyon, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr">Takahashi, 1985</xref>; <xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">Tohmi, Meguro, Tsukano, Hishida, &#x00026; Shibuki, 2014</xref>). Furthermore, the identified thalamus-cerebellar connection was supported by a prior finding that the posterior thalamus was connected to inferior cerebellum (Crus I) in individuals with early-onset schizophrenia (<xref rid="R77" ref-type="bibr">M. Q. Zhang et al., 2021</xref>). Importantly, the identified reduced anti-correlation (i.e., hyperconnectivity) between higher order thalamic nuclei and the visual network in SZ aligned well with the findings that SZ patients presented decreased negative correlation between visual cognition network and the dorsomedial part of thalamus (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Gong et al., 2019</xref>), as well as the entire thalamus (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Ferri et al., 2018</xref>), compared to HC. Aberrant FC between the left thalamus and the visual cortex has been documented to be related to attention deficits in schizophrenia (<xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr">Yamamoto et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="P48">The approach and findings presented in this study should be considered in context with its strengths and limitations. The proposed aNy-way flexibly integrates multimodal or 4-D multidomain fMRI data with allowing distinct spatial scales per modality/domain, facilitating finer-grained exploration of brain circuits underlying complex brain disorders. One potential limitation of aNy-way is that aNy-way ICA optimizes multimodal/multidomain linkage within each minibatch defined in infomax (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Bell &#x00026; Sejnowski, 1995</xref>) using IVA-G for efficient alignment of sources, which may be not scalable to large datasets due to the inherent time complexity of the IVA-G model (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Anderson et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr">Vu et al., 2024</xref>). However, this limitation can be potentially relieved by employing efficient variants of IVA models (<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">Gabrielson, Sun, Akhonda, Calhoun, &#x00026; Adali, 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr">Vu et al., 2024</xref>), which will be tested in our future studies. Given this study&#x02019;s focus on the development and initial validation of the aNy-way ICA method in simulated and schizophrenia fMRI data, future work is needed to explore possible moderating effects of schizophrenia clinical variables and treatments.</p><p id="P49">In conclusion, we proposed a flexible N-way multimodal/multidomain data fusion approach called aNy-way ICA to account for variable spatial scales across different modalities/domains, enabling comprehensive and finer-grained exploration of coherent multimodal or multidomain patterns. We validated the effectiveness of aNy-way ICA using both simulated data and human brain fMRI data. Using the proposed aNy-way ICA, we identified and replicated a cortico-thalamo-cerebellar functional circuit, highlighting the functional linkages among higher order thalamic nuclei, the visual cortex, and the posterior lobe of the cerebellum. The identified connection between higher order thalamic nuclei and visual cortex differentiates individuals with SZ from HC and aberrant connection between these regions is associated with multiple cognitive deficits observed in individuals with SZ. This underscores the clinical relevance and potential utility of the identified cortico-thalamo-cerebellar connectivity patterns in elucidating the pathophysiology of SZ and its associated cognitive deficits.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1</label><media xlink:href="media-1.docx" id="d67e4456" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S21"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p id="P51">We greatly appreciate individuals who participated in this research study. We would also like to thank research coordinators and principal investigators involved in data collection and data sharing. This work is supported in part by NSF grants 2112455 and 2316421 to VDC. This work was also supported by the National Institutes of Health grants: 1U24 RR021992 (Function Biomedical Informatics Research Network) and 1U24 RR025736-01 (Biomedical Informatics Research Network Coordinating Center), and 1R01MH130595 to JL.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S20"><title>Data and Code Availability</title><p id="P50">The code for aNy-way ICA is publicly available in the Fusion ICA Toolbox (FIT, <ext-link xlink:href="https://trendscenter.org/software/FIT/" ext-link-type="uri">https://trendscenter.org/software/FIT/</ext-link>). COBRE data can be downloaded from COINS (<ext-link xlink:href="https://coins.trendscenter.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://coins.trendscenter.org/</ext-link>), MPRC data can be access from the NIMH Data archive. FBIRN data are not available due to IRB restrictions.</p></sec><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akhonda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>ICA and IVA for Data Fusion: An Overview and a New Approach Based on Disjoint Subspaces</article-title>. <source>IEEE Sens Lett</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LSENS.2018.2884775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hof</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gattass</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Ungerleider</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Visual cortical projections and chemoarchitecture of macaque monkey pulvinar</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source>, <volume>419</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(sici)1096-9861(20000410)419:3&#x0003c;377::aid-cne9&#x0003e;3.0.co;2-e</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10723012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sampath</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiappelli</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jahanshad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Kochunov</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Functional network connectivity impairments and core cognitive deficits in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>40</volume>(<issue>16</issue>), <fpage>4593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4605</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31313441</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aine</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bockholt</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bustillo</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Canive</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caprihan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gasparovic</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Multimodal Neuroimaging in Schizophrenia</article-title>: <source>Description and Dissemination. Neuroinformatics</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12021-017-9338-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28812221</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>American Psychiatric</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders : DMS-IV</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>APA</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Joint Blind Source Separation With Multivariate Gaussian Model: Algorithms and Performance Analysis</article-title>. <source>Ieee Transactions on Signal Processing</source>, <volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1672</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1683</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/Tsp.2011.2181836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Nonorthogonal Independent Vector Analysis Using Multivariate Gaussian Model</article-title>. <source>Latent Variable Analysis and Signal Separation</source>, <volume>6365</volume>, <fpage>354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage>. doi:Doi <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-15995-4_44</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andreasen</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paradiso</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>O&#x0013d;eary</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>"Cognitive dysmetria" as an integrative theory of schizophrenia: A dysfunction in cortical subcortical-cerebellar circuitry?</article-title>
<source>Schizophrenia Bulletin</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage>. doi:DOI <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a033321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9613621</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andreasen</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The role of the cerebellum in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>, <volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18395701</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anticevic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Repovs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brumbaugh</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Glahn</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Characterizing Thalamo-Cortical Disturbances in Schizophrenia and Bipolar Illness</article-title>. <source>Cerebral Cortex</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>3116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3130</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bht165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23825317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Association</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders.(DSM-IV) Washington (DC): American Psychiatric Association; 1994</article-title>. <source>Tradu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o portuguesa. Fernandes JC edt, Climepsi Editores, Lisboa</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Avram</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandl</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bauml</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Cortico-thalamic hypo- and hyperconnectivity extend consistently to basal ganglia in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>2239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2248</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-018-0059-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29899404</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaskan</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chino</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Kaas</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Cortical and subcortical connections of V1 and V2 in early postnatal macaque monkeys</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source>, <volume>520</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>569</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.22732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21800316</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>An information-maximization approach to blind separation and blind deconvolution</article-title>. <source>Neural Computation</source>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1159</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/neco.1995.7.6.1129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bijsterbosch</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glasser</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Essen</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The relationship between spatial configuration and functional connectivity of brain regions</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>, <volume>7</volume>. doi:ARTN e32992 <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.32992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Multisubject independent component analysis of fMRI: a decade of intrinsic networks, default mode, and neurodiagnostic discovery</article-title>. <source>IEEE Rev Biomed Eng</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/RBME.2012.2211076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23231989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pekar</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiehl</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Pearlson</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Method for multimodal analysis of independent source differences in schizophrenia: combining gray matter structural and auditory oddball functional data</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16108017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearlson</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Pekar</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A method for making group inferences from functional MRI data using independent component analysis</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.1048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wager</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosch</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nebel</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Kiehl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The Impact of T1 Versus EPI Spatial Normalization Templates for fMRI Data Analyses</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>5331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5342</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.23737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28745021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bustillo</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrone-Bizzozero</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Canive</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Genome-Transcriptome-Functional Connectivity-Cognition Link Differentiates Schizophrenia From Bipolar Disorder</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Bull</source>, <volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1317</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbac088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35988022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Association between Thalamocortical Functional Connectivity Abnormalities and Cognitive Deficits in Schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Scientific Reports</source>, <volume>9</volume>. doi:ARTN 2952 <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-39367-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pol</surname><given-names>H. E. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haijma</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cahn</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Van den Heuvel</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Impaired Cerebellar Functional Connectivity in Schizophrenia Patients and Their Healthy Siblings</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia Research</source>, <volume>136</volume>, <fpage>S98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S98</lpage>. doi:Doi <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0920-9964(12)70335-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ladret</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abbas-Farishta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>The pulvinar as a hub of visual processing and cortical integration</article-title>. <source>Trends in Neurosciences</source>, <volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2023.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38143202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diedrichsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A spatially unbiased atlas template of the human cerebellum</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.05.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16904911</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Cerebellar structural and functional abnormalities in first-episode and drug-naive patients with schizophrenia: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res Neuroimaging</source>, <volume>283</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pscychresns.2018.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30500474</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dobromyslin</surname><given-names>V. I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salat</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fortier</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leritz</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milberg</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>McGlinchey</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Distinct functional networks within the cerebellum and their relation to cortical systems assessed with independent component analysis</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>, <volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>2073</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2085</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.01.139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22342804</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <collab>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging, I.</collab> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>NeuroMark: An automated and adaptive ICA based pipeline to identify reproducible fMRI markers of brain disorders</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage Clin</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>102375</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2020.102375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32961402</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>, <conf-date>20&#x02013;24 July 2020</conf-date>). <source>aNy-way Independent Component Analysis</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the 2020 42nd Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine &#x00026; Biology Society (EMBC)</conf-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rootes-Murdy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schoenmacker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Genomic patterns linked to gray matter alterations underlying working memory deficits in adults and adolescents with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>Transl Psychiatry</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>50</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-023-02349-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36774336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rootes-Murdy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schoenmacker</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arias-Vasquez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buitelaar</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Gray matter networks associated with attention and working memory deficit in ADHD across adolescence and adulthood</article-title>. <source>Transl Psychiatry</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>184</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-021-01301-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33767139</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Premi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pilotto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cristillo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benussi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Libri</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Alterations of frontal-temporal gray matter volume associate with clinical measures of older adults with COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Stress</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>100326</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynstr.2021.100326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33869679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Erhardt</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eichele</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>SimTB, a simulation toolbox for fMRI data under a model of spatiotemporal separability</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>59</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>4160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.11.088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22178299</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roach</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Erp</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voyvodic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Mathalon</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Resting-state thalamic dysconnectivity in schizophrenia and relationships with symptoms</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>, <volume>48</volume>(<issue>15</issue>), <fpage>2492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2499</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S003329171800003X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29444726</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>First</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Gibbon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <source>The structured clinical interview for DSM-IV axis I disorders (SCID-I) and the structured clinical interview for DSM-IV axis II disorders (SCID-II)</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iraji</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearlson</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Dynamic state with covarying brain activity-connectivity: On the pathophysiology of schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>224</volume>, <fpage>117385</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32950691</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><name><surname>Gabrielson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akhonda</surname><given-names>M. A. B. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2023</year>). <source>Independent Vector Analysis with Multivariate Gaussian Model: a Scalable Method by Multilinear Regression</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the ICASSP 2023&#x02013;2023 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)</conf-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giraldo-Chica</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Review of thalamocortical resting-state fMRI studies in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia Research</source>, <volume>180</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2016.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khundrakpam</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of functional connectivity in subdivisions of the thalamus in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>, <volume>214</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>296</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.2018.299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30791964</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Linked independent component analysis for multimodal data fusion</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>2198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2217</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.09.073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20932919</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Aberrant cortico-thalamo-cerebellar network interactions and their association with impaired cognitive functioning in patients with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>50</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37573437</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertolero</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>D'Esposito</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The Human Thalamus Is an Integrative Hub for Functional Brain Networks</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience : the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>23</issue>), <fpage>5594</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5607</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0067-17.2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Insausti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lerma-Usabiaga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bocchetta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Leemput</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Paz-Alonso</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A probabilistic atlas of the human thalamic nuclei combining ex vivo MRI and histology</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>183</volume>, <fpage>314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>326</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2018.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30121337</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Cerebro-cerebellar gray matter abnormalities associated with cognitive impairment in patients with recent-onset and chronic schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia (Heidelb)</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41537-024-00434-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38280893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Keator</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Erp</surname><given-names>T. G. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <collab>Fbirn</collab>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The Function Biomedical Informatics Research Network Data Repository</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>124</volume>(<issue>Pt B</issue>), <fpage>1074</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1079</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26364863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khalilullah</surname><given-names>K. M. I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agcaoglu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Multimodal fusion of multiple rest fMRI networks and MRI gray matter via parallel multilink joint ICA reveals highly significant function/structure coupling in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>44</volume>(<issue>15</issue>), <fpage>5167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.26456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37605825</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moussa-Tooks</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bolbecker</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Apthorp</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Hetrick</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Cerebellar-cortical dysconnectivity in resting-state associated with sensorimotor tasks in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>3119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.25002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32250008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levin-Schwartz</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schreier</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Sample-poor estimation of order and common signal subspace with application to fusion of medical imaging data</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>134</volume>, <fpage>486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.03.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27039696</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chui</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>An FMRI study of the neural systems involved in visually cued auditory top-down spatial and temporal attention</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>e49948</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166800</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Cerebellar gray matter volume changes in patients with schizophrenia: A voxel-based meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1083480</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.1083480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36620665</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Estimating the number of independent components for functional magnetic resonance imaging data</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>28</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1266</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17274023</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearlson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Windemuth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrone-Bizzozero</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Combining fMRI and SNP Data to Investigate Connections Between Brain Function and Genetics Using Parallel ICA</article-title>. <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>255</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18072279</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moosmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eichele</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nordby</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hugdahl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Joint independent component analysis for simultaneous EEG-fMRI: principle and simulation</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychophysiol</source>, <volume>67</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2007.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17688965</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nuechterlein</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baade</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Marder</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The MATRICS Consensus Cognitive Battery, part 1: test selection, reliability, and validity</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>, <volume>165</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2007.07010042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18172019</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pergola</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Selvaggi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trizio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertolino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Blasi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The role of the thalamus in schizophrenia from a neuroimaging perspective</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.01.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25616183</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Pierre Comon</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Handbook of Blind Source Separation: Independent Component Analysis and Applications</source> (<edition>1st</edition> ed.). <publisher-loc>The Boulevard, Langford Lane, Kidlington, Oxford, OX5 1GB, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Purushothaman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Casagrande</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Gating and control of primary visual cortex by pulvinar</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>905</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>912</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22561455</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>A connectivity-based parcellation improved functional representation of the human cerebellum</article-title>. <source>Scientific Reports</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>9115</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-45670-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31235754</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sabatinelli</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fortune</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krafft</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Emotional perception: meta-analyses of face and natural scene processing</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>2524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2533</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.10.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20951215</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foik</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Projections between visual cortex and pulvinar in the rat</article-title>. <source>Journal of Comparative Neurology</source>, <volume>529</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32361987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giraldo-Chica</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landman</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blackford</surname><given-names>J. U.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Thalamocortical Anatomical Connectivity in Schizophrenia and Psychotic Bipolar Disorder</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Bull</source>, <volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1062</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1071</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbaa022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32219397</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plis</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pattichis</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Multidataset Independent Subspace Analysis With Application to Multimodal Fusion</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Image Process</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>588</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TIP.2020.3028452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33031036</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Federspiel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slavova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiest</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grunt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinlin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Everts</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Functional topography of the thalamo-cortical system during development and its relation to cognition</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>223</volume>, <fpage>117361</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.117361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32919055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Statistical significance for genomewide studies</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>, <volume>100</volume>(<issue>16</issue>), <fpage>9440</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9445</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1530509100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12883005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearlson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caprihan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiehl</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Discriminating schizophrenia and bipolar disorder by fusing fMRI and DTI in a multimodal CCA+ joint ICA model</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>855</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.05.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21640835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabrielson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akhonda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laport</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Adali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>A Scalable Approach to Independent Vector Analysis by Shared Subspace Separation for Multi-Subject fMRI Analysis</article-title>. <source>Sensors (Basel)</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>11</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s23115333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>The organization of the lateral thalamus of the hooded rat</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source>, <volume>231</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.902310302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3968240</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tohmi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meguro</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsukano</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hishida</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Shibuki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The extrageniculate visual pathway generates distinct response properties in the higher visual areas of mice</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.01.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24583013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Network-specific cortico-thalamic dysconnection in schizophrenia revealed by intrinsic functional connectivity analyses</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia Research</source>, <volume>166</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;3</issue>), <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2015.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26081977</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tzourio-Mazoyer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landeau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papathanassiou</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crivello</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Etard</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delcroix</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Joliot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Automated anatomical labeling of activations in SPM using a macroscopic anatomical parcellation of the MNI MRI single-subject brain</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2001.0978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11771995</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Erp</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Preda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bustillo</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; Fbirn. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Neuropsychological profile in adult schizophrenia measured with the CMINDS</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>, <volume>230</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>826</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>834</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2015.10.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26586142</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ulloa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boutte</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A three-way parallel ICA approach to analyze links among genetics, brain structure and brain function</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.04.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24795156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><name><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laport</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabrielson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Adal&#x00131;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <source>A Robust and Scalable Method with an Analytic Solution for Multi-Subject FMRI Data Analysis</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the ICASSP 2024&#x02013;2024 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)</conf-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kushima</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Branko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Aberrant functional connectivity between the thalamus and visual cortex is related to attentional impairment in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Research-Neuroimaging</source>, <volume>278</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pscychresns.2018.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29981940</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neggers</surname><given-names>S. F. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Thakkar</surname><given-names>K. N.</given-names></name> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Altered thalamocortical structural connectivity in persons with schizophrenia and healthy siblings</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage Clin</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>102370</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2020.102370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32798913</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gohel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Biswal</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Functional topography of the thalamocortical system in human</article-title>. <source>Brain Structure &#x00026; Function</source>, <volume>221</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1984</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-015-1018-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25924563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>A. Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sansbury</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimony</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Raichle</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic functional relations between human cerebral cortex and thalamus</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>, <volume>100</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1748</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.90463.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18701759</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M. Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palaniyappan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y. Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Z. B.</given-names></name>, &#x02026; <name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Abnormal Thalamocortical Circuit in Adolescents With Early-Onset Schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2020.07.903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32791099</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.-S. R.</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Functional Connectivity Parcellation of the Human Thalamus by Independent Component Analysis</article-title>. <source>Brain connectivity</source>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>602</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>616</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/brain.2017.0500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28954523</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>X. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adelstein</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>F. X.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Milham</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Reliable intrinsic connectivity networks: test-retest evaluation using ICA and dual regression approach</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>, <volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>2163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19896537</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p id="P52">Diagram of aNy-way ICA. Sources <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold-italic">S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are estimated by maximization of independence in each modality separately. Corresponding loadings <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold-italic">A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are then organized into SCVs <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold-italic">k</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, followed by minimization of their mutual information with IVA-G, which amounts to maximization of the correlation structure within the SCV without orthogonality constraint (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Li, &#x00026; Adali, 2010</xref>). The model is optimized with stochastic gradient descent (SGD) until convergence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p id="P53">Scenario 1, cross-correlation of SCVs (the order of modalities is sMRI, fMRI and EEG for each SCV) from (a) ground-truth, (b) aNy-way ICA, (c) mCCA+jICA, and (d) mCCA. Correlation coefficients between (e) recovered sources and ground-truth, and between (f) recovered loadings and ground-truth for each IC: sMRI (downward triangle), fMRI (star), and EEG data (upward triangle) from aNy-way ICA (red), mCCA+jICA (green) and mCCA (blue).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p id="P54">Scenario 2(a), where the number of the SCVs varied from 3 to 11. Recovered source accuracies for (a) sMRI, (b) fMRI, and (c) EEG data, and loading accuracies for (d) sMRI, (e) fMRI, and (f) EEG data using aNy-way ICA (red), mCCA+jICA with maximum (solid green) or minimum component number (dashed green), mCCA with maximum (solid blue) or minimum component number (dashed blue). Values are averaged across matched components per modality.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p id="P55">Scenario 2(b), where the number of subjects <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" display="inline"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:math></inline-formula> varied from 100 to 1000. Recovered source accuracies for (a) sMRI, (b) fMRI, and (c) EEG data, and loading accuracies for (d) sMRI, (e) fMRI, and (f) EEG data. Values are averaged across runs and matched components per modality.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p id="P56">Scenario 2(c), where SNR varied from 30db to 0db. Recovered source accuracies for (a) sMRI, (c) fMRI, and (e) EEG data, and loading accuracies for (b) sMRI, (d) fMRI, and (f) EEG data. Values are averaged across runs and matched components per modality.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p id="P57">The identified cortico-thalamo-cerebellar SCV and their linkages in the FBIRN (discovery) dataset. (a) The Z-scored spatial map of the identified cortico-thalamo-cerebellar SCV and (b-d) corresponding pairwise connections: (b) thalamus-cerebellum, (c) thalamus-cortex, (d) cerebellum-cortex.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p id="P58">(a) Group difference and (b-g) associations with cognitive variables ((b) CMINDs composite, (c) processing speed, (d) reasoning/problem solving, (e) verbal learning, (f) attention/vigilance, (g) working memory) of the thalamus-cortex connection in SCV6 in the discovery dataset after adjusting effects from age, sex, site, and head motion. Red dots denote individuals with SZ and blue dots represent HCs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0007" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p id="P59">(a) The connectogram of significant FNCs (the color of the edge represents correlation values between subdomain components) and (b) the connectogram of FNCs showing significant SZ vs HC difference (the color of the edge represents Cohen&#x02019;s d values of SZ vs. HC difference).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0008" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p id="P60">(a) The pair-wise connections of the identified SCV 6 and (b) the association between thalamus-cortex connection in SCV 6 and cognitive variables in the COBRE dataset after adjusting effects from age, sex, site and head motion. Red dots denote individuals with SZ and blue dots represent HCs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0009" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p id="P61">(a-b) The pair-wise connections of the identified SCV 6 and (c) group difference of the identified thalamus-cortex connection in SCV6 in the MPRC dataset after adjusting effects from age, sex, site and head motion. Red dots denote individuals with SZ and blue dots represent HCs. (d) The connectogram of FNCs replicated for SZ vs. HC difference in the MPRC dataset (the color of the edge represents Cohen&#x02019;s d values of SZ vs. HC difference).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.02.657541v1-f0010" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table I.</label><caption><p id="P62">Demographic Information and Cognitive Scores for SZ and HC Individuals in the FBIRN Cohort.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SZ</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value (SZ vs. HC)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (M/F)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115/45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115/36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 <sup><xref rid="TFN1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.04 (10.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.77 (11.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 <sup><xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CMINDS</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Composite score</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.59 (1.22)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;28 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Speed of processing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (1.02)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.34 (1.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;24 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attention/vigilance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.36 (1.40)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.15&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;19 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working memory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.16 (1.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;20 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal learning</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (1.00)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.38 (1.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;23 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visual learning</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.09 (1.14)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;16 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reasoning/problem solving</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.85 (1.22)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;10 <xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><label>a</label><p id="P63">Pearson&#x02019;s chi-squared test.</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><label>b</label><p id="P64">Welch&#x02019;s two sample t test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table II.</label><caption><p id="P65">Demographic Information and Cognitive Scores for SZ and HC Individuals in the COBRE Cohort.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SZ</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value (SZ vs. HC)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (M/F)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61/22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 <sup><xref rid="TFN3" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.35 (11.84)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.26 (13.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 <sup><xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MCCB</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Composite score</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.92 (8.69)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.68 (13.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.89&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;17 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Speed of processing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.81 (8.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.97 (11.77)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;21 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attention/vigilance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.99 (9.21)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.38 (13.29)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;10 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working memory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.92 (10.67)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.28 (12.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal learning</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.53 (8.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.66 (8.78)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visual learning</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.02 (10.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.37 (12.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;7 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reasoning/problem solving</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.74 (8.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.02 (10.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;11 <xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN3"><label>a</label><p id="P66">Pearson&#x02019;s chi-squared test.</p></fn><fn id="TFN4"><label>b</label><p id="P67">Welch&#x02019;s two sample t test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table III.</label><caption><p id="P68">Demographic Information of SZ and HC Individuals in the MPRC Cohort.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SZ</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value (SZ vs. HC)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (M/F)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143/86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49/86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6 <xref rid="TFN5" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.52 (15.22)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.79 (13.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 <sup><xref rid="TFN6" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN5"><label>a</label><p id="P69">Pearson&#x02019;s chi-squared test.</p></fn><fn id="TFN6"><label>b</label><p id="P70">Welch&#x02019;s two sample t test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>