<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40501567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12157351</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.05.658044</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A window of cell cycle plasticity enables imperfect regeneration of an adult postmitotic organ in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>Navyashree A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5064-0650</contrib-id><name><surname>Buttitta</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1">Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Author for correspondence <email>buttitta@umich.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2025.06.05.658044</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and build upon the material in any medium or format for noncommercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2025.06.05.658044.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P1">The <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> ejaculatory duct (ED) is a secretory tissue of the male somatic reproductive system responsible for producing components of the seminal fluid which support fertility, serve antimicrobial functions and influence the physiological changes in the female after mating. The ED is a simple organ made up of secretory epithelial cells that are encased by extracellular matrix and a layer of innervated contractile muscle. These secretory cells are post-mitotic and lack known stem cells or progenitors in the adult, but they are not fully quiescent. They undergo a variant cell cycle called endoreplication immediately post-eclosion to increase organ size and protein synthesis capacity. Polyploid and post-mitotic tissues often face unique challenges in response to cell loss due to their inability to proliferate. Here, we show that the adult ED is capable of significant recovery after cell loss due to a combination of increased nuclear and cellular hypertrophy that partially restores tissue mass and organ function. The early cell cycle plasticity of this adult tissue is critical for this recovery, as older tissues that have few or no endocycles exhibit reduced capacity for recovery after cell loss. Together, our findings establish the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> ED as a model to study post-mitotic polyploid tissue repair and highlight a combination of endocycles and hypertrophy as a key mechanism for functional regeneration in the absence of mitosis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">The <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> male ejaculatory duct (ED) serves as conduit for sperm and seminal fluid transfer to the female via the ejaculatory bulb during mating. In addition to its transport function, the ED itself is a secretory organ, producing a substantial number of seminal fluid proteins (SFPs) including antimicrobial peptides and peptides involved in a range of reproductive functions (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Date-Ito et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Imamura et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Lung et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Richmond et al., 1980</xref>; <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Sturm et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Takemori and Yamamoto, 2009</xref>). Anatomically, the ED is composed of a basal, innervated muscular layer and an apical layer of polyploid secretory cells (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>; <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Susic-Jung et al., 2012</xref>). These secretory cells are the primary source of ED-derived fertility factors.</p><p id="P3">ED secretory cells of newly eclosed adult are post-mitotic, but not fully quiescent (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). Hours after eclosion, secretory cells of the ED undergo a variant cell cycle known as endocycling (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2014</xref>). Endocycling cells alternate between G1 and S phases without undergoing mitosis, resulting in polyploidy (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). The post eclosion endocycles are essential in the secretory cells for post-eclosion growth of the ED and full male fertility (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). Endocycles in the ED are rare after 48h and cease by 72h post-eclosion, after which the cells remain fully quiescent. This tissue contains no known stem or progenitor cell population and thus is thought to have very limited to no regenerative capability.</p><p id="P4">Tissues respond to cell loss by initiating regenerative programs to restore lost mass and function. In mitotically active tissues, this typically involves compensatory cellular proliferation (CCP), where either resident stem cells or surrounding progenitor cells divide to replace the lost cells (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">de Morree and Rando, 2023</xref>; <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Xia et al., 2018</xref>). However, largely post-mitotic tissues such as the heart, kidneys, cornea, bladder, and brain possess relatively few or no regenerative stem cell populations (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Lavecchia et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Losick, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Shu et al., 2018</xref>). Understanding how postmitotic tissues respond to injury, to maintain structural integrity and partially restore function remains a major challenge in regenerative biology.</p><p id="P5">Here, we show that the secretory cells of the young adult male ED retain a surprising capacity to restore tissue morphology and recover fertility function after genetically-driven partial organ ablation. In response to cell loss, the window for endocycling in the young adult ED is extended temporarily, providing an opportunity for postmitotic polyploid cells to restore tissue mass in part through compensatory endocycles. As the tissue matures and cell cycle plasticity is lost, the regenerative capacity of this tissues declines, suggesting that the regulators of endocycle exit and entry into quiescence limit this organ&#x02019;s recovery after damage. We propose the ED can be a genetically tractable model to study postmitotic regeneration and cell cycle plasticity in a terminally differentiated adult tissue.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results &#x00026; Discussion</title><sec id="S3"><title>Apoptotic cell loss in the ED occurs through apical extrusion and leads to irreversible cell loss.</title><p id="P6">Secretory cells of the ED in newly eclosed males undergo a variant cell cycle called endoreplication, in which they replicate their DNA without entering mitosis, thereby increasing cellular ploidy. We previously showed that post-eclosion endocycles in this tissue are essential for full male fertility (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). However direct studies of secretory cell loss in the ED have not been performed. We induced apoptosis in the secretory cells of the adult ED by expressing the IAP antagonist <italic toggle="yes">Reaper</italic> (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Ryoo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Sandu et al., 2010</xref>) using an ED-secretory cell specific <italic toggle="yes">Luna-Gal4</italic> (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). Inducing <italic toggle="yes">Reaper</italic> in the ED led to cells with pyknotic nuclei, indicating that the cells were undergoing apoptosis (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). By co-expressing RFP tagged with a nuclear localization signal (<italic toggle="yes">UAS-nls-RFP</italic>) we could observe cell loss (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Fig 1A</xref>), and disruption of epithelial cell-cell contacts, such as septate junctions labeled with Fasciclin III (Fas III). Following nearly complete ablation of secretory cells, only muscle/neuronal nuclei, which were Elav-positive, remained in the ED (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Fig 1A</xref>).</p><p id="P7">Upon cell death, the ED secretory cells underwent apical extrusion into the ED lumen (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). These apoptotic cells were further expelled through the ejaculatory bulb (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). Despite the loss of most secretory cells, the external basal muscle layer remained largely unaffected (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1C</xref>), while organ size was significantly reduced (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>,<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">E</xref>). To determine whether epithelial cell loss triggered proliferation or cell cycles within the diploid cells of the muscle layer or adjacent non-Luna Gal4 expressing tissues, such as the diploid anterior ED papillae, we fed the animals 5-Ethynyl-2&#x02032;-deoxyuridine (EdU) to label S-phases and stained for phospho-Histone H3 (PH3 Ser10) to visualize mitotic activity. We observed no evidence of cell cycles in the muscle layer or nearby ED papillae in response to the loss of the secretory cells (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>). We also did not observe any evidence of multinucleated cells that would result from cell fusion.</p><p id="P8">Our previous study revealed that blocking post-eclosion endoreplication in ED secretory cells led to reduced fertility and fewer offspring (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). In line with this, loss of secretory cells severely affected fertility (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1G</xref>). Mating behaviors and mating attempts were performed at the same frequency and rate as control males without tissue damage. Post fertility assay, we dissected the EDs and observed that sperm becomes entrapped within the lumen when the secretory layer is severely disrupted. By contrast, undamaged mated males very rarely retain any sperm in the duct (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1D</xref>). It is likely that these cells secrete factors required for the effective transfer of sperm, seminal fluid proteins, and other peptides to the female reproductive tract.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Recovery from transient damage in the anterior region of the Ejaculatory Duct</title><p id="P9">To investigate whether the secretory epithelium can recover following transient cell loss, we employed a conditional approach using the <italic toggle="yes">Gal4/UAS-Reaper</italic> system in combination with a temperature-sensitive <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic> repressor (<italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup>). At a lower temperature (18 &#x000b0;C), Gal80 is active and represses Gal4-mediated transcription (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). However, at higher temperatures (25&#x02013;29&#x000b0;C), Gal80<sup>ts</sup> becomes inactive, allowing Gal4 to drive transgene expression (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">McGuire et al., 2004</xref>). To validate the <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> system with the ED driver, we raised flies carrying <italic toggle="yes">Luna-Gal4, UAS-nls-RFP</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> at 18 &#x000b0;C. At this temperature, <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> repressed Gal4, and no <italic toggle="yes">nls-RFP</italic> expression was detected. Upon shifting the flies to 29 &#x000b0;C, we observed robust <italic toggle="yes">nls-RFP</italic> expression in the ED (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Fig 2A</xref>), indicating activation of <italic toggle="yes">Gal4</italic> due to <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> inactivation. To determine how quickly Gal4 activity is repressed after returning to 18 &#x000b0;C, we used a <italic toggle="yes">destabilized GFP (dsGFP)</italic> reporter, which is rapidly degraded in the absence of <italic toggle="yes">Gal4</italic> activity, providing a readout of transient gene expression. Flies expressing <italic toggle="yes">Luna-Gal4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">UAS-dsGFP</italic>, were maintained at 18 &#x000b0;C and showed no GFP signal. After shifting to 29 &#x000b0;C, GFP expression appeared in the anterior region of the ED after 32 hours, with no expression in the posterior ED. We then shifted the animals back to 18 &#x000b0;C to assess the time required for Gal4 repression following <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> reactivation. We observed that within 24 hours, GFP fluorescence was completely lost, indicating detectable repression of Gal4 and degradation of <italic toggle="yes">dsGFP</italic> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Fig 2B</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Based on these observations, we shifted <italic toggle="yes">Luna-Gal4/UAS-ReaperGal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> animals from 18 &#x000b0;C to 29 &#x000b0;C on the day of eclosion (DOE) for 32 hours to induce transient damage (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). As the ED is a post-mitotic tissue with secretory cells that undergo endoreplication for the first 2 days post-eclosion, we chose to induce damage on the day of eclosion, during the window of endogenous endoreplication. Upon activation of <italic toggle="yes">Reaper</italic>, we observed caspase-induced apoptosis in cells located in the anterior ED, marked by the presence of multiple pyknotic nuclei (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). In contrast, no pyknotic nuclei were observed in the posterior region within 32h of <italic toggle="yes">Reaper</italic> induction (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 2D</xref>), indicating region-specific cell ablation. We observed a similar pattern with an antibody against cleaved Death caspase-1 (DCP-1, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 2D</xref>) as well as a <italic toggle="yes">Drice</italic>-Based Sensor GFP (<italic toggle="yes">DBS-GFP</italic>) which indicate active caspase-mediated cleavage of substrates (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Baena-Lopez et al., 2018</xref>) (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 2C</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2E</xref>). The anterior ED contains larger secretory cells with higher ploidy levels of 16&#x02013; 32C, while the middle and posterior ED contains smaller secretory cells with lower ploidies of 8&#x02013;4C. We speculate that the increased Gal4 copy number and expression level in the anterior ED preferentially induces apoptosis with this limited activation window.</p><p id="P11">With transient <italic toggle="yes">UAS-Reaper</italic> expression, 100% of animals exhibited loss of secretory cells in the anterior region of the ejaculatory duct (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2F</xref>). Cell loss could be completely suppressed by co-expression of the baculoviral apoptosis inhibitor <italic toggle="yes">UAS-P35</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">UAS-Reaper</italic> (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Hay et al., 1994</xref>). Interestingly, organs co-expressing <italic toggle="yes">UAS-P35</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">UAS-Reaper</italic> appeared indistinguishable from control animals without Reaper, suggesting that apoptosis-induced proliferation does not take place in this tissue (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 3</xref>) (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Perez-Garijo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Perez-Garijo et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, our system efficiently induces partial ablation in the anterior ED through caspase-induced apoptosis.</p><p id="P12">We shifted the animals back to 18 &#x000b0;C to repress <italic toggle="yes">Reaper</italic> expression via <italic toggle="yes">Gal80</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">ts</italic></sup> and maintained them at this temperature for 10 days to observe tissue response to damage (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Remarkably, we observed substantial recovery of the ED 10 days post-damage. Cells were no longer DCP1-positive, indicating the resolution of apoptosis (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 2E</xref>). In the animals after a 10-day recovery without Reaper expression, we observed near-normal tissue size (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>). As our damage paradigm induces cell loss in 100% of animals, we interpret this to be evidence of significant restoration of both organ mass and epithelial integrity in this postmitotic and terminally differentiated tissue (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>The ED undergoes compensatory cellular hypertrophy (CCH) in response to cell loss.</title><p id="P13">The loss of anterior secretory cells led to organ shrinkage, however we observed no disruption of the muscle following secretory cell loss. By contrast, epithelial septate junctions were severely disrupted immediately after damage (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2F</xref>), but after 10 days of recovery at 18 &#x000b0;C septate junctions were restored and appeared normal (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2G</xref>). We observe cell loss in 100% of animals immediately after damage, but the degree of cell loss is variable. In cases where cell loss appears mild, we observe enlarged epithelial cells with normal or near normal nuclear sizes, suggestive of cellular growth without increased ploidy (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2G</xref>, bottom row). However in cases where many secretory cells are lost, the remaining cells undergo compensatory cellular hypertrophy (CCH) with visibly enlarged nuclei, indicative of an increase in cellular ploidy (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Tamori and Deng, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Tamori and Deng, 2014</xref>) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2G</xref>, middle row). Cells are significantly larger after damage followed by recovery compared to undamaged controls (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>) with enlarged nuclei (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). Thus, the secretory cells of the ED are capable of growth after mild cell loss and compensatory cellular hypertrophy (CCH) in response to more severe cell loss to restore lost tissue mass.</p><p id="P14">To quantify the ploidy of the cells in the anterior region, we measured the integrated DAPI intensity from nuclei, normalized to diploid cells of the innervated muscle within the same organ. The ploidy of the ED immediately post-damage was significantly reduced compared to controls (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>), consistent with loss of the anterior-most, highest ploidy ED cells. This increased the number of 8C and 16C cells in the anterior region immediately post-damage (compared to 32C in controls). By contrast, after 10 days of recovery at 18&#x000b0;C, we found that cellular ploidies in the anterior region were nearly fully restored (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3G</xref>), with the reappearance of many 32C cells in the anterior ED. We confirmed these results using flow cytometry, showing loss of the highest ploidy cells immediately after damage with substantial restoration of 32C cells after recovery (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3H</xref>). Notably the effect on ploidy in the flow cytometry assay is muted compared to the imaging quantifications because the flow assay uses nuclei isolated from the entire ED, while our imaging ploidy measurements reveal differences that are specific to the anterior region of the ED, where the most severe cell loss occurs. As a whole, these findings support that an increase in cellular ploidy accompanies the observed CCH following damage and recovery.</p><p id="P15">To visualize DNA synthesis during CCH, we fed the animals EdU immediately after the 32-hour damage period and tissues were dissected after 2, 5 and 10 days of recovery in the presence of EdU. We co-stained for phospho-Histone H3 (PH3 Ser10) to detect any mitotic activity. At Day 5, we observed many EdU-positive cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>, middle panel), however, no PH3-positive cells were detected throughout the secretory and muscle layers of the ED. Control undamaged EDs (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>, top panel) showed no EdU-positive cells, consistent with our prior observations that the tissue exits endocycling by Day 3 post-eclosion normally (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). We included <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> larval imaginal discs as a positive control for PH3 staining, which undergo robust mitotic proliferation (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 4B</xref>). By Day 5, despite significant endocycling, the anterior ED remained smaller than controls, but by Day 10, the ED tissue mass was fully restored with significant EdU labeling and no evidence of mitoses. This time course indicates that most endoreplication likely occurs between Days 2 &#x02013; 4 of recovery (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3F</xref>). This is equivalent to ~72&#x02013;96 hours post-eclosion without damage, a time when the ED has normally exited the endocycle and is fully quiescent (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). This suggests that following secretory cell ablation during the post-eclosion endocycle, the remaining ED cells extend their endocycling window to complete additional damage-induced endocycles as a compensatory mechanism. Following the compensatory endoreplication, the tissue eventually regains mass through increased cell growth.</p><p id="P16">To test whether secretory cell restoration in the ED could originate from other cell types in or near the ED, we performed G-TRACE labeling after induced damage using the <italic toggle="yes">Luna-Gal</italic>4 driver. G-TRACE (Gal4 Technique for Real-time and Clonal Expression) enables visualization of both real-time (RFP) and permanent Gal4-lineage driven expression (GFP) (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Evans et al., 2009</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Luna-Gal4</italic> driver used here is specific to the secretory cells of the ED in the male reproductive system and is active in the ED secretory cells from 1 day prior to eclosion throughout adulthood (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh et al., 2025</xref>). We found that all secretory cells in the ED co-express both GFP and RFP, immediately after damage, as well as 10 days post-damage (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 4E</xref>). These findings suggest that tissue mass recovery occurs from within the preexisting Luna-Gal4-expressing lineage of differentiated secretory cells, without the involvement of stem or progenitor cells.</p><p id="P17">Perfect regeneration restores tissue mass, patterning and function after cell loss. Tissues with few or no progenitors or stem cells may undergo &#x0201c;imperfect&#x0201d; regenerative mechanisms which may fail to restore cell numbers and prior tissue pattern, but can aid in restoring tissue or organ function, as in the mammalian liver (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Cordero-Espinoza and Huch, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Poss and Tanaka, 2024</xref>). To test whether the CCH we observe in the ED restores male fertility, we performed fertility assays on males during damage as well as after recovery. In brief, we crossed males expressing <italic toggle="yes">UAS-Reaper</italic> to Canton-S virgin females at a male-to-female ratio of 1:8, either at 29 &#x000b0;C to sustain Reaper-induced damage during mating or after 10 days of recovery at 18 &#x000b0;C. Males with damaged EDs produced significantly fewer offspring (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3I</xref>), and exhibited sperm trapped within the ED (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppl Figure 4C</xref>). By contrast, males that recovered after transient damage for 10 days exhibited significantly improved fertility (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>) and lacked sperm entrapped within the ED lumen, indicating that the tissue had recovered function. Thus, the post-mitotic ED is capable of partial functional regeneration following transient loss of anterior secretory cells.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Cell cycle plasticity is required for ED regeneration.</title><p id="P18">Thus far, our damage induction paradigm begins killing secretory ED cells on the day of eclosion, when these cells are still actively undergoing endocycling. However, this window of cell cycle plasticity closes by 48&#x02013;72h post eclosion, when nearly all secretory ED cells exit the endocycle and become quiescent. To test whether active endocycling is required for ED recovery after damage, we induced ED cell death on Day 3 post-eclosion by shifting the males to 29 &#x000b0;C for 32 hours to activate Reaper expression (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). We observed ablation of secretory cells from the anterior ED, with noticeable shrinkage of the anterior region compared to controls (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). This loss of cells also disrupted epithelial cell-cell junctions, as indicated by Fas III staining. We then shifted the damaged males back to 18 &#x000b0;C for 10 days to allow for recovery. However, the tissue was unable to exhibit the level of recovery we observed when damage was induced on the day of eclosion. The anterior ED remained smaller, and although some compensatory cellular hypertrophy (CCH) was observed, cell junctions were not fully restored (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>). Even after 10 days, the tissue remained small, with obvious loss of tissue mass. We saw no significant difference in cell size or recovery of cell density after 10 days of recovery (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4E</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4F</xref>).</p><p id="P19">We also examined EdU labeling in males damaged at day 3 followed by EdU feeding during 10 days of recovery. We observed increased EdU labeling in damaged animals compared to undamaged controls (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4G</xref>). However, the number of EdU-positive cells in response to damage induced on day 3 was substantially lower than that observed after damage on the day of eclosion. This suggests that the limited window of endocycling on day 3 may limit tissue recovery. Consistent with this, we observed a loss of higher-ploidy (32C) cells immediately after damage (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4H</xref>), and these high-ploidy cells did not recover, even after 10 days (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4I</xref>). Together, these results highlight that the early endoreplication window is likely to be essential for the regenerative capacity of post-mitotic ED secretory cells following transient damage.</p><p id="P20">Compensatory cellular hypertrophy can be triggered by a local alteration of tissue tension which accelerates the endocycle (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Tamori and Deng, 2013</xref>). Here we show that the adult ED responds to a threshold level of cell loss to prolong the window of cell cycle plasticity in the adult to enable CCH to improve regenerative capacity. Future work will examine the signaling that determines the window of cell cycle plasticity in the adult ED and how cell loss and damage can extend this window.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="S8"><title><italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> husbandry</title><p id="P21">All the flies for constitutive Reaper expression for experiments in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supplementary Figure 1</xref> were housed at room temperature (23&#x000b0;C) on a Bloomington Cornmeal food recipe without crowding (&#x0003c;50 animals per vial). For the damage and recovery paradigm with Gal80<sup>ts</sup>, flies were housed at 18&#x000b0;C in the same media and shifted to 29&#x000b0;C for 32hrs for the activation of UAS-Reaper and shifted back to 18&#x000b0;C for the recovery. All the male flies used in all the experiments are virgins except for fertility assays. We used the fly lines Luna-Gal4 (BDSC#63746), UAS-Reaper (BDSC#5824), Luna-Gal4 recombined with UAS-<italic toggle="yes">nlsRFP</italic> (BDSC#8546), UAS-Destabilized GFP (provided by D. McKay Lab, UNC Chapel Hill), GTRACE (BDSC#28280) and <italic toggle="yes">Tubulin</italic>-Gal80<sup>ts</sup> (BDSC#7017).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>ED dissection, fixation, and Immunostaining</title><p id="P22"><italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> male EDs were dissected in 1X Phosphate buffered Saline (PBS), the dissected EDs were immediately transferred to an Eppendorf containing 1ml of 4% Paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 1X PBS to fix the tissues for 30 minutes under continuous rocking. Fixed EDs were rinsed twice using 0.1% Triton-X +1&#x000d7; PBS for 10 minutes each wash. Fixed EDs were permeabilized with 1% Triton-X+1X PBS for 30 minutes on a rocker. Permeabilized tissues were blocked with PAT (1X PBS, 0.1% Triton X-100, 1% BSA) for 10 min. Tissues were resuspended in primary antibody freshly diluted in PAT at an appropriate concentration (below) and incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C on a rocker. Tissues were then washed these tissues with 1XPBS 0.1% Triton X-100, 3 times 10 min. prior to incubation with secondary antibody in PBS-T (1&#x000d7; PBS + 0.1% bovine serum albumin + 0.3% Triton-X (PBT)-X, + 2% Normal Goat Serum (NGS)) for 4h at room temperature. Secondary antibodies were diluted to 1:2000. EDs were washed thrice with 1X PBS 0.1% Triton-X after the secondary antibody incubation for 10 minutes each wash. For actin staining we added 2 drops of Actin Red 555 in 1ml of PBS and incubated the EDs for 30 mins and washed twice with 10 mins each wash to remove unbound stain and incubated the EDs in DAPI 1&#x003bc;g/ml for 15 minutes to stain the DNA. EDs were washed with 1&#x000d7; PBS + 0.1% Triton-X after the DAPI staining and mounted in vectashield (Vector Labs). Tissues were mounted by creating a spacer between the slides and coverslip with double-sided tape or one layer of clear nail polish. The list of antibodies used is in the following table with their dilutions.</p><table-wrap position="anchor" id="T1"><table frame="box" rules="all"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibody</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalog numbers</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dilutions Used</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse Anti-Myosin</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MF 20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin Red 555</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thermo Fisher Scientific</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R37112</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 drops/ml</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse Anti-Fas III</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7G10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rat Anti-Elav</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7E8A10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit Anti-Phospho Histone3 Serine 10 (PH3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millipore</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06&#x02013;570</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabbit Cleaved Drosophila Dcp-1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell Signaling Technology</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9578S</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAPI-DNA Dye</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D9542</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexa Fluor Goat 488 anti-mouse</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A11029</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexa Fluor 568 goat anti-mouse</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A11031</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexa Fluor 568 goat anti-rat</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A11077</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexa Fluor Goat 633 anti-mouse</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A21052</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S10"><title>5-Ethynyl-2-deoxyuridine (EdU) feeding and labeling</title><p id="P23">To capture the endoreplication in ED secretory cells after inducing the damage, we fed the animals immediately after the 32hrs of 29&#x000b0;C damage with an EdU solution made with 1mM EdU, 10% Sucrose, and blue food coloring (5&#x003bc;l/ml). We visually verified uptake of the EdU by the presence of food color in the abdomen. In cornmeal agar food vial, a Whatman paper was wetted with EdU solution (250&#x003bc;l in each vial). Flies were allowed to feed on this solution for 10 days during the recovery. The Whatman paper was replaced with a new one with a freshly made EdU solution every 2 days to prevent contamination due to the presence of sucrose. EDs were dissected at different time points during recovery when fed on EdU and proceeded with fixing, permeabilizing, and iclick-it reaction. We used Click-IT Plus EdU AlexaFluor-555 or 488 (Thermo Fisher C10638). We quantified the total number of EdU positive secretory cells by using the cell counter plugin in ImageJ Fiji.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Confocal imaging</title><p id="P24">EDs for all the experiments were imaged using a Leica SP8 Confocal microscope with 40X objective. Some of ED&#x02019;s 10X and 20X magnification images were imaged using Leica SP5 Confocal microscope and Leica DMI6000B epifluorescence system.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Area measurements</title><p id="P25">For the ED area measurement ED image was captured in one frame using a Leica SP5 Confocal microscope with 10X objective. The images were opened in Fiji Imagej software and obtained the maximum Z projection of the stacks of the image. Manually using the free hand selection tool the area around the ED was drawn from the Anterior end of the ED where the AG, Seminal vesicles are connected to the posterior end of the ED where it connects to the EB. Now the area around the ED was measured by clicking Analyze and then Measure. These area values were plotted using the Graph pad Prism.</p><p id="P26">For measuring the Secretory cell size using Fiji ImageJ we drew the area around the Fas III cell-cell junction staining of each cell using the free hand selection tool in the anterior region of ED and measured the area of each cell. For measuring the area of nuclei of secretory cells in the anterior region we took the maximum Z-projections of DAPI staining images and measured area for nuclei in the anterior region of ED.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Ploidy/DAPI intensity measurements</title><p id="P27">All the ED DAPI images were obtained without saturating the DAPI using a Leica SP8 confocal microscope. Images were exported in Tiff format and opened in Fiji Imagej. The maximum projection of the stacks of DAPI-stained images was obtained. We have observed that the basally located nuclei in the external muscle layer of the ED are diploid by flow cytometry. We used these diploid muscle nuclei of ED to normalize the measurements and to calculate the haploid nuclei intensity. We measured the background intensity by drawing the region of interest (ROI) in the background region of the images. After the background subtraction ROI was manually drawn around the DAPI-stained nuclei of Diploid and polyploid secretory cells. Measured the Raw integrated Intensity of both diploid and secretory cells polyploid nuclei. We measured around 30 secretory cell polyploid nuclei and 10 diploid nuclei from muscle for each ED and We calculated the corrected fluorescence intensity from each nucleus raw integrated intensity, by subtracting the average background intensity. The intensity of the haploid nuclei DNA was calculated by taking the average of the diploid nuclei intensity and dividing it by half, we used this as a reference of haploid nuclei with DNA content of 1C. Based on these haploid nuclei we estimated the DNA content of polyploid secretory cell nuclei. For <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4F</xref> we directly scored the DNA content without binning. For all other DNA content/ploidy measurements we plotted the after the following binning-2N (1.9&#x02013;2.9), 4N (3.0&#x02013;6.9), 8N (7&#x02013;12.9), 16N (13.0&#x02013;24.9), 32N (&#x0003e;24.9).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Fertility Assay</title><p id="P28">Virgin males were used to set up the fertility assay in all the mentioned figures. For the fertility assay showed in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref> we used 2&#x02013;3 day old virgin males expressing reaper and control were crossed to Canton S females. We used a ratio of 1:8 (Male: Female) to set up the fertility assay in each vial and allowed them to mate for 3 days in 25&#x000b0;C incubator. The total number of the pupae and the offspring eclosed were counted and plotted as the result of fertility. For each genotype we performed the fertility assay with 15 animals in each trial and repeated it three trials. For the fertility assay with Gal80<sup>ts</sup> Reaper presented in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> we performed the fertility assay at two different temperatures. (i)For the post damage fertility test after the animals of both control and Gal80<sup>ts</sup> Reaper underwent 32hrs 29&#x000b0;C damage and they were mated with virgin <italic toggle="yes">Canton S</italic> females with a ratio of 1:8 (Male:Female) in each vial in 29&#x000b0;C incubator to keep the damage on and allowed to mate for six days where we flipped them to fresh vial every two days. The total number of pupae were counted and plotted. (ii) For Day 10 post recovery after damage we performed the fertility assay after the 10 days of the recovery. The males were crossed to virgin <italic toggle="yes">Canton S</italic> females with a ratio of 1:8 (Male:Female) in each vial and allowed to mate in 18&#x000b0;C incubator for 6 days with every two days flipping and finally we counted the total number of pupae.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p id="P29">Nuclei from the ED were isolated post dissection in S2 media (Thermofisher #21720024) with 10%Fetal Bovine Serum (Cytiva # SH30396.02HI) and 1% Pen-strep antibiotic solution. We used 25&#x02013;30 intact EDs for the nuclear extraction per sample. We briefly spun the tissues to settle, S2 media was removed, then 1ml of Lysis Buffer (10mM Tris HCl-pH 7.4, 10mM NaCl, 3mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1% NP40) was added and the sample was transferred to a Dounce homogenizer placed on ice. To release the nuclei we homogenized the tissues with 20 strokes of loose Dounce pestle and allowed the tissue to rest on ice for 5 minutes. Following this we homogenized with tight Dounce pestle for 40 strokes. We triturated the tissue 15 times with a silanized fire-polished glass Pasteur pipette (BrainBits). This homogenate was filtered through 100 microns filter mesh, followed by 40 micron filter mesh to remove debris and unlysed tissue. To this homogenate 100&#x003bc;l of S2 media was added to stop the lysis reaction. This filtrate was centrifuged at 800 rcf for eight minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. Removed the supernatant and added 200&#x003bc;l of S2 media to the nuclei pellet with and incubated on ice for 5 minutes. To this additional 800&#x003bc;l of S2 media was added and centrifuged for eight minutes at 800 rcf, 4&#x000b0;C, supernatant was removed and the pellet was resuspended in 200&#x003bc;l S2 media with Vybrant DyeCyle Violet (Invitrogen #V35003) at a ratio of 1:100 and allowed to incubate on ice for 5 minutes, after the incubation to this 800&#x003bc;l of S2 media was added and centrifuged at 800rcf for eight minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was removed and resuspended the pellet in 1ml of S2 media, gently vortexed, and run on an Attune NxT Flow Cytometer.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Software and data analysis</title><p id="P30">We used Fiji ImageJ to analyze all the data. We used GraphPad Prism software to perform statistical significance in each graph plotted in the figures. The tests used to run the significance are mentioned in the figure legends.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>Supplement 1</label><media xlink:href="media-1.pdf" id="d67e760" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S17"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P31">We thank Dr. Allison Box and members of the Buttitta Lab for helpful discussions regarding this project. We also thank Dr. Jill Haenfler and the lab of Dr. Josie Clowney for assistance with male courtship assays. N.R. was supported in part by an U. Michigan MCDB Edwards fellowship. Work in the Buttitta Lab is supported by NIH R35GM149273 and NIH P01CA093900. Stocks obtained from the Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center (NIH P40OD018537) were used in this study. Several antibodies used in this study were obtained from the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank (DSHB), created by the NICHD of the NIH and maintained at The University of Iowa, Department of Biology, Iowa City, IA 52242. We used FlyBase (most recently release FB2025_02, released April 17, 2025) to find information on Drosophila gene sequences, phenotypes, and gene functions (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Ozturk-Colak et al., 2024</xref>).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baena-Lopez</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arthurton</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bischo5</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Novel initiator caspase reporters uncover previously unknown features of caspase-activating cells</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>145</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cordero-Espinoza</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Huch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The balancing act of the liver: tissue regeneration versus fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29293095</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Date-Ito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Chigusa</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Rapid evolution of the male-specific antibacterial protein andropin gene in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>670</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11965438</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Morree</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Regulation of adult stem cell quiescence and its functions in the maintenance of tissue integrity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>354</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36922629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zielke</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Endocycles: a recurrent evolutionary innovation for post-mitotic cell growth</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556841</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuoy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patananan</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>G-TRACE: rapid Gal4-based cell lineage analysis in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633663</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wol5</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Expression of baculovirus P35 prevents cell death in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>2121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2129</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7925015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haino-Fukushima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aigaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Fuyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Ovulation stimulating substances in Drosophila biarmipes males: their origin, genetic variation in the response of females, and molecular characterization</article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9692238</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lavecchia</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pelekanos</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mavelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Xinaris</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Cell Hypertrophy: A &#x0201c;Biophysical Roadblock&#x0201d; to Reversing Kidney Injury</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>854998</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35309910</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Losick</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Wound-Induced Polyploidy Is Required for Tissue Repair</article-title>. <source>Adv Wound Care (New Rochelle)</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27274437</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lung</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Wolfner</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Drosophila males transfer antibacterial proteins from their accessory gland and ejaculatory duct to their mates</article-title>. <source>J Insect Physiol</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>622</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11249950</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Spatiotemporal gene expression targeting with the TARGET and gene-switch systems in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Sci STKE</source>
<volume>2004</volume>, <fpage>pl6</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14970377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ozturk-Colak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marygold</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antonazzo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Attrill</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goutte-Gattat</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millburn</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tabone</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <etal/> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>FlyBase: updates to the Drosophila genes and genomes database</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>227</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perez-Garijo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Morata</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Caspase inhibition during apoptosis causes abnormal signalling and developmental aberrations in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>5591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5598</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15496444</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perez-Garijo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shlevkov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Morata</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The role of Dpp and Wg in compensatory proliferation and in the formation of hyperplastic overgrowths caused by apoptotic cells in the Drosophila wing disc</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>1169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19244279</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poss</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2024</year>). <article-title>Hallmarks of regeneration</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1244</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39163854</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Box</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Buttitta</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2025</year>). <article-title>Post-eclosion growth in the Drosophila ejaculatory duct is driven by Juvenile hormone signaling and is essential for male fertility</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>519</volume>, <fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39719194</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gromko</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Butterworth</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Esterase 6 and reproduction in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>207</volume>, <fpage>1483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1485</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6767273</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ryoo</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ciechanover</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Steller</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Regulation of Drosophila IAP1 degradation and apoptosis by reaper and ubcD1</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12021769</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sandu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryoo</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Steller</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Drosophila IAP antagonists form multimeric complexes to promote cell death</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source>
<volume>190</volume>, <fpage>1039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1052</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20837774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Row</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Endoreplication: The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>474</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29567370</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dowle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Audsley</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Isaac</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Mass spectrometric characterisation of the major peptides of the male ejaculatory duct, including a glycopeptide with an unusual zwitterionic glycosylation</article-title>. <source>J Proteomics</source>
<volume>246</volume>, <fpage>104307</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34174476</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Susic-Jung</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hornbruch-Freitag</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuckwa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rexer</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lammel</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Renkawitz-Pohl</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Multinucleated smooth muscles and mononucleated as well as multinucleated striated muscles develop during establishment of the male reproductive organs of Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>370</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22841645</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takemori</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Proteome mapping of the Drosophila melanogaster male reproductive system</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2493</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19343724</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamori</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Tissue repair through cell competition and compensatory cellular hypertrophy in postmitotic epithelia</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>363</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23685249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">---- (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Compensatory cellular hypertrophy: the other strategy for tissue homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Tissue repair and regeneration with endogenous stem cells</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Materials</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Reaper expression induces apoptosis in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> ED secretory cells.</title><p id="P32">(A) Schematic showing targeted expression Reaper in ED.</p><p id="P33">(B) Confocal images of control, constitutive Reaper ED at Day 10 post-eclosion (PE), immunolabeled with FasIII, DAPI.</p><p id="P34">(C) Single optical sections of EDs through the lumen on the day of eclosion (DOE) stained with FasIII.</p><p id="P35">(D) Confocal image of the male reproductive tract, highlighting reduced size of ED upon Reaper expression. (E) Quantification of control, Reaper ED area on Day 0 and Day 10 PE. One-way ANOVA with multiple comparisons. P&#x0003c;0.0001****.</p><p id="P36">(F) Confocal images of ED stained with EdU, PH3 and DAPI. Unpaired two-tailed t-test. P&#x0003c;0.0001****.</p><p id="P37">(G) Quantification of male fertility in control and Reaper- expressing animals.</p><p id="P38">Scale bar:50&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.05.658044v1-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Recovery from transient damage in the anterior region of the Ejaculatory Duct</title><p id="P39">(A)(i) Schematic illustrating the use of the temperature-sensitive Gal80<sup>ts</sup> system to control Luna-Gal4-mediated expression of Reaper in ED cells.</p><p id="P40">(ii) Illustration of ED damage and recovery paradigm: Flies housed at 18&#x000b0;C to suppress Gal4 via Gal80<sup>ts</sup>. On day of eclosion, flies were shifted to 29&#x000b0;C for 32 hours to induce Reaper, leading to apoptosis of secretory cells in the anterior ED. Flies are then returned to 18&#x000b0;C for 10days to allow tissue recovery.</p><p id="P41">(B) Confocal images of the anterior region of ED immediately after 32 hours of damage induction at 29&#x000b0;C. Tissues are stained with DCP-1 and DAPI.</p><p id="P42">(C) Confocal images of anterior ED post day10 recovery, stained with DCP-1, DAPI.</p><p id="P43">(D) Confocal images of whole EDs post-damage and post day10 recovery (10&#x000d7;magnification).</p><p id="P44">(E) Quantification of ED area from images of (D). One-way ANOVA with multiple comparisons. P&#x0003c;0.0001****.</p><p id="P45">(F) Confocal images of anterior ED region post 32 hours damage stained with Phalloidin, FasIII and DAPI.</p><p id="P46">(G) Confocal images of anterior ED after 10-day recovery stained with Phalloidin, FasIII, and DAPI. The middle row represents partial recovery, with CCH. The bottom panel shows full recovery of ED morphology.</p><p id="P47">Scale bar:50&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.05.658044v1-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Endoreplication in the ED after cell loss restores ploidy, tissue mass and supports functional regeneration.</title><p id="P48">(A) Quantification of average secretory cell size per ED. Each dot represents the mean cell size per animal. (B) Quantification of nuclear area of ED secretory cells in anterior region. Each dot represents the area of an individual nucleus.</p><p id="P49">(C) Quantification of ploidy in secretory cells of the anterior ED, measured by DAPI intensity, after 32 hours damage</p><p id="P50">(D) Flow cytometric analysis of nuclear ploidy in control and Reaper EDs post 32 hours damage. Grey peak-control ED nuclei, red peak-Reaper EDs.</p><p id="P51">(E) Confocal micrographs of the anterior ED Control, Day5 recovered, and Day10 recovered stained for EdU, PH3.</p><p id="P52">(F) Quantification of EdU-positive cells in control and Reaper EDs from images of (E).</p><p id="P53">(G) Quantification of ploidy in the anterior secretory cells of control and Reaper EDs post day10 recovery.</p><p id="P54">(H) Flow cytometric analysis of nuclear ploidy in control and Reaper EDs after Day10 recovery.</p><p id="P55">(I) Quantification of male fertility in control and Reaper-expressing animals.</p><p id="P56">Damaged ED: Mating performed post 32hours damage at 29&#x000b0;.</p><p id="P57">Recovered ED: Mating performed day10 post-recovery at 18&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="P58">Scale bar:50&#x003bc;m.</p><p id="P59">Statistical analysis: One-way ANOVA with multiple comparisons. P&#x0003c;0.0001 ****.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.05.658044v1-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Cell cycle plasticity is required for ED regeneration</title><p id="P60">(A) Schematic of damage and recovery paradigm for Day3 post-eclosion damage induction. Flies housed at 18&#x000b0;C suppress Gal4 activity via Gal80<sup>ts</sup>. On Day3 post-eclosion, flies were shifted to 29&#x000b0;C for 32 hours to induce Reaper expression. Flies were returned to 18&#x000b0;C for 10 days to allow recovery.</p><p id="P61">(B) Confocal images of anterior ED region immediately after damage on Day3 stained with FasIII, DAPI.</p><p id="P62">(C) Confocal images of anterior ED region after 10 days of recovery at 18&#x000b0;C stained with FasIII, DAPI.</p><p id="P63">(D) Quantification of nuclear area of secretory cells after damage on Day3 and following 10 days of recovery.</p><p id="P64">Each dot represents average nuclear area per ED. One-way ANOVA with multiple comparisons. P&#x0003c;0.0001****.</p><p id="P65">(E) Quantification of average cell size of secretory cells after damage on Day3 and following 10 days of recovery.</p><p id="P66">(F) Quantification of total nuclei per unit area in anterior ED post Day3 damage and recovery.</p><p id="P67">(G) Quantification of EdU-positive secretory cells in undamaged controls and after damage on Day3 following 10 days of recovery in the presence of EdU. Unpaired two-tailed t-test. P&#x0003c;0.0001****.</p><p id="P68">(H) Quantification of ploidy in anterior secretory cells after damage on Day3.</p><p id="P69">(I) Quantification of ploidy in anterior secretory cells after damage on Day3 followed by 10 days of recovery.</p><p id="P70">Scale bar:50&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2025.06.05.658044v1-f0004" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>