<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40032401</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11877276</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-067574</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2022-067574</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1706</subject><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Accuracy of individual signs and symptoms and case definitions for the diagnosis of influenza in different age groups: a systematic review with meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3228-2877</contrib-id><name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>Mark H</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6956-5016</contrib-id><name><surname>Rahmatullah</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hulme</surname><given-names>Cassie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buhr</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kotnik</surname><given-names>Jack Henry</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0256-8444</contrib-id><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>Barry</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Family Medicine</institution>, <institution>Michigan State University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">East Lansing</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Michigan</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Faculty of Medicine</institution>, <institution>Universitas Airlangga</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Surabaya</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">East Java</addr-line>, <country>Indonesia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Biomedical Informatics and Medical Education</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Washington</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Epidemiology</institution>, <institution>Cincinnati Children&#x02019;s Hospital Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Cincinnati</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Ohio</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</institution>, <institution>Emory University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Atlanta</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Georgia</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Bioengineering</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Washington</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Family Medicine</institution>, <institution>University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Washington</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>MT is one of the authors and also a member of the Editorial Board of BMJ Open. There are no other relevant conflicts of interest.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">Professor Mark H Ebell; <email xlink:href="ebell.mark@gmail.com">ebell.mark@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e067574</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-15-3.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title> Abstract</title></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>The objective of this study is to perform a comprehensive systematic review and meta-analysis of the accuracy of signs, symptoms and case definitions for the diagnosis of influenza.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>Systematic review and meta-analysis of diagnostic accuracy.</p></sec><sec><title>Setting</title><p>Inpatient or outpatient setting.</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Three databases (PubMed, CINAHL and EMBASE) were searched through February 2024 for studies of clinical diagnosis of influenza using prospective data collection and a high-quality reference standard. Data were abstracted by researchers working in parallel and resolving discrepancies by discussion.</p></sec><sec><title>Primary and secondary outcome measures</title><p>Quality was assessed using QUADAS-2. Summary estimates (or ranges) of sensitivity and specificity, likelihood ratio (LR), the Youden Index and the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The final meta-analysis included 67 studies, each with between 119 and 155&#x02009;866 participants. Most were judged to be low risk of bias. The signs and symptoms with the highest overall accuracy for all studies based on the Youden Index were any fever (0.32), overall clinical impression (0.28), coryza (0.25), cough and fever (0.25), and measured fever (0.25). Accuracy varied widely by age group. Only the overall clinical impression had a positive LR greater than 2.0. Cough was the most sensitive finding (0.92) with a negative LR of 0.28 in adults. The absence of any fever also had a low negative LR (0.30). The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) definition of influenza-like illness (ILI) had good specificity but poor sensitivity in adults, while in infants, it had good sensitivity but widely varying specificity. The European CDC and WHO case definitions for ILI had modest sensitivity and specificity.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Individual signs and symptoms, their combinations, and ILI case definitions have very limited accuracy for identifying persons with influenza. More accurate surveillance and diagnosis will require the development and validation of accurate risk scores or greater use of point-of-care testing.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>INFECTIOUS DISEASES</kwd><kwd>Public health</kwd><kwd>PRIMARY CARE</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Gates Ventures, Seattle, WA</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="disclaimer"><p>The funder was not involved in the design of the study, does not have any ownership over the management and conduct of the study, the data, or the rights to publish.</p></notes></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>This was a comprehensive search of the literature through 2024 that identified 67 studies.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Bias was assessed using the QUADAS-2 framework; and the included studies all used prospective data collection and a highly accurate reference standard test.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Analysis used modern methods for meta-analysis of diagnostic accuracy.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Seasonal influenza accounts for an average of 389&#x02009;000 deaths worldwide every year and has recurred after the COVID-19 pandemic as people have reduced their use of social distancing and mask-wearing.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 2</sup></xref> Neuraminidase inhibitors, such as zanamivir and oseltamivir, can reduce the duration and severity of influenza symptoms for both influenza virus type A and B but must be initiated within 36 hours of symptom onset to be effective.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3 4</sup></xref> Prompt diagnosis of influenza is, therefore, needed to avoid overuse of antiviral therapy and to recommend infection control measures. While rapid antigen and molecular tests for influenza are widely used in some countries such as the USA,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> in most countries and especially in low-resource settings, diagnosis relies on interpretation of clinical signs and symptoms.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p>The World Health Organization (WHO), the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and others have developed clinical case definitions for influenza-like illness (ILI) that are used both for disease surveillance and for clinical decision-making. These same organisations have also created definitions for acute respiratory infection (ARI) and severe ARI (SARI) that are also used clinically and for disease surveillance (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). To date, though, the diagnostic accuracy of these definitions has not been assessed by systematic reviews and meta-analyses.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Case definitions for influenza-like illness and acute respiratory illness</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza-Like Illness (ILI)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Influenza Like Illness (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/overview.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/overview.htm</ext-link>)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDC_ILI: Measured fever AND (cough OR sore throat) and no known cause other than influenza</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO 2018Influenza Like Illness<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO_ILI: Cough AND measured fever AND onset in last 10 days</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Centers for Disease Control Influenza-Like Illness<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC_ILI: At least one of: (measured fever, feverishness, headache, malaise or myalgia) AND at least one of (cough, sore throat or shortness of breath)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute Respiratory Illness (ARI)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Centers for Disease Control Acute Respiratory Illness<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC_ARI: Acute onset and at least one of the following (cough, sore throat, shortness of breath or nasal discharge) and thought to be caused by infection</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Centers for Disease Control Febrile Acute Respiratory Illness<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC_FARI: ECDC ARI with self-reported fever</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO 2018Severe Acute Respiratory Illness<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO_SARI_2018: Acute respiratory infection with cough AND measured or subjective fever AND onset &#x0003c;10 days AND requires hospitalisation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO 2011Severe Acute Respiratory Illness (&#x0003c;5 years)<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO_SARI_2011_LT5: (Cough or difficulty breathing) AND (unable to feed or vomits or convulsions or lethargic/unconscious or chest indrawing or stridor) AND requires hospitalisation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO 2011Severe Acute Respiratory Illness (&#x02265;5 years)<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO_SARI_2011_GT5: Fever (measured) AND (cough or sore throat) AND (shortness of breath OR difficulty breathing) AND requiring hospital admission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario Ministry of Health Febrile Respiratory Index (<ext-link xlink:href="www.health.gov.on.ca/english/providers/program/emu/health_notices/ihn_gd_ed_042909.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">www.health.gov.on.ca/english/providers/program/emu/health_notices/ihn_gd_ed_042909.pdf</ext-link>)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario_FRI: (Shortness of breath OR cough) AND (subjective fever OR measured fever OR chills)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands Medical Assistance for Accidents and Disasters (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ghor.nl" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ghor.nl</ext-link>)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dutch_GHOR: Measured fever AND 2 or more of cough, rhinorrhoea, sore throat, headache, myalgia, malaise, chills</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thai Bureau of Epidemiology<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBE: Fever AND myalgia AND one of the following: headache, cough, sore throat, prostration, nasal congestion and conjunctivitis</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Systematic reviews have been performed of individual signs and symptoms for influenza but were limited by the search strategy, by not using modern bivariate analytic methods for diagnostic meta-analysis, and because they were published 10 or more years ago,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> In addition, previous reviews did not stratify assessment of accuracy by patient age. Our goal is, therefore, to perform a comprehensive systematic review and meta-analysis of signs, symptoms and definitions of ILI, ARI and SARI for the diagnosis of influenza stratified by age group.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>This was a systematic review and meta-analysis of published studies of the accuracy of signs, symptoms and ILI definitions for the diagnosis of influenza. The study was registered with the PROSPERO database (#CRD42020161801) and followed PRISMA guidance regarding conduct and reporting of a diagnostic meta-analysis.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref></p><sec id="s2-1"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Patients or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of our research.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p>Inclusion criteria were selected to avoid spectrum bias, verification bias and information bias. Studies were included if they recruited a prospective cohort of infants, children, adolescents or adults presenting with symptoms of respiratory tract infection (RTI) or clinically suspected influenza in the inpatient or outpatient setting. Studies had to report sufficient information to calculate sensitivity and specificity for the diagnosis of influenza for at least one sign, symptom, combination of symptoms or case definition such as ILI or SARI. No limits were set for country or year; language was limited to those spoken by at least one of the authors (English or German). The reference standard had to be PCR, culture or paired serology and had to have been performed in all participants to avoid verification bias.</p><p>Studies were excluded if they did not enrol patients with acute RTI or suspected influenza, or if they were in a specialised population such as only patients in skilled nursing facilities, immunosuppressed patients, or patients with chronic lung disease. Studies were also excluded if they gathered data retrospectively using chart or medical record review, or if they used a diagnostic case&#x02013;control design (ie, recruited patients with known influenza and healthy controls or used banked samples).</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Search strategy</title><p>The search was built around the concepts for &#x0201c;signs, symptoms, clinical prediction rules&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;influenza&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;diagnosis&#x0201d; linked by Boolean AND joins and used three databases (ie, PubMed, Embase and CINAHL) and is shown in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix A</xref>. The limits &#x02018;has abstract&#x02019; and &#x02018;English&#x02019; were applied to the search using the PubMed database only; there was no limitation by age of study. In addition, the reference lists of included studies were reviewed for additional articles, as were three older systematic reviews identified by our search. A separate search for studies of the accuracy of case definitions was also performed, and the results merged (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix B</xref>). Finally, a bridge search was performed in February 2024.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Data abstraction</title><p>All abstracts were reviewed for inclusion in parallel by two authors, one of whom was always a physician. For any abstract deemed potentially of interest, the full article was obtained and reviewed in parallel by two authors to determine inclusion. Studies meeting inclusion and exclusion criteria were reviewed in parallel by two authors who each abstracted study characteristics, study quality and test accuracy data. Discrepancies were resolved through consensus discussion.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Quality assessment</title><p>The QUADAS-2 framework was used for our study and definitions for low, unclear and high risk of bias prespecified for each domain. These are shown in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix C</xref>.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> It was assumed that ascertainment of clinical signs and symptoms was masked to the results of PCR, culture or serology performed later in a reference laboratory.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Data preparation</title><p>Similar signs and symptoms were grouped together. For example, &#x02018;purulent sputum&#x02019;, &#x02018;sputum (purulent)&#x02019; and &#x02018;mucopurulent sputum&#x02019; were grouped into a single variable called &#x02018;sputum (purulent)&#x02019;. For vital signs and other continuous variables, similar cut-offs to define an abnormal finding were combined where clinically reasonable, that is, temperature greater than 37.7&#x000b0;C and temperature greater than 38&#x000b0;C. For studies reporting the overall clinical impression in multiple categories of disease likelihood, categories were combined to create a dichotomous variable.</p><p>With regard to case definitions of ILI, data for the older WHO definition and for the US Department of Defense Definition was combined with that of the CDC ILI as they are essentially identical (measured fever AND [cough OR sore throat]), with the CDC adding &#x0201c;and no known cause other than influenza&#x0201d;, the WHO adding &#x0201c;and thought to be due to respiratory infection&#x0201d;, and the US Department of Defense adding &#x0201c;and specimen collected within 72 hours&#x0201d;.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p>We defined infants as less than 5 years, children as 5&#x02013;17 years and adults as 18 years or older. Participants were classified based on the best fit, for example, a study of persons 16 and older would be classified as &#x02018;adult&#x02019;, of children 1&#x02013;17 years as &#x02018;infant and child&#x02019;, and of infants 3 months to 3 years as &#x02018;infant&#x02019;.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Analytical strategy</title><p>Data were imported into R (V.4.3.2, 2023) using the R Studio framework (V.2023.12.1+402). If there were five or more studies of a sign, symptom or case definition in any age group or overall, then bivariate meta-analysis was performed and summary estimates for the sensitivity, specificity and likelihood ratios (LR) were reported, as well as the area under (AUC) the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve and the Youden Index. A sign, symptom or case definition was considered significantly associated with the diagnosis of influenza if the 95% CI for the LRs excluded 1.0.</p><p>The Youden Index is the sum of sensitivity and specificity minus one and is an overall measure of discrimination.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> A value of 0.0 is equivalent to an AUC of 0.5, a value of 1.0 indicates a perfectly accurate test. Negative values suggest that a positive test (eg, presence of a sign or symptom) reduces the likelihood of influenza. The mada package (V.0.5.11) was used to calculate summary ROC curves and measures of accuracy with 95% CIs. If there were 1&#x02013;4 studies of a sign or symptom in an age group or overall, then the range or point estimate of sensitivity and specificity are provided and the AUC and Youden index are not reported.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Our search of the literature is summarised in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>. A total of 1449 unique studies were identified, and 281 were reviewed in full text. The final systematic review included 67 studies, each with between 119 and 155&#x02009;866 participants (median of 838 participants). Characteristics of the 67 included studies are summarised in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref> (a table including inclusion criteria, country and year is in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table 1</xref>). Studies were set in a wide range of countries, including 27 in North America, 16 in Europe, 12 in Asia, 5 in Africa, 3 in Australia or New Zealand, 3 in the Middle East and 1 in multiple regions of the world. Where reported, the mean or median age ranged from 22 months to 76 years. The most common settings were outpatient and/or emergency department for 39 studies, followed by inpatient for 11 studies and population or school-based for 11 studies. 10 of the outpatient studies specifically described being a primary care setting (general practice, family medicine or paediatrics). With regard to the reference standard, 55 studies used PCR, 4 viral culture, 2 paired serology and the remainder a combination of these reference standards.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>PRISMA diagram showing the results of the literature search. PRISMA, Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-15-3-g001" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Characteristics of included studies</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of patients</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age (years)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setting</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza strain</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference standard</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andrew, 2020<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#x02009;379</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aung, 2021<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">717</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barbara, 2012<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barry, 2021<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1653</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bellei, 2007<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">343</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient and healthcare worker</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BinSaeed, 2011<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BinSaeed, 2014<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brouqui, 2009<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bruning, 2018<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bryant, 2010<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campe, 2016<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">665</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carrat, 1999<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">610</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Casalegno, 2017<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x02009;994</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conway, 2013<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">944</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 months (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient, inpatient and ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR and culture</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crum-Cianflone, 2009<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">697</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davis, 2022<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6378</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DeMarcus, 2018<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5575</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dugas, 2015<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dugas, 2019<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1941</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duque, 2010<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">828</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient and outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farrell, 2013<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gupta, 2012<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1043</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guzm&#x000e1;n-Esquivel, 2023<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6027</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hirve, 2012<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3179</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hombrouck, 2012<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">949</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsieh, 2014<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">School based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired serology</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hulson, 2001<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hung, 2023<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2189</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient and ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jiang, 2015<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">700</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired serology</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kasper, 2010<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2639</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim, 2010<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">828</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kotnik, 2022<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">976</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lam, 2016<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1318</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.4 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maman, 2014<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">955</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Michiels, 2011<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4584</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monamele, 2020<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#x02009;816</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monto, 2000<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3744</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moretti, 2011<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">513</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mulpuru, 2013<xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murray, 2013<xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4800</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuzil, 2003<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">585</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ngobeni, 2019<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1939</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitsch-Osuch, 2013<xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okiyama, 2022 (deriv)<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7831</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient or outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okiyama, 2022 (valid)<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">659</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient or outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ouchi, 2022<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2614</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Padin, 2014<xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x02009;570</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedersen, 2019<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr"><sup>67</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prasarnphanich, 2010<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">838</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puzelli, 2009<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr"><sup>68</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">580</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radin, 2014<xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr"><sup>69</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1444</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rao, 2022<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr"><sup>70</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1478</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED and outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rowlinson, 2021<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6113</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senn, 2005<xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shahid, 2010<xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr"><sup>73</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population-based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smit, 2011<xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr"><sup>74</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">964</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sreng, 2010<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155&#x02009;866</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient and outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stein, 2005<xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr"><sup>75</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED or outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">van den Dool, 2008<xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr"><sup>76</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">van Vugt, 2015<xref rid="R77" ref-type="bibr"><sup>77</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1801</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vuichard-Gysin, 2019<xref rid="R78" ref-type="bibr"><sup>78</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2191</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Walsh, 2002<xref rid="R79" ref-type="bibr"><sup>79</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">332</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Woolpert, 2012<xref rid="R80" ref-type="bibr"><sup>80</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">789</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient and ED</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yang, 2015<xref rid="R81" ref-type="bibr"><sup>81</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (median)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR and/or culture</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zambon, 2001<xref rid="R82" ref-type="bibr"><sup>82</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1026</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zigman Suchsland, 2021<xref rid="R83" ref-type="bibr"><sup>83</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">739</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zimmerman, 2016<xref rid="R84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4173</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient primary care</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+B</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="abbr"><p>.ED, emergency department; ILI, influenza-like illness; NR, not reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3-1"><title>Study quality</title><p>Regarding assessment of study quality, 45 studies were judged to be at low risk of bias, 19 at moderate risk of bias and 3 at high risk of bias. The three studies at high risk of bias were downgraded due to failure to clearly have recruited consecutive patients, not accounting for all recruited patients,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13 14</sup></xref> and use of inappropriate exclusion criteria.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> The full quality assessment is in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Individual signs and symptoms and their combinations</title><p>The accuracy of individual signs and symptoms and simple combinations of symptoms with a Youden index of 0.10 or greater is shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref> (the full summary table including stratification by age can be found in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">tables3 </xref><xref rid="T4" ref-type="table"> 4</xref> and complete study-level data can be found in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix tables 6 and 7</xref>). We show 95% CIs for each measure of accuracy in the tables but have not reproduced them in the text for clarity. While many studies reported the accuracy of various combinations of symptoms, only the combinations of &#x02018;cough+fever&#x02019; and &#x02018;fever+sore throat&#x02019; were reported by at least five studies. The signs and symptoms with a Youden index greater than 0.15 were any subjective or measured fever (LR+ 1.7, LR&#x02212; 0.30, Youden 0.32), the overall clinical impression (LR+ 2.1, LR&#x02212; 0.63, Youden 0.28), coryza (LR+ 1.6, LR&#x02212; 0.52, Youden 0.25), the combination of &#x02018;cough+fever&#x02019; (LR+ 1.5, LR&#x02212; 0.53, Youden 0.25), measured fever (LR+ 1.7, LR&#x02212; 0.62, Youden 0.25), subjective fever (LR+ 1.4, LR&#x02212; 0.49, Youden 0.22) and chills (LR+ 1.4, LR&#x02212; 0.71, Youden 0.17). In addition to cough+fever, the combinations of &#x02018;cough+fever+myalgias&#x02019; (LR+ 2.0, LR&#x02212; 0.56, Youden 0.31, AUC 0.70) and &#x02018;cough+fever+ sore throat&#x02019; (LR+1.9, LR&#x02212; 0.63, Youden 0.26, AUC 0.69) had fair accuracy but were only reported in three studies (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Accuracy of signs and symptoms, sorted by Youden Index and then by AUC</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sign or symptom and age group</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of Studies</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR+ (95%&#x02009;CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR&#x02212; (95%&#x02009;CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Youden index</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever (subjective or measured)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.79 to 0.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.24 to 0.69)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.2 to 2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.17 to 0.50)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall impression</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.35 to 0.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.57 to 0.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.6 to 2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.50 to 0.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coryza</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.68 to 0.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.27 to 0.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.1 to 2.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (0.35 to 0.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough and fever</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.57 to 0.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.29 to 0.72)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (1.2 to 2.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.42 to 0.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever (measured)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.50 to 0.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 (0.54 to 0.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.5 to 2.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.55 to 0.68)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever (subjective)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.73 to 0.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 (0.29 to 0.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (1.2 to 1.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.39 to 0.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chills</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.50 to 0.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 (0.44 to 0.67)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (1.2 to 1.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.63 to 0.78)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.90 to 0.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.17 to 0.29)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 (0.30 to 0.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal congestion</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.56 to 0.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.31 to 0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (1.1 to 1.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.55 to 0.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute onset</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (0.36 to 0.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.48 to 0.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (1.03 to 1.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.64 to 0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.56 to 0.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (0.30 to 0.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.66 to 0.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myalgia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.52 to 0.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (0.44 to 0.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.73 to 0.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss of appetite</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.34 to 0.68)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.43 to 0.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (1.2 to 1.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.74 to 0.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 (0.58 to 0.71)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.37 to 0.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.73 to 0.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhinorrhoea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (0.63 to 0.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.32 to 0.48)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.68 to 0.84)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joint pain</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.19 to 0.41)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.66 to 0.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (1.15 to 1.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.87 to 0.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weakness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.74 to 0.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.11 to 0.37)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (1.01 to 1.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.65 to 0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest pain</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.13 to 0.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.65 to 0.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.01 to 1.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.85 to 0.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.51 to 0.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 (0.41 to 0.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (1.0 to 1.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.84 to 0.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rash</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.01 to 0.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.86 to 0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (0.50 to 0.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (1.01 to 1.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diarrhoea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.11 to 0.17)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.66 to 0.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.40 to 0.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccinated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (0.16 to 0.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.48 to 0.74)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.57 to 0.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (1.1 to 1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.11</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN2" fn-type="other"><p>Only signs, symptoms and combinations with an LR significantly different from 1.0 are included; the full data stratified by age can be found in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix D, table A1</xref>. CIs are reported for signs or symptoms reported by five or more studies; otherwise ranges or a single study estimate are given.</p></fn><fn id="T3_FN1" fn-type="abbr"><p>AUC, area under the curve; DOR, diagnostic OR; LR, likelihood ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Accuracy of case definitions for the diagnosis of influenza</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case definition and age group</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR+ (95%&#x02009;CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR&#x02212; (95%&#x02009;CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Youden index</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO ILI (2018)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;All studies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.48 to 0.81)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.39 to 0.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.91 (1.30 to 3.00</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.54 (0.43 to 0.66</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 to 0.47</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 to 0.97</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Infant, child or adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 to 0.90</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 to 0.52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC FARI</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;All studies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (0.56 to 0.81)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.38 to 0.77)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.76 (1.26 to 2.59</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.52 (0.41 to 0.65</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Infant</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 to 0.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 to 0.44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Child or adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 to 0.86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 to 0.84</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDC ILI</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;All studies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.49 to 0.77)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.40 to 0.78)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.68 (1.27 to 2.35</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.60 (0.50 to 0.70</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Infant</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 to 0.86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 to 0.43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Child or adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 to 0.97</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 to 0.85</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.21 to 0.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.67 to 0.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.13 (1.71 to 5.57</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.70 (0.54 to 0.84</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Infant, child or adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.56 to 0.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 (0.19 to 0.64)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.30 (1.08 to 1.75</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.58 (0.37 to 0.82</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO SARI (2011)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;All studies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.13 to 0.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.49 to 0.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.89 to 1.44)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.87 to 1.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Infant</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (0.16 to 0.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.19 to 0.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.75 to 1.01)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.99 to 1.48)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Child or adult</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 (0.05 to 0.51)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.64 to 0.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.43 (1.19 to 1.70</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.92 (0.75 to 0.99</bold>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T4_FN2" fn-type="other"><p>Only those definitions evaluated in five or more studies are shown here; see <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix D table A2</xref> for the full set of studies.</p></fn><fn id="T4_FN3" fn-type="other"><p>Bold face indicates a Likelihood Ratio significantly larger or smaller than 1.0.</p></fn><fn id="T4_FN1" fn-type="abbr"><p>ARI, acute respiratory infection; CDC, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; ECDC, European CDC; FARI, febrile acute respiratory infection; ILI, influenza&#x02009;like illness; SARI, severe acute respiratory infection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Summary ROC curves for the most accurate signs and symptoms stratified by age group are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2A&#x02013;F</xref>. Subjective or measured &#x02018;fever+coryza&#x02019; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2A,C</xref>) are both fairly uniformly sensitive, but with widely varying specificity. The overall impression, &#x02018;cough+fever&#x02019;, measured fever and subjective fever (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2B, D&#x02013;F</xref>) all show evidence of threshold effects, where sensitivity increases as specificity decreases. This is typically caused by different implicit or explicit cut-offs for defining an abnormal test.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>(<bold>A&#x02013;</bold>F) Summary receiver operating characteristic curves for the six most accurate individual signs and symptoms stratified by age group.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-15-3-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>Symptoms significantly but more weakly associated with influenza (Youden 0.10&#x02013;0.14) included cough (LR+ 1.2, LR&#x02212; 0.36, Youden 0.14), nasal congestion (LR+ 1.3, LR&#x02212; 0.71, Youden 0.14), acute onset (LR+ 1.3, LR&#x02212; 0.81, Youden 0.12), fatigue (LR+ 1.2, LR&#x02212; 0.74, Youden 0.11, myalgias (LR+ 1.2, LR&#x02212; 0.79, Youden 0.11), loss of appetite (LR+ 1.3, LR&#x02212; 0.83, Youden 0.11), headache (LR+ 1.2, LR&#x02212; 0.78, Youden 0.10) and rhinorrhoea (LR+ 1.2, LR&#x02212; 0.75, Youden 0.10).</p><p>The presence of joint pain, weakness, chest pain and sore throat were significantly but only very weakly associated with influenza (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix 3</xref>, Youden index 0.05&#x02212;0.09). Abdominal pain, cough with sputum, wheeze, seizures, ear pain, confusion, conjunctivitis, sinus symptoms, impaired feeding, digestive symptoms, sweats or diaphoresis, dyspnoea, tachypnoea, nausea, vomiting and &#x02018;nausea or vomiting&#x02019; had no significant association with the diagnosis of influenza based on non-significant LRs and Youden indices near 0.0. The presence of rash, history of vaccination and diarrhoea made influenza less likely (Youden index range from &#x02212;0.02 to &#x02212;0.11).</p><p>The Youden index generally paralleled the AUC, with the exception of any cough (AUC 0.79, Youden 0.14). Only the overall clinical impression had a positive LR (+LR) greater than 2.0; it was also the most specific finding (0.74). Cough was the most sensitive finding (92%). Findings with the lowest negative LR and therefore best at ruling out influenza when absent were absence of cough (LR&#x02212; 0.36 overall and 0.28 in adults) and absence of any fever (LR&#x02212; 0.30).</p><p>Relatively few symptoms had sufficient data to calculate summary estimates of accuracy by age group. For most other signs and symptoms, the positive and negative LRs were generally similar regardless of age group or groups. Fatigue and myalgias were less sensitive and overall less accurate for the diagnosis of influenza in infants than in older populations.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Case definitions of influenza-like illness and ARI</title><p>The accuracy of clinical case definitions stratified by age group is shown in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>. The WHO ILI 2018 (LR+ 1.91, LR&#x02212; 0.54, Youden 0.30) and European CDC (ECDC) febrile ARI (FARI) case definitions (LR+ 1.76, LR&#x02212; 0.52, Youden 0.29) were most accurate overall. Slightly less accurate was the CDC ILI (23 studies, LR+ 1.68, LR&#x02212; 0.60, Youden 0.25). The WHO SARI 2011 case definition had poor accuracy for diagnosis of influenza (11 studies, LR+ 1.13, LR&#x02212; 0.96, AUC 0.50, Youden 0.03). The full table includes other definitions that were reported by four or fewer studies and are presented in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix tables 5 and 8</xref> for study-level data.</p><p>Summary ROC curves for the four best-studied case definitions stratified by age group are shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3A&#x02013;D</xref>. The European CDC and WHO case definitions for ILI had modest sensitivity and specificity. The WHO ILI case definition had low sensitivity and good specificity in studies done in adults, while studies that included infants and children as well as adults had better sensitivity but worse specificity. The CDC definition of influenza-like illness had a clear threshold effect, which may be due to implicit differences in determining when a cough, sore throat or subjective fever was present between studies. As with the WHO ILI, studies in adults tended to have lower sensitivity and better specificity. The WHO SARI 2011 case definition was unhelpful for diagnosing influenza. See <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table A2</xref> for the complete data.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>(<bold>A&#x02013;</bold>D) Summary receiver operating characteristic curves for the four best-studied case definitions stratified by age group. CDC, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; ECDC, European CDC; FARI, febrile acute respiratory infection; ILI, influenza-like illness; SARI, severe acute respiratory infection.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="bmjopen-15-3-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have performed a comprehensive systematic review of signs, symptoms, their combinations and case definitions for the diagnosis of influenza. We found that individual signs and symptoms are of very limited value for distinguishing influenza from other causes of respiratory symptoms. The most accurate individual signs and symptoms are any &#x02018;subjective or measured fever&#x02019; (LR+1.7, LR&#x02212; 0.30), the overall clinical impression (LR+ 2.1, LR&#x02212; 0.63), coryza (LR+1.6, LR&#x02212; 0.52) and the combination of cough+fever (LR+1.5, LR&#x02212; 0.53). Absence of any fever (LR&#x02212; 0.30) and absence of cough (LR&#x02212; 0.36 overall, LR&#x02212; 0.28 in adults) were the individual signs and symptoms best at ruling out influenza when absent. The most sensitive individual findings were fever (0.87) and cough (0.92), while the most specific single finding was the overall clinical impression (0.74).</p><p>There was considerable heterogeneity with regard to the accuracy of signs and symptoms as shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2A&#x02013;F</xref>. A threshold effect, with sensitivity and specificity varying inversely due to different explicit or implicit thresholds for a positive test were especially apparent for overall impression, &#x02018;cough+fever&#x02019;, measured fever and subjective fever. There were also some differences by age group: any fever appeared to be less sensitive in adults than in younger groups, while fatigue was much more sensitive in adults than in infants (0.82 vs 0.27). Not surprisingly, symptoms relying on patient report such as fatigue and myalgia were unhelpful in infants. There was good consistency across age groups for cough as a predictor of influenza. Symptoms previously found to be independent predictors of influenza such as acute onset (LR+1.3, LR&#x02212; 0.81) and myalgia<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> (LR+ 1.2, LR&#x02212; 0.79) had only modest accuracy in our systematic review.</p><p>Among combinations of symptoms, &#x02018;cough+fever&#x02019; was best studied but had only modest accuracy (LR+1.5, LR&#x02212; 0.53). In a separate systematic review, we identified 14 clinical prediction rules (CPRs) that used combinations of signs and symptoms to predict the likelihood of influenza.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> However, none has been successfully validated in an independent population. Future studies to develop and validate CPRs should include the most accurate individual signs and symptoms identified by our analysis, including variables not previously included such as coryza and the overall clinical impression, as well as signs and symptoms found to decrease the likelihood of influenza such as vaccination and gastrointestinal symptoms. Different CPRs are likely needed for children and adults.</p><p>The WHO case definition for ILI was the most accurate overall (8 studies, LR+ 1.91, LR&#x02212; 0.54, AUC 0.70), while for adults only the CDC ILI was most accurate (9 studies, LR+ 3.1, LR&#x02212; 0.70, AUC 0.68).</p><p>In a population with a 25% prevalence of influenza, an adult meeting the CDC case definition would have a 51% likelihood of influenza. However, not meeting the case definition only reduces that likelihood to 19%. The 2018 version of the WHO ILI case definition and the European CDC FARI case definition had similar overall accuracy to the CDC case definition, but were less well studied, especially in subgroups by age. Thus, other than the ability of the CDC ILI case definition to help rule out influenza in adults when criteria are met, case definitions do not appear to be helpful to clinicians for the diagnosis of influenza.</p><p>The assessment of signs and symptoms is inherently subjective and may be influenced by clinician expectations around the likelihood of influenza, which is in turn driven by prevalence in the community at that time. The studies in this systematic review were done during times of year when influenza was circulating. Incorporating the prevalence of a pathogen using surveillance data is a promising way to enhance the accuracy of diagnostic risk scores<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> and could be applied to influenza. The assessment of signs and symptoms can also be influenced by implicit differences in what is classified as coryza or sore throat or cough. For example, any cough or only moderate or severe cough? This is captured by the threshold effects seen in many of the ROC curves in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figures2 </xref><xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig"> 3</xref>.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p>Our analysis had several notable strengths. The search was comprehensive and identified 67 studies, most studies were judged to be at low risk of bias, and the analysis used a bivariate approach with stratification by age group. All studies gathered data prospectively and used high-quality reference standards. Also, all studies but one gathered data prior to the current COVID-19 pandemic. A limitation was that for many of the signs and symptoms, there were relatively few studies reporting accuracy separately for infants, children and adults.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Implications for clinicians, researchers, policy-makers</title><p>For clinicians, it is clear that using either individual signs and symptoms or existing combinations of clinical features has very limited accuracy for identifying adults or children with influenza, and likely in differentiating influenza from COVID-19 and other respiratory pathogens.</p><p>Diagnostic tests to accurately identify patients who have influenza, perhaps used in conjunction with CPRs, have the potential to identify patients who might benefit from antiviral drugs and reduce inappropriate antibiotic use.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The development of more accurate molecular tests combining detection of influenza virus with SARS-CoV-2 and possibly other pathogens such as respiratory syncitial virus (RSV) in children is promising.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> While the cost of point-of-care molecular tests remains high, more accurate diagnosis of highly contagious infections has the added benefit of allowing the institution of isolation and mask-wearing to reduce transmission to others. Dissemination of cheap rapid antigen tests to low-resource settings is also needed.</p><p>With increasing availability of point-of-care tests, including in low-resource countries, a pragmatic strategy for clinical practice would be initially using a combination of signs and symptoms that is highly sensitive with adequate specificity (to miss as few cases as possible) and then using a point-of-care test to confirm the diagnosis. Fever and cough (individually) both have high sensitivity, with fever having higher specificity. We did not find a combination of fever and any respiratory symptom that would be worth exploring as an initial filter.</p><p>For researchers, more work is needed to validate existing CPRs, as well as to develop and validate new ones. We recently published a systematic review of CPRs for the diagnosis of influenza and identified a number with very good accuracy that were able to risk stratify patients into low, moderate and high-risk groups. This kind of risk stratification better fits the clinical practice of rule out, need more information, and rule in for low, moderate and high-risk groups. However, none of the CPRs were successfully prospectively validated. Future work is needed to develop and validate new or existing CPRs for influenza.</p><p>For example, an individual patient meta-analysis using combined datasets with similar inclusion criteria from different populations could be used to develop CPRs in one set of populations and validate them in others. Integrating the overall impression and creating separate rules for adults and children will also be important. CPRs using only symptoms can facilitate evidence-based triage decisions and telemedicine care, perhaps in conjunction with the availability of home rapid antigen tests for influenza. We recently studied the impact of such a home test on physician decision-making and found that the availability of such a test could have a major impact on the need for in-person consultations, potentially reducing overall cost and increasing convenience (manuscript in review). It could also help avoid transmission of infection to other patients in the outpatient practice and to staff.</p><p>For policy-makers, it is important to understand the poor accuracy of existing case definitions for influenza-like illness. This limits their ability to perform accurate disease surveillance. In fact, we found no studies reporting the accuracy of a case definition in a population of children only, yet clinicians and policy-makers in low-resource settings often rely on these case definitions in the absence of diagnostic testing to make clinical and policy decisions about the care of children with respiratory infections. Better case definitions are needed with evaluation in children and/or more widespread dissemination of point-of-care tests.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-067574</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xlink:href="bmjopen-15-3-s001.docx" id="d67e2367" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by Gates Ventures, Seattle, WA.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Prepublication history and additional supplemental material for this paper are available online. To view these files, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-067574" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-067574</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> Data are available from the authors on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> The Human Subjects Division (HSD) at the University of Washington (UW) in Seattle assessed this study under IRB ID STUDY00019018 and concluded that the study does not involve human subjects as defined by federal and state regulations, and human subjects were not asked for consent. Consequently, review and approval by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) at UW are not required for this study.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influenza-associated hospitalizations in the United States</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2004</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.292.11.1333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367555</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in the United States</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2003</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.289.2.179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517228</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Call</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shinholser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of oseltamivir in adults: a meta-analysis of published and unpublished clinical trials</article-title><source>Fam Pract</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/fampra/cms059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22997224</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doshi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Neuraminidase inhibitors for preventing and treating influenza in adults and children</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><elocation-id>CD008965</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD008965.pub4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24718923</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cals</surname><given-names>JWL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Current and future use of point-of-care tests in primary care: an international survey in Australia, Belgium, The Netherlands, the UK and the USA</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic>
</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e005611</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Call</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vollenweider</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Does this patient have influenza?</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2005</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.293.8.987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728170</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casault</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A Systematic Review of the History and Physical Examination to Diagnose Influenza</article-title><source>J Am Board Fam Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3122/jabfm.17.1.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A systematic review of clinical decision rules for the diagnosis of influenza</article-title><source>Ann Fam Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.1192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21242564</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2009</year><volume>339</volume><elocation-id>b2535</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.b2535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622551</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutjes</surname><given-names>AWS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>QUADAS-2: a revised tool for the quality assessment of diagnostic accuracy studies</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-155-8-201110180-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22007046</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fitzner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qasmieh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mounts</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Revision of clinical case definitions: influenza-like illness and severe acute respiratory infection</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ</source><year>2018</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.17.194514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29403115</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ruopp</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitcomb</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Youden Index and Optimal Cut&#x02010;Point Estimated from Observations Affected by a Lower Limit of Detection</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Biometrical J</italic>
</source><year>2008</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bimj.200710415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Okiyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sode</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Examining the Use of an Artificial Intelligence Model to Diagnose Influenza: Development and Validation Study</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>e38751</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/38751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36374004</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sreng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Touch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sovann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A description of influenza-like illness (ILI) sentinel surveillance in Cambodia, 2006-2008</article-title><source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20578488</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a clinical decision rule for the diagnosis of influenza</article-title><source>J Am Board Fam Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2012.01.110161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22218625</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahmatullah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A Systematic Review of Clinical Prediction Rules for the Diagnosis of Influenza</article-title><source>J Am Board Fam Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2021.06.210110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34772768</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nigrovic</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Use of population health data to refine diagnostic decision-making for pertussis</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Inform Assoc</italic>
</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1197/jamia.M3061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20064807</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Impact of a Rapid Point of Care Test for Influenza on Guideline Consistent Care and Antibiotic Use</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">J Am Board Fam Med</italic>
</source><year>2019</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2019.02.180183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30850459</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>Diagnostics</collab>
</person-group><source>cobas&#x000ae; SARS-CoV-2 &#x00026; Influenza A/B Assay</source><comment>Available</comment><ext-link xlink:href="https://diagnostics.roche.com/us/en/products/params/cobas-sars-cov-2-influenza-a-b-nucleic-acid-test.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://diagnostics.roche.com/us/en/products/params/cobas-sars-cov-2-influenza-a-b-nucleic-acid-test.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Commission implementing decision (EU) 2018/ 945 - of 22 June 2018 - on the communicable diseases and related special health issues to be covered by epidemiological surveillance as well as relevant case definitions:74</article-title></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prasarnphanich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The accuracy of clinical diagnosis of influenza in Thai children</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Infect Dis</italic>
</source><year>2010</year><volume>05</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JPI-2010-0244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McElhaney</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGeer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influenza surveillance case definitions miss a substantial proportion of older adults hospitalized with laboratory-confirmed influenza: A report from the Canadian Immunization Research Network (CIRN) Serious Outcomes Surveillance (SOS) Network</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/ice.2020.22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32146920</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aung</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The &#x0201c;timeless&#x0201d; use of influenza-like illness criteria for influenza detection in the tropics</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.03.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33741485</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barbara</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dolovich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A Comparison of Self-report and Health Care Provider Data to Assess Surveillance Definitions of Influenza-like Illness in Outpatients</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Can J Public Health</italic>
</source><year>2012</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03404072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22338332</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arinal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Performance of case definitions and clinical predictors for influenza surveillance among patients followed in a rural cohort in Senegal</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>31</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-05724-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33413174</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bellei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carraro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Patterns of influenza infections among different risk groups in Brazil</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Braz J Infect Dis</italic>
</source><year>2007</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1413-86702007000400005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873992</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BinSaeed</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Khedhairy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandil</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A validation study comparing the sensitivity and specificity of the new Dr. KSU H1N1 RT-PCR kit with real-time RT-PCR for diagnosing influenza A (H1N1)</article-title><source>Ann Saudi Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0256-4947.83212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21808109</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>BinSaeed</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandil</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The role of rapid testing and clinical decision in the diagnosis of human influenza A H1N1 infection</article-title><source>Saudi Med J</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24623208</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brouqui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vu Hai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nougairede</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Improving the diagnostic efficiency of H1N1 2009 pandemic flu: analysis of predictive clinical signs through a prospective cohort</article-title><source>PLoS Curr</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>RRN1120</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.rrn1120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20029658</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bruning</surname><given-names>AHL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Kruijf</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Weert</surname><given-names>HCPM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Respiratory Viruses in a Primary Health Care Facility in Amsterdam, the Netherlands</article-title><source>
<italic toggle="yes">Infect Dis Clin Pract</italic>
</source><year>2018</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/IPC.0000000000000604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tebruegge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papadakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical and microbiologic features associated with novel swine-origin influenza A pandemic 2009 (H1N1) virus in children: a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/INF.0b013e3181de4b9c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20458257</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heinzinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical symptoms cannot predict influenza infection during the 2013 influenza season in Bavaria, Germany</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>2016</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268815002228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26388141</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carrat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tachet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rouzioux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluation of clinical case definitions of influenza: detailed investigation of patients during the 1995-1996 epidemic in France</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>1999</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/515117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10064245</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Casalegno</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eibach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Performance of influenza case definitions for influenza community surveillance: based on the French influenza surveillance network GROG, 2009-2014</article-title><source>Euro Surveill</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2017.22.14.30504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wake</surname><given-names>ZV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical Predictors of Influenza in Young Children: The Limitations of &#x0201c;Influenza-Like Illness&#x0201d;</article-title><source>J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpids/pis081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26619439</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crum-Cianflone</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical and epidemiologic characteristics of an outbreak of novel H1N1 (swine origin) influenza A virus among United States military beneficiaries</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1801</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/648508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19911946</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Sensitivity and specificity of surveillance case definitions in detection of influenza and respiratory syncytial virus among hospitalized patients, New Zealand, 2012-2016</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2022</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2021.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34953903</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeMarcus</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soderlund</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Assessment of 12 influenza-like illness case definitions using Department of Defense Global, Laboratory-based Influenza Surveillance Program data, 2011-2014</article-title><source>MSMR</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valsamakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atreya</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical Diagnosis of Influenza in the Emergency Department</article-title><source>Am J Emerg Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25827595</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>LoVecchio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Derivation and Validation of a Clinical Decision Guideline for Influenza Testing in 4 US Emergency Departments</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciz171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30843056</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The early days of pandemic (H1N1) 2009 virus infection in the central region of Portugal</article-title><source>Rev Port Pneumol</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>870</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21067692</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sebeny</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klena</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influenza risk management: lessons learned from an A(H1N1) pdm09 outbreak investigation in an operational military setting</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e68639</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23874699</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Validity of clinical case definitions for influenza surveillance among hospitalized patients: results from a rural community in North India</article-title><source>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-2659.2012.00401.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22804843</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guzm&#x000e1;n-Esquivel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendoza-Cano</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trujillo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluating the performance of WHO and CDC case definitions for influenza-like illness in diagnosing influenza during the 2022-2023 flu season in Mexico</article-title><source>Public Health (Fairfax)</source><year>2023</year><volume>222</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2023.07.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hirve</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chadha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lele</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Performance of case definitions used for influenza surveillance among hospitalized patients in a rural area of India</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ</source><year>2012</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>804</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.12.108837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23226892</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hombrouck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sabbe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Casteren</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Viral aetiology of influenza-like illness in Belgium during the influenza A(H1N1)2009 pandemic</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-011-1398-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21901635</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C-A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Asymptomatic ratio for seasonal H1N1 influenza infection among schoolchildren in Taiwan</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>80</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-14-80</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24520993</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hulson</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mold</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheid</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Diagnosing influenza: the value of clinical clues and laboratory tests</article-title><source>J Fam Pract</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742606</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Developing and validating clinical features-based machine learning algorithms to predict influenza infection in influenza-like illness patients</article-title><source>Biomed J</source><year>2023</year><volume>46</volume><elocation-id>100561</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bj.2022.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36150651</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Performance of case definitions for influenza surveillance</article-title><source>Euro Surveill</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES2015.20.22.21145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wierzba</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sovann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluation of an influenza-like illness case definition in the diagnosis of influenza among patients with acute febrile illness in Cambodia</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>320</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-10-320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21054897</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical predictors of novel influenza A (H1N1)infection in Korea</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J</source><year>2010</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2010.51.6.895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20879057</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kotnik</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smedinghoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Flu@home: the Comparative Accuracy of an At-Home Influenza Rapid Diagnostic Test Using a Prepositioned Test Kit, Mobile App, Mail-in Reference Sample, and Symptom-Based Testing Trigger</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>60</volume><elocation-id>e02070-21</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.02070-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35107302</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P-P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Predictors of influenza among older adults in the emergency department</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>615</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-016-1966-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27793117</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badziklou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Landoh</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Implementation of influenza-like illness sentinel surveillance in Togo</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>981</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-14-981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25239536</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Royen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical prediction rules combining signs, symptoms and epidemiological context to distinguish influenza from influenza-like illnesses in primary care: a cross sectional study</article-title><source>BMC Fam Pract</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2296-12-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21306610</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monamele</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kengne-Nde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munshili Njifon</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical signs predictive of influenza virus infection in Cameroon</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e0236267</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0236267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32701976</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monto</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gravenstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical signs and symptoms predicting influenza infection</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>3243</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.160.21.3243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11088084</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinkoc</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>LG de O</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Lessons from the epidemiological surveillance program, during the influenza A (H1N1) virus epidemic, in a reference university hospital of Southeastern Brazil</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2011</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s0037-86822011005000048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21789355</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mulpuru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Influenza infection screening tools fail to accurately predict influenza status for patients during pandemic H1N1 influenza season</article-title><source>Can Respir J</source><year>2013</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>e55</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/762140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23762891</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khagayi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ope</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>What are the most sensitive and specific sign and symptom combinations for influenza in patients hospitalized with acute respiratory illness? Results from western Kenya, January 2007&#x02013;July 2010</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>2013</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S095026881200043X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22417876</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neuzil</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gorse</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Recognizing influenza in older patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease who have received influenza vaccine</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/345668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12522748</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ngobeni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tempia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The performance of different case definitions for severe influenza surveillance among HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected children aged &#x0003c;5 years in South Africa, 2011-2015</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e0222294</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31536552</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nitsch-Osuch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wozniak-Kosek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korzeniewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical features and outcomes of influenza A and B infections in children</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>788</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-6627-3_14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23835964</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ouchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Sangen&#x000ed;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moragas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical prediction of laboratory-confirmed influenza in adults with influenza-like illness in primary care. A randomized controlled trial secondary analysis in 15 European countries</article-title><source>Fam Pract</source><year>2022</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/fampra/cmab122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34611715</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Padin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brodine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Retrospective analysis of demographic and clinical factors associated with etiology of febrile respiratory illness among US military basic trainees</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>576</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-014-0576-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25475044</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Factors Associated With Influenza in an Emergency Department Setting</article-title><source>J Emerg Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jemermed.2018.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30803847</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puzelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valdarchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ciotti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Viral causes of influenza-like illness: Insight from a study during the winters 2004-2007</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2009</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>2066</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.21610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19856468</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawksworth</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kammerer</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of pathogen-specific respiratory infections among three US populations</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e114871</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25549089</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Vital sign predictors of severe influenza among children in an emergent care setting</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>e0272029</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0272029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35960719</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowlinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Comparison of common acute respiratory infection case definitions for identification of hospitalized influenza cases at a population-based surveillance site in Egypt</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e0248563</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0248563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33765010</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Favrat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Acremont</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>How critical is timing for the diagnosis of influenza in general practice?</article-title><source>Swiss Med Wkly</source><year>2005</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4414/smw.2005.11018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16402478</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shahid</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kleppinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical and immunologic predictors of influenza illness among vaccinated older adults</article-title><source>Vaccine (Auckl)</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>6145</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2010.07.036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Limper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Gorp</surname><given-names>ECM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Adult outpatient experience of the 2009 H1N1 pandemic: clinical course, pathogens, and evaluation of case definitions</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2011.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21420427</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flanders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Performance Characteristics of Clinical Diagnosis, a Clinical Decision Rule, and a Rapid Influenza Test in the Detection of Influenza Infection in a Community Sample of Adults</article-title><source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2005.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16271670</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van den Dool</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallinga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Symptoms of influenza virus infection in hospitalized patients</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/529211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18462143</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Vugt</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broekhuizen</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zuithoff</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Validity of a clinical model to predict influenza in patients presenting with symptoms of lower respiratory tract infection in primary care</article-title><source>Fam Pract</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/fampra/cmv039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045544</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vuichard-Gysin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mertz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pullenayegum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Development and validation of clinical prediction models to distinguish influenza from other viruses causing acute respiratory infections in children and adults</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e0212050</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30742654</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falsey</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical features of influenza A virus infection in older hospitalized persons</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1498</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1532-5415.2002.50404.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12383146</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woolpert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brodine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lemus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Determination of clinical and demographic predictors of laboratory-confirmed influenza with subtype analysis</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>129</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-12-129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676850</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shie</surname><given-names>S-S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Predictive Symptoms and Signs of Laboratory-confirmed Influenza: A Prospective Surveillance Study of Two Metropolitan Areas in Taiwan</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2015</year><volume>94</volume><elocation-id>e1952</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000001952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26554802</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zambon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of influenza in the community: relationship of clinical diagnosis to confirmed virological, serologic, or molecular detection of influenza</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>2116</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.161.17.2116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11570941</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zigman Suchsland</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahmatullah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluating an app-guided self-test for influenza: lessons learned for improving the feasibility of study designs to evaluate self-tests for respiratory viruses</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>617</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06314-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34187397</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balasubramani</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nowalk</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Classification and Regression Tree (CART) analysis to predict influenza in primary care patients</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>503</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-016-1839-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27659721</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available on reasonable request.</p></sec></back><sub-article id="sub-article1" article-type="aggregated-review-documents"><front-stub><title-group><article-title>Review Process File</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></pub-date></front-stub><body><fig id="d67e4611" position="anchor"><media xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-067574.reviewer_comments.pdf"/></fig></body></sub-article></article>