<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuroimage Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neuroimage: Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-9560</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35434691</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC9009824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-9560(21)00025-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynirp.2021.100027</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100027</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article(s) from the Special Issue on Null findings in basic, cognitive and clinical neuroscience studies; Edited by Dr. Gesa Hartwigsen</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcranial magnetic stimulation of right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex does not affect associative retrieval in healthy young or older adults</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Paul F.</given-names></name><email>paulhill@arizona.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>Erin D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Koen</surname><given-names>Joshua D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>Michael D.</given-names></name><email>mrugg@utdallas.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Center for Vital Longevity, University of Texas at Dallas, Dallas, TX, 75235, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Psychology, University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, IN, 46556, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Psychology, University of East Anglica, Norwich, NR4 7TJ, UK</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>paulhill@arizona.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Center for Vital Longevity, University of Texas at Dallas, Dallas, TX, 75235, USA. <email>mrugg@utdallas.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">PFH is now at the Department of Psychology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>2</label><p id="ntpara0015">EDH is now at the Center for Brain Health, University of Texas at Dallas, Dallas, TX 75235.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>100027</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We examined whether post-retrieval monitoring processes supporting memory performance are more resource limited in older adults than younger individuals. We predicted that older adults would be more susceptible to an experimental manipulation that reduced the neurocognitive resources available to support post-retrieval monitoring. Young and older adults received transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) to the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) or a vertex control site during an associative recognition task. The right DLPFC was selected as a TMS target because the region is held to be a key member of a network of regions engaged during retrieval monitoring and is readily accessible to administration of TMS. We predicted that TMS to the right DLPFC would lead to reduced associative recognition accuracy, and that this effect would be more prominent in older adults. The results did not support this prediction. Recognition accuracy was significantly reduced in older adults relative to their younger counterparts, but the magnitude of this age difference was unaffected following TMS to the right DLPFC or vertex. These findings suggest that TMS to the right DLPFC was insufficient to deplete the neurocognitive resources necessary to support post-retrieval monitoring.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Episodic memory</kwd><kwd>Recognition</kwd><kwd>Retrieval monitoring</kwd><kwd>Dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</kwd><kwd>Transcranial magnetic stimulation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Episodic memory, or the ability to recollect specific details about a unique event, declines with advancing age (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Koen and Yonelinas, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Nilsson, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Old and Naveh-Benjamin, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Schoemaker et al., 2014</xref>). Successful recollection is assumed to rely on multiple, interacting cognitive processes (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Eichenbaum et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Yonelinas, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Rugg and Wilding, 2000</xref> for review). Here, we focus on processes held to be engaged during evaluation of the outcome of a retrieval attempt, or <italic>post-retrieval monitoring</italic>. Specifically, we examined whether older adults are more vulnerable to an experimental manipulation that was hypothesized to reduce the resources available for post-retrieval monitoring. To address this question, we used transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) to temporarily deplete cognitive resources dependent on the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) &#x02013; a region held to be a key member of the brain network supporting monitoring &#x02013; during an associative retrieval task.</p><p id="p0015">Post-retrieval monitoring refers to a class of control processes engaged to evaluate the outcome of a retrieval attempt in relation to a behavioral goal (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Burgess and Shallice, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Rugg, 2004</xref>). For example, when asked to remember one's most recent trip to a favorite restaurant, several competing memories are likely brought to mind. Accurate retrieval requires the selection and maintenance of the appropriate retrieval goal (e.g., memory for the most recent visit), and then the monitoring and evaluation of retrieved content in light of this goal (e.g., discriminating between memories for the most recent and prior visits; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Rugg and Wilding, 2000</xref>). Importantly, post-retrieval monitoring is widely assumed to be supported by domain-general executive control processes which are shared with other cognitive operations (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Cocci et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Duncan, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hayama et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hayama and Rugg, 2009</xref>). We therefore predicted that behavioral outcomes associated with successful monitoring would be impaired by experimental manipulations aimed at interfering with these domain-general processes.</p><p id="p0020">Neuropsychological studies of patients with lesions of the prefrontal cortex (PFC) were among the first to provide a neurobiological basis for post-retrieval monitoring. Compared to healthy control subjects, patients with frontal lesions showed elevated false alarm rates on tests of recognition memory, a finding held to be diagnostic of monitoring failure (Burgess &#x00026; Shallice; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Schacter et al., 1996</xref>). Concordant with these early findings, more recent studies using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) have consistently reported retrieval &#x02018;monitoring effects&#x02019; &#x02013; operationalized as enhanced brain activity elicited by weak relative to strong memory signals for correctly remembered study items &#x02013; in right and, to a lesser extent, left DLPFC as well as in the anterior cingulate cortex (e.g. <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Achim and Lepage, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Henson et al., 1999</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">The executive control processes assumed to support post-retrieval monitoring are generally considered highly vulnerable to advancing age (e.g., <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Braver and Barch, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Buckner, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Grady, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Hedden and Gabrieli, 2004</xref>). However, only a handful of studies have contrasted fMRI retrieval monitoring effects between healthy young and older adults. The findings from these studies are mixed, with some studies reporting a null effect of age (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dulas and Duarte, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Giovanello et al., 2010</xref>; Wang et al., 2015), and others reporting attenuated monitoring effects in older relative to young adults (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Duarte et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">McDonough et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2013</xref>; see Horne et al., 2020 for detailed discussion of these discrepant findings). Of importance, correlations between frontal monitoring effects and memory performance have been reported to be both highly robust and age invariant (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>), suggesting that age does not moderate the functional relationship between the effects and memory accuracy.</p><p id="p0030">Recently, we (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>) proposed that a key factor determining whether age differences are observed in the capacity to effectively engage retrieval monitoring is the availability of the neurocognitive resources required to support monitoring operations. According to the CRUNCH model (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Reuter-Lorenz and Cappell, 2008</xref>), for example, recruitment of task-related neural resources will track task demands until a resource limit is reached, at which point (the &#x02018;crunch point&#x02019;) task performance will suffer. According to this model, older adults will reach this resource limit at lower levels of task demand than will young adults. Thus, it is possible that in prior studies where age-invariant prefrontal monitoring effects were reported (e.g., <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>), task demands were such that monitoring did not run up against a resource limit in either young or older participants. One limitation of the neuropsychological and neuroimaging findings described above is that they are inherently correlational in nature. By contrast, TMS provides a viable means for addressing the causal relationship between brain and behavior and has emerged as a useful tool for modulating episodic memory (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Widhalm and Rose, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Yeh and Rose, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0035">Building off the hypothesis outlined in the preceding paragraph, we reasoned that older adults would be more susceptible than their younger counterparts to an experimental manipulation that reduced the neurocognitive resources available to support post-retrieval monitoring &#x02013; that is, they would be more likely to reach their &#x02018;crunch point&#x02019;. We predicted this would manifest behaviorally as attenuated recollection accuracy in older adults. To this aim, we used TMS to temporarily disrupt the right DLPFC with the objective of reducing the neurocognitive resources available to support post-retrieval monitoring. Young and older adults studied visually presented word pairs followed by an associative recognition task. Offline TMS was administered to the right DLPFC or a control site (vertex) immediately prior to the retrieval phase. The right DLPFC was selected as the TMS target as the region has been previously reported to give rise to robust age-invariant retrieval monitoring effects in fMRI studies (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>) and is readily accessible to administration of TMS.</p><p id="p0040">Test items on the associative recognition test comprised pairs of &#x02018;intact&#x02019; (studied together), &#x02018;rearranged&#x02019; (studied on different trials), and &#x02018;new&#x02019; (unstudied) word pairs. Word pairs endorsed as rearranged are thought to impose heavier demands on retrieval monitoring than word pairs endorsed as intact, because of the need to resolve the conflict between the familiarity of the individual test items and the novelty of the item association (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>; see also <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Achim and Lepage, 2005</xref>). We predicted that TMS administered to the right DLPFC would lead to reduced associative recognition accuracy. As discussed previously, we believed the negative impacts of DLPFC stimulation would be most prominent in older adults by virtue of their being closer to the &#x02018;crunch point&#x02019; for monitoring than younger adults. We further predicted that the effect would be driven largely by an increase in associative false alarms (rearranged pairs incorrectly endorsed as intact), under the assumption that rearranged items impose a heavier monitoring demand and hence are more vulnerable to the consequences of a monitoring failure (cf. <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Schacter et al., 1996</xref>). In addition, we anticipated that TMS administered to the right DLPFC might affect the response times (RT) associated with associative false alarms, and that this effect would be more pronounced in older adults. We were however agnostic as to the direction of any potential RT effects. One possibility is that the reduction of resources available to support retrieval monitoring will lead to a truncation of monitoring, and hence to faster RTs than those in the control condition (cf. <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>). Alternately, participants might attempt to compensate for the relative lack of resources by prolonging the engagement of monitoring processes, leading to a relative slowing of RTs.</p><sec id="sec1"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec1.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Participants</title><p id="p0045">Twenty-one healthy young adults and 18 healthy older adults volunteered and were monetarily compensated $30/hour for their time. All participants were right-handed, had normal or corrected-to-normal vision, and spoke fluent English before the age of five. Each participant had a structural MRI scan available from participation in a prior fMRI study. Self-reported TMS exclusion criteria followed safety guidelines (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Rossi et al., 2009</xref>) and included potential pregnancy, prior or current neurological illness, current use of psychoactive medications, prior head injury or concussion, history of severe headaches/migraines, a personal or family history of seizure or epilepsy, and current use of prescription or over-the-counter medications associated with an increased risk of seizure. Additionally, prior to undergoing TMS, all participants acknowledged that they had not consumed alcohol in the previous 24&#x000a0;h. One young adult and two older adults voluntarily withdrew from the study prior to completing all cycles of the TMS protocol and their data were dropped from subsequent analyses. This resulted in a final sample of 20 healthy young adults (mean age: 23.5 years, range: 19&#x02013;30 years, 12 female) and 16 healthy older adults (mean age: 69.6 years, range: 65&#x02013;75 years, 6 female).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Neuropsychological testing</title><p id="p0050">All participants completed a neuropsychological test battery on a separate day consisting of the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), the California Verbal Learning Test-II (CVLT; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Delis et al., 2000</xref>), Wechsler Logical Memory Tests 1 and 2 (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 2009</xref>), Trail Making tests A and B (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Reitan and Wolfson, 1985</xref>), the Symbol Digit Modalities test (SDMT; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 1982</xref>), the F-A-S subtest of the Neurosensory Center Comprehensive Evaluation for Aphasia (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Spreen and Benton, 1977</xref>), the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale&#x02013;Revised subtests of forward and backward digit span (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 1981</xref>), category fluency (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Benton, 1968</xref>), and Raven's Progressive Matrices (List 1, Raven et al., 2000). In addition, participants completed the Wechsler Test of Adult Reading (WTAR, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 2001</xref>) or its revised version, the Wechsler Test of Premorbid Functioning (TOPF; <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 2011</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">Participants were excluded from entry into the study if they scored &#x0003c;27 on the MMSE, &#x0003c; 1.5 SDs below age-appropriate norms on any memory test, &#x0003c; 1.5 SDs below age norms on any two other tests, or if their estimated full-scale IQ was less than 100. These criteria were employed to minimize the likelihood of including individuals with mild cognitive impairment. Results from the neuropsychological test battery are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Note that the pattern of scores is typical of that reported for cross-sectional studies of cognitively healthy young and older adults (e.g., <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>), with higher scores for the young adults on tests involving episodic memory, processing speed, and fluid intelligence.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and mean (with SD) neuropsychological test scores.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Younger Adults</th><th>Older Adults</th><th><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">16</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex (M/F)</td><td align="left">8/12</td><td align="left">10/6</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="left">23.11 (4.01)</td><td align="left">69.63 (3.07)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">Years of education</td><td align="left">15.26 (1.91)</td><td align="left">16.88 (2.80)</td><td align="left">.062</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MMSE</td><td align="left">28.40 (3.45)</td><td align="left">28.94 (1.00)</td><td align="left">.515</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVLT Short Delay - Free</td><td align="left">13.80 (4.38)</td><td align="left">10.94 (3.04)</td><td align="left">.027*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVLT Short Delay - Cued</td><td align="left">12.80 (3.04)</td><td align="left">12.56 (2.53)</td><td align="left">.800</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVLT Long Delay - Free</td><td align="left">12.98 (3.32)</td><td align="left">11.38 (2.87)</td><td align="left">.131</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVLT Long Delay - Cued</td><td align="left">13.08 (3.20)</td><td align="left">12.31 (2.44)</td><td align="left">.424</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVLT Recognition - Hits</td><td align="left">14.98 (3.22)</td><td align="left">15.25 (.93)</td><td align="left">.720</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CVLT Recognition - False Alarms</td><td align="left">0.73 (1.41)</td><td align="left">2.50 (2.63)</td><td align="left">.024*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Logical Memory I</td><td align="left">32.00 (8.16)</td><td align="left">30.06 (5.58)</td><td align="left">.405</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Logical Memory II</td><td align="left">28.50 (6.15)</td><td align="left">27.19 (5.36)</td><td align="left">.499</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SDMT</td><td align="left">60.75 (15.43)</td><td align="left">50.5 (8.08)</td><td align="left">.016*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Digit Span</td><td align="left">19.30 (4.12)</td><td align="left">18.50 (2.88)</td><td align="left">.498</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Trails A</td><td align="left">20.53 (8.08)</td><td align="left">26.73 (9.27)</td><td align="left">.040*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Trails B</td><td align="left">44.45 (13.03)</td><td align="left">63.55 (22.98)</td><td align="left">.007*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F-A-S</td><td align="left">46.43 (17.82)</td><td align="left">48.06 (12.61)</td><td align="left">.749</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Category Fluency (Animals)</td><td align="left">24.65 (6.48)</td><td align="left">22.25 (4.43)</td><td align="left">.197</td></tr><tr><td align="left">WTAR/TOPF<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left">114.94 (5.40)</td><td align="left">114.81 (8.67)</td><td align="left">.959</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Raven's (List 1)</td><td align="left">10.95 (.91)</td><td align="left">8.94 (1.88)</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;.001*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Note</italic>: Significant differences between age groups are denoted by an asterisk. <sup>1</sup>Presented as a standardized score computed from WTAR and TOPF raw scores. MMSE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Mini-Mental State Examination; CVLT = California Verbal Learning Test; SDMT = Symbol Digit Modalities Test; WTAR = Wechsler Test for Adult Reading; TOPF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Wechsler Test of Premorbid Functioning.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><label>2.3</label><title>MRI acquisition and preprocessing</title><p id="p0060">MRI data were acquired with a 3T Philips Achieva MRI scanner (Philips Medical Systems, Andover, MA, USA) equipped with a 32-channel receiver head coil. T1-weighted structural images (MPRAGE sequence, 240&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;240 matrix, 1&#x000a0;mm isotropic voxels) were acquired. Each T1 image was normalized to an independent sample-specific template derived from 36 young and 64 older adult T1 images using Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM12) software. The transformation matrix was then used to back-project a DLPFC ROI into each participant's native space using neuronavigation software (see TMS procedure).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Associative memory task</title><p id="p0065">The experiment proper consisted of two study-test cycles corresponding to the right DLPFC and vertex TMS stimulation conditions, the order of which was counterbalanced across participants.</p><sec id="sec1.4.1"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Stimuli</title><p id="p0070">Cogent 2000 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vislab.ucl.ac.uk/cogent.php" id="intref0010">www.vislab.ucl.ac.uk/cogent.php</ext-link>) implemented in Matlab (2012b) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mathworks.com" id="intref0015">www.mathworks.com</ext-link>) was used for stimulus presentation and response collection. The stimuli were presented on a 30&#x0201d; Dell LCD monitor with a screen resolution of 1024&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;768 pixels at a viewing distance of ~100&#x000a0;cm. All critical stimuli for the study and test phases were presented in white Helvetica 30-point font on a black background. Study and test items subtended a vertical visual angle of 2.7&#x000b0; and a maximum horizontal visual angle of 6.2&#x000b0;.</p><p id="p0075">Experimental stimuli comprised 240 semantically unrelated word pairs (see Supplemental Materials). All words were concrete nouns between three and nine letters in length, with a mean frequency per million of 8.28 (SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;31.69, range 0.04&#x02013;479.92) obtained from the SUBTLEX-US corpus (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Brysbaert and New, 2009</xref>). Concreteness ratings ranged between 3 and 5 (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.67, <italic>SD</italic> = .29) on a scale from 1 (most abstract) to 5 (most concrete) (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Brysbaert et al., 2014</xref>). Separate stimulus lists were created for yoked young and older adult pairs. Two sets of 90 randomly selected word pairs served as the critical stimuli for the study phase. An additional two sets of 120 word pairs served as the critical stimuli for the test phase. Each test list included 60 &#x02018;intact&#x02019; pairs (words presented together at study), 30 &#x02018;rearranged&#x02019; pairs (words presented on different trials at study), and 30 &#x02018;new&#x02019; pairs (words not encountered at study). All test pairs were inspected by the second author to ensure they were not semantically related. Study and tests lists were assigned to one of the two TMS stimulation conditions (right DLPFC, vertex). An additional 24 word pairs were used as practice stimuli. The practice study phase comprised 18 word pairs, and the practice test phase comprised 24 pairs (12 &#x02018;intact&#x02019; pairs, 6 &#x02018;rearranged&#x02019; pairs, and 6 &#x02018;new&#x02019; pairs).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.4.2"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Study phase</title><p id="p0080">Word pairs were presented for a duration of 2000&#x000a0;ms and were preceded by a red fixation cross for 500&#x000a0;ms. The presentation of each word pair was followed by a white fixation cross for 1000&#x000a0;ms, giving a response window of 3000&#x000a0;ms per trial. The study phase for each TMS stimulation condition (DLPFC, vertex) was administered as a single block and lasted approximately 6&#x000a0;min (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A for task schematic). Encoding was intentional, as participants were aware of the subsequent associative recognition test and trained on both study and test phases before beginning the experiment. Study words were presented simultaneously, one above and one below fixation. The task was to judge which of the two objects denoted by the words would more likely &#x02018;fit&#x02019; into the other and to respond via a button press. To encourage relational encoding of the word pairs, participants were instructed to focus on imagining a scenario (constructing a vivid visual image or verbal story) to determine which item would fit into the other. Participants were instructed to respond as quickly as possible without sacrificing accuracy.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(a) Timing and schematic of the associative memory task. (b) Depiction of the TMS target ROIs in the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (red) and vertex (yellow) overlaid on an age-invariant retrieval monitoring contrast from de Chastelaine et al. (2016; thresholded at <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05 FWE corrected).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec1.4.3"><label>2.4.3</label><title>Test phase</title><p id="p0085">The test phase began approximately 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;min after completion of the study phase, immediately following the TMS procedure. Word pairs during the test phase were presented for a duration of 2000&#x000a0;ms and were preceded by a red fixation cross for 500&#x000a0;ms. The presentation of each word pair was followed by a white fixation cross for 2000&#x000a0;ms, giving a response window of 4000&#x000a0;ms per trial. The test phase for each TMS stimulation condition (DLPFC, vertex) was administered as a single block and lasted approximately 8&#x000a0;min (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). Test words were presented simultaneously, one above and one below fixation.</p><p id="p0090">For the associative memory task, participants were required to judge whether each word pair was &#x02018;intact&#x02019;, &#x02018;rearranged&#x02019;, or &#x02018;new&#x02019;. Participants were instructed to respond &#x02018;intact&#x02019; when they could recall with high confidence and specificity that the two items had been studied together, and to respond &#x02018;rearranged&#x02019; when the words were recognized as having been studied but there was either no memory of the words having been studied together, or the memory was uncertain. Participants were informed that the test list did not include mixed pairs of new and studied words. They were however instructed to respond &#x02018;new&#x02019; whenever they could recognize only one of the words as studied, or when both words were judged to be unstudied. Participants again indicated their responses via a button press; they were instructed to respond as quickly as possible without sacrificing accuracy.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec1.5"><label>2.5</label><title>TMS procedure</title><sec id="sec1.5.1"><label>2.5.1</label><title>Equipment and co-registration</title><p id="p0095">TMS was delivered using a Magstim Super Rapid2 stimulator equipped with a 70-mm figure-of-eight coil. Frameless stereotaxy was used to co-register participants to their MRI scans and to align the coil over the target stimulation sites using Brainsight (Rogue Research; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rogue-research.com/" id="intref0020">www.rogue-research.com/</ext-link>) software equipped with a Polaris infrared camera. During co-registration and TMS, each participant's head was stabilized with a padded headrest to minimize movement.</p><p id="p0100">Four anatomical landmarks were identified on the skin reconstruction of a participant's MRI scan: nasion, nose tip, and bilateral pre-auricular points. The nose tip was excluded if it was outside of the field-of-view of the structural MRI, leaving only three points for co-registration. Co-registration was performed by identifying the relevant anatomical landmarks on the participant's head using a pointer; this allowed us to track the location of the coil in real-time relative to the ROIs targeted for stimulation for each participant. Reflective markers attached to the TMS coil and each participant's head (via an elastic velcro strap) were used to monitor coil position and head location, respectively, using the infrared camera.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.5.2"><label>2.5.2</label><title>Motor threshold</title><p id="p0105">After obtaining informed consent and immediately prior to delivering the task instructions and practice trials, a motor threshold was determined for each participant using single pulse TMS (up to 70% maximum stimulator output) over the left motor cortex (visually identified on the structural MRI) using a procedure identical to that described in detail by <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Koen et al. (2018)</xref>. In brief, a motor threshold was defined as the lowest stimulator intensity that produced visible muscle contractions in the right hand in 5 out of 10 pulses. In a subset of participants (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15; nine young and six older adults), motor threshold was estimated with motor evoked potentials (MEPs) in lieu of visible contractions. The switch from MEPs to visual detection was necessitated by technical issues with the MEPs recording equipment. A <italic>t</italic>-test revealed that the mean motor threshold derived from the motor evoked potentials (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;67%, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8%) was significantly greater than the mean motor threshold derived from the visible contractions approach (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;59%, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6%) (<italic>t</italic><sub>(16.76)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.74, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.014). It is not immediately clear why motor thresholds were higher when recorded using the MEPs procedure (c.f. <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Westin et al., 2014</xref>). One possible source of this discrepancy was in the use of MEPs to measure evoked responses specifically in the first dorsal interosseous muscle, whereas the visible twitch procedure included motion from the entire right hand and wrist. It is also possible that this difference in motor thresholds was a consequence of restricting stimulation intensity to 70% of maximum stimulator output threshold. We further address this difference below (see 3. Results).</p><p id="p0110">The mean motor threshold was 62% (SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8%) of maximum stimulator output in younger adults and 65% (SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5%) in older adults. Stimulator intensity for continuous theta-burst stimulation (cTBS, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2005</xref>; see below) was set nominally at 80% of motor threshold with the constraint that it never exceeded 45% of maximum stimulator output. This constraint was due to a hardware limitation of the Rapid2 stimulator. Thus, cTBS threshold was set at 45% for participants in whom no motor response was identified, or if 80% of the identified motor thresholds were above the 45% cutoff. As a result of these constraints, cTBS intensity was set at the 45% maximum stimulator output in 17 of 20 younger adults and all older adults. The resultant cTBS intensity in young (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44%, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2%) and older (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;45%) adults did not significantly differ between the two age groups (<italic>t</italic><sub>(19)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.75, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.096). The mean percentage of motor thresholds obtained in young (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;72%, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7%) and older (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;69%, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5%) adults after accounting for hardware limitations did not significantly differ between the two age groups (<italic>t</italic><sub>(21.96)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;1.17, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.253).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.5.3"><label>2.5.3</label><title>Stimulation protocol</title><p id="p0115">Offline cTBS was delivered to either the right DLPFC or vertex target <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">(Fig. 1B)</xref> immediately following each study phase and hence prior to the beginning of the succeeding test phase. The cTBS protocol involved delivering 50&#x000a0;Hz trains of three TMS pulses every 200&#x000a0;ms for 40&#x000a0;s (600 total pulses) at 80% resting motor threshold (see above). Similar cTBS protocols have been employed to suppress cortical excitability in prior studies of episodic memory (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Berkers et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bonnici et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Marin et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Ryals et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Yazar et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The order of the DLPFC and vertex targets was counterbalanced across subjects. The right DLPFC target (MNI coordinates: x&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;48, y&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;32, z&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;28) was the same as that defined in a previously published experiment using the associative memory design (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>). The vertex was selected for the control stimulation condition (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Koen et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Sandrini et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Thakral et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Yazar et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), and was identified in each participant as the intersection between the central sulcus and longitudinal fissure. The TMS coil was oriented such that the coil handle was angled approximately 45&#x000b0; (right DLPFC condition) or parallel (vertex condition) with the longitudinal fissure.</p><p id="p0120">A 45-min stimulation &#x02018;washout&#x02019; period separated the end of the first cTBS session with the beginning of the second study-test cycle to allow any residual stimulation effects to dissipate (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2005</xref>). This resulted in approximately 60&#x000a0;min separating the respective cTBS sessions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec1.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="p0125">Statistical analyses were carried out using R software (R Core Team, 2017). ANOVAs were conducted using the <italic>afex</italic> package (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Singmann et al., 2016</xref>) and the Greenhouse-Geisser procedure (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Greenhouse and Geisser, 1959</xref>) was used to correct degrees of freedom for non-sphericity when necessary. Post-hoc tests on significant effects from the ANOVAs were conducted using the <italic>emmeans</italic> package (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Lenth, 2018</xref>). Results were considered significant at <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05. We also report results from Bayesian repeated-measures ANOVAs using JASP software (version 0.13.1.0). Specifically, we computed Bayes Factors (BF) corresponding to evidence in favor of the null hypothesis relative to alternative models for the effects of interest (e.g., the age x TMS target interaction contrasts). We report these values as BF<sub>01</sub>, with values&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1 indicating relatively greater evidence favoring the null hypothesis. The BF<sub>01</sub> values for ANOVA main effects and interactions were computed using the &#x02018;BF Inclusion&#x02019; values output by JASP with the &#x02018;Across Matched Models&#x02019; option. Bayes factors are interpreted using the categorical labels proposed by <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Jeffreys (1961)</xref>: BF<sub>01</sub> values between 1 and 3 correspond to anecdotal evidence, values between 3 and 10 correspond to moderate evidence, and values between 10 and 30 correspond to strong evidence in favor of the null hypothesis.</p><p id="p0130">A summary of associative memory performance and median RTs for each age group and TMS target is shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The proportion of &#x02018;intact&#x02019;, &#x02018;rearranged&#x02019;, and &#x02018;new&#x02019; test responses for each of the different pair types is reported in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The critical trials used in the following analyses included associative hits (intact pairs correctly endorsed as intact), associative misses (intact pairs incorrectly endorsed as rearranged), and associative false alarms (rearranged pairs incorrectly endorsed as intact). Estimates of recollection accuracy (pR) were indexed as the difference between the proportion of associative hits and associative false alarms (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>) using the formula:<disp-formula id="ufd1"><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mean (with SD) of associative memory performance and median RT as a function of age group and TMS target.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Measure<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Younger<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Older<hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th>DLPFC</th><th>Vertex</th><th>DLPFC</th><th>Vertex</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Recollection (pR)</td><td align="left">.54 (.15)</td><td align="left">.51 (.21)</td><td align="left">.28 (.16)</td><td align="left">.28 (.15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Familiarity (pF)</td><td align="left">.51 (.19)</td><td align="left">.52 (.23)</td><td align="left">.48 (.15)</td><td align="left">.49 (.14)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Associative False Alarm Rate</td><td align="left">.12 (.10)</td><td align="left">.11 (.10)</td><td align="left">.30 (.16)</td><td align="left">.29 (.15)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left"><italic>Median RTs</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Associative Hits</td><td align="left">1613 (301)</td><td align="left">1584 (231)</td><td align="left">1927 (512)</td><td align="left">1919 (427)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Associative False Alarms</td><td align="left">1825 (295)</td><td align="left">1967 (435)</td><td align="left">2078 (522)</td><td align="left">2004 (469)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mean proportion (with SD) of responses to intact, rearranged, and new test pairs as a function of age group and TMS target.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Trial Type<hr/></th><th>Response<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Younger<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Older<hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th/><th>DLPFC</th><th>Vertex</th><th>DLPFC</th><th>Vertex</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Intact</td><td align="left">Intact</td><td align="left">.66 (.14)</td><td align="left">.62 (.19)</td><td align="left">.58 (.20)</td><td align="left">.56 (.19)</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Rearranged</td><td align="left">.21 (.10)</td><td align="left">.22 (.11)</td><td align="left">.30 (.17)</td><td align="left">.30 (.16)</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">New</td><td align="left">.13 (.09)</td><td align="left">.16 (.12)</td><td align="left">.13 (.06)</td><td align="left">.14 (.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rearranged</td><td align="left">Intact</td><td align="left">.12 (.10)</td><td align="left">.11 (.10)</td><td align="left">.30 (.16)</td><td align="left">.29 (.15)</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Rearranged</td><td align="left">.69 (.16)</td><td align="left">.63 (.18)</td><td align="left">.49 (.14)</td><td align="left">.49 (.18)</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">New</td><td align="left">.19 (.14)</td><td align="left">.26 (.14)</td><td align="left">.21 (.11)</td><td align="left">.23 (.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">New</td><td align="left">Intact</td><td align="left">.01 (.02)</td><td align="left">.01 (.03)</td><td align="left">.03 (.05)</td><td align="left">.04 (.04)</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">Rearranged</td><td align="left">.12 (.08)</td><td align="left">.11 (.11)</td><td align="left">.18 (.13)</td><td align="left">.17 (.13)</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">New</td><td align="left">.87 (.09)</td><td align="left">.88 (.12)</td><td align="left">.79 (.15)</td><td align="left">.80 (.13)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0135">Estimates of familiarity strength (pF) were estimated under the independence assumption (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Yonelinas and Jacoby, 1995</xref>) using the formula:<disp-formula id="ufd2"><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0140">Estimates of recollection (pR) and familiarity (pF) were entered into separate 2 (age group: younger, older) x 2 (TMS target: DLPFC, vertex) ANOVAs. There was a significant main effect of age on pR (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;23.36, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .41, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002) which was driven by reduced recollection accuracy in older adults relative to their younger counterparts (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). The main effect of TMS target on pR was not significant (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.47, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.498, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .01, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.23), nor was there a significant age x TMS target interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.50, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.484, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .01, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.63). The analysis of pF failed to reject the null hypothesis for the main effects of age (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.31, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.579, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .009, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.5) and TMS target (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.17, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.679, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .005, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.70), or the age x TMS target interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.902, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .001, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.45) <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">(Fig. 2B)</xref>.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Estimates of (a) recollection, (b) familiarity, and (c) false alarm rates for the DLPFC and vertex targets in young and older adults. Error bars reflect the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0145">An ANOVA performed on the proportions of associative false alarms (see Introduction) revealed a significant main effect of age (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20.54, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .38, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004) which was driven by an elevated false alarm rate in older relative to young adults <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">(Fig. 2C)</xref>. The main effect of TMS target was not significant (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.80, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.378, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .02, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.94), nor was there a significant age x TMS target interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,34)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.902, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .001, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.03).</p><p id="p0150">To investigate the effect of TMS condition on retrieval response times, we entered the median test phase RTs for associative hits and associative false alarms into a 2 (age) x 2 (TMS target) x 2 (memory: hit, false alarm) ANOVA. This analysis revealed a modest but significant three-way interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,29)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.77, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.037, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .14, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.09). To unpack these results, we performed subsidiary 2 (age) x 2 (memory) ANOVAs on test phase RTs for the right DLPFC and vertex TMS conditions, respectively <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">(Fig. 3)</xref>. The analysis of RTs in the right DLPFC condition revealed a significant main effect of age (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,32)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.32, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.046, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .12, BF<sub>01</sub> = .74) which was driven by faster RTs for young compared to older adults, as well as a main effect of memory response (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,32)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;17.89, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.0002, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .36, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01) which was driven by faster RTs for associative hits compared to associative false alarms. The age&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;response interaction was not significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.233, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .04, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.33). An analogous analysis of RTs in the vertex condition revealed a significant age&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;memory interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,29)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.88, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.002, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = .29, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.07) which was driven by significantly faster RTs for hits compared to false alarms in young adults (<italic>t</italic><sub>(29)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.35, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.0001, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.04) but not older adults (<italic>t</italic><sub>(29)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.36, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.186, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.5).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Median test phase response times (RTs) for associative hits and associative false alarms for young and older adults in (a) right DLPFC and (b) vertex TMS target conditions. Error bars reflect the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0155">We performed a final set of analyses to rule out the possibility that the TMS manipulation may have been confounded by methodological factors. Turning first to differences in resting motor thresholds described in section &#x02018;2.5.2. Motor Threshold&#x02019;, we performed 2 (age) x 2 (TMS target) x 2 (MT method: MEPs, Visual Inspection) ANOVAs separately for the three primary measures of associative memory performance (pR, pF, and FA). For each measure, the main effect of MT method was non-significant (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.1, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1), and nor were any of the two- or three-way interaction terms involving MT method significant (<italic>ps</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.2, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1.43). We thus found no evidence that differences in motor threshold arising from the different measurement methods significantly moderated the TMS target manipulations.</p><p id="p0160">The cTBS washout period between study-test cycles was ~60&#x000a0;min. To rule out that residual cTBS effects from the first study-test cycle may have confounded performance on the second cycle, we performed 2 (age) x 2 (TMS target) x 2 (stimulation order: DLPFC first, vertex first) ANOVAs separately on each of the memory performance measures. The analysis of recollection accuracy (pR) revealed a significant, albeit modest, main effect of stimulation order (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,32)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.28, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.047, partial-&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.12, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.51) which was driven by greater recollection accuracy among participants receiving stimulation to the vertex first (<italic>M</italic> = .46, <italic>SD</italic> = .17) compared to those receiving stimulation to the DLPFC first (<italic>M</italic> = .35, <italic>SD</italic> = .15). All two- and three-way interactions involving stimulation order were non-significant (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.1, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1.43). We thus found no evidence that the order in which cTBS was applied to the respective targets moderated the magnitude of TMS or age effects on recollection accuracy. Turning to the analyses of familiarity strength and associative false alarms, the main effects of stimulation order were not significant (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.3, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1.43), nor did we observe any significant two- or three-way interactions involving stimulation order (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.1, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1).</p><p id="p0165">Another possibility is that residual effects of cTBS began to wear off over the course of the test phase. To assess this possibility, we split the test phase into early (trials 1&#x02013;60) and late (trials 61&#x02013;120) epochs. We then performed 2 (age) x 2 (TMS target) x 2 (test epoch: early, late) ANOVAs for each of the associative memory measures. In all cases, the main effect of test epoch was not significant (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.2, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1), and nor were any of the two- and three-way interactions involving test epoch significant (<italic>p</italic>s&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;.06, BF<sub>01</sub>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.65).</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0170">In the present study, we investigated whether healthy older adults were more vulnerable than younger adults to an experimental manipulation that was intended to reduce the availability of neurocognitive resources associated with post-retrieval monitoring. To this aim, we delivered offline TMS to the right DLPFC and a control site (vertex) immediately prior to completion of an associative recognition test. Collapsed across the two TMS target conditions, recognition accuracy was significantly lower in older relative to young adults. By contrast, estimates of familiarity strength did not reliably differ between the two age groups. This pattern of results is consistent with numerous prior findings of attenuated recollection accompanied by relatively preserved familiarity in healthy older adults (e.g., <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>; for review, see <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Koen and Yonelinas, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Schoemaker et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0175">We predicted that TMS administered to the right DLPFC would lead to reduced associative recognition accuracy, and that this effect would be more prominent in older adults. We also predicted that the effect would be driven largely by an increase in associative false alarms. Our results however provide no evidence that TMS administered to the right DLPFC had any impact on associative recognition accuracy in either age group. These null results were supported by Bayes Factors indicating anecdotal (BF<sub>01</sub> values between 1 and 3) to moderate (values between 3 and 10) evidence in favor of a null effect of TMS target condition on associative memory performance. The results therefore suggest that any impact on cognitive resources dependent on the right DLPFC resulting from TMS was not sufficient to influence the accuracy of associative recognition judgments regardless of age.</p><p id="p0180">As was noted in the Introduction, we selected the right DLPFC as a TMS target because the region has been previously reported to give rise to robust age-invariant retrieval monitoring effects (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>) and is readily accessible to administration of TMS. However, monitoring effects have also been consistently reported in other regions, most notably in the anterior cingulate cortex and left DLPFC (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>). These findings raise the possibility that redundancy across the different regions allowed for sufficient neurocognitive resources to compensate for depletion arising from TMS of the right DLPFC.</p><p id="p0185">We observed a main effect of stimulation order on associative recollection accuracy such that memory performance was reduced among participants in whom TMS was delivered to the right DLPFC during the first study-test cycle. This effect was modest and supported by a Bayes Factor indicating anecdotal evidence for the alternative hypothesis. Although the two cTBS sessions were separated by approximately 60&#x000a0;min (cf. <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2005</xref>), we cannot rule out the possibility that residual stimulation effects from the first study-test cycle may have carried over into the second study phase. Therefore, stimulation of the right DLPFC may have adversely affected encoding during the second study-test cycle. This raises the possibility that cTBS has longer lasting effects when delivered to DLPFC as compared to the previously published effects of motor cortex stimulation. Future work is needed to address this issue. Despite this modest effect, we did not observe any evidence that the effects of TMS on age differences in associative recognition performance were moderated by stimulation order. Thus, we found no evidence that the null effects described in the foregoing paragraphs could be explained by memory differences arising from stimulation order.</p><p id="p0190">We also predicted that TMS administered to the right DLPFC would affect RTs for associative false alarms, and that this effect would be most prominent in older adults. This prediction too was unfulfilled. However, we did identify a significant effect of TMS on RTs to test items, albeit in young rather than older participants. Whereas RTs were robustly shorter for associative hits than false alarms in the vertex stimulation condition in the young group, this difference was absent after TMS to the right DLPFC. By contrast, older adults failed to demonstrate an RT advantage for hits in either stimulation condition. Thus, TMS administered to the right DLPFC appears to have shifted the patterning of the RTs for hits and false alarms in the young adults so that it resembled the pattern evident in the older group. We stress however that these results were unanticipated, and that they most decidedly merit replication. While not supporting our initial predictions, the results converge with those described in the preceding paragraph to provide evidence that the TMS intervention impacted some aspects of task-related behavior. These findings provide some reassurance that the null results of TMS on associative recognition accuracy did not stem from a blanket failure of the TMS protocol to modulate neural function. However, we note that the Bayes factor for the above-described effect was equivocal (BF<sub>01</sub> ~ 1.0), thus it is possible that our stimulation protocol was not sufficient to produce behavioral impairments.</p><p id="p0195">The present null findings converge with those from a study employing a quite different strategy to examine the age-related &#x02018;resource limitation hypothesis&#x02019; motivating the present study. <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Horne et al. (2020)</xref> employed a dual-task procedure in which an associative recognition test was paired with a secondary tone detection task to limit the neurocognitive resources available to support post-retrieval monitoring. While the manipulation disproportionately impaired the associative recognition performance of older relative to young participants, fMRI correlates of retrieval monitoring, including those in right DLPFC, were unaffected in both age groups. Thus, as in the present case, these fMRI findings suggest that the monitoring operations supported by this region are relatively resistant to a manipulation aimed at disrupting these operations by limiting access to domain-general processing resources.</p><p id="p0200">A potential limitation of the present study concerns the spatial extent of TMS. Right DLPFC is a sizeable and, it has been argued (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Duncan, 2001</xref>), near-equipotential cortical region, and the relatively focal stimulation provided by TMS might have failed to disrupt a large enough proportion of the tissue capable of supporting monitoring. Future studies using methods that have the potential to disrupt a broader expanse of the DLPFC, such as transcranial direct-current stimulation, might yield different results (e.g., <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gaynor and Chua, 2019</xref>). Another potential limitation stems from our use of a group-level fMRI monitoring effect (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Chastelaine et al., 2016</xref>) to identify right DLPFC TMS targets at the single participant level. It is possible that our null findings arose due to inter-subject variability in the locus of the critical DLPFC region necessary for effective monitoring operations. We note however that prior studies have reported successful TMS interventions using a similar approach to targeting TMS (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Thakral et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Yazar et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). A third limitation is that, although we aimed for a stimulation intensity of 80% of motor threshold, most of our participants were stimulated at a lower intensity due to a hardware limitation (see Methods). Thus, our null results might reflect the employment of an inadequate stimulation intensity. While we cannot rule out this possibility, it is noteworthy that <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bonnici et al. (2018)</xref> and <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Yazar et al. (2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2017)</xref> employed stimulation intensities of a similar magnitude to those employed here (70% motor threshold) to study the role of the angular gyrus in memory retrieval and reported positive findings. Moreover, it has been reported that the relationship between the intensity of cTBS stimulation and degree of cortical suppression is complex and possibly non-linear, at least in some participants, casting doubt on the assumption that the behavioral effects of such stimulation should correlate positively with stimulation intensity (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Sasaki et al., 2018</xref>). Further work is needed to establish the stimulation parameters that have the greatest likelihood of impacting episodic memory processes (cf. <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Yeh and Rose, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Widhalm and Rose, 2019</xref>). We also cannot definitively rule out the possibility that the null TMS effects were driven in part by individual differences in susceptibility to cTBS (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Jannati et al., 2017</xref>). Finally, we acknowledge that the sample size for both age groups was relatively small and may have been insufficient to detect modest TMS effect sizes.</p><p id="p0205">In conclusion, we found that TMS to the right DLPFC had no detectable impact on associative memory performance in young or older adults. These results suggest that stimulation of the right DLPFC was insufficient to impact the neurocognitive resources available to support post-retrieval monitoring.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0210">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000049</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Aging</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (grant number <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs1">R21AG054197</award-id>).</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0215"><bold>Paul F. Hill:</bold> Validation, Formal Analysis, Investigation, Data Curation, Writing &#x02013; Original Draft, Review &#x00026; Editing, Visualization, Project Administration. <bold>Erin D. Horne:</bold> Methodology<bold>,</bold> Software<bold>,</bold> Investigation, Data Curation<bold>,</bold> Writing &#x02013; Review &#x00026; Editing<bold>,</bold> Project Administration<bold>. Joshua D. Koen:</bold> Methodology<bold>,</bold> Software<bold>,</bold> Investigation<bold>,</bold> Data Curation<bold>,</bold> Writing &#x02013; Review &#x00026; Editing<bold>,</bold> Project Administration<bold>. Michael D. Rugg:</bold> Conceptualization<bold>,</bold> Methodology, Validation, Formal Analysis<bold>,</bold> Resources<bold>,</bold> Writing &#x02013; Editing &#x00026; Review<bold>,</bold> Supervision<bold>,</bold> Project Administration, Funding Acquisition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0220">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achim</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dorsolateral prefrontal cortex involvement in memory post-retrieval monitoring revealed in both item and associative recognition tests</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.10.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15670688</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential behavioral effects in frontal lobe disease</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>6</volume><year>1968</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0028-3932(68)90038-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkers</surname><given-names>R.M.W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Linden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>N.C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bovy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dresler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>R.G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transient medial prefrontal perturbation reduces false memory formation</article-title><source>Cortex</source><volume>88</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cortex.2016.12.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28068640</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonnici</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheke</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>D.A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>FitzGerald</surname><given-names>T.H.M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specifying a causal role for angular gyrus in autobiographical memory</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>49</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>10438</fpage><lpage>10443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1239-18.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30355636</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braver</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A theory of cognitive control, aging cognition, and neuromodulation</article-title><source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0149-7634(02)00067-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12470692</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brysbaert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving beyond Ku&#x0010d;era and Francis: a critical evaluation of current word frequency norms and the introduction of a new and improved word frequency measure for American English</article-title><source>Behav. Res. Methods</source><volume>41</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BRM.41.4.977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897807</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brysbaert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warriner</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuperman</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concreteness ratings for 40 thousand generally known English word lemmas</article-title><source>Behav. Res. Methods</source><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13428-013-0403-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142837</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buckner</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memory and executive function in aging and AD: multiple factors that cause decline and reserve factors that compensate</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2004.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15450170</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shallice</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confabulation and the control of recollection</article-title><source>Memory</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/096582196388906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8817460</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cocchi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalesky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattingley</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic cooperation and competition between brain systems during cognitive control</article-title><source>Trends Cognit. Sci.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2013.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24021711</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Chastelaine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donley</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neural correlates of recollection and retrieval monitoring: relationships with age and recollection performance</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>138</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.04.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27155127</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Chastelaine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donley</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Independent contributions of fMRI familiarity and novelty effects to recognition memory and their stability across the adult lifespan</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><volume>156</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2017.05.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28528847</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delis</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ober</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>California Verbal Learning Test</part-title><edition>second ed.</edition><year>2000</year><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related changes in neural activity associated with familiarity, recollection and false recognition</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Aging</source><volume>31</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1814</fpage><lpage>1830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2008.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19004526</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dulas</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aging affects the interaction between attentional control and source memory: an fMRI study</article-title><source>J. Cognit. Neurosci.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>2653</fpage><lpage>2669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn_a_00663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24800631</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An adaptive coding model of neural function in prefrontal cortex</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>820</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11715058</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multiple-demand (MD) system of the primate brain: mental programs for intelligent behaviour</article-title><source>Trends Cognit. Sci.</source><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2010.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20171926</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eichenbaum</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonelinas</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The medial temporal lobe and recognition memory</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Neurosci.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.neuro.30.051606.094328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417939</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaynor</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcranial direct current stimulation over the prefrontal cortex alters encoding and judgments of learning based on fluency</article-title><source>J. Cognit. Neurosci.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1710</fpage><lpage>1725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn_a_01449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31322469</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giovanello</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kensinger</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related neural changes during memory conjunction errors</article-title><source>J. Cognit. Neurosci.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19445606</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cognitive neuroscience of ageing</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22714020</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenhouse</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geisser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On methods in the analysis of profile data</article-title><source>Psychometrika</source><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1959</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02289823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayama</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between the right frontal old/new ERP effect and post-retrieval monitoring: specific or non-specific?</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>46</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1211</fpage><lpage>1223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2007.11.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234241</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayama</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex is engaged during post-retrieval processing of both episodic and semantic information</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>47</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>2409</fpage><lpage>2416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2009.04.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383503</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabrieli</surname><given-names>J.D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insights into the ageing mind: a view from cognitive neuroscience</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14735112</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>R.N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shallice</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confidence in recognition memory for words: dissociating right prefrontal roles in episodic retrieval</article-title><source>J. Cognit. Neurosci.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/08989290051137468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11177413</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>R.N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shallice</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Right prefrontal cortex and episodic memory retrieval: a functional MRI test of the monitoring hypothesis</article-title><source>Brain</source><volume>122</volume><issue>7</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/122.7.1367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388802</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Chastelaine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neural correlates of post-retrieval monitoring in older adults are preserved under divided attention, but are decoupled from memory performance</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Aging</source><volume>97</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2020.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33190122</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rounis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theta burst stimulation of the human motor cortex</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2004.12.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15664172</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jannati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberman</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotenberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual-Leone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interindividual variability in response to continuous theta-burst stimulation in healthy adults</article-title><source>Clin. Neurophysiol.</source><volume>128</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>2268</fpage><lpage>2278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2017.08.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29028501</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeffreys</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Theory of Probability</part-title><edition>third ed.</edition><year>1961</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confabulation, memory deficits, and frontal dysfunction</article-title><source>Brain Cognit.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/brcg.1997.0873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9220085</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koen</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thakral</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcranial magnetic stimulation of the left angular gyrus during encoding does not impair associative memory performance</article-title><source>Cognit. Neurosci.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17588928.2018.1484723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29870300</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koen</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonelinas</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of healthy aging, amnestic mild cognitive impairment, and alzheimer's disease on recollection and familiarity: a meta-analytic review</article-title><source>Neuropsychol. Rev.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11065-014-9266-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25119304</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenth</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emmeans: estimated marginal means, aka least-squares means. R package version 1.3.0</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=emmeans" id="intref0030">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=emmeans</ext-link><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>VanHaerents</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridge</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prefrontal &#x003b8;-burst stimulation disrupts the organizing influence of active short-term retrieval on episodic memory</article-title><source>Eneuro</source><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/ENEURO.0347-17.2018</pub-id><comment>ENEURO.0347-17.2018</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related differences in prefrontal cortex activity during retrieval monitoring: testing the compensation and dysfunction accounts</article-title><source>Cerebr. Cortex</source><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhs064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankudowich</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related differences in agenda-driven monitoring of format and task information</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>51</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>2427</fpage><lpage>2441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2013.01.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23357375</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memory function in normal aging</article-title><source>Acta Neurol. Scand.</source><volume>107</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0404.107.s179.5.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12542507</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Old</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naveh-Benjamin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of age on item and associative measures of memory: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Psychol. Aging</source><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0882-7974.23.1.104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18361660</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lautenschlager</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Earles</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frieske</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwahr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaines</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mediators of long-term memory performance across the life span</article-title><source>Psychol. Aging</source><volume>11</volume><year>1996</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037//0882-7974.11.4.621</pub-id><comment>621-637 17</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reitan</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The Halstead-Reitan Neuropsychological Test Battery: Therapy and Clinical Interpretation</part-title><year>1985</year><publisher-name>Neuropsychological</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tucson</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reuter-Lorenz</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappell</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognitive aging and the compensation hypothesis</article-title><source>Curr. Dir. Psychol. Sci.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8721.2008.00570.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual-Leone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety, ethical considerations, and application guidelines for the use of transcranial magnetic stimulation in clinical practice and research</article-title><source>Clin. Neurophysiol.</source><volume>120</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>2008</fpage><lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2009.08.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833552</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilding</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrieval processing and episodic memory</article-title><source>Trends Cognit. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1364-6613(00)01445-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10689345</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>E.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polnaszek</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associative recognition memory awareness improved by theta-burst stimulation of frontopolar cortex</article-title><source>Cerebr. Cortex</source><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1200</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhu311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandrini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappa</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miniussi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of prefrontal cortex in verbal episodic memory: RTMS evidence</article-title><source>J. Cognit. Neurosci.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/089892903322370771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14511538</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Togashi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirota</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokushige</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inomata-Terada</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intensity of continuous theta burst stimulation, but not the waveform used to elicit motor evoked potentials, influences its outcome in the human motor cortex</article-title><source>Brain Stimul.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brs.2017.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29258807</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galluccio</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milberg</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>False recognition and the right frontal lobe: a case study</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0028-3932(95)00165-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8817509</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoemaker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruessner</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recollection and familiarity in aging individuals with mild cognitive impairment and alzheimer's disease: a literature review</article-title><source>Neuropsychol. Rev.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11065-014-9265-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115809</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westfall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aust</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Afex: analysis of factorial experiments. R package version 0.22-1</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=afex" id="intref0035">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=afex</ext-link><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Symbol Digit Modalities Test (SDMT) Manual</part-title><year>1982</year><publisher-name>Western Psychological Services</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spreen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Neurosensory Center Comprehensive Examination for Aphasia</part-title><year>1977</year><publisher-name>Neuropsychology Laboratory</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Victoria</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thakral</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madore</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for the left angular gyrus in episodic simulation and memory</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>34</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>8142</fpage><lpage>8149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1319-17.2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28733357</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Chastelaine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donley</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of age on the neural correlates of recollection success, recollection-related cortical reinstatement, and post-retrieval monitoring</article-title><source>Cerebr. Cortex</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1698</fpage><lpage>1714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhu333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>WAIS-R: Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale-Revised</part-title><year>1981</year><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Wechsler Test of Adult Reading</part-title><year>2001</year><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Antonio</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Wechsler Memory Scale, Ed 4</part-title><year>2009</year><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Antonio</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The Test of Premorbid Function (TOPF)</part-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westin</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisanby</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luber</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of motor threshold using visual observation overestimates transcranial magnetic stimulation dosage: safety implications</article-title><source>Clin. Neurophysiol.</source><volume>125</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2013.06.187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23993680</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Widhalm</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How can transcranial magnetic stimulation be used to causally manipulate memory representations in the human brain?</article-title><source>Wiley Interdiscipl. Rev.: Cognit. Sci.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1469</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcs.1469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yazar</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Continuous theta burst stimulation of angular gyrus reduces subjective recollection</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e110414</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yazar</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced multimodal integration of memory features following continuous theta burst stimulation of angular gyrus</article-title><source>Brain Stimul.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brs.2017.02.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28283370</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How can transcranial magnetic stimulation Be used to modulate episodic memory?: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Front. Psychol.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>993</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2019.00993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31263433</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yonelinas</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nature of recollection and familiarity: a review of 30 Years of research</article-title><source>J. Mem. Lang.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmla.2002.2864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yonelinas</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relation between remembering and knowing as bases for recognition: effects of size congruency</article-title><source>J. Mem. Lang.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1006/jmla.1995.1028" id="intref0040">https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1006/jmla.1995.1028</ext-link></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0225">The following is the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.xlsx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0230">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ynirp.2021.100027" id="intref0025">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ynirp.2021.100027</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>